<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLMcL-0015">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>1861 February 1: McLean to Colenso</title>
				<author>
					<name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70546/">McLean</name>
				</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p/>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Transcription reprinted by Ian St George in eColenso May 2015 Supplement, available at http://www.colensostudy.id.au/Newsletters/eCol%205%20May15%20supplement.pdf</p>
				<p>Encoded into TEI by Jamie Norrish, 17.11.15</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<correspDesc>
				<correspAction type="sent">
					<date when="1861-02-01">1861 February 1</date>
				</correspAction>
				<correspAction type="received">
					<name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
				</correspAction>
			</correspDesc>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<p>1861 February 1 McLean to Colenso (#1027452) </p>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p>Auckland February 1st, 1860. </p>
			<p>My dear Mr Colenso </p>
			<p>Many thanks for your kind letter of the 21st. Decr. with its accompanying enclosures. I have read Mr Fitzgerald’s answer to the natives with great interest. I shall bring in portions of it to the Maori Messenger whenever some other matter now in hand is disposed of. </p>
			<p>I know well how Renata must have been prompted when he made such a speech; it is much to be regretted that clerical influence is turned to such a very bad account. </p>
			<p>I feel much indebted for the assistance you are a affording in the Maori question and shall order, indeed I have already done so, additional numbers of the Messenger for you. </p>
			<p>The last sweep at Taranaki in which the natives sustained an ascertained loss of 50 killed and the English only 5 and 12 wounded will be a lesson to the poor deluded fanatics are rushing to their own destructions. The General &amp; the troops under him are behaving admirably; now that they understand Maori tactics it is to be hoped they will soon bring the war to termination. The English press is with us and quite against ecclesiastical interference.  </p>
			<p>The Saturday review takes Hadfield’s part. </p>
			<p>I am sending a book that Dr Knight handed to me for you. I should be at Napier by this time but the critical state of affairs so near the scene of King making disaffection prevents my leaving. I start with the Governor to the Bay of Islands, Ahipara and Hokianga on Monday next. I shall be always glad to hear from you. </p>
			<p>Yours very truly Donald McLean </p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>