<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1118">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>7 January 1868: Hector to Hooker.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">James Hector</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Kew DC 174, 511-514, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 568-571.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Hooker: 
Transcriptions of letters from James Hector to  
Joseph Dalton Hooker between 1860 and 1898", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133B, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-21-8. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133B.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1868-01-07">1868 January 7</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hector to Hooker, 7-1-1868, Kew DC 174, 511-514, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 568-571.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p> Geological Survey Office and 
Colonial Museum, Wellington </p>
            <p>7th January 1868</p>
            <p>My dear Hooker,</p>
            <p>The plants refd. to in a list sent 
to you on 6th Nov. leave to day by the 
Asterope
 in four cases secured on the deck.</p>
            <p>
I enclose the Bill of  £/- for those and will send duplicates via Suez.</p>
            <p>The same Bill/£ also includes a case containing the Cabinet which I hope will reach you in safety and be accepted. I cannot as yet 
send you the names of those who have formed 
in the presentation but you will find all your appreciating friends on the list. </p>
            <p>I have to acknowledge your letters of Oct. &amp; Sept. I have 
only recd. them as I have 
been up at Taupo Lake and at Ruapehu &amp; Tongariro. I was too early for plants but made a 
large collection of the few that 
were in flower. I got nothing new but most things that were got previously by Colenso &amp; Bidwill. </p>
            <p>Tongoriro is still active. Ruapehu is not. They both sit 
on marine tertiaries to the westward of a straight edged mass of Palaeozoic
 Slates. The elevation of
 the Tertiaries which
are Upper Pliocene is equal to 2700 ft. It is much the same kind of
 thing as if a great volcano
were to burst out at the base of the submarine cliff along the West Coast of the South Island 
&amp; during the display of Volc. Energy the
sea bottom were to rise with 
its covering of marine 
strata to the above altitude. </p>
            <p>
            a. Highly fossiliferous crag
[?] Pliocene. Rises from Sea le
vel to 2700 ft. both from E. 
&amp; W. in a sh--- only broken by gullies of denudation. </p>
            <p>b. Turb----- Clay Marls. Foss
ils from ---- Calc. strata. </p>
            <p> c. Clay silt evidently deep water beds with --- as far foraminifera.  </p>
            <p>d. Trachyte &amp; ----- Mts. d
------ P---- drifts ---. </p>
            <p>I am going back there at once as I have 
only come down for some business connected 
with the medical board 
of which I am Pres. </p>
            <p>How glad I am you are to be Pres. of Brit. Assoc. I wish to goodness I could get home.  I would add my little effort to make it a meeting worthy of its President. I wont despair but the visit of
the Prince will turn everything topsy turvy.  </p>
            <p>
I am glad you are pleased with the chert flakes. I will send you more &amp; also some of 
the more highly finished axes &amp;c. 
I have a very fair collection now. </p>
            <p>            I am putting up a new[?] Maori House 55 ft 
long 20 ft wide &amp; 16 ft high all Carved in 
the most splendid fashion. It is the finest Carved Ho. the Maories have built and the Govt. 
ery wisely took the occasion of their turning rebel to confiscate it &amp; transfer it to my care for 
preservation. In 50 years it will 
promise sincere interest[?]. </p>
            <p> Many thanks for the Ward Case of plants of which I have recd. B/L. I will report 
hen they arrive. The next cases I send I shall 
build in a very different style. If you send out more plants please send 
Pines &amp; Rododendrons.</p>
            <p> 
I had a letter from R---- about the Flora Hand Book &amp; have placed it in a publishers hands. I hope some will soon arrive as there is
 a great demand for them. The
 Littergrass[?] 
ou send are very good. Buchanan has not seen th
em yet as he is away in the South.</p>
            <p>  Your notes on 
Olearia traversii
 have been sent on to Mr
. Potts. Haast is down about 
the Rangitata now will no doubt find the plant if it
 is there. He has been building up Moas at 
 great rate &amp; has no doubt sent you Photos of them.</p>
            <p> With all good wishes of the season </p>
            <p> 
Your affectionate friend </p>
            <p> 
James Hector. </p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>