<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1120">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>8 August 1868: Hector to Hooker.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">James Hector</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Kew DC 174, 527-528, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 602-604.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Hooker: 
Transcriptions of letters from James Hector to  
Joseph Dalton Hooker between 1860 and 1898", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133B, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-21-8. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133B.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1868-08-08">1868 August 8</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hector to Hooker, 8-8-1868, Kew DC 174, 527-528, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 602-604.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p> [Wellington?] </p>
            <p>
 8th August 1868 </p>
            <p>My dear Hooker,</p>
            <p>            I have to thank you for your letter of 31 May. The mention that Lyell is interested in my work is very gratifying and greatly strengthens my hands.</p>
            <p>
            I enclose a copy of a memo: which will s
how the steps I have taken to
information about childbearing 
among the Natives for Darwin. </p>
            <p>Also notices
Branch and also at our big gathering of the N.
Z. Institute which comprises all the societies 
throughout the colony incorporated under the Act of
 Parliament I sent you last year, when it 
was passed.</p>
            <p>  
Also notices of our proceedings both at the Phil. Society which is the local Wellington
Branch and also at our big gathering of the N.
Z. Institute which comprises all the societies 
throughout the colony incorporated under the Act of
 Parliament I sent you last year, when it 
was passed.</p>
            <p>  
We have meetings of one kind or other 
every week. The Society meets for discussion 
every third week &amp; an adress &amp; conversazione of
 the Institute inter---- 
along with lectures by
my self. The first of which is on Tuesday next.</p>
            <p>
I enclose you all our proceedings up to date 
&amp; it would be very useful if they were noticed in some of the 
scientific Journals</p>
            <p>            I will send them regularly. We are to publish proceedings containing a notice of what
is said in discussion at all the societies &amp; Transactions containing the 
papers at length. There 
have already been some capital papers read both in Auckland &amp; here. I set Kirk &amp; Colenso 
to a little scientific skirmish about
Pittosporums
 &amp; Travers &amp; Buchanan at one another about 
e distribution of 
Veronicas
. Mantell I have managed to commit to a thorough overhaul of all we know about Moas &amp; the authority we have
 for different species &amp; their distribution. </p>
            <p> I suppose when I raise my voice   
 about Geology some one will be down on me in time - 
 but it will all help to have us going &amp; I trust will show a result creditable to the colony.  </p>
            <p>            We have our meeting in the carved Maor
i house which is 50 ft long &amp; surround by
carved figures of the most hideous description each 4 ft high. When lighted up &amp; the long table covrd. with Moa bones it formed a 
sight that would be famous in London.  </p>
            <p> I meant 
 to have sent some papers by this 
mail but have been too busy. Haast is out of work now &amp; wants to get on to my staff but I fear 
there is little chance for this year of getting 
even the votes we have.  </p>
            <p>
Very Sincerely Yours </p>
            <p>James Hector.</p>
            <p>
I send a sample of the Meteorological return I publish each month. Do you care to get 
this?  </p>
            <p>
            At this time you will be in the midst of your
 work at Norwich. I have lots of seeds for you but hardly dry
 yet. I hope Mrs. Hooker is 
all right – give her my kind remembrances. </p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>