<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1112">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>16 June 1865: Hector to Hooker.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">James Hector</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Kew DC 174, 456-458, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 470-473.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Hooker: 
Transcriptions of letters from James Hector to  
Joseph Dalton Hooker between 1860 and 1898", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133B, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-21-8. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133B.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1865-06-16">1865 June 16</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hector to Hooker, 16-6-1865, Kew DC 174, 456-458, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 470-473.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p> 
Geological Survey of New Zealand </p>
         <p>Dunedin</p>
         <p>16th June 1865 </p>
         <p>My dear Hooker, </p>
         <p>In your last letter you say you will be glad to propose any one I recommend for F.L.S.</p>
         <p>I will take advantage of your kind offer for myself &amp; for John Buchanan. I think he
quite deserves it as he has worked very hard. What are the Fees? If elected you can apply to 
Stanford – Charing Cross for them. By the way I 
am in rather an awkward scrape. In printing 
off Colenso’s Essay I put F.L.S. after his name
. I dont know why but I fancied he was a very 
old member of the Society. He writes me that he
 was not aware of his having been elected but 
that he expects that he 
is by this time – I really hope he 
is as I have 1,000 copies of the Essay 
printed off with the letters F.L.S. after his name.</p>
         <p>Might I ask you to propose him 
if you have not done so. I am
 certain he will feel it to 
be a great compliment &amp; a recognition of 
his services in the cause of Botany.</p>
         <p>I hope you will have received all the tracings of the fossil plants before this reaches 
you. They were sent by last mail. If you see your
 way to naming any of them please send the
duplicate tracings with the names to Wellington which will be my future adress.</p>
         <p>I have now a complete set of drawings of 
all the organic remains that have yet been 
found in New Zealand &amp; I only wish I knew how 
to get them described &amp; published. I have always planned my work as if I were to get 
home &amp; take it with me for publication so that 
remaining out here puts me in a very disadvantageous possition in that respect.</p>
         <p>I have a curious theory about the cause 
of (Geologically speaking) – temporary[?] 
alternate submergence of the N. &amp; S. Hemispheres sketched out for you but I wont send it by 
this mail, as I want to think a little more about
 it. It occurred to me 
more than 2 years since
but I am so badly off for Books out here that I 
could not refer to what others have said on the 
subject. By the way I wish when any book comes out that you think I should see, if you 
happen to be passing Stanford’s just give him a 
note[?] to send it to me by Book Post. I have 
ordered the Quarterly Journal of
 Science from seeing one number with a sheet ----- of your 
Flora N.Z.  Is it to be considered reliable? I thought the discussions very good.  </p>
         <p>When are copies of the 
Flora N.Z. coming out for the market. My copy is nearly worn 
out with the constant thrashing of borrowers. 
I am sure I could sell 150 copies here right 
way.  
</p>
         <p>With kind regards to Mrs. Hooker &amp; Sir William I remain Ever Yours affectionately  
James Hector </p>
         <p>Dr. J.D. Hooker </p>
         <p>Kew</p>
         <p>          
         I enclose a tracing of another plant that Buchanan has made out. The part within the 
red line is slightly “helped” in the drawing – but the rest is a faithful copy. I think you will
find it interesting. It is from the 
Upper Secondary Coal Formation at 
Shag Point. I have already sent you a 
lot of things from the 
same rock. Buchanans insists on its being a 
My----.</p>
         <p>Can afford the time for him, I would like 
to send Buchanan to work at the rocks in
situ. It would be better than his working at 
a ------ --- specimen as
 he has been doing. </p>
         <p>JH </p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>