<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1110">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>15 July 1864: Hector to Hooker.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">James Hector</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Kew DC 174, 429-430, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 424-429.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Hooker: 
Transcriptions of letters from James Hector to  
Joseph Dalton Hooker between 1860 and 1898", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133B, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-21-8. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133B.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1864-07-15">1864 July 15</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hector to Hooker, 15-7-1864, Kew DC 174, 429-430, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 424-429.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p> 
Christchurch</p>
            <p>15th July 1864 </p>
            <p>My dear Hooker</p>
            <p>As I have been travelling about N.Z. I have
 not yet received my letters by either of the last two last mails &amp; so cannot answer them. I wrote you a few lines from Auckland 
acknowledging receipt of the lists 
of plants. Since then Buchanan has compared it with the plants and has sent me a few notes
 which I enclose. </p>
            <p>I trust that by this time you have received the West Coast Plants which were sent by 
the Jany. &amp; Feby. mails. – Also the Analyses
 of the Geographical distributions. </p>
            <p>In answer to your enquiries – The 
Areca sapida
 does not occur in 
Otago,but I believe 
is found on Banks Peninsula and also at the mouth of the Grey on the West Coast. This having[?] it as high as Lat. 44° S. &amp; very 
considerably above its S. American limit!! Dr. 
Munroe fancied from the Nelson specimens that 
Cordyline indivisa 
was always sessile, but both on our West Coast and near 
Auckland I have seen them w
ith stems 12 ft high. All those 
I saw in the Nelson woods were however without stems. Can these be two similar species. 
The leaves also appeared diff. to me. 
</p>
<p>I shall send you full illustrations of 
C. australis. I have enjoyed my tour very much &amp; 
have made acquaintance with many persons I only knew by name previously – such as Dr. Knight, Colenso, Travers, Haast &amp;c. Travers 
is going home soon and I have no doubt
you will like him. He is a natural born botanist that has only lately 
discovered his vocation. 
And as he is rich &amp; can afford the business you must secure him as a work man. Haast 
improves very much on acquaintance &amp; is really a very good fellow on the whole. He is most 
indefatigable &amp; has done lots of good work in 
the way of collecting and measuring sections.
The excellence of his botanical work you will know
. He shewed me some of the Proof sheets
of your 
Flora
. It is splendid &amp; will be highly appreciated in this Colony as there are an 
unusual percentage of folk here that take an interest in Botany.</p>
<p>Haast asks me to tell you that he has not had time to write by this mail. We have been
up country for a few days together looking at the structure of the plains where the rivers 
emerge on them from the Mts. Haast as I 
suppose you know goes in strongly for Glacier action, &amp; has made some excellent observations, but his notions on 
the subject are very confused I think as he does not distinguish 
sufficiently between the extension of glaciers 
under existing conditions &amp; their mode of opperating when the features of the Mts. were 
different. Oscillations &amp; Faultings 
have
 undoubtedly occurred in late Geological times &amp; 
they must have aided &amp; even over ---- the Ice action in the formation of the Mt. valleys. I dont 
member if I ever pointed out to you the relation of our great Lakes to the Sounds of the West Coast.</p>
<p>Here it is evident that rock
 bound basins have been formed on the East side and deep 
sounds on the West side of the Mt. by the whole mass of the Island having undergone 
depression at unequal rates – the West side sinking fastest. The original formation of the 
alleys I have no doubt were formed
 by the errosion of glaciers along 
Anticlines
 &amp; lines of 
fault.</p>
<p>My principal news this mail is that the 
General Govt. have asked me to organise &amp; 
direct a permanent Geol: Survey of the whole of
 New Zealand on the same footing as in other 
Colonies, and that as I have agreed to do so I 
must give up all hope of 
returning to Europe for
many years to come.</p>
<p>I think you will agree that this is right step 
on the part of Govt. so far as the principle 
is concerned, but whether they have pitched on 
the right man or not I wont venture to say. At 
any rate I will work hard to make New Z. what you predicted it should be, viz. a Geological Gauge on which we may measure the changes 
which Physical Geography has undergone in 
recent Geol: times, by a study of the recent fossils &amp; the living animals &amp; plants.</p>
<p>Already I begin to perceive
 that in the matter of shells there has been a gradual 
displacement of S. American (Miocene &amp; Pliocene) forms by forms that are in the equivalent
strata of Australia so that the littoral fauna of
 N.Z. were say in Miocene times, identical or 
nearly so with that of W. America but 
now
 it is almost Australian.  </p>
<p>I return to Otago today in the mail steamer 
&amp; if I have time after getting my letters &amp; 
anything requires answer I shall write you a few lines. Now that I have seen the whole of 
New Zealand do you know that I think the South Island will be the greater Colony. The N. Island has all the natural advantages but the S. Island shows all the signs of active development. I fear very much they are going to break asunder as
 the miserable Maori 
question is dragging the whole into the mud while
 the S. Island has no interest in the matter 
whatever.</p>
<p>Pray tell Mrs. Hooker that I have never ye
t been able to get the Postage Stamps sh
wished – they must be very rare indeed but I do not despair yet. </p>
<p>Ever Yours affect. friend </p>
<p>James Hector.</p>
<p>Dr. Hooker </p>
<p>Kew.</p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>