<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1115">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>12 November 1865: Hector to Hooker.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">James Hector</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Kew DC 174, 469-470, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 485-487.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Hooker: 
Transcriptions of letters from James Hector to  
Joseph Dalton Hooker between 1860 and 1898", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133B, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-21-8. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133B.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1865-11-12">1865 November 12</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hector to Hooker, 12-11-1865, Kew DC 174, 469-470, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 485-487.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p> 
Colonial Museum </p>
            <p>Wellington, 12th November 1865</p>
            <p>My dear Hooker, </p>
            <p>I need not tell you how sorry we all were to
 get the news of your fathers death by last
mail, for though he had reached a ripe old age st
ill he was so active &amp; useful up to the last 
that he will be missed more by science than
 many a younger man that is called from the ranks. Sir George Grey, Dr. M
unroe, Colenso, Travers &amp; several others all called on me to 
leave particulars at once after the mail arrived. I 
was sorry to have to tell them that you we
also unwell but I hope that
 attack soon passed off.  It was so kind of you to write in the 
middle of all your troubles. I will never forget
 it. But you must not let my business bother you 
too much – it can always wait. I am glad you like
 the fossil plants. Of course the drawings are clearer than the originals but I 
dont think there has been the least exageration or contraction 
employed in copying them. </p>
            <p> 
I have a few of the original fossils on slabs here – but most of them are in the 
Museum at Dunedin, where they can be referred 
to at any time. I have had to start a Museum here at once so that in order to make some show I have temporarily arrested the duplicates of
the Otago collection that were packed to send home to you &amp; to others. As soon as I get into 
the Field however I will get collecting to supply 
this place &amp; then will send them on to their 
proper destination. I always thought that an arrangement would be made by the Colonial 
Govt. to take over the Survey Collections &amp; all from the Otago Govt. I wish they had done 
so, as the Museum at Otago will not be cared for or looked after I fear. The Museum here is 
getting into shape. I enclose a plan of it from which you will see that only a small part of it is 
yet built. By next steamer I leave for the North &amp; will go as far as the Bay of Islands &amp; 
perhaps the North Cape. I take Buchanan with 
me, so you may expect a share of the results. 
Buchanan has been collecting largely here but is disappointed at 
finding so slight a change in the Flora from that in the South. The diff. is confined to some additional forest trees &amp; a few
shrubs. However he has only seen 
the wooded district yet. I enclose a list of the 
plants he has 
found 
here
 for the first time. He also desires me to call your attention to the 
Drymis 
axillaris here (if you have specimens – none of his 
in flower are dry enough to send by this mail). He would not have recognised it except by
 the flower it is so unlike the tree in the 
South. The parts of diff. are in the tree here – </p>
            <p>The leaves are hardly coriaceous.</p>
            <p>Green on both sides </p>
            <p>not Glaucous</p>
            <p>not spotted </p>
            <p>mid rib not hairy </p>
            <p>The flowers are very abundant &amp; on long pedicles.</p>
            <p>The bark is pale coloured instead of black-brown. It may be worth while your looking to your N &amp; S In species again. </p>
            <p>Veronica hulkeana
 is common in the Gardens here, having been introduced by Mr. Weld about 15 years ago
 from the 
Kaikoras. It is known as Weld’s 
Veronica.
 I promised Mantell[?] I would mention this
. I am filling a Wards Case for 
you. I have got a lot of nice 
plants for you. Among other some plants of the 
Myosotidium 
nobile from Chatham Is. It grows well here but is destroyed by an aphids. Insect life is 
bearing to have a sad 
----on the 
introduced plants in New Zealand for want no doubt
 of the small ----- that
 keep them in check at home. There are some beautiful Gardens here
. The best is Ludlams up the Hutt Valley. It 
reminds one a little bit of Kew. He has 
about 50 kinds of Pines &amp; other trees - &amp; Rhododendrons, Azaleas &amp; Camilias in profusion. I never saw anything equal to the Camilias
anywhere. If they thrive so well dont you think that some of the 
Hill Trees
 should grow.</p>
            <p>Before leaving Dunedin Buchanan packed a Ward Case for you with all the new West Coast alpine plants &amp; some of the doubtful species of the East Coast. This Case has since been dispatched by way of Melbourne so look out for it. I enclose a list of the Plants it 
contains. </p>
            <p>With kind regards to Mrs. Hooker &amp; hoping you 
are quite well long before now. Believe me 
my dear Hooker </p>
            <p>Your affectionate friend </p>
            <p>James Hector.</p>
            <p>I have been reading Tyndals lecture on heat
[?] with great interest. Mantell says he 
now understands how HE came into existence as
 a necessity – for when Satan was pitched 
out of heaven with the other, on being pulled up 
at the end of this journey the velocity would
be changed to heat – without the direct[?
] creation of roasting place by an unvengeful[?] 
deity!! </p>
            <p>By this mail I send home to the R.S.E. a good paper by Skey (my chemist) on the
formation of Coal seams. You will be interested
 in the subject. We have been working at the 
idea for the last two years. This
 paper is the experimental[?] 
matter. I have helped him in 
every way but do not feel justified 
in going in for a share of the "plunder".</p>
            <p>I see Lauder Lindsay has been going “twice -----” to the R.S.E. of N.Z. Coals from my reports. Very well for a magazine 
article but hardly the thing for an original? paper to the 
R. Soc. Skey
 is more “riled” than I am about it.  </p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>