<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1119">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>3 June 1868: Hector to Hooker.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">James Hector</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Kew DC 174, 520-5, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 583-591.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Hooker: 
Transcriptions of letters from James Hector to  
Joseph Dalton Hooker between 1860 and 1898", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133B, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-21-8. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133B.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1868-06-03">1868 June 3</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hector to Hooker, 3-6-1868, Kew DC 174, 520-5, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 583-591.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>  

Wellington </p>
            <p>3rd June 1868 </p>
            <p>My dear Hooker, </p>
            <p>            I suppose this will reach you in the midst of 
your reign at Norwich and I feel it almost
wrong to write to you having nothing particular to say. How I wish I could be one of your 
most devoted though unworthy subjects. I will 
keep an anxious outlook for the gleams of 
wisdom we are sure to get from you in your adress.</p>
            <p> 
            Since I last wrote I have been again at 
the Bay of Islands reexamining the Kawakawa
Coal-Field which is now assuming a position of importance in the country. The 
Coal
 is 
undoubtedly as good &amp; even better for steam pur
poses than the N.S. 
Wales coal, but is 
ssociated with plants that I 
fancy you would call Miocene. The Roof is a Green sand full of very badly preserved casts of marine shells but none characteristic of any older forma
than Tertiary.</p>
            <p>            At the  same time from Analogy with other parts of the Colony I believe it to be at the 
base of what I have termed my cretaceo-tertiary series &amp; that a great thickness of Chalk 
Marls have been removed by denudation being 
now represented by a superficial drift of 
flints. I am going to lithograph all the fossils both 
plants &amp; shells &amp; give them interim field 
names. We have not the books nor the skill to 
do more &amp; cant spare the specimens yet.</p>
            <p>     
Haast has at last got a museum &amp; from 
Mantell who is a good judge I hear it is a 
perfect model of good arrangement. I am going to take a run down to see it. </p>
            <p>
His Moas must be a splendid sight – the cut 
in the illustrated news falls far short of 
the reality I understand. I am anxious to have some skeletons carefully collected so that we 
will have the bones &amp; all the bones &amp; nothing but 
the bones of the same bird. This has never 
yet been done. I have set one 
D. giganteus
 up 9 ft high, but had to introduce the pelvis of a 
different individual. </p>
            <p> 
I sent Kirk up to the North Cape, &amp; he has 
made large collections 
of plants &amp; is very 
sanguine as to many of them being new in which neither I nor Buchanan agree. Kirk is a 
capital botanist, but is too critical
 for a new country. It is not fair
 to expect your flora to be as 
rigidly correct in the diagrams of species as an
 English Flora for instance, &amp; if he finds the 
least discrepancy in the description from the plant itself, he
 jumps at its being new although 
there is no doubt of its being the plant you meant. </p>
            <p> 
            Thus he wanted to make 
Sapota costata a different tree from yours because your 
general ch. says 1 seed &amp; it has from 1 to 3 seeds. This we all know &amp; Colenso pointed it out 
in his first Essay in 1847!! He has fallen foul of 
Dacrydium colensoi
 also just as we did &amp; the 
list says it is now calling out Silver Pine (or 
Podocarpus dacrydiodes
 var. Yellow Kahikatea) 
that grows on dry ground &amp; has sing
le sparse burrs or seeds the 
Dacrydium colensoi
. I think 
he is wrong but at the same time the Silver pine is more allied to 
Dacrydium 
than 
Podocarpus
. </p>
            <p> Pittosporum
 is the genus after his own heart in the North as he can play the changes in 
 and 
Coprosma it to any extent just as we can with 
Veronica
 in the South. He is such a capital 
observer however that he will do much good. We have managed to get him a scientific staff 
appointment. He is to be Secty. of the Auckland 
Branch of the N.Z. Institute – Curator of the
Museum &amp; Meteorological Observer – which 
combined will give him enough to live on.</p>
            <p>
I have never except old Bourgeau 
seen his equal at drying plants.</p>
            <p> The wretched waiting for the Prince who did not come after all, but was 
advised
 to 
bolt to his Mamy’s apron strings, lost me my
 trip at the proper season to Tongariro &amp; 
Ruapehu. When I was there in Novemb
er I was much too early.</p>
            <p> 
 
I have just got the second vol. of Lyell’s 
Principles
. It is splendid – he touches on all sorts of things I have been dreaming about. I wish
 I could get home to rub up a little. I see in 
the International[?] Observer a writer has started the old notion of our s
ea level in South Lat.
not being the same distance from the Earths’ centre as Jones’[?] North which is a pet notion 
of mine. He arrives at it from comparing the Barom. readings which show 1 inch less 
pressure in 50° South than at 50° N. Some recent observations on Refractions observed at the 
Melbourne observatory with the new instruments 
have not been explained as they differ from 
hat they should be theoretically. Can this diff.
 level of the sea have anything to do with it? How the difficulties of our maraine drifts alternating with Glacial or Alpine drifts would 
disappear if we had a cyclical change of s
ea level proved without chopping up the crust of the
Earth in the usual North---- manner. Now 
I have bored you long enough with my chat. 
Consider that I applaud you vehemently – and trust that all of us 
in N.Z. take a great pride in
your minted elevation to the 
chair R. to Brit. Assoc.  </p>
            <p> 
Believe me ever your affectionate friend</p>
            <p>  
James Hector.  </p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>