<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1116">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>24 January 1867: Hector to Hooker.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">James Hector</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Kew DC 174, 488-491, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 526-530 .</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Hooker: 
Transcriptions of letters from James Hector to  
Joseph Dalton Hooker between 1860 and 1898", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133B, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-21-8. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133B.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1867-01-24">1867 January 24</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hector to Hooker, 24-1-1867, Kew DC 174, 488-491, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 526-530.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>
Wangapeka, Nelson Province, N.Z.</p>
            <p>24th January 1867</p>
            <p>My dear Hooker, </p>
            <p>Many thanks for your interesting letter of 4t
h Sept. which has just reached me. I have 
been in the Mts. for the last 2 months &amp; have 
had rough work of it as the Country is the most 
inaccessible in N.Z. &amp; the weather has been horrible. Nevertheless I have never spent time to 
more advantage Geologically as the natural sections are so fine &amp; varied
 that I have cleared 
up many points that were before doubtful &amp; obscure, &amp; I almost fancy I begin to see 
something like a reliable classification of our formations begin to loom out. There is still a great deal of contradictory evidence
 as to our 
Coal deposits &amp; that is 
the subject I am most 
interested in at present. The 
widest deduction I have got to is
 that we have been putting the cart before the horse in laying so much
 status 
on the presence of Granite &amp; Igneous rocks as 
causing disturbances. In this district the disturbances since 
Miocene times have been most 
gigantic &amp; are distinctly
 seen – yet there are 
no Igneous rocks of such modern date – the 
Granite behaves in all the dislocations quite
 as passively a part
 as Clay slate. </p>
            <p>The 
faultings
 are the real first effects of the cause whatever it is &amp; the usual 
ccompanying volcanic &amp; metamorphic phenomena not being present here, must be looked on as accidental &amp; not necessary consequences of dislocations of the Earths crust – but at any
rate they must not be considered as the 
causes
 – either proximate 
or remote of these 
dislocations. You will be glad to hear that I have also 
at last
 found Pelaeozoic Fossils, 
Trilobites Orthis &amp;c. in Calcareo
us slates in our upper Auriferous
 rocks so that we get a clue
to the arrangement of our slate Formations. 
 I have also got a lot 
of Fossils of newer 
formations &amp; plenty more Fossil plants, but the latter will be more confusing than ever. 
However I shall take your advice &amp; describe them all provisionally as soon as I can. We must 
at least get local field names for 
them as characteristic of the 
various strata, even though they be very wide of their real relationship to a tr
ue Botanical classificati
on [therefore] I am  much 
obliged for the hints you have given h----- &amp; th
ey will be duly turned to account in the 
omenclature I adopt. On the whole the resembla
nce to the Vancouver Is. fossil Flora is very 
marked as far as I can remember, but of course
 exact comparison can only establish this. I am 
certain you will find some of the 
Damara araucarioides
 among my Nanaimo &amp; Bellingham 
Bay fossils &amp; the Podocarpus is just the old Taxites[?] again. The mineral resemblance of the
beds &amp; their distributi
on also “bears” out this similarity &amp; in Tasmania &amp; Victoria the same 
appears to be the case. I have wondered if all these Coal deposits which invariably occupy narrow valleylike depressions in very ancient rocks can have been the subalpine equivalents 
of the more extensive &amp; regular Coal strata such as of N.S. Wales which latter may have been 
the delta or Coal plain deposits of the same period. In that case it would be only in accordance with what we know of alpine Floras 
at present that there should be a greater 
affinity among the plants embedded in the alpine valley deposits than 
in those of the low grounds. I think this is worth looking into, 
only as you remark, it would be necessary to 
verhaul all the collections[?] from the 
various Coal deposits in the world. </p>
            <p>If I was only home for a spell I would brighten[?] up &amp; look into all these points. I 
feel quite rusty here all alone 
as I have no one to discuss some matters with. I am glad you like the notion of the Volcanic
 origin of Hydrous &amp; Anhydrous
 Coals. Certainly tell Lyell anything I --- may write
 you if you think it worth 
while. Since I wrote you 
I have seen a great deal to confirm me in it.</p>
            <p>I am sorry I should have mislead
 you about[?] the Mt. Egmont plant. Buchanan got 
it from a Gardener who vowed that he had it so
me years ago from Mt. Egmont – but I have 
not much confidence in the “cove” in question &amp; I can easily be
lieve it came out of Hulks’ Garden at Taranaki. I am sorry Colenso 
should give you so much bother with his 
Cryptogams.
 I never attempt to collect any as I 
know nothing about them except that I would be deceived by all sorts of forms &amp; stages of growth. </p>
            <p> I have been up some Mts. lately &amp; got some alpines but the 
H.Bk.
 was left by mistake 
at Motueka &amp; till I get 
it I wont say whether there is anything good, new or rare. Some are 
new to me, but then I dont know what has been got
 in these Mts. before. At present we talk of 
N.Z. Botanically as ours – but in time we local
 workers with the help of your invaluable book 
will have to work out the Bot.
 peculiarities of all our Nat. systems which are quite as 
diversified as those of the Grampians, 
------ Mts. or Norway Mts. I dare say.</p>
            <p>  Was not 
Cordyline stricta 
in the large 
N.Z. Flora
? or was it only mentioned as a 
synonym as it is in the 
Handbook
? At any rate there is a second narrow leaved
, 
lax-flower
Cordyline
 which has a stem &amp; I think bluish (not blue though) flower but I am getting 
specimens of it for you. These since I wrot
e I have seen lots of the Southern 
Cor. indivisa 
which is also in the South part of the Wellington Province N. 
Is. &amp; is the true 
C. indivisa
 – but the broad leaved[?] Ti of the Taupo district
 though it has the same leaves (or nearly so) 
must surely be a different thing as it has 40 to 50 heads, has 
a huge Flower head with long &amp; 
broad ---asts &amp; has 
black shining seeds
. This is the true Toii of the Maoris that they make 
mats of – not the one they eat
!! That is the Ti-Tawhiti or 
Stranger-Ti
 which grows with
 50 to a 100 heads on thin flexible stems which grow 
very rapidly as the Maoris propagate it by 
layers &amp; cut out lengths 
of the stems to eat. They bake it 
&amp; beat it to a pulp extracting a
starchy matter which they boil to a gruel. I 
heard that the Ti Tawhiti never flowers &amp; was 
introduced to the various locallities by the natives, but the only one I have seen which was up 
a spur of Mt. Egmont had dead Flower stalks on it &amp; I have specimens.</p>
            <p> I was very much surprized to find a strong resemblance in the Flora of the Cape
Farewell district to that of the N. part of the Auckland Province. The same heathy flora as 
round the Bay of Islands with Epacris, rushes, 
Gleichenia dicarpa
 drosseras &amp; small Towhai
(Weinmannia signlinola) only 
Pomaderis 
is 
wanting
. This flora extends down the West 
Coast on certain soils as far as 20 miles S. of
 the Buller River or the same range as the 
Nikou
Palm. Why is it that in the N. the 
Nikou
 loves the deepest shade &amp; shelter in forrest &amp; dells –
but on the West Coast you will se
e whole forrests of nothing else standing bluff &amp; ----- 
through with battered leaves on the most expos
ed headlands when all the rest of the 
vegetation is beat down by the wind to a clear 
felt like mass that you can walk on many feet 
above the ground?</p>
            <p>By the way – The dwarf 
Weinmannia
 that grows in the heart lands of the N. has 
always pinnate leaves &amp; is supposed to be the young state of 
W. racemosa 
but the shrubby 
plant occupying the same 
situation in this Island 
never
 has pinnate leaves, I shall try to find 
out more about this as I hear that
 old Dr. Sinclair always insisted
 that the little
 shrub with the Pinnate leaves was a distinct species. But you must be sick of discussing the N.Z. Flora now I
should think. When we get the 2nd vol. &amp; suggt.
 we must go to war among ourselves &amp; neve
bother you except as Umpire by right of conquest. I am very sorry so few of the plants 
reached you alive. I left two cases ready for sending off to you when I was last in Wellington. 
I suppose they are on their way. I will not forget seeds. They are just coming in. The 
Cinchona
 seeds I have sent to the Gov.’s Garden 
at Kawau at the place where they will have 
most chance.</p>
            <p>Thanks for your kindness in writing to the Sec. R.S.
 I wrote to him &amp; remitted the
money for the first year but
 I intend to correspond[?].</p>
            <p>Ever Your Sincere Friend </p>
            <p>James Hector. </p>
            <p>Cant you send me a copy of your lecture on 
Darwin. I wish I could have made a 
2501st auditor.</p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>