<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1113">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>13 September 1865: Hector to Hooker.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">James Hector</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Kew DC 174, 464-465, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 479-481.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Hooker: 
Transcriptions of letters from James Hector to  
Joseph Dalton Hooker between 1860 and 1898", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133B, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-21-8. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133B.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1865-09-13">1865 September 13</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hector to Hooker, 13-9-1865, Kew DC 174, 464-465, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 479-481.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p> 
Geological Survey Office</p>
            <p>Wellington </p>
            <p>13th September
 1865 </p>
            <p>My dear Hooker,</p>
            <p> I got no letter from you by last mail but from a note that the Governor showed I was 
glad to see that your father is better again. The N.Z. Parliament is sitting just now but they have got into such bad blood in setting up about
 this War expedition that they are not well disposed to spend much money on science. At the Govn. suggestion I proposed the 
examination of the South Island as you wished 
but the Ministry would not propose it to the House even. Next year however the House may be in a more amiable temper.</p>
            <p>I am now in my new quarters at least the 
portion that is to be built in the mean time 
which is only one fourth of the whole building 
as designed. It is nothing but a large oblong 
Hall lighted by a 
clearstory. Part of it I have fenced off as
 offices in the way they do at the 
Brit. Museum. As a Museum I shall not have much
 to start it with at 
first as all my past 
collections had to be left in Dunedin. However 
I shall have a good set of Tertiary Fossils &amp; 
Recent Shells &amp; a fair share of Rock Specimens
 &amp; must just work hard collecting till the 
specimens of all kinds accumulate. I am very 
anxious to hear what you say about the Fossil 
Plants, the tracings of which I sent some mails since. The West 
Coast Coal fields will soon be
developed now through the agency of the 
Gold that is now being found in their 
neighbourhood. Haast has been over there lately
 &amp; will send you a copy of his Report I have 
no doubt.  </p>
            <p> Mantell put a Question to the Govt. the other day in the House about the distribution 
of your Flora. The Govt. said they had got 
two hundred copies according to agreement &amp; to 
give away &amp; that as the copy right was the publishers they had no control in the matter. You should therefore urge the Publishers to send some
 copies out for sale as lots of people want 
them who wont get any of the 200
 from Govt. &amp; the Booksellers
 out here have not ordered 
any, being under the impression th
at the whole Edition was to be sold by the Govt.</p>
            <p>I got hold of a copy of Lyell’s 
New Elements
 lately &amp; have been
 reading his chapter 
on the Miocene Flora.If I could send home a 
collection of our Fossil Plants do you think that 
Heer[?] would work them up – In any future collecting I will bear it 
in mind at any rate. I 
have one box of leaf impressions packed for you already of most of what you have received drawings. Buchanan is going 3 weeks to collecting plants from some out of the way places in Otago before he comes North. I heard from him yesterday that he had got some good mosses but nothing else worth while. He 
will be up here next steamer &amp; I shall let him collect a while in
Spring. Sir G. Grey proposes a trip this season to examine the Inlets off the NE Coast of N.Z. If I go I shall take Buchanan. Colenso is so sea sick that he wont face the sea at all. He is a Member of the House &amp; is here just now. 
He tells me he is sending you a new moss this mail. </p>
            <p>I have no news at all that you wont find in 
newspaper ----. I have been working like aCarpenter for the last month.  
With kind regards to your 
father &amp; to Mrs. Hooker</p>
            <p>Ever yours sincerely</p>
            <p>James Hector. </p>
            <p>Mantell sends his regards. </p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>