<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1114">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>12 October 1865: Hector to Hooker.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">James Hector</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Kew DC 174, 467-468, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 483-485.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Hooker: 
Transcriptions of letters from James Hector to  
Joseph Dalton Hooker between 1860 and 1898", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133B, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-21-8. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133B.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1865-10-12">1865 October 12</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hector to Hooker, 12-10-1865, Kew DC 174, 467-468, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 483-485.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p> 
Colonial Museum</p>
            <p>Wellington </p>
            <p>12th October 1865</p>
            <p>My dear Hooker, </p>
            <p>As I have not heard from you for the last
 two mails I suppose you have been enjoying 
summer holidays. However it is possible that 
my last mail may have gone on to Dunedin and
it will be some days before the letters can be returned to this place.</p>
            <p>  I have very little news to give you as I have hardly been out of Wellington since I came up.  The Assembly is still sitting &amp; wrangling as usual &amp; as yet have hardly got through any
any of the real business. For in
stance they have not voted my estimates! The Colony is very 
hard up in consequence of the attitude of the Home Govt. who will neither bear the expenses
of this tedious war – but the Colonists do without
[?] it or put an end to it the best way they can, or on the other hand give the Guarantee to help
 to sell the Loan 
which has already been expended on Imperial troops. I see no cure for 
the mess till every soldier is out of the country 
&amp; the Natives get a little harsh treatment from 
the Colonists when required. If Great Britain 
would withdraw the troops &amp; Guarantee the t---- Million Loan 
that has been expended for the for the [sic] Colonists in carrying out a Native policy which they know to be useless, the 
Colonial Office would never need
 to ask another sixpence from
 Parliament for New Zealand. 
The way in which the General Govt. has been pulled up &amp; the discredit that has been unjustly 
thrown on New Zealand by the discussions in 
Parliament &amp; the illtempered correspondence 
between the Provinces &amp; the General, has stopped all influx of capital &amp; arrested all the 
Public works in the Colony. Things never looked
 worse &amp; were it not for the confidence I have in the natural Resources 
of the Country &amp; the importance 
of developing these at once, I would not have the
face to ask for expenditure on
 account of science. However as all my staff 
have come up &amp; the museum is far advanced I 
hope they will not cut down the Dept. now.  
 </p>
 <p>Buchanan has been spending all his spare time in collecting but does not find this neighbourhood so rich as he expected. He says 
it falls far short of Otago both in Cryptogams &amp; flowering plants
. It is richer in forrest trees. We are getting an index to your handbook, of 
ative names. I shall send you a copy to print 
with the 2nd Edit. if you like to do so. Mantell &amp; Colenso have furnished most of the names. There is not a copy of your Handbook to be
had now. I wish some more were sent out they 
have sold at 16/- p. part, the purchaser of the 
first part being required to pay at the same time for the 2nd part also.</p>
            
            <p>I am longing to hear something of the tracings of the fossil plants I sent you home, 
also of the 
Moa bones
. I have got several other fine 
skeletons, especially one
 of 
Dinornis 
giganteus
 that I am going to set up. The bones conform to this species, but the Head which is 
8 1/2 inches long is 
that of Owen’s Genus 
Palapteryx
!!  </p>
            <p>I suppose Haast will be telling you all the news of the shift which the Gold ------- has 
made from Otago to the West Coast of Canterbury. The area is small as compared to Otago as 
the Gold does not appear to cross to the Eastern Watershed at all &amp; there is only a strip about 
4 miles in width being on the Coast on the 
West slope. The sudden slope &amp; enormous volume of water descending by short
 straight channels to the sea has served to sluice off a 
tremendous bulk of Auriferous Tertiary formations &amp; so do a deal of work in preparing the way for the ------. The Gold rock crops out on the West slope thus. 
reminding me very much of the British Columbia except that there is no Coast range of Volcanic rocks. In Otago on the other hand the Gold rocks form
 a broad central area of about
14 times the area of the West Coast slope, but from its possition it has 
not been so violently denuded. The yield from the new diggings 
with a population of 
20,000 miners is about 
45,000 p. month just now. The 4 or 5 ------ 
rushes  that took place to various parts of Otago 
each reached for a short time about 70,000 p. month. It is very wonderful to see such a 
difficult &amp; densely bushed country opened up as 
the West Coast has been during the last 6 
months. There is a rumour of Gold being disc
overed in the Auckland Province. If there could
only be a good rush then the Maori influence would soon be at an end.</p>
            <p>Haast no doubt will send you his Rept. on the West Coast diggings this mail. As usual
he drags in Glaciers in rather 
a violent way to account for everything. He always forgets that 
coincidence is not necessarily causation.</p>
            <p>Ever Yours Sincerely </p>
            <p>James Hector. </p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>