<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1117">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>7 October 1867: Hector to Hooker.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">James Hector</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>7-10-1867, Kew DC 174, 504-505, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 551-556.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Hooker: 
Transcriptions of letters from James Hector to  
Joseph Dalton Hooker between 1860 and 1898", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133B, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-21-8. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133B.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1867-10-07">1867 October 7</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hector to Hooker, 7-10-1867, Kew DC 174, 504-505, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 551-556.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p> 
Geological Survey Office and Colonial Museum </p>
            <p>Wellington </p>
            <p>7th October 1867 </p>
            <p>My dear Hooker, </p>
            <p>I was very glad to receive 
your note of July 29th &amp; to hear
 that you had been away for
a trip. I am sure you must have needed it as the 
work you have got through in the last two 
years is very wonderful. It is very pleasing to 
think that you are satisfied with the conduct of
the Govt. about your Flora and I told Mr. Stafford so.
 I will tell you a secret – that some 
few of us who are really able
 to appreciate the great labour
 you have undergone for the good
of the 
 Colony have conspired to make you a present that you will we hope keep and hand 
down as an heirloom to testify that we are not 
ungrateful. It stands in
 the museum now &amp; is an object of Universal admiration – being (s
ee Photogram enclosed) a Cabinet &amp; writing 
table of inlaid New Zealand woods only second 
in value (&amp; by the same workman) to that 
sent to the Queen in 1861. I hope you will like it. 
It will be sent by the first wool ship that leaves direct for London, and I will
 then send you full particulars. </p>
            <p>
My time has been cut up very much of late and I have not been able to get the paper ready I promised in my last letter on the Moa remains. I cant do it very well till I get 
Mantell’s help &amp; he is 
occupied with legislation at present. I will take your hint about the 
Lake basin Theory &amp; put it in a short form before I start on my Museum work.
 If we only had proper means for publishing I could do lots of
 work, but the printing establishments are 
very weak here 
as you will gather from the style of the abstract report of the Department 
which I enclose. The four Wardian cases of plants are now filled &amp; ready to go by the first 
chance. I think every one of the plants should reach you alive as
 we have been very careful 
deed to pick out sickly ones &amp; to secure
 them in every way we could think of. </p>
            <p> 
Buchanan found out that the 
Senecio he sent was 
Ozothamnus
. It is very curious 
getting a new 
Phyllocladus
 in Auckland. Colonel Haultain is 
very curious about it as he is 
well up in the Auckland Flora.</p>
            <p>Your explanation about the mosses is quite 
satisfactory to Buchanan only he naturally 
feel a little sore that his good work should have been lost through Wilson’s action.</p>
            <p>I quite agree with all you say about the feeble action of streams as erroding agencies 
only I object in N. Zealand at least to the term 
Glacial Epoch. It is not a particular period or 
some places – where the producing circumstances 
ill prevail. The distance to which Ice action radiates depends on the area of country above 
the line of perpetual c------ - &amp; that must be a
very Ice action it gives rise to.</p>
            <p>I am going up to Taupo &amp; on to the Thames this
 year as I wish to be where they are 
n the North. 
It is a curious circumstance the occurrence of Gold in what 
ppears to be a Trachytic tuffa probably of Miocene age. I must have the Thermal waters carefully analysed for Gold &amp; may perhaps find a clue to its manner of deposit.  </p>
            <p>I sent you some Chert Flakes by last mail – are they like those at the Cape? I have just
recd. a live 
Apteryx australis
 (one died) and an egg, its 
circumferences are 12 1/2 &amp; 10 
inches! </p>
            <p>Your affectionate friend  </p>
            <p>James Hector</p>
            <p>When did Colenso send you the Maori index? Mantell is very anxious to know as he borrowed his map &amp; kept it some time.  </p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>