<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1109">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>17 May 1864: Hector to Hooker.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">James Hector</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Kew DC 174, 427, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 418-420.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Hooker: 
Transcriptions of letters from James Hector to  
Joseph Dalton Hooker between 1860 and 1898", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133B, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-21-8. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133B.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1864-05-17">1864 May 17</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hector to Hooker, 17-5-1864, Kew DC 174, 427, ATL Micro-MS-Coll-10-16, 418-420.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p> 
Dunedin</p>
         <p>17th May 1864</p>
         <p>My dear Hooker,</p>
         <p>My last letter was allowed to miss the Post most stupidly last
 month so that you 
would receive a parcel containing a few mosses without any advice. 
I trust that you have 
received all the Parcels that 
have been sent by Book Post now as they contained the West 
Coast Plants.</p>
         <p>In answer to your question about the absolute diff. of the E. &amp; W. Coast flora I
enclose you a classified list. It is of course very imperfect as we dont know the names 
rightly. It is mainly all done by Buchanan who has laboured hard to make it as exact as 
possible.</p>
         <p>When shall we have a list of Plants out &amp; can we hope for your 
Book
 before the 
opening of the Exhibition? I have already told
 you that Munroe and Colenso are going to 
write essays on the Botany of N.Z. Haast Crawford &amp; I write on the 
Geology &amp; other authors
will do for the other ------ of the subject.</p>
         <p>The 
Areca
 does not come so far south as this &amp; is limited almost to the Province of 
Nelson in this Island I believe.  I sent you some notes about the 
Cordylines 
two mails ago
which I hope you received.</p>
         <p>I am quite in a fog about the 
Astelia
 here – it is certainly a bisexual plant at least what  I take to be the 
Astelia 
 is so I enclose a part of a flower.</p>
         <p>I start in a few days for a six weeks tour of the other Provinces in order to drum up the folks to work for the Exhibition. It makes a nice trip for me. I shall visit the New diggings which have broken out in Nelson. 
It is very interesting. It has always puzzled me why the 
diggings have hitherto been confined to this Province. </p>
         <p>Along with the enclosed list 
I send a map of the Province 
with the districts marked into where I have
divided it. I also send you 
a photograph of a map I have brought out of the 
N.W. district which will
 serve to show you the cut of our 
Alpine regions. Also a page of a 
report that is passing through the Press as it relates to the Herbarium work. I shall be glad of a
trip away just now as I have not
 been feeling altogether right. 
In confidence
 I may mention
that the General Government have, or intend 
to propose engaging 
me as Geologist for the whole colony in which case I shall 
not see you &amp; other friends for many days to come. I have 
 getting the stamps 
for Mrs. Hooker I am sorry to say – </p>
         <p>Ever Yours Affectionately </p>
         <p>James Hector. </p>
         <p> PS <!--illegible: one line-->
</p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>