<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="diaryHadfld-0001">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Diary, 1839 September 30 - December 21: Octavius Hadfield</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions, spine title "Hadfield, Typescript Miscellaneous Fragments 1833-1897", stamped 19 Dec 1979.  Section: Diary, 30 Sept. - 21 Dec. 1839 + 2 typed transcripts.  Pages 52-71.</p>
         <p>MS annotation correctly states "Repeated pp 72-91".</p>
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 11.12.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
		 <date from="1839-09-30" to="1839-12-21">1839 September 30 to December 21</date>
		</creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Diary, 1839 September 30 - December 21: Octavius Hadfield</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>PAIHIA - SEP. 1839.</p>
      <p>Sep. 30.  Left Waimate this afternoon having taken leave of all there, and arrived here this evening.  I have been so busily engaged all day that I have given scarcely any time to prayer and meditation.  Oh may the Lord have mercy upon me for Jesus' sake.  The Com. have decided that I should go to Kapiti; I expect to start in about a fortnight.  The Rev. N.W. purposes to accompany me.  Oh! that I had more dependence upon God.</p>
      <p>Oct.1-2.  Took a walk and had some conversation with the Rev.R.P. relative to the school and the mission generally.  Went with the Rev.N.W. to look after necessaries to take with me to Kapiti.  I find I can procure but little here.  Oh may I remember that the Lord disposes of me in all things; may I therefore not only be submissive in <hi rend="underline">all</hi> matters, but rejoice knowing that all is ordered in Covenant love: this is a difficult thing, never to be disappointed, but always to bear in mind that little things as well as great are ordered by God.  Oh that I had a more habitual sense of God's love in Christ.  (2) Went early to Kororareka where the Rev. N.W. buried a child.  Had some conversation with some persons over there, they desire to have a minister among them.  Went to Mr. Busby, dined with him; had some interesting conversation with him, told him I could not support his proposed school for half-cast<!--sic--> children upon the British and Foreign School Society principles.  He purposes altering his plan.  Reminded P.M. of Job IV, 21 &amp;c.  I have spent but little time in reading and prayer.</p>
      <p>Oct.3.  Unable to proceed about business from the badness of the weather.  Engaged in learning native.  Employed some time in reading and prayer.  Alas! how cold I feel, how weak in faith.  May the Lord quicken me by his spirit.</p>
      <p>Oct.4-5.  Did very little.  Engaged in learning native.  Read the scriptures with some profit; felt much comfort in prayer: was thinking about what I might want for southwards.  Alas, what I most want is a heart dependent upon God.</p>
      <p>Oct.5.  Lost the early part of the day.  Went in the water, and made some preparations for Kapiti; trust I shall get a few necessaries.  Oh! how little do I really want.  Oh! that I felt more my spiritual wants.  May the Lord fit and qualify me to minister before him in holy things.  My heart has this day longed after God, but enjoyed but little communion with him.  Would that I had a quiet place of retirement.</p>
      <p>Oct.6.  Lord's Day.  Tho' I have met with some hindrances I have enjoyed much of the Lord this day.  Preached morn.  Is.XXVIII.16. with considerable ease and comfort.  In the afternoon John XIV.16.  My head failed me during the latter part.  Administered the Lord's Supper for the first time by myself, enjoyed a blissful feast.  Oh! I wonder when I may again meet with so many Christian friends around the Lord's table.  Expect to go shortly to Kapiti.  Oh I rejoice that the Lord will be with me there.  Am this day twenty five years old: oh! how little have I yet done for the Glory of God, and yet how gracious has the Lord been to me.  May I <hi rend="underline">return the time</hi>.</p>
      <p>Ot.7-8.  Almost all the morning engaged in <hi rend="underline">talking</hi> about the concerns of the mission, and seeking information with respect to Kapiti.  In the afternoon rode in to Waimate with the Rev.W.W.  Slept at Mr.Wade's.  Enjoyed much communion with God in the morning.  Most of the day lost.</p>
      <p>Oct.8.  Left Waimate and rode to Pakaraka, dined there, and came back to Paihia.  Studied native a little.  Read with some comfort, and drew near to God in prayer.  Would that my soul were more devoted to God and more fully set on glorifying Christ.</p>
      <p>Oct.9-10.  Employed the morn. in writing, did but little the rest of the day, felt unwell towards evening and went to bed early. (10) Lost a great part of the day thro' the delay of others while engaged in procuring necessaries for my intended house-keeping at Kapiti.  Not very well.  Learned a little native.  Uncertain when I shall proceed to the southward.  Feel considerable deadness of spirit, feel little love in my heart towards God when I consider the abundance of His rich grace exhibited towards my soul in my eternal salvation by Christ Jesus.</p>
      <p>Oct.11-12.  Lost nearly all the morn.  In the afternoon wrote to the Bishop &amp; Mr.Coates.  Believe I am going in the Columbine, thus visiting Tauraunga<!--sic--> in our way.  Wrote some letters.  Lost some time in uncertainty what to be doing.  Read native, and enjoyed communion with God in prayer in the afternoon.  Oh! that I were actively engaged in duty, devoting every hour to God.</p>
      <p>Oct.13. Lord's Day.  Went to Kororarika.  Preached in morn. on 1 Pet.III, 18.  In afternoon RomVIII, 1.  Baptized an infant, the daughter of Capt.-----  Am doubtful whether I ought to baptize such persons.  Trust the Lord was with me during the services.  Have not this day enjoyed much of God thro' my inability to retire for prayer.  Have mercy O Lord upon a poor sinner for Jesus' sake.</p>
      <p>Oct.14.  Lost a great part of the day in uncertainty how to proceed; not altogether my own fault.  I do lament this waste of precious time.  Went to Kororarika on business.  Oh! that I were engaged in the work of the Lord.  Oh! that my heart were more disposed to prayer.</p>
      <p>Oct.15.  Passed a little time in the forenoon in reading and prayer; studied native a little.  Passed some time talking about the best mode of proceeding to Kapiti.  In the afternoon went about making several arrangements for my departure.  Oh! that I were more fully convinced that the best mode of preparing was by seeking directions from the Lord and making prayer to Him.</p>
      <p>Oct.16-17.  Went to the Kirikiri with the Rev.W.W. to obtain more stores; did not return till 10 o'clock.  Felt wearied and unwell.  (17) Engaged in making preparations for sailing and employed some time in getting materials on board the Columbine for a future dwelling house.  I have not had my heart sufficiently set upon God.  Oh how prone my heart is to cleave to this vain world and to allow its passing concerns to occupy my attention and affections.</p>
      <p>Oct.18.  Unable to go out in the morn. on account of the heavy rain.  Wrote to George.  Engaged in making necessary preparations: got thro' some business.  Have been but little in prayer, but have had my heart nearer to God than is usually the case.  Oh! that I may be filled with the Spirit, and abound in love to the Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
      <p>Oct.19.  Put everything on board the vessel.  Am now ready to start.  Felt somewhat of communion with God this day tho' I feel unaccountably cold to spiritual things.  Alas, whence this deadness.  Oh for a more abiding sense of God's infinite goodness towards me.  May I be prepared for the evening Sabbath.</p>
      <p>Oct.20.  Lord's Day.  Have not felt that holy desire after the enjoyment of God that I could have wished.  In the morn. preached on Is.XLII.21, in afternoon on Sam.IV.16.  The congregation appeared inattentive: fear that I spoke with little love or warmth of soul.  Went home with Mrs.F. after service, felt much refreshed at family prayer with her and Mr.F. while singing 'Salvation oh the joyful sound' and afterwards while expounding part of 1Cor.1 and in prayer.</p>
      <p>Oct.21-24.  (21) Engaged the greater part of the day in making preparations for my departure.  Took leave of all my friends and embarked on board the Columbine at seven o'clock together with the Rev.N.W., Mr.W., Mr.C, &amp; Mr.S. sailed out of the Bay of Islands with a fair wind; soon began to feel a little sea-sick.  Retired to be at about 12 o'clock after remaining on deck till I was very cold.  (22) Rose in the morn. and went on deck, after remaining on deck some time during which time I felt very unwell I went below and retired to bed, felt exceedingly unwell, nevertheless could trust in the Lord and rejoice in the hope of the Glory of God.  (23) Felt very unwell: however the wind continued fair, and I lay patiently in bed till I was told at a quarter past 3 o'clock that we had anchored at Pauranga<!--sic; should this be Tauranga, perhaps?-->.  The wind blew very fresh as we entered the harbour, and in a narrow part of the entrance the vessel was nearly drifting upon rocks, but the Lord preserved us.  We landed at about seven o'clock and were met upon the short by the Rev.A.B. and conducted by him to his house where we passed the evening, and I retired to bed at Mr.S. not feeling very well, but rejoicing that I was on shore.  (24) Not very well.  Have been engaged in doing nothing but looking round the settlement and talking about matters here.  Much prefer the christian simplicity of proceedings here to those in the northern stations.  Oh may the gracious Lord carry on His own great work here to His own glory and the eternal welfare of His people.  Have not had my heart fully set upon the Lord as I could have wished.  Oh! that I could reduce time, and when I have health and strength so to glorify God and devote every hour to His service.  Oh! may my soul experience more of the love of Christ towards my soul.</p>
      <p>Ot.25.  Rose very unwell, found it necessary to take strong medicine and confine myself to the house almost all day.  Engaged in reading.  Had some interesting conversation with Mr.S.  If all is well am likely to proceed shortly to Kapiti.  There is a body of about 1,000 natives in the neighbourhood, who are set on mischief.  Oh may my trust be ever in the Lord.  What an unaccountable deadness of soul I feel: how little love is there in my soul<!--typescript: "sould"; surely a transcription error--> to the Lord my God.  Oh for Divine help!</p>
      <p>Oct.26-27.  Not very well.  Passed the day without much profit.  I would that I were more disposed to seek the glory of God.  Read native for some time.  I want more application.  (27) Lord's Day.  Attended the native service in the settlement.  Gathered together a small English congregation at the Rev.Mr.B's and preached on Zach.IX.9-11.  Purposed going to a neighbouring Pa in the afternoon, but was unable to get across the river for want of a boat.  Enjoyed a season of private prayer with comfort.  In the even. partook of the Lord's Supper with the other brethren here; felt refreshed tho' my mind was in a wandering frame and state.  May I live more under a holy conviction that my God sees and knows all my thoughts and words and deeds.  Have mercy O Lord!!</p>
      <p>Oct.28-29.  Had intended accompanying the Rev.N.W. &amp; B. &amp; Mr.C. to Maketu where they are gone to endeavour to make peace between the Waikata and Rotorua natives, but did not feel well enough.  Did but little all day, however I trust I am gaining information respecting my work.  (29) Have been engaged almost all day in preparing prescriptions for medicines.  Oh while I feel anxious for the bodily health of the natives who may be under my care, may I above all seek their eternal health.</p>
      <p>Oct.30.  Passed the day in making various notes of matters which I thought might be useful.  Intend starting tomorrow.  Mr.W. &amp; B. &amp; C. returned this evening from Maketu.  They were very nearly making peace: the Waikata natives were well disposed but the offer of friendship of the Ware-Kura lads hindered it by representing to the Maketu natives that the others were afraid.</p>
      <p>Oct.31 to 7 Nov.  Set sail about half past one o'clock from Tauranga after having taken leave of all friends there, there being on board besides myself the Rev.N.W., Mr.B. and Mr.S.  Felt nothing of sea sickness, tho' not very comfortable as is usual with me on board ship.  (Nov.1) Landed with Mr.Clarke at Motu some miles beyond Opotiki in the Bay of Plenty, where we left two Christian natives Samuel &amp; Richard and their wives.  The natives appeared savage, but very civil and kind.  (2) Landed with Mr.Clarke and Mr.Stack at Warokaika in the forenoon about 20 miles from Waiopu, where after taking leave of them and procuring a little ballast of pine wood we set sail.  (3) Lord's Day.  The wind blew hard all day and night and quite foul so that we did not advance at all.  (4) Fair wind.  Passed Taranga and the Makia.  Off the point of the Makia we passed a rock a few feet under water under our lee; it lay about 4 miles north east of the southern point of the head and about 5 miles E. by N. of the southern end of the island off the point.  Full thankful to the Lord for guiding me safely thro' these unsurveyed seas.  (5) Sailed a little beyond Cape Turn-again, having fresh breeze off the land.</p>
      <p>Nov.6-7.  (6) Had a foul wind all night and morn. blowing hard, with rain.  Went on deck in the afternoon for two hours, wind then rain, off Flat point.  (7) Wind fair.  Rounded Cape Pallisu<!--sic: Palliser?--> in the forenoon and came to an anchor in Port Nicholson at about 3 o'clock.  This is a beautiful harbour, having deep water and perfectly surrounded, being thus secure from all winds; about 30 natives came on board, among whom was Dick from Waimate.  It appears from their statements that the ship Tory has brought people from England who have bought this harbour, and part of Kapiti &amp;c.&amp;c. for a mere trifle.  We purpose proceeding onward tomorrow to the abode of Rauparaha.  May the Lord be with us.  Pardon O Lord the hardness and deadness of my heart the last few days and wash me from my sins in the blood of Jesus.</p>
      <p>Nov.8-9.  (8) Wind not favourable for leaving this place.  Not at all wild during the night and forenoon, my head very painful.  In the afternoon went on shore for two hours, found some plants which do not grow at the northern part of the Island.  Came on board somewhat better.  Believe this is not Port Nicholson, but that Nicholson harbour is around the next point.  This is, however, a beautiful port.  (9) Suffered considerable pain in my head during the night.  We got under way early in the morn. but as the wind soon headed us we ran away for Cloudy Bay.  We anchored there about one o'clock.  Not being able to beat against a stray wind we did not get into the proper anchorage and a Portuguese who has a whaling establishment came on board a few hours after, and tho' it rained and blew much we got in to a safe anchorage.  We could not form a correct notion of the place from the badness of the weather.</p>
      <p>Nov.10.  Lord's Day.  I rose rather better in health, but not well<!--typescript: "will"-->.  The Rev.H.W. went on then to hold service with a party of natives and English, and after I had had service on board and preached from John III.14.15, I went on shore to the party of English who were with the Portuguese.  It was a miserable place, and the men looked in a deplorable condition spiritually.  They assembled for service to the number of about twenty, and having read prayers I preached from John III.30.  Some appeared attentive and one or two applied for the New Testament.  The wind blew so hard that I and the master of the vessel were detained on shore for two hours; but as the wind abated a little and we had a good whole boat and good hands we put off and after taking some water in we arrived safe on board.</p>
      <p>Nov.11.  Rose early purposing to go to Queen Charlotte's Island to see Col.Wakefield who has been out here purchasing land, but we heard that the Tory had sailed for Taranake.  Went on shore, and find that they have made a kind of nominal purchase of land not having been over it to define boundaries, or having consulted all parties.  Was pleased with the many enquiries for books both native and English, but was unable to supply many.  We got underway in the afternoon, but were obliged to anchor again for want of wind. </p>
      <p>Nov.12.  Weighed anchor early in the morn: but as the wind soon drew ahead, we went into Port Nicholson and anchored there in the afternoon.  Lay in bed all day suffering from pain in my bowels.</p>
      <p>Nov.13.  Determined to leave the Columbine and go over land to Kapiti, the Rev.N.W. and myself started with about 10 natives in the morning; we landed at a small Pa on Richard's (a native from Waimate) ground, and drew a plan of it; saw two native chapels which have been lately built, but which are standing on ground which is now sold: went from there to another Pa and after some conversation with the natives, we had prayers and Mr.W. addressed them, and then went to bed.</p>
      <p>Nov.14.  Suffered all night from a severe attack of asthma which obliged me to sit up in my bed; at the dawn of day I went off to sleep and had rest for about an hour.  I had serious thoughts of returning to the vessel having suffered such extreme pain in the night and feeling very great oppression still in my chest.  But after prayers for divine<!--typescript: diving--> guidance and for strength determined to start on my journey, as I rather feared remaining in Port Nicholson having felt considerable pain in my chest on my former stay there.  We started at 9 in the morning and walked all day with slight intervals of rest thro' a thick and hilly forest.  I suffered much pain in my chest but did not feel tired, and we arrived at a convenient resting place after having crossed 14 rivers at about 4 o'clock, when my tent being pitched and having eaten some potatoes I retired to rest.  I seemed to be supported beyond my expectation all the day.</p>
      <p>Nov.15. Rose in the morn: much refreshed by a night's rest, free from that distressing pain arising from asthma.  Oh how forgetful am I of the manifold mercies I receive and how much the days of health have hitherto exceeded my days of sickness.  Some natives who accompanied us having gone in the evening to Nangarautawiri, a Pa opposite the island of Mana early in the morning some natives arrived from there with food and a message from the chief Rangitakaroro, requesting us to go over to see him and his people, we went there after breakfast, passing thro' a wood for about 3 miles.  It lies on a small point on the shore.  After speeches form the chief and others, in the evening we had prayers and Mr.W. addressed them.  They have for some time been in the habit of having prayers (since the arrival of Richard)  I was much pleased with the disposition of the natives to attend at least externally to divine things.</p>
      <p>Nov.16.  Left the Pa in the morn. and went with the chief in a large canoe with about 60 persons to Mana.  It is an island situated about two miles from the land, about three miles long and two wide, some hundred feet high and quite flat; there are sheep and cattle grazing on it.  The natives of the Pa have lately also had services morn. and even.  The chief however, Rangihaeata is opposed to the gospel.  He is the person who formerly accompanied Rauparaha to the southward in the Elizabeth when acts of the greatest treachery and atrocity were committed by them.  We remained there some hours, and they supplied our natives with abundance of food.  On leaving the chief said that since he had seen Mr. W. he would attend to the gospel.  We left the island in the afternoon in a canoe and went to Hongeoka<!--sic: Hongoeka?--> a small Pa on the mainland about 5 miles from Mana; there were but few natives.  Then I retired early to rest.  The wind blew and it rained hard but my tent was comfortable. </p>
      <p>Nov.17.  Lord's Day.  Rose early in the morn. and after a sweet season of prayer went to Mr.W.'s tent, had prayers and breakfasted there as usual.  We then started to a Pa about 3 miles distantg.  I remained in the Pa.  The natives assembled and George, a Ngapuki<!--sic: Ngapuhi?--> native read prayers and gave a good discourse.  We then had school and I was much delighted with the attention of the natives, and more especially with the earnestness and beauty with which the native christian enforced on his countrymen the blessedness of receiving and believing the precious truths of the gospel.  My soul rejoices in the work in which I have engaged.  Afterwards went to two Englishmen, and had prayers and expounded a chap. to them; they were attentive and well disposed.  Mr. W. had even. prayers and preached, and thus the day closed.  O Blessed look down and prosper Thine Own work. </p>
      <p>Nov.18. Left Hongeoka<!--sic: Hongoeka?--> at 4 1/2 in the morn. and after a rough walk of about 5 miles over to Pukerua where we remained some time with the natives and had breakfast, they were very desirous<!--typescript: disirous--> of obtaining books.  We then proceeded, and passed Poripori, Wainui, Pipapa, Wareroa, Waremoku and Paurui and then arrived atr Waikanae about 5, having walked about 15 miles the latter part of our road being sandy beach.  The natives are at war only acting on the defensive.  They met for prayers as soon as we arrived, when the Rev.H.W. addressed them.  There were near a thousand present.  It was an interesting sight and I lifted up my heart to God with feelings of gratitude, and prayed that His blessing might come down upon them.  Oh may I labour here abundantly to the glory of my God.</p>
      <p>Nov.19.  Rose early.  About 9 o'clok the chiefs began to speak, Noturoa a very pleasing interesting chief of Port N. began and was followed by the old chief of the place Reretaunangawanga, others spoke in succession.  Abot 2 o'clock crossed over to Kapiti to the place where Rauparaha lives.  He was sitting in state ready to receive us.  He certainly looked more like a chief than any man I have yet seen: he listened very attentively to what was said, and <hi rend="underline">appeared</hi> much interested in the gospel message.  He has been one of the most bloodthirsty men in the land; may the Lord have mercy upon him, we had prayers with him and the natives there, and went on board the Atlas for the night, Capt. Murphy's ship, being invited by him.  </p>
      <p>Nov.20.  The wind blew so hard in the forenoon that we could not leave the ship.  Wrote letters to Mr.Wilson Ford &amp; Wade.  In the afternoon went on shore and spent some time with Rauparaha, had but little time for private reading and prayer - not very well.</p>
      <p>Nov.21.  We slept on board and went early to a flat point of land on the island of Kapiti; saw a few natives, met some Englishmen at a Whaling station belonging to Mr.Jones, several of them with the foremen at their head treated us with great insolence.  May the Lord have mercy upon them and give them light - visited another party who were civil and well behaved.  In the afternoon went and saw Rauparaha.  Purpose leaving in the morning.  Had some interesting conversation with a young American.</p>
      <p>Nov.22.  Rose early, had my horses safely brought over in a large canoe to Waikanae: we came across in our boat; after some conversation with the natives went up the river, walked over the ground where the late battle took place among the natives, saw the place where they buried 31 of the Ngatiraukawa - walked for some hours.  There are many acres of land covered with grass, wheat, barley, and oats mixed together, and fine trees.  After prayers with the natives etc. retired to rest.</p>
      <p>Nov.23.  Did not start early to Otaki on account of the rain.  Left Waikanae about 9 o'clock and walked on a sandy beach for about 11 miles, till we arrived at a small Pa near Otaki called Pakakutu, where we stopped on account of the rain, being wet.  There is here a large piece of land, well watered and abounding with wild ducks.  After prayers had some conversation with the chief of the Pa, Ruru and some others; they trace the war to one act of indiscretion on the part of Paul, a wesleyan lad at Waikanae.  Some appear still disposed for war.  The chief, who cannot yet read repeated the even. ch. service, having learnt it orally.  Here they have had no instruction but that of a few volunteer natives.  Oh may the Lord pour out His spirit upon this people, and upon me, that I may come among them with the fulness of the blessing of the gospel of peace. </p>
      <p>Nov.24.  Lord's Day.  We walked with the natives of the small Pa Pakakutu to Rangiuru the large Pa of Otaki and there had divine service.  There were about 600 or 700 present.  I was gratified to see so many present as I had been led to believe that most of the inhabitants of this place were disposed to reject the gospel.  We afterwards had school and I was surprised to find many acquainted with the catechisms we have in use, May the Lord look down to help this people, and may my soul be refreshed with peace and may I be endowed with wisdom to fit me for the work in which I am engaged.</p>
      <p>Nov.25.  Moved from the small Pa to Rangiuru about 9 o'clock.  They do not appear very desirous of peace, they will go tomorrow to arrange about it.  Did not leave the Pa.  Many of the natives here are disinclined to attend to the gospel, some on the other hand are very attentive.  The sons of the chief Watanui, Roha and Haua are interesting enquiring young men, and can read a little.  There were not many present at evening prayers.  Oh may I be directed by the Lord as to where I should reside and how I should proceed.  Increase my love O Lord, and a sense of my dependence on thee, for Christ Jesus' sake.</p>
      <p>Nov.26.  Spent the day at Rangiuru, went about looking for a site for a small cottage to reside in occasionally.  I was pleased with the young men Roha and Haua, they are the most interesting young people I have yet seen.  Felt somewhat discouraged at the apparent apathy of the people; but remembered that as a missionary it is my work to break up barren ground.  Help, Lord!!</p>
      <p>Nov. 27.  Went to two small Pas about 5 miles distant, called Waikawa where there was a small chapel and then on to another about 2 miles distant called Ohau, to endeavour to make peace.  The people here are very ignorant, one man very urgent for a book.  Not very well, retired early to rest.</p>
      <p>Nov.26.  Left Ohau and returned to Rangiuru (about 6 miles) road very good at low water.  Was much interrupted by natives while endeavouring to read in my hut.  Walked out to look for a site for a house, fixed on one that will I think do.  The people here are not very attentive, but few only assemble for prayers.  May the Lord fill me with love and endue me with patience and every grace.  Help me O Lord!  Help me for Jesus' sake!</p>
      <p>Nov.29 &amp; 30  Continued till about 3 o'clock in the Pa, then left the Pa to proceed with the natives towards Waikanae to endeavour to establish peace.  The mob of natives soon joined us.  Having had prayers with them, we left them and proceeded for about 4 miles, when it being very dark and raining we stopped, and having managed to pitch my tent in the sand, Mr.W. and myself lay from about 10 o'clock till three when the mob consisting of about 200 natives with Watanui at their head joined us.  They requested us to have prayers with them.  We then proceeded all together after they had been thro' several native manoeuvres.  They remained about two miles from the Pa.  We entered it and after some speeches, they determined to establish peace.  Matahou was sent out with conditions of peace and the hostile mob returned.  The natives of Waikanae in the afternoon went thro' various military exercises.  Suffered all day from pains in my bowels having caught cold being out at night.</p>
      <p>Dec.1.  Lord's Day.  Received the Lord's Supper with several of our natives.  The congregation both in the morn. and in the even. consisted of about 900.  In the evening they were particularly attentive, when addressed by the Rev. H.W. on the 3 last v. of Matt. gos.  I was much interested with the school.  May the Lord be with me and pour out his spirit upon these people.  </p>
      <p>Dec.2.  Have suffered the three last days with a severe complaint in my bowels, from living entirely upon vegetable food.  Went to Kapiti.  Procured several things from Capt.Mayhew for our trip to Wanganui as the Columbine had not yet arrived.  About 100 natives came in the evening for instruction.  It was on Mr.D's plan from Waimate.  I did not like it.  I shall stop it.  Looked about for a spot for a house.  Help me O Lord.</p>
      <p>Dec.3.  Not well, still suffering from my bowels.  Remained all day at Waikanae.  Walked out with Matahou to look for a place for a house, did not see any suitable place.  Mr.W. addressed the natives (about 900).  Sat up late talking to Mr.W.</p>
      <p>Dec.4.  Still unwell.  Assembled in the chapel and Matahou was baptised by Mr.W. and called Joseph.  He is not well instructed having been a long time from the ministry of the gospel, but is evidently dependent entirely on the blood of Jesus for pardon and his conduct is in every respect consistent with the profession that he makes.  By him undoubtedly as the instrument all the good there is here has been effected.  Witnessed the purchase of some land situated beyond Port N. for natives and also Richard's at Port Nicholson for the use of the mission.  Left Waikanae purposing to proceed to Wanganui as the Columbine had not yet arrived.  Reached Otaki.  Felt very unwell, my bowels much disordered ever since I was out at night with the mob of natives when peace was made.  Went to bed as soon as my tent was pitched.</p>
      <p>Dec.5.  Suffered all night from violent pains in my bowels and asthma.  Went about 3 in the morning to Mr.W's tent and took about 50 drops of laudanum and a little rhubarb.  Felt a little relieved.  Made an attempt about noon to get up but was unwell.  Determined, having no particular object in view not to proceed to Wanganui.  Purpose proceeding when I have books.  Mr. W. left me about 2 o'clock on his way thro' the country.  Continued suffering continual pain all day.</p>
      <p>Dec.6.  Felt rather better this morn: left my tent about 11 and sat with Watanui and his son and wife in the warm sunshine.  Returned and sat in my tent reading etc. for some hours.  Went to evening service.  Very few natives assembled.  Felt cold in returning which was soon followed by violent pain in my bowels.  Took about 40 drops of laudanum and went to bed.</p>
      <p>Dec.7.  Very unwell all day, my bowels in a very painful disordered state.  Took more laudanum and a little rhubarb (the only medicine I have with me)  Remained in bed all day, somewhat annoyed by the ignorant curiosity of natives.  Capt.Mayhew and Brown came to see me.  The wind blew so hard in the night that I was obliged to go out and fasten my tent, was in fear lest it should be carried away.  Have nothing to eat but boiled flour and biscuit and water: nevertheless feel thankful and satisfied.</p>
      <p>Dec.8.  Lord's Day.  Felt somewhat better all day, but unable to move from my bed, somewhat annoyed by the rude noisy behaviour of the natives.  Received a letter from my dear brother Charles of May the 6th, thereby I learned that all were well at home up to that time: felt thankful.  Tho' many vain thoughts distressed, read and meditated upon God's word with delight.  Thought how unworthy the sufferings of this present time are to be compared with the glory that awaits me: felt desirous to pray for the poor people among whom I live and among whom I hope to spend my few remaining days.  O may the Lord bless me and them.</p>
      <p>Dec.9.  Felt much better.  Determined for many reasons to leave Otaki and go to Waikanae.  Started with three natives about 10 and after being some time in the rain and much fatigued I reached it, at least a quiet spot just by.  I had some boiled flour for my dinner, and sat over a fire talking with natives.  Heard that Columbine had just arrived.  Fill my heart with gratitude to thee O my God.</p>
      <p>Dec.10.  Felt better all day but not well - confined to my tent by the rain, read a little and prayed a little - have nothing but boiled flour which does not agree with me.  O may I live soon with my God.</p>
      <p>Dec.11.  Went early to the Pa.  There were some Englishmen there in trouble because having uttered an oath the day before, the chief Witi detained their boat.  The chief would not attend to anything they said but went with me to the Columbine at Kapiti.  Capt. Livingston says that he has met with very bad weather.  Went on shore and looked after my things.  Felt still very unwell: took a strong doze<!--sic--> of castor oil and went to bed on board at about 6 o'clock.</p>
      <p>Dec.12.  Passed a good night, felt better.  Arranged matters and left the Columbine.  As soon as I landed the men came to me and asked me to intercede for the best.  I spoke to the chief and for a slight payment he allowed the boat to go.  Fixed on a spot in the Pa for a site for the Mission.  The natives are civil and disposed to assist me in any manner.  O Blessed may I look up to Thee for help and put my trust in Thee alone.</p>
      <p>Dec.13.  My health a little improved, walked about noon towards Waikanow<!--sic: Waikanae?--> and stopped and talked with several small parties of natives.  Learned that a man had been murdered at Otaki: he was the brother of Joseph and was murdered by Puatara.  Continued a short time in the pa, saw a few preparations for my house.  On account of the extreme heat of the sun went for a few hours into a native house and was covered with vermin.  Felt my soul somewhat drawn towards God in thought and prayers, feel ready to endure anything for the honour and glory of Christ in his service, Tho' dwelling in a tent among these people with whose language I am still unacquainted I would not change my lot with any person in the whole world.  </p>
      <p>Dec.14.  Came early to the Pa and took up my abode within it.  Witi the principal chief (son of the old chief Reretauwangawanga) is extremely civil.  Occupied in various arrangements also in studying the language.  Have mercy O Lord upon my manifold sins and infirmities for Jesus' sake.</p>
      <p>Dec.15.  Lord's Day.  The service was conducted in the morn. by the christian native who accompanied me.  Afterwards we had school.  In the even. I for the first time read the native service.  Simon, a christian native gave me an address from Col.III, 1-3 in a very able manner.  Before service for several reasons I felt rather in low spirits.  A Wesleyan lad Paul had set up an opposition service in the Pa etc. etc. but during the service and even before when I saw the natives crowding to the chapel till many were obliged to stand and many to remain outside, I looked up with thankfulness to the Lord and gave thanks.  Help me O Lord continually.</p>
      <p>Dec.16.  Rose at half past four in the morn: and began school in the Pa after service.  The sight was indeed pleasing.  There were about 180 men and boys engaged in four different classes in learning to write on slates.  We have but four able to teach.  It was indeed interesting to see the old chief Reretauwangawanga beginning to learn to write and read, and others as old.  I have not yet devised a plan for the women.  There were about 150 of them but having not teachers or slates, they were instructed only in the catechisms.  O that I had help here.  I trust shortly to get the school into good order.  Went after breakfast over to Kapiti and brought<!--sic--> more slates.  Old Rauparaha came and attacked me and said that I had forsaken him and carried all my things to the other side.  I gave him a testament and some small books.  He used bad language and intimated to me that if I did not supply all his wants he would not favour the gospel, and that many would be influenced and guided by him; he stated moreover that he would stir up another attack upon Waikanae.  In fact I was much disgusted with him, and must be civil to him on account of his great influence, but I can now see into his character and shall know how far to trust him.  Felt unwell all day.  May the Lord strengthen me.  Paul attended school in the morn. as a teacher.  I said nothing to him but he came afterwards into my tent and asked me for a New Test.  I told him I had something to say to him and spoke to him of the impropriety of his conduct in making divisions.  He said he was willing to join me in everything but that those who went to him for instruction were not.  I told him to consider and speak to them.  In the even. he and they were at service.</p>
      <p>Dec.17.  Went to school before 5 o'clock.  The numbers have increased since yesterday but I have not yet sufficiently ascertained their knowledge to classify them.  Was much pleased and delighted with it.  After breakfast rode to Otaki on the hard sandy beach and carried a few books in my pocket.  Went first to Pakukutu and was very pleased with the chief Ruru to whom I gave a Testament and some small books.  He appeared very grateful.  He is, I trust really drawn to spiritual things.  I then went to Rangiuru and sat for an hour and a half with Watanui and his sons.  I gave him and one of his sons each a book.  I learned from some notes to natives that Mr.W. was at Rangitiki having met a party of natives coming from Taranaki to join their people.  He remained there and persuaded them to return.  I rode back to Waikanae. </p>
      <p>Dec.18.  Did not meet for school in the morn. because of the heavy rain.  Sat in my bare church all day, engaged during the morn. in writing, afterwards in talking to natives and preparing medicines.  Oh may I daily grow in grace and in the knowledge of the Lord my God and of Jesus Christ my Saviour.</p>
      <p>Dec.19.  Attended school at 5 in the morn.  230 adults present - 182 males, 48 females.  Having only 5 teachers these are all that I can manage.  It is an interesting sight to see persons of all ages learning to read the Word of God - the only book they have.  Passed the day principally in attending to the sick and writing and studying the language.  I have felt better in health today and yesterday.  O Lord make me grateful for all thy favours I pray Thee.  Wrote to dear Charles by way of America.  Had a visit from a surgeon living in the neighbourhood.</p>
      <p>Dec.20.  No school on account of the rain.  Enjoyed<!--sic: Employed??--> a considerable part of the day in attending the sick, I fear to little profit as they will not attend to directions.  Not very well - May my soul and body be strengthened by the Lord for the work He may pleased to entrust to me.</p>
      <p>Dec.21.  Attended school in the morn. as usual.  Went after breakfast to Paripari (and also Wainui) and carried books.  It is about 8 miles distant.  The people were very civil.  Attended 2 or 3 sick persons.  Richard's brother I hope will recover.  It is twelve months today since I arrived in N.Z.  Oh how unprofitably I have hitherto spent my time.  Do Thou O gracious God have mercy and compassion upon me and grant that I may live more in communion with Thee and seek grace and strength to enable me to do Thy will.  Bless O Lord thy people among whom I am now come.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
