<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1108">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>27 February 1869: Holmes to Haast.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70510/">Robert Langley Holmes</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>ATL MS-Papers-0037-089, sheet 6.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Dr Haast: 
Transcriptions of selected letters from Robert Langley 
Holmes to Julius Haast between 1864-65 and 1868-70 ", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133C, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-22-5. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133C.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1869-02-27">1869 February 27</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9511/&gt;Sir Julius von Haast">Sir Julius von Haast</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Holmes to Haast, 27-2-1869, ATL MS-Papers-0037-089, sheet 6.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>
Col. Museum </p>
            <p>27 Febry. 69 </p>
            <p>My dear Dr Haast,</p>
            <p>I enclose herewith copy of your earthquake 
paper, as printed for the Transactions. I 
hope it will meet your approval. Only those 
portions, already mentioned, were left out, 
together with a few lines of unimportant matter here and there, kept back so as to allow the 
paper to be printed on the sheet, which it now does, as you see to a letter. A few more words 
or sentences would have necessitated a great deal of extra work and some expense, as the 
Paper closes the Transactions proper. Part III will be Essays, many (5) of them have been 
already been[sic] printed, but 3 (on botany) are 
now in the hands of the printer. After the 
essays comes Colenso’s “Maori 
races” then an Appendix &amp;c. In all about 500 p.p. Your little 
article on the Chathams, and H. Travers long one, are included in the enclosed; also Mr. 
Dobson’s Address, by no means the most uninteresting part of the volume. I think you have 
one of the little maps of Chathams, as lithographed to be appended to these papers, I need 
therefore not send you another.
 Dr Hector sent you a copy of
 your notes (Chatham) but not 
hearing from you when it was ready for the press,
 he concluded that you had nothing further 
to add on the subject, so it was printed off.</p>
            <p>I suppose you have seen Dr Hector on his 
way south, I hope he will
 soon be back here 
again. He will give you all the Wellington news
. I have nothing more to add just now. </p>
            <p>Yours very sincerely 
R L Holmes. </p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>