<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1107">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>28 November 1868: Holmes to Haast.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70510/">Robert Langley Holmes</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>ATL MS-Papers-0037-088, sheets 33 &amp; 30.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "My Dear Dr Haast: 
Transcriptions of selected letters from Robert Langley 
Holmes to Julius Haast between 1864-65 and 1868-70 ", Rowan Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133C, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-22-5. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133C.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1868-11-28">1868 November 28</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9511/&gt;Sir Julius von Haast">Sir Julius von Haast</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Holmes to Haast, 28-11-1868, ATL MS-Papers-0037-088, sheets 33 &amp; 30.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p> 
Colonial Museum </p>
            <p>Wellington </p>
            <p>28 Novr. 68 </p>
            <p>My dear Dr Haast, </p>
            <p>Having an idle half hour in office I devote 
it to you, other I have very little news to 
communicate.</p>
            <p>Dr Hector left for Nelson last Sunday, en 
route for the Interior of that Province, he 
talked however of being back here again in a mo
nth or so; his marriage is to take place in the 
first week of January so I question very much 
if we shall see him before that interesting 
event. It seems possible he may pay Ch.Ch. a vis
it, if his wanderings take him any where near 
the Hurunui. He has however pr
obably told you about his inte
nded movements, the more so 
as you appear to be medita
ting a trip here yourself. </p>
            <p>There is nothing doing whatever in the way 
of meetings of the Phil. Societies, beyond 
the printing of the vol. of Trans
actions which is now in the pre
ss: a day or two ago I corrected 
the first few sheets, which work falls to my lot, altho I refer the proofs to one or other of the 
Governors before the final striking off.</p>
            <p>I think the book will in every way be a success, the type is good and clear, and the 
illustrations very fair; of the latter there will be some 6 or 8 mostly referring to Auckland 
papers of Capt. Hutton’s, geologi
cal, or topographical. A very fair
 view of Rapa to illustrate 
Capt. Vine Hall’s paper has been
 already struck off the stone; Buchanan of course did the 
designing, the govt. lithographer did 
the rest. The printing is let to a private printing firm, and 
the cost will be pretty heavy, but it is uncertain
 how much it will come to yet. There will be 
some 300 p.p. of Royal Octavo, quite a respec
table vol., besides the 5 Exhibition essays which will be bound up with it. The contract for printing binds the firm to complete the whole 
affair before Janry. 31, but another ten days 
or fortnight will be required for binding &amp;c. </p>
            <p>I was directed to write to Mr Fraser a day or two asking, once more
 for the particulars 
of your Society required for insertion in the Proceedings: viz list of office bearers, members 
&amp;c, which information was promptly and fully supplied by the remaining 3 affiliated 
societies long ago. I had to fill in the
 office bearers yesterday as the lists appear in the very 
beginning of the vol., and fortunately I had retained a copy of the 
Lyt. Times
 which contained 
a list of such, but whethe
r correct or not, I can not 
say, it must remain as it is now in any case, 
I hope Mr Fraser will send the me
mbers list before it is too late, 
he appears to ta
ke little or no 
interest in the affairs,
 he ought to take a less
on from Kirk the Auckland Secy. I forgot to say 
that a long essay by Colenso on the Maori races
 will also be appended to the vol., it will 
contain by itself some 100 pages of print. </p>
            <p>We are to become a nation of Soldiers at last
, all classes of militia have been called 
out, and the 1 &amp; 2 are already sworn in, but not 
yet armed[?]. The Govt. get fearfully abused, 
but everyone agrees that the militia 
should have been enrolled long ago
 if only to show the 
savages (the word Maori ought to 
be dropped for the present) that 
we do not yet intend to see 
Carlyle’s satyre carried out here, and have a 
Maori sketching the ruins of Wellington from the 
end of the Queen’s wharf, and the last Pakeha making off through the Heads. It is however by 
no means impossible that the 1st
 Class may be sent to the Front, I rather hope they will, it 
would be a little excitement in these dull times, provided the 
officers are not duffers. </p>
            <p>H. Travers went off to Nelson with Dr 
Hector, under whose wing he will work for a 
while, but be enabled to make collections for himself as well; he proposes to be away for 
about 6 months. Dr Hector is 
enlarging his House considerably, extending the sitting room 
back towards the Museum &amp;c. </p>
            <p>There is to be a small observatory constr
ucted near the Museum at the back, and the 
time ball will be removed there, everything to
 be placed under Dr 
Hector’s charge, the 
meteorological business, has been transferred 
back to this office, as Knowles gave it up, 
when they reduced his screw.</p>
            <p>Mr Travers has taken one of the nices
t houses in Wellington, on the Terrace, near 
Domett’s, formerly Ledger’s, he will remove into
 it from the Hutt in
 about a fortnight, the 
lease of Fitzherbert’s house expiring then. Olliv
ier his clerk, who is liv
ing with me tells me 
he is doing a very good bus
iness, a great deal of 
it being advice of one 
kind or another to all 
parts of N.Z. By the bye Miss T. seems to be a 
very nice girl, no nonsense
 or little exhibitions 
of temper
; I must not however praise up the family to much to you
. Kind regards to Mrs 
Haast. </p>
            <p>Yours very sincerely</p>
            <p>R. L. Holmes.  </p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>