<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1106">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>11 May 1883: Haast to Gore.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9511/>Sir Julius von Haast">Sir Julius von Haast</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Te Papa MU000094/007/0001.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "The Correspondence of 
Julius Haast and James Hector, 1862-1887", Sascha Nolden, Rowan 
Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand Miscellaneous Publication 133D, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-23-2. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133D.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1883-05-11">1883 May 11</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">James Hector</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Haast to Hector, 11-5-1883 Te Papa MU000094/007/0001.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>11/5/83 </p>
            <p>My dear Hector, </p>
            <p>In a letter lately received from Buller, he says “Hector says you have abandoned your 
Moa theory and given in your adhesion to him on this 
quaestio vexata
”. In order not to give 
rise to any misunderstanding, I give 
you a verbatim copy of my answer. </p>
            <p>I fear Hector has somewhat misunderstood me
; what I said was that since I read that 
speech of yours in the Cambridge Maori case 
that a legend about a Pet Moa had been 
accepted by both sides as correct, I had lost my fa
ith in Colenso’s statement, that beyond the 
fabulous account of a Moa with a human 
head etc all the other accounts had been 
manufactured since the Maories had been told
 by the Europeans, that the big bones were 
those of a large bird once inhabiting New Zeala
nd. This as you will see, does not change in 
any degree the evidence of the long extinction 
of the Moa, as shown by me, but proves only 
the fact, that the inhabitants of NZ for long generations past
 have retained an account of these 
large birds which became extinct through their ancestors. However as I wish only truth, I 
shall wait patiently &amp; I have no doubt, that gradually we shall have more evidence to 
establish the former beyond dispute.  </p>
            <p>So far my letter to Buller. I hope you had a 
pleasant trip to the North &amp; are now back 
to your home.  </p>
            <p>Ever faithfully yours </p>
            <p>Julius von Haast. </p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>
