<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1104">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>11 July 1867: Haast to Hector.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9511/>Sir Julius von Haast">Sir Julius von Haast</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Te Papa MU000147/001/0415.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "The Correspondence of 
Julius Haast and James Hector, 1862-1887", Sascha Nolden, Rowan 
Burns &amp; Simon Nathan.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand Miscellaneous Publication 133D, 2012.  ISBN 978-1-877480-23-2. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133D.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1867-07-11">1867 July 11</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/.">James Hector</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Haast to Hector, 11-7-1867, Te Papa MU000147/001/0415.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>
Glückauf</p>
         <p>11/7/67</p>
         <p>My dear Hector, </p>
         <p>I received last night
 your note of the 5
th
 &amp; thought I had told you for what I wanted 
the loan of a skull of 
Din. giganteus
; namely to have our skeleton photographed, but as I 
neither got it or an answer we searched the pieces together &amp; got a tolerably nice skull. Over 
moa I repeat what I told you in one of my letters
, that I am quite willing to let you have from 
my duplicates of Moa bones, what you want. All what I wish is to see 
our colonial
collections, may they be made by A or B as complete and instructive as possible. I have now 
a complete
 set of Owen’s papers &amp; I went to the trouble to have them all bound together &amp; to 
catalogue text (I mean letterpre
ss) &amp; plates. This was the only way to get done. You have 
overlooked to send me the promised fossils from 
the Northern Island. Please to remember it. </p>
         <p>I need scarcely tell you, how thoroughly disheart
ened I am that after all the P. Council 
has not voted the money to build me a Museum. I shall now try to arrange our collections in 3 
rooms in the Government Buildings as well as 
the space will allow it. Also there is no money 
to print my topographical map of the Southern 
Alps or the geological map of the Province. I 
can have both printed at once in Germany, but 
think that it would be wrong to send them 
there before all means to have them printed 
in New Zealand or in England are exhausted. 
What do you think? Both are on a scale of 4 miles to one inch. I intended to have them 
printed in sheets of the same size as those of the Geol Survey of Victoria. </p>
         <p>Concerning the tunnel section 
I am glad that my idea to publish our work together 
pleases you. The following would be a good plan: </p>
         <p>first,
 a small geol. map of the Peninsula, in which all the different 
craters, formations 
etc are shown. </p>
         <p>2) Perhaps a few outlines of the Peninsula as seen from different points of view, so as 
for inst. the outlines of Mt Etna by Sartorius von Waltershausen.
 They can easily 
be taken by photograph. </p>
         <p>3) a short description of the peculiar featur
es of the beds &amp; lavastreams their age etc, 
by which the general character 
of the system of Banks Peninsula can be pointed out. </p>
         <p>4) a few sections in different directions to show the nature, direction &amp; dip of the 
beds.</p>
         <p>5) The chemical part; the last by yourself, 
whilst some of the former can be our joint 
production.  
            This would no doubt form a most interesting 
work &amp; would give no discredit to us in 
N.Z. – only the 
great
 question is; where shall 
the money come from for such a publication as 
the Prov. Chest is empty? Have you funds for such publication in your Department; the 
printing could be done in the Govt. press in 
Wellington I suppose, but the illustrations would 
cost a good deal. </p>
         <p>I had yesterday a long letter of Colenso,
 who is very anxious about his Exhibition 
Maori Essay, I mean to say to see it printed. 
When will you let those unfortunate Essays be 
printed?!</p>
         <p>Mrs Haast who generally has a look at your letters, is rather angry with you, because. . 
. . you have not sent her your kind regards for such a long time, in fact forgotten her 
existence. You may therefore look out for squalls when you are coming again to 
Christchurch. </p>
         <p>I suppose your busy time is now coming, although you will not be able to do much 
actual work with the Assembly sitting. I am just preparing another set of specimens of the 
tunnel for you, which you have not yet got &amp; 
send them by first opportunity, but perhaps I 
shall wait till I have done the last piece in the centre, which will be done in about a fortnight 
&amp; send the lot together. There are some interesting rocks in the centre. </p>
         <p>I shall afterwards go once more over the whole section with the Magnesia light lamp 
so that no mistakes are possible. You have no id
ea how very interesting my European friends 
find this section. I have lots of
 details about dykes etc. Did I 
send you a set of all other rocks 
of the Peninsula? Now take the time if possi
ble &amp; answer my questions &amp; give your ideas 
about my suggestions. </p>
         <p>Ever my dear Hector </p>
         <p>yours very sincerely </p>
         <p>Julius Haast</p>
         <p>Dr Hector FRS</p>
         <p>PS</p>
         <p>Mr Th. Triphook came to ask me if there was any chance of employment in your 
Dept., either in the Laboratory or in the field; 
as he intended to offer 
his services to you. As 
he is a trustworthy &amp; industrio
us man, I think you would not re
gret to give him employ. He 
assisted me sometimes very materially in th
e examination of minerals &amp; has done sometimes 
geological work at home. Hitherto he has been an
 Assistant Surveyor of 
this Govt. but as the 
Survey Dept. has been considerably been curtailed he is now out of employ.</p>
         <p>Yours, JH. </p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>
