<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLKHadfld-0001">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>December? 1858-April? 1859: Kate Hadfield to her parents</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions, spine title "Hadfield, Typescript Miscellaneous Fragments 1833-1897", stamped 19 Dec 1979.  Section: Section: Typescripts of inwards letters extracts + fragments.  "Mrs Hadfield's Diary of journey from Auckland to Whanganui via Waikato &amp; Whanganui Rivers, 1853.  Copied by J.W. Marshall from the originals."  Page 92 of this volume; pages 30-34 of the typescript from which this was photocopied. </p> 
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 10.12.15</p>
         <p>Note states "Handwritten transcript includes copies of Mrs. Hadfield's letters, 1858-59, on their voyage to England, a brief account by Hadfield on his boyhood, and a paper on the work of the early missionaries and the change of attitude by the Maori when they saw that christianity did not stop wars among the white people."  However, these items are not present in this volume.  There is only an extract from what is presumably the 'diary', in the form of letters signed "Your affectionate daughter, Kate Hadfield" - possibly posted separately, or in groups? - accompanied with the following (?author):</p>
         <p>"Notes to Mrs Hadfield's Diary." :</p>
         <p>Mr. Morgan.  A clergyman, and missionary, married Maria Coldham, sister of Mrs Henry Williams <!--Kate's mother, wife of Archdeacon Henry Williams--> --- the 'Aunt Maria' mentioned later.</p>
         <p>Thomas.  T.C. Williams, Mrs Hadfield's brother.</p>
         <p>Baby.  Henry Hadfield, the eldest child.</p>
         	<p>(These are all mentioned at the beginning.)</p>
         <p>Mr Taylor. The Reverend Richard T, missionary at Wanganui.</p>
         	<p>(end of the first journal)</p>
         <p>Mrs McCleverty, wife of Col. Mc.C., G.S.O. in New Zealand</p>
         	<p>(at the beginning of the second journal.)</p>  
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1858----">December 1858-March 1859</date>
                  
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/72040/">Marianne Williams</name>
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/72000/">Henry Williams</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>December? 1858-April? 1859: Kate Hadfield to her parents</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>than Thursday.  Dear Lydia spent Wednesday with us, Octavius had a bad cough so could not go out or we should have gone to Oxford.  However Lydia and I went shopping instead.  We went to Sydney Williams' in Henrietta St.  He seemed very pleased to see us and wanted us to go and dine with him and his wife Kate the next day.  Then we went to call on Miss Byron and we went to Covent Garden Market, Lydia went with us, in the evening.  Sydney sent us some maps and pictures for Henry as a remembrance of our visit to his place.  He is very like his father.  I was sorry not to see Uncle Sydney and Aunt Caroline again but they had not returned home.  On Thursday was the end of our English visit and we went in the train to Gravesend where the "Acasta" had come that morning.  Oh! dear! the sight of the ship made our hearts die within us, but only for a few minutes.  We soon looked across the sea, to our distant home and our precious child, all dear to us, in that far distant land.  We then turned to to<!--sic--> arrange our cabin and by evening had made it look quite respectable.  We have not a stern cabin this time but a comfortable one.  The largest is mine but you must not laugh at my drawing.  We are a small party but I think we shall be comfortable.  I find Miss Cox - the lady who is going out to marry Mr. Baker of Wellington - a pleasant Companion.  Dear baby had a very bad cough in London and we had to call in a doctor.  His name was Dunn and strange enough he asked us if we happened to know Mr. Busby.  Was it not odd?  He knew him very well and asked kindly after him.  The first days on board were bitter cold, for tho' we went on board on Thursday we did not leave Gravesend till Saturday.  On Friday evening the owner's wife came on board and took a great fancy to Baby.  She had little ones of her own and was so distressed that there should be no fire for the dear baby.  She made her husband go on shore and get a stove and had it fixed in the cuddy.  She said she could not go away happy until she knew the dear baby was warm and could have food and warm water when she wanted it, so now we have a beautiful fire and indeed we find it a great comfort.  Baby is as well as we could I think expect, I trust she may be preserved through all the long voyage, dear lamb.  </p>
      <p>Sunday.  We got as far as Sheerness and Tuesday came on to Deal and here we have been ever since.  It is very trying but we know in whose hand we are.  It has been blowing a westerly gale, but last night it was frightful, the night before there was a schooner wrecked and all hands lost.  Friday it has been very calm, but tonight the wind is rising again and they say a little more to the northward and if so I hope we shall soon be off.  I find Miss --- a great comfort, she bears seasickness well; if she only continues we shall do well.  I was very sea sick the first day but since then tho' we have had a great tossing about I have not been the least sick, so now we are all very well we must cheer up and hope for a good voyage.  God has been very good to us hitherto and we may still confide in Him.  I am hoping to see many of you on your arrival and hope to find my dear boy there.   If however anything should have prevented his going, Mrs. Abraham has kindly promised to take charge of him.  I have written to Jane about it, but I know you will do your best to get him to us as soon as you can, so I will say no more about the dear pet.  I had hoped very much to have brought you each some little remembrance of my visit to England but we have spent so much money in travelling and many necessary expenses that I found I could not.  I shall be able to tell you about dear friends which is much better.  And now it is Xmas morning with you and I am wishing you all<!--sic-->, and I must go to bed.</p>
      <p>Your affectionate daughter  </p>
      <p>Kate Hadfield.</p>
      <p>Ship Acasta.  Long. 20 E. Lat 30 S.  February 11. 1859.</p>
      <p>This is dear Papa's birthday, and as I cannot spend it with you in person my thoughts will be with you.   It is a great happiness to think each morning and evening that we are so much nearer to you all and my dear child.  If I may but see him soon how thankful I shall be.  I try not to set my affections on him too much, but this is always difficult.  We have been brought thus far on our way in safety and have many ...... mercies to be thankful for.  I wrote to you from Deal where we were anchored nearly a fortnight.<!--previous editor's note: (?) --> It was very cold and if we had not had a fire we should have been very miserable.  We both came on board with bad colds and dear baby very unwell.  Baby's cough continued very obstinate for several weeks all through the hot weather.  At one time she was so ill that we hardly thought she would reach the end of the voyage and there being no doctor on board made us very anxious, but our Heavenly Father has in mercy to us blessed the means used for recovery, and she is now beginning to look quite herself again and I trust we may all be permitted to reach our journey's end in safety.  Henry has been very well all this time.  The first few weeks Octavius and I were both very unwell with cold and fever.  I think we must have caught the influenza in London.  Many people were suffering from it when we left London.  I was getting much better when we sailed from Deal but unfortunately that morning I went on deck to see the ships.  It was such a splendid sight.  There were 500 sail, the Captain said, beside steamers, all of whih had been detained like ourselves by the wind.  It was a sight worth seeing tho' I paid dearly for it, for I caught cold again and was quite ill with fever for nearly three weeks.  I have not suffered from seasickness this time and on the whole am as well as I could expect tho' I feel very weak and long as you can fancy to be once more at home again.  We have found the nurse we got for baby a very valuable assistant.  She is a very respectable and religious woman of about 38 and has taken great care of the dear little pet.  She has not been ill and though often sick in the rough weather still she always nurses dear baby well.  Thus you see we have all our wants supplied.  Dear little Annie, she is cutting her teeth.  She cut her first about two weeks ago and three more are nearly through and now she can put up her little mouth to kiss and shakes her little had and says "ta-ta".  These are all her accomplishments at present.  We are now out of the tropics and very glad to get into cooler weather tho' it is not very much yet.  Still we feel the change.  We often talk about the time for our landing and wonder what day it will be.  Last Sunday they said we might easily do it in eight weeks, which would be the 3rd. April, the day we went on board the "SouthernCross" last April.  I find it does not do to let the mind dwell too much on the end of the voyage; it makes me feel impatient.  I allow myself to think of it more on Sunday than any other.  Octavius has service on Sunday morning at 11 o'clock which is very pleasant.  We have not had an opportunity of writing to England but we spoke to an American brig last week, so that they will see by the paper that we were safe so far.  It was so nice to have another vessel so close to us.  We have come on very well tho' slowly.  We have passed every vessel that we have seen.  I think I told you that we were nearly taking our passages in the "Alfred the Great".  The Captain asked her name twice and could not quite hear, tho' others said they heard she was from London and bound for Port something.  When she heard this was the "Acasta" she asked no more questions beside "How many days have you been out?"  The Captain says he feels sure it was her.  We are rather anxious to know whether it was.  We shall not know now till we get to Wellington - poor things!  If it was her I pity the poor passengers so much and feel thankful that we were led to think she was not a fit ship for us.  She is larger than this but we did not like her or her Captain.  I think I must leave off now.</p>
      <p>Wellington, April 13. </p>
      <p>Here we are once again safe in Wellington.  We have been preserved through dangers, seen and unseen, and I trust are truly thankful.  I have hardly time to collect my thoughts yet but must have a few lines ready for the "White Swan".  You will quite be able to fancy the happy meeting we had with our darling child and brothers and sisters and dear Uncle; besides many of our dear friends.  There is one cloud that makes me feel sad it is poor Hutton's failing health and the absence of himself and dear Sarah and family from among us.  I cannot fancy the Hutt without them.  It was however a relief to us to find on landing to hear that they were at the Bay instead of what this pilot told us - gone to England.</p>
      <p>Wednesday night.  I have tried in vain to write today; such crowds of people in this house.  Our bedroom has been the reception rook for the family party and so much to talk about.  We have been trying hard to persuade Henry and Jane to remain this trip of the "White Swan" but I shall not know till the morning the result.  You will I know excuse this hurried letter.  I am now writing on the floor in our bedroom.  Everyone is gone to bed as they wish to be up early to go to see the "White Swan" off, as soon as I can at all collect my thoughts I will write a long letter.  At present I am not quite myself ...........</p> 
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
