<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0050">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1845 January 10: Octavius to Octavia Hadfield</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  Page 111.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 30.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1845-01-10">1845 January 10</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/3619/">Wellington</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key=" http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70767/">Octavia Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1845 January 10: Octavius to Octavia Hadfield</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Wellington, </p>
      <p>New Zealand.</p>
      <p>Jan. 10th. 1845</p>
      <p>My dear Octavia,</p>
      <p>I had the pleasure, the day before yesterday, of receiving a long and kind letter from dear George, dated July 19, which gave me considerable satisfaction, as he gives a tolerably good report of you all.  My last letter was in November, addressed to Maria.  A Cowes Cutter having just come in here on her way home from Hobart-town, I gladly avail myself of the opportunity of writing though I cannot give a very good account of myself &amp; fear my writing will be scarcely legible as I am writing in bed.  </p>
      <p>Since I last wrote, from Waikanae, I have been almost wholly confined to my bed; occasionally for a few days suffering rather acutely, at other times, more easy. I was removed last week to this place; my friends here not thinking it proper that I should remain alone any longer. The Rev. R. Taylor from Wanganui came to entreat me to go to his house &amp; remain there, &amp; my friend Mr. St. Hill came at the same time, but the latter prevailed on me to move; &amp; I was carried by my natives on a litter through the woods &amp; arrived here safely. I am now in my old quarters with my very kind friends.  I am grieved to say that Mrs. St Hill has been latterly a severe sufferer, though now doing very well.  A few weeks ago she was confined (for the first time) she suffered extremely for two days, but by the blessing of God, through the assistance of our two very able medical men, her life was preserved; her infant of course was sacrificed.  She is in a delightful frame of mind.  I should not of <!--sic--> come here so soon, but she sent her husband to me with a positive injunction not to return without me with him, so I was obliged to consent &amp; come.  </p>
      <p>As I have been seen by three very able medical men &amp; their opinion is that I can do no more work I am perfectly easy on that score &amp; do not allow myself to be anxious about my late charge. While we have health &amp; strength we are bound to devote them to the service of God, for they are His gifts; when deprived of them, we may be easy, knowing that nothing is required of us. I have prayed for guidance lately, but do not exactly know what to do; I do not much like being burdensome to my friends here (though I know they do not think me so), &amp; if I remain as I am I shall move by &amp; by into some little cottage in the neighbourhood. I have sometimes thought of trying to see you again; but when I asked the Dr. concerning the probability of my reaching England alive, I thought he rather evaded a direct answer, and I concluded that it would not be advisable to try: there will however be a <supplied>[fine?]</supplied> ship (having a surgeon on board) sailing in about one month, &amp; I might attempt it, though I do not think it probable that I shall. Nothing can exceed the kindness of all here towards me. I could find plenty of homes here if I needed them. I had a few days ago a very kind letter from Mrs. Selwyn asking me to go to their house at Auckland, &amp; promising to nurse me herself. I expect also to see the Bishop in a few days; but I shall not avail myself of their kind invitation.</p>
      <p>I can scarcely tell you the nature of my complaint, and the Dr.s do not tell me themselves; but I have found out from others what their opinion is: but it is very difficult to be positive. It is however, a large artery, near the heart, that is out of order &amp; diseased, &amp; for this I know very well that there is no remedy. I know that I may die any day very suddenly. The disease will reach a certain point &amp; then the artery will open &amp; life consequently will be extinct in a few minutes. When this may occur, God only knows. Now that I am doing nothing, eating very little, &amp; almost continuously in a quiet state &amp; in a recumbent posture, I feel but little pain &amp; may go so for some time, and may indeed even improve a little. I hope my honesty in telling you all this will not make any of you uncomfortable about me.  You know that for some years I have professed to be only a pilgrim upon earth &amp; to be awaiting an admission into my heavenly home.  Why then, when my admission into the glorious mansions of my Heavenly Father appears to be drawing near should any of you grieve at the thought, or wish for a moment to detain me here.  I know that we are all far too worldly, our faith is not sufficiently to us "the substance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not seen".  But I can truly say now that I wish to be "absent from the body and present with the Lord" - that "I have a desire to be with Christ which is far better".  I have had during the last year my faith considerably awaked, &amp; my apprehension of divine things much enlarged, much to my comfort.  I have been led to think much more concerning the divine attributes, &amp; seem to have become more <hi rend="underline">acquainted with God</hi>.  Oh for the glorious period when I shall know Him &amp; love Him perfectly!  &amp; thus knowing that He is "<hi rend="underline">my God</hi>" I feel that <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the <hi rend="underline">Divine attributes</hi> are secured for my protection &amp; salvation according to the terms of God's gracious covenant with his elect in Christ, their Living Head.  I therefore rejoice with "joy unspeakable and full of glory".  You are too well acquainted with the glorious Gospel of the grace and love of God to mistake my meaning or I would not write as I do - you now, when I rejoice at the prospect of death, &amp; look forward to an <hi rend="underline">immediate</hi> admission into my Fathers presence, that I am not mistaking my ground or resting on false hopes.  No, while I now write I feel as strongly my sinfulness - my guilt - my folly - my rebellion - my ingratitude &amp; my desert of hell as ever I did - nay more so but these in no degree shake my confidence; I know &amp; feel that God has loved me eternally &amp; must love me eternally - for He changes not - in His Son, even in Jesus Christ.  I know that though I am the most sinful of His creatures - &amp; how little do I know of my own sinfulness in comparison to what I really am in the sight of a holy God - that in Christ I am accepted &amp; beloved.  Oh the unspeakable blessedness of having the Triune God, the Father, the Son, the Holy Ghost, for <hi rend="underline">my God</hi>.  I cannot explain to you the love &amp; gratitude I feel towards God for giving me latterly so much time to reflect &amp; consider &amp; to grow more intimately acquainted with His incomprehensible love.  I seem to long to reach Heaven that I may know Him &amp; love Him better.  I feel deeply grieved when I think what a poor unprofitable creature I have been - what a poor unfaithful minister, not in declaring divine truth that, I believe, I have always done, tho' imperfectly, but in saving sinners &amp; seeking them out: but I feel that my sins are utterly obliterated by the blood of Christ.  I feel very happy in one respect; that I have not the least wish to live under the impression that I could be of any use, or that my loss will be felt by my dear people, such a thought has never entered my head, &amp; if it should when I grow weaker I shall not allow it to trouble me.  I feel that I have been made by God, His instrument in doing a little good, &amp; I do feel that however imperfect my endeavours to glorify Him &amp; benefit His church have been, that I have this consolation that I have not been occupying any ground to the exclusion of a better or more efficient man, that, humanly speaking if I had not been here nobody would.  I am not at all anxious about the future prospect of these people, it is God's concern &amp; I will not encroach on His prerogatives.  (Do you, however, continue to pray that His blessing may rest here).  I never had much strength; &amp; I am sure neither you nor I can regret the way in which I have spent it, that is, in coming to this country, however I may lament that my exertions have not been greater.  How could any of us have expected when I came to this country, how in an hour of need, I should be surrounded with kind friends &amp; possessing as many comforts as I could possibly have in England.  I have nothing to trouble me in my affairs - such as they are - in all matters, I have destroyed always any letters &amp; papers that I cared about &amp; given instructions about everything, so you need not have any kind of anxiety about me.  You may continue to write if you like because any letters will either be destroyed or sent back.  Notwithstanding all that I have said, I <hi rend="underline">may</hi> life on for some time, may get a little better &amp; <hi rend="underline">may</hi> try &amp; reach you... George tells me that Alexander was shortly to be married, I am very glad to hear it.  Pray give him my most hearty congratulations, &amp; wishes for his happiness, &amp; also to his wife, (G. does not tell me any Christian name).  Give my kindest remembrances to all friends especially the Warrens etc. etc.  Give my most affectionate love to my Father, Mother &amp; all my brothers &amp; sisters - Believe me, my dear sister, ever your most affectionate &amp; attached brother.    
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
