<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0020">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1839 March 7: Octavius Hadfield to his father Joseph</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960. "Letter 44." (page 39)</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 23.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1839-03-07">1839 March 7</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70864/">Waimate</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70741/">Joseph Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1839 March 7: Octavius Hadfield to his father Joseph <!--Previous editor's note: Letter 44. To Mr. J. Hadfield-->
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Waimate</p>
      <p>New Zealand.</p>
      <p>March 7th. 1839</p>
      <p>My dear Father,</p>
      <p>I much regret that I have not yet heard from you, tho' I am thankful that I have heard of you.  Since I wrote, which was on the 4th. of Jan. via Sydney (I now write direct) to my mother, I have received a letter from George dated July, &amp; one from Caroline of August.  I have also received two, one from my mother of March, &amp; one from Amelia of April which had been sent on during my stay in Sydney and forgotten.  I am glad that the news these letters contain is for the most part good.  I was sorry to hear that my mother had been suffering from the influenza.  I trust to hear again soon and to hear of your welfare.  It is, believe me, a great comfort to hear from you.  I was ordained by the Bishop at Paihia on the 6th. of Jan, &amp; a few days after I came here.  It is about 16 miles from the Bay, at leat from the missionary stations, which is Paihia.  When you read of the grog shops &amp; all the eveils in the Bay of Islands you must be told that they are at Kororadika 3 miles from the missionary station on the opposite side.  There has been, I believe, much said lately in England concerning N.Z. much of which, for I have seen some of the evidence given before the House of Lords, is the greatest imaginable nonsence<!--sic-->, both with respect to the Natives &amp; the country lands etc.  The land generally is very bad tho' there be some very rich spots.  I have moved a little here &amp; I should say that there are one thousand acres of bad to one of good.  I fear the emigrants will be much disappointed.  The country is beautiful certainly, &amp; the climate good tho' it felt very cold to me for a few weeks after leaving Sydney which is curious as there is so little difference in latitude, that being 33' 53' &amp; Waimate 35' 30'.  Indeed, tho' when I came the sun was almost vertical at midday I was glad to sit by the fire in the evening, but this may be accounted for I now find inasmuch as this place is at least 1000 ft. above the level of the sea.  I am residing with the Rev. William Williams.  They have had a room built for me at one end of the house which opens on to the verandah so that I am quite independent of the house, &amp; only enter it to get my meals unless I feel inclined for company.  They are very kind to me.  They are, I suppose, the best educated &amp; most respectable people in the land; so far I am very fortunate.  </p>
      <p>Soon after my arrival here I had a very pleasant trip which I must not forget to mention.  There is a station formed at Kaitaia where there are two laymen residing, Mr. Matthews &amp; Mr. Puckey who have married the daughters of Mr. Davis.  The station, I believe, is the most prosperous of any in the land.  It has been formed above 5 years, but as there is no clergyman it is necessary to visit them at least once in six months for the purpose of baptising &amp; administering the Lord's Supper.  So Mr. W.W. was going there for this purpose &amp; as I had nothing to do, (as it was holiday time with the boys) I went with him.  It is 54 miles from this <supplied>[place]</supplied> &amp; 34 miles is thro' a very thick forest where daylight is scarcely visible more than only 3 or 4 times.  The road thro' the wood was cut about a year ago by Mr. Mathews with a party of 70 natives, which occupied them a month.  The road is very rough, so much so that a horse can scarcely climb up some of the hills, &amp; I suppose I was obliged to dismount 150 times in that distance.  The forest is about 10 miles from this; we reached it about 12 o'clock, accompanied with several natives on foot who carried our tents &amp; a <supplied>[pan]</supplied> for each of us &amp; some food, &amp; at six o'clock when we stopped to sleep for the night we had only entered <!--blank--> miles.  There I gathered some fern leaves for my bed &amp; pitched my tent, &amp; having spread a piece of painted canvas over them to obstruct the dampness &amp; placed my blankets in order I slept comfortably, after having had supper which the natives prepared, having quickly lighted fires.  The next day we proceeded twenty miles further thro' the wood &amp; again slept in it &amp; on the following afternoon reached Kaitaia to my great delight as I was very tired, not having had much horse or foot exercise for some time.  However the beauties of nature which I saw in the forest amply compensated for any fatigue during my journey, laying aside the object of my journey, which did so abundantly.  I will not attempt to describe nature in its most beautiful appearance &amp; form for I am quite unequal to it.  Nothing lies more out of my line.  I am totally at a loss in attempting it, but I will leave you to imagine it who are not unacquainted with such scenery, after stating a few facts.  The celebrated Kauri trees whih are so famous for spars were magnificent.  I alighted from my horse to measure one by the roadside.  It was exactly 30 feet in circumference (I am speaking accurately) about 5 feet from the ground &amp; perfectly smooth &amp; circular; it was in perfect health &amp; vigour.  I could not measure the height to the first branch but I considered it about 80 feet, tho' Mr. W. said 100, &amp; then I should think it was at least 32 feet.  This was a splendid tree but there <supplied>[are]</supplied> many almost as large.  The flowering shrubs &amp; creepers were abundant and beautiful &amp; as Mr. W. who knew the names was kind enough to amuse me I was highly delighted.  There was one high hill, the highest point of land in this part of New Zealand called Mangotoniwa, a short distance from the road.  We left our horses &amp; climbed to the top.  Here the view was magnificent, we could see about 50 miles in every direction.  I cut a Myrtle upon the summit, the highest point, which I will if I can send to you on some occasion - but I must leave you to imagine the rest.  Mr. W. was busily employed at Kaitaia examining natives whom he purposed to baptise &amp; I was amusing myself by visiting Christian natives with Mr. Mathews &amp; looking at the country.  We continued there about 10 days.  Mr. &amp; Mrs. Mathews were very civil to me &amp; wish me to pay them another visit.  It was most pleasing to see so many natives there who had received the gospel, men who 5 years ago were the most savage in N.Z. &amp; who, I am told, looked ferocious beyond measure, &amp; thought nothing of murdering anybody they met with &amp; devouring them, now possessed calm placid countenances &amp; were "sitting at Jesus' feet clothed &amp; in their right minds".  On the Lord's Day I was almost overcome during Divine Service which is held in a large rush building; there were about 400 present.  There would have been many more but they were suffering from influenza.  Mr. W. baptised 59 adults &amp; about 20 children, all of whom he had previously examined &amp; of whom Mr. P. &amp; Mr. M. spoke highly.  Afterwards the Lord's Supper was administered to about 50 other natives.  I assisted Mr. W. in presenting the cup &amp; in pronouncing the words in N.Z. language.  It was, I can assure you, something to cheer me.  When we left Kaitaia Mr. &amp; Mrs. Mathews returned with us, however Mr. W. &amp; I the last day left them, &amp; rode 30 miles &amp; got to W's.  I was on horseback 11 hours, but was not at all fatigued having got used to exercise.  I hope I am not wearying you with my stories, excuse me if I be.</p>
      <p>I am now engaged in the school.  My work is very easy &amp; light; there are 32 boys, some well disposed &amp; anxious to improved.  Mr. W. takes the school three days in a week &amp; I the other three.  I am in it six hours during the day.  I have nothing more to do with it at any other time.  My other time therefore is presently my own, tho' as soon as I have acquired the language I can employ it in missionary labours.  There is an assistant in the school, a son of Mr. King's; my work therefore is light enough.  I preach twice on the Sunday to a congregation including the boys, workmen etc. of about 60.  But tho' my work is thus easy etc. I cannot continue long in it.  Tho' there is much that pleases me in it, there is much that displeases me.  The persons engaged in the mission are for the most part ignorant men who have been advanced beyond their proper station in life, &amp; consequently presume upon it.  They likewise, never having possessed any property, think it very fine to buy large estates of land at a very low prie &amp; have cattle &amp; wheat et.  This grieves me to the heart.  I am persuaded the Lord is working even by such instrument but I mourn to see such worldly mindedness in persons who have professedly given themselves entiredly to God's service.  The consequence of all this is that at East Cape &amp; Poverty Bay the natives are very desirous of missionaries &amp; are very numerous, there being several thousand at each (the whole population I conceive of this Island to be 100,000), but the old hands are tied to their lands etc.  I am consequently determined that as soon as I can acquire the language (of which at present I know nothing), to go there if possible.  My mind has been always set on missionary work &amp; here I have no prospect of any.  I will not build upon another man's foundations but will go among the heathen.  I am, however, daily expecting the Rev. Mr. Taylor, &amp; then something will be decided upon.  I do not think I am much liked here - they are rather afraid of me.  My coming with the Bishop etc. makes them a little cautious, neither do they like my preaching.  However I never felt more happy &amp; comfortable &amp; I believe one or two are differently disposed towards me.  They are all, however, very kind &amp; civil &amp; what is very ridiculous fancy me a clever fellow!! They are what I call low in doctrine &amp; low in discipline, but I now stand here as a minister of Christ, &amp; like Elijah of old I trust thro' God's help fearless of consequences to speak my mind freely where duty calls for it.  I sometimes wish I had some of you out here.  Here is a fine country &amp; plenty of room; I would then get a house to myself.  There is no moving here without a horse, &amp; they are very expensive &amp; very bad, however I shall soon be obliged to buy one.  It luckily costs nothing to keep it.  I must now close this.  I trust tho' you may not be able to read this, some of them will read it for you.  I do not know what postage you may have to pay for my letters, but they cost me nothing from you, so I hope you will all write very often.  I get them very regularly by the post, much better than any other way.  Messrs. Campbell &amp; Co. are my agents in Sydney.  Give my kind regards if you please to all my friends high &amp; low, I have not room to mention names.  Give my love to my dear Mother &amp; all my brothers &amp; sisters both present &amp; absent, I pray for you all daily &amp; find much pleasure in doing so.</p>
      <p>Believe me, ever, my dear Father,</p>
      <p>Your affectionate son,
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      <p>P.S. You must not <hi rend="underline">let Mr. Coleman know anything that I say</hi> about N.Z. for it will all come out here again.  They knew my sentiments etc. before I came from more than one quarter.  I am sorry Henry is gone so far away from you, send my love to him &amp; Charlotte.  O.H.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
