<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0071">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1849 February 28: Octavius Hadfield to his brother Lieut. Charles Hadfield</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  "Letter 10".  Page 197.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 8.12.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1849-02-28">1849 February 28</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/3619/">Wellington</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70819/">Charles Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1849 February 28: Octavius Hadfield to his brother Lieut. Charles Hadfield</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Wellington N.Z. Feb. 28 1849</p>
      <p>My dear Charles,</p>
      <p>I have already written to my mother &amp; Henry by the ship which will also take this, but as I am sure you will like to have a letter from me also, &amp; I do not know when I will have another opportunity of sending a letter direct, I will not delay until I have something new, but write at once,.  I have to thank you for your letter of April which I received some time after it was written but which was not the less acceptable on that account.  I was gratified to hear by some later letters from home that you had obtained promotion, at which I rejoice, &amp; on account of which I beg to congratulate you, as it will doubtless make your position more pleasant, both as giving you increased means, &amp; enabling you to remain on shore, &amp; when you do go to sea, do so in a more convenient manner.  Though your views have materially changed on religious subjects, since you entered the profession you are now in, still you must feel that in these times it is quite necessary that the defence of the nation should be strengthened by honest men determined to do their duty both in the army &amp; navy.  We cannot like war, but in the present state of the world, the question is not put to us whether we will have it or no, but whether we will maintain our national existence against the encroachments of other nations.  May God continue to bless you, &amp; give you comfort, &amp; enable you to serve Him if it be His will, in that line of life in which you are.  I have heard more of my sister from home than from you; I hope she will next time you write honour me with a note.  Your little girl also appears to be a great favourite at Ventnor.  </p>
      <p>I have already related to my mother how my health has been, by God's blessing, improved by a new mode of treatment; I shall now only further add that my present improvement is wonderful; &amp; from being almost confined to my bed (quite, I may say, for I only rose for an hour most days to have my room refreshed) I can now walk two or three miles in the course of the day.  If it should please God that I should sufficiently recover my strength to be enabled to go to work, I trust I may do so earnestly &amp; energetically tho' with prudence, for I have not abated one whit of my desire to praise God &amp; cause Him to be praised among this people.  I have learnt many lessons during my sickness, I trust tho' I have many more to learn.  I have learnt to love Him more &amp; to love my fellow men more.  And I think all my views on religion have become more profound &amp; more enlarged.  The Bible seems to me full of meaning; I seem to be unable to read much of it; I am stopped every moment with the beauty  &amp; depth of some passage.  I seem to have reflected- turned my thoughts more into my inner being- to have become more conscious of our being &amp; of the being of God, ever present revealing himself to my soul, than I used to be: I seem to realize more than ever the meaning of "walking with God" &amp; of worshipping Him "in spirit &amp; in truth", &amp; to feel that it is not so much I who have life as "Christ Who liveth in me" Who sustains my life by His life, not figuratively, but really &amp; in truth.  Still tho' such is the condition of the spirit, &amp; I cannot doubt it, the affections- the desires- the appetites are not always so obedient &amp; so thoroughly subjected to the spirit as they ought to be; but even in this respect I shall be enabled to triumph over them thro' Christ strengthening me.  God's will is the supreme will &amp; only absolutely holy will, &amp; each being, who is a free agent, is holy in proportion as his will is brought into conformity with the Divine will, but the Divine will is revealed to us by the light of conscience &amp; by the written word: what we want therefore is God's spirit to work in our spirit a conformity of will to His will; now this He effects under different dispensations, &amp; under affliction or bodily suffering this is frequently done.  The process seems to be to get an assurance that Christ is the full &amp; perfect &amp; sufficient atonement for all, our sins; this gives us a sense of God's readiness to receive us &amp; acknowledge us as His children: then a conformity of will to His: from these flow peace with Him, &amp; peace too, in our own conscience-"our heart condemns us not", &amp; thence also joy, hope et.  And then we can show forth the praise of God, we can be a light to the world, &amp; a comfort to our brethren.  May I ever grow in grace &amp; in conformity to the Divine Image.</p>
      <p>The Bishop is now anxious that I should become the head of the proposed new College in this district, if my health should enable me to do anything of the kind, &amp; he thinks I shall not be strong enough for missionary work.  He says "It would be too much to expect that you should be able to resume the active habits of a missionary for which your strength was never adequate; but I think that I know your mind sufficiently to feel assured that you will dedicate your returning health to such employment as is nearest to the missionary work.  I would point to the Porirua College as a post in which your influence would be brought to bear on all those in whom you are most interested without much bodily fatigue.  If you will consent to find head &amp; heart for the new college, I will do my best to provide you with arms &amp; legs."  A personal superintendance of the whole is what the Bishop means; I do not think he intends that I should immediately be confined to mere tuition,.  The establishment will consist of English boys &amp; natives, &amp; also young men who are candidates for holy orders.  It would be a useful post, but I do not think my strength would be equal to it, nor my education either, at least so as to do it to my own satisfaction.  Nor am I quite sure that if I were very closely associated with the Bishop I should agree with him so well as I do at a little distance.  Still, supposing my health will not allow me to return to my old station,-Otaki, I do not know how better I could employ myself: at present, however, I am against <supplied>[it]</supplied>, but it will be some time before the College can be begun &amp; proceeded with.  May God continue as He always previously has, to direct &amp; guide me; &amp; may I be found ready to obey His will- to go whither He may send me.  He wishes also to make me Archdeacon of this district, but I must decline it from a deep sense of my unfitness for any higher office than what I now hold.</p>
      <p>I suppose you may have sometimes thought of ordination, have you?  I think at times that every intelligent Christian ought to look forward to it, so that those who <supplied>[are]</supplied> in the different walks of life may after various services in the world bring their experience of the Christian life to benefit their brethren.  I am afraid the Bishop would require Latin &amp; Greek for priest's orders, but he does not absolutely require a knowledge of them for deacon's orders, &amp; there is much to be done here in that capacity both among natives &amp; whites.  Our Bishop wants men who will work &amp; though a high-church man in many respects is by no means prejudiced against what are called encyclical doctrines, &amp; himself brings forward justification by faith alone with great power &amp; clearness, &amp; is a very good man.  He is a very hardworking man &amp; expects others to work as hard &amp; be as devoted to their work as he is.  I do not know why I mention this subject, but it has frequently crossed my mind in reference to you.  I have written to Harry about coming here to settle,.   Perhaps you may come by &amp; by, &amp; then you might judge for yourself whether what I have hinted at might be possible.  In the mean time may God direct you in all things.  </p>
      <p>I have been surprised to find that many good people in England are under an impression that the N.Z. mission is not prospering, this is an erroneous one; I believe things never prospered better here.  Unfortunately the vessel carrying the account of our last annual meeting in London was lost so I did not see any account of it.  The truth is, the progress of a work like this is not very manifest from month to month, or even from one year to another, but every slight &amp; temporary interruption of a forward motion must not be regarded as a retrograde one.  And as to the wars which occurred in this country they originated through the mismanagement of the government &amp; the misrepresentations of the N.Z. Company chiefly, &amp; were forced upon the natives; but very few if any respectable Christian natives were led into them, &amp; the greater part who stood aloof were more strengthened in their faith &amp; their profession by beholding the evils practiced, &amp; evils which resulted from them.  I am very happy that so good &amp; energetic a man as Mr. S. Williams<!--previous editor's note: check if S. or J. Williams-->, son of Henry Williams is occupying my old post; he does his work well &amp; the natives appreciate his labours.  They are getting on well at Otaki with the church, for which I began making preparations five years ago, it is the finest native building in the country, &amp; is much admired by all.  I hope, God willing, to be able to visit it before very long, but must attempt nothing for some time to come.  Their persevering exertions in reference to this speak well for them, as they might obtain good wages on the government works and so on, but they prefer working for nothing on their church.  We are also going to have, by &amp; by, a better schoool-room, there are more than 150 children in daily attendance at the school at Otaki alone, &amp; Williams tells me they go on well.  We are anxious to get a young man, a son of Mr. Baker, one of our old catechists, to live at Otaki, &amp; take daily charge of it, Williams &amp; I managing to support him; I think we shall succeed in this.  It is absolutely necessary among a people like this to endeavour, while they become Christians, to elevate their social position, to enable them to hold a respectable position.  It is difficult to convey this notion clearly to people who have no experience of missionary work, but there can hardly <supplied>(be)</supplied> two opinions on the subject among those who have been accustomed to the work.  Until they have made some outward improvement, it is improbable that they can send their children to school, because there are no means of feeding or clothing them, &amp; nothing can proceed with regularity; but as they advance in outward improvement, provided they are imbued with christian principles, they manage to find these, &amp; are glad to see their children attend regularly at schoool.  And the contrast between those places where some pains have been taken with them &amp; those places where they have been left to their own native habits is very striking.  They have at Otaki a good many decent houses &amp; barns, &amp; have already a good many horses &amp; cows; &amp; cultivate wheat to a great extent, more than sufficiently to supply all their own wants; they have the machinery for a good water-mill &amp; are only now delayed in its erection by their being occupied on the church.  The instability among them has also, I feel very happy to say, been on the decrease since these improvements have been introduced among them.  I think personally that there has existed a greater degree of confidence among most people here as to the prospect of ultimately benefiting &amp; civilising the natives, since the improvements which I began at Otaki &amp; which have been since well carried out, have proceeded so well- people begin to think that their case is not hopeless- Sir G.Grey &amp; others are very sanguine about them; if there were no other result from this attempt of mine, I should be delighted that I made it.  And in fact, it goes hand in hand with the more immediately missionary work.  I am not aware they ever spent two whole day's allocation on these subjects, but a few words of encouragement, - the present of a little seed-wheat purchased for them which they valued more for my sake than for itself- a few instruments of husbandry- led to these results.  I cannot but feel pleasure when I consider how much these people still value &amp; respect my opinion on all subjects.  May I be anxious to improve any influence so acquired to the glory of God.  To overcome all selfishness &amp; live for God &amp; our fellowmen if our great practical business, but how difficulty to acquire, at least to realise, in our society &amp; daily experience.  And now, my dear Charles, I must close this long letter.  I trust it will put you in peace.  Pray give my love to my sister &amp; your little son.</p>
      <p>&amp; Believe me,</p>
      <p>Ever your affectionate brother
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      <p>I have not time to read it over, so excuse my blunders.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
