<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0064">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1847 August 15: Octavius Hadfield to his sister Maria</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  "Letter 16"  Page 165.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 7.12.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1847-08-15">1847 August 15</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/3619/">Wellington</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70928/">Maria Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1847 August 15: Octavius Hadfield to his sister Maria</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Wellington Aug. 15 1847</p>
      <p>My dear Maria</p>
      <p>I was gratified a few days ago by receiving a very interesting letter from you dated Dec. 30., accompanied by one from dear Octavia of Feb. 16.  I was highly delighted with them both &amp; beg to return my sincere thanks.  You appeared to have been visited by the influenza, but by the blessing of God to have been all restored to health at the latest date.  It gives me great pleasure to hear as much as I can of you all, &amp; of all my old friends; but I always seem to want to know more than even your kind letters communicate, but when love exsists <!--sic--> there requires but a word to call up a train of thought furnished by the imagination which supplies the deficiency.  My last letter was, I am afraid, so far back as May, written to Octavia, I think I delayed writing till I heard from you. </p>
      <p>I continue in much the same state, though certainly suffering less than I did.  I am waiting for my summons to leave this tabernacle of clay, whensoever it may be the Lord's will.  My dear kind friends here still minister with unabated love, &amp; attention to my every want.  Accustomed to a life of great activity for some time previous to my illness, it seems strange to be confined to my bed for so long; but even in this state I cannot fail to see that the Lord has hitherto preserved me to be in a slight degree useful.  The Bishop was here for a few days making some arrangements, occasioned by the sudden death of Mr. Bollard, the clergyman at Taranaki, whose place is to be supplied by Mr. Govett who had been some time at Waikanae.  As Mr. Cotton, his chaplain, who purposes leaving this for England in about two months, offered to accompany me in case I determined on making the attempt, I consulted the Bishop on the subject,, <!--sic--> relying much upon his judgement,.<!--sic-->  I told him that I had long since ceased to be guided by private feelings, &amp; that having left all my friends once with the view of serving God here, I could not take into my consideration, or allow myself to be influenced by, anything but duty.  He stated his opinion, kindly &amp; strongly, &amp; said that he, considered I might still be very useful here in various ways.  I have therefore at present determined to remain &amp; assist here.  They have been severely tried by a fever which visited the College at Auckland &amp; continued for about four months.  A son of Arch. W. Williams died of it after a long illness: they are now all free from it.  The Bishop was only here for a week, but he came to me almost every evening, &amp; remained very late with me, discussing many questions connected with the mission &amp; the natives etc.  He is a man of very uncommon power of mind &amp; seems to unite with strength of intellect &amp; strength of faith, a heart full of love &amp; kindness, with energy &amp; resolution &amp; perseverance which no difficulties or apparent obstacles can at all affect.  He seems to place great reliance upon my judgement in reference to all questions respecting the natives.  He is now wishing to establish a College near this place (at Porirua about 14 miles distant in a very beautiful and convenient spot) for both English &amp; natives on the same plan as his at Auckland; &amp; has consulted me upon the best place, to which I am now giving my attention.  As the natives are my old friends, they will give the land, and the Bishop having some funds already provided, I hope that there will be no delay, but that beginning will be made this summer if I can be of any real assistance in furthering this object I shall be delighted.  I should be delighted if some really well-educated talented &amp; pious man would come from England to be engaged in it; but the truth is we have very little money to offer, &amp; men do not like coming so far without some prospect of a certain salary of tolerable amount; though if people in England knew what a blessed work it is &amp; how cheaply they can live in this country, that is, if they were once here, they would care very little about that subject.  I take an especial interest in the College because I see clearly what I have already posited on paper to the Bishop, that the church in N.Z. must be making an effort to support itself,- both as respects money &amp; men.  I could not recommend the C.M. Society to spend a greater amount of money in N.Z. than they now do when I consider the wants of other parts of the world; nor can we expect a constant supply of men: it becomes necessary therefore that a part of our present funds should be devoted to the education of the most promising of the children of missionaries, settlers, &amp; natives; &amp; it would be want of faith to presume that the blessing of God would not rest on these endeavours &amp; that He would not raise up some from among them to do His work.  With regard also to funds, I have made some suggestions as to how they might be raised here, at least how a beginning might be made.  There are some subjects rather more of a political nature on which the Bishop's thoughts have been running in the same direction as mine.  Lord Grey has written a despatch in which in the coolest manner possible, he proposes to act in the most illegal way to appropriate lands belonging to the natives.  Now though I have no notion that an attempt would be made for many years to come to do anything of the kind, as about 20,000 men would immediately take up arms to resist it, &amp; that they would resist it successfully nobody acquainted either with them, or their mode of warfare, of which we have had some experience lately, can have any doubt: still is is important to protest at once against a principle so entirely opposed to all reason &amp; justice as that put forth by Lord Grey.  There has been a decision in the Supreme Court lately in which the law has been so clearly laid down that had any doubt existed previously in the mind of any reasonable man upon the subject, it could scarcley <!--sic--> exist now.  I wrote a letter in one of the papers of this place, a copy of which I forward to you, exposing the absurdity of Lord Grey's arguments.  I have written another since (which perhaps I will send also) turning more upon the legal question.  These letters have cried out against him but I defy anyone to refute or invalidate what I have said.  On the Bishop's arrival here he told me that he had sent a protest through the Governor to the Secretary of State on the same subject.  What we intend to do in case Lord Grey is obstinate is to show the natives how they can resist the arbitrary conduct of Lord Grey by carrying their case in to the Supreme Court, where the law will protect them.  But what I most feared was that if no protest were made against it, persons ignorant of the law might lead the natives to think that it was to be acted on, when a general insurrection would unquestionably take place.  I am informed that my letters have not been without effect.  Captain Grey would never consent to anything of the kind, &amp; I have just received a very kind &amp; friendly letter from him in which he labours to convince me that Lord Grey had no intention of acting upon his own principle, but merely asserts it as that which he conceives ought to have been acted upon originally.  Even would Lord Grey's despatch bear this interpretation, which I deny, I should be equally obliged to protest against it.  Captain Grey's letter is very pleasing, &amp; I am sure while he remains here that nothing unjust, which he can prevent will be done.  The new Lieut-Gov. Mr. Eyre, called on me the day before yesterday.  He appears a well-disposed man, but by no means equal to Captain Grey.  Wanganui, Mr. Taylor's station, still continues disturbed, but I do not think it will last long, or that the disaffection will spread.  The Christian part of the population there, with a few trivial exceptions, remains quiet.  Perhaps these little wars, however much to be deplored, may be the means of convincing government &amp; military men how impossible it is to make war successfully in a country like this, &amp; thereby good may come out of evil. </p>
      <p>I was much pleased with the extract from the Malta "Times" which appeared in the "Record" which you forwarded to me.  I have been hoping to hear from George a full account of everything connected with the College &amp; himself.  I should have enclosed a letter for him but I believe the vessel that is to take this will sail directly (if I have time I will do so), you must therefore give my affectionate love to him when you write.  I was glad to hear of the birth of Charles' little daughter, pray give my kind love to him also.  I hope Alexander may have his health better in India than he has previously had.  I trust Henry &amp; Charlotte &amp; their little ones are prospering, though I do not much like his habit of travelling about: you must give my love to them also.  And now I think I must have tried your patience, &amp; therefore conclude.  Pray give my warmest love to my Father &amp; Mother &amp; all my dear sisters - &amp; with kind regards to all dear friends,</p>
      <p>Believe me,</p>
      <p>My dear sister</p>
      <p>Your very affectionate brother</p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      <p>I have been much grieved to hear of the great distress in Ireland &amp; some parts of England &amp; Scotland.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
