<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0028">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1840 September 19: Octavius Hadfield to his father Joseph</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  "Letter 40." Page 60.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 25.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1840-09-19">1840 September 19</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70954/.">Kapiti</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70741/">Joseph Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1840 September 19: Octavius Hadfield to his father Joseph
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Kapiti,</p>
      <p>near Port Nicholson),</p>
      <p>New Zealand</p>
      <p>Sep. 19th. 1840</p>
      <p>My dear Father, </p>
      <p>It is a long time, I think, since I addressed you, but I doubt not that you all make common property of my letters, &amp; therefore I am not very particular when I write which of you I address.  The last I wrote was to George in July; one I wrote to my mother a few months ago, I fear, from what I hear here was lost, I may be mistaken.  I am glad that my leters had all arrived safe to you, but I have lost some of yours.  The last I received, a few days ago, was from Maria, of December, for which I felt thankful, tho' it reached me many months after it was written, (direct henceforward as above, without any reference to Sydney).  I was glad to hear that you were all at that period tolerably well, &amp; my mother better; George, tho', I fear not very strong.  It gives me great pleasure to hear from you, you cannot write too often.  I sometimes think I should like to see you, but then again I could not, no, I would not, leave the work I am now engaged in, while the Lord appears to prosper me, tho' I loved you all ten-fold more than I do.  I was glad to hear of the birth of Henry's son, I hope he &amp; Charlotte &amp; the children are all well; I was sorry to hear that Alexander had suffered from a return of his old jungle fever.  I have not had a letter from him since he arrived in India.  I wrote to persuade him to pay me a visit here; this certainly is the best climate I ever was in.  I hear of wars &amp; rumours of wars in India, but know not whether it be truth or no.  Oh, that the time were come when the Gospel of Jesus, the Gospel of peace, prevailed throughout the world!  I feel thankful at least that I, &amp; yet not I but the Gospel I preach, has been the means of stopping the war between the two tribes among whom I live.  Many of the chiefs of the tribe who began the war before I came, now tell me that tho' they cannot understand all I tell them about a God in Christ reconciling sinners to Himself, washing away sins in His atoning blood, they have never the less learned to leave off fighting &amp; working on the Lord's Day, so far among this, perhaps the most obdurate of all the tribes in N.Z. there is a little done; many of the young people &amp; a few of the chiefs however, regularly attend to my instructions.  The other tribe all attend to me, &amp; in the one village in which I reside there are about 500 or 600, at service in the native chapel on the Sunday.  I do not take such a sanguine view of these things as some of our people here; it is not all gold that glitters; nevertheless there is much to encourage me even in "the day of small things"; vast numbers can now read &amp; write well, &amp; when I have lectures of an even, it amuses me to see the means they resort to to get a place inside the building which will not hold above 200, they climb up on stands that they have made on the sides of their native buildings, &amp; many come half an hour before the bell rigns that they may get a seat, so anxious are they to hear the word of God explained.  Some come about 10 miles on the Saturday for the services of the next day.  It is remarkable to see gun-barrels used for bells, instruments of war turned into instruments for calling to peace; these are very common, what a literal fulfilment of prophecy, &amp; yet, as I before remarked, among all these professors, who really believes the gospel &amp; acts according to its beautiful precepts?  few, indeed, very few, &amp; yet I feel thankful that there are a few who I believe are the children of God, &amp; if this be, the case, may I not with the angles in Heaven rejoice over a few sinners that repent, a few that are plucked as brands from the burning to be made heirs of glory.  I have too much work here, but do not misunderstand me, not that I over-exert myself, alas my indolence I fear is my chief sin, but I mean too much for one person to do so that I can do nothing with pleasure, for while I am about <hi rend="underline">one</hi> thing I leave <hi rend="underline">two</hi> undone.  I long for help, the fields are ripe for the harvest, &amp; none to reap; oh, may I have more love in my heart &amp; more zeal for the glory of God &amp; salvation of my fellow-sinners.  It is a curious kind of life I lead in the midst of these people, subject to so many interruptions, &amp; moving about as much as I do.  I have not much time for reading.  I sometimes long for the End that remains for me.</p>
      <p>This country is changing fast from the multitudes of English coming here, in fact it is impossible to look forward at all, as to what the probable consequence will be as regards the natives.  For my part, I anticipate no good for the natives, nay I look forward with grief to the state of these poor people, may the Lord disappoint my forebodings.  Government at present are well disposed towards the natives, but this may be partly policy, being a little afraid of them, time only will show.  These people are a very wicked people, &amp; if civilisation without the influence of the Gospel to bear upon it will not be benefited in any way.  The influence of the immoral English living in the land is the greatest difficulty I have to contend with as they continually object to me the lives &amp; conduct of my own countrymen, these objections I should observe, come from those who have not yet made any profession of the gospel.  I have been abused by the Port Nicholson people in their paper, that is, accused of buying land, &amp; trading for pigs &amp; potatoes with books; I care little what they say about me, &amp; if you should see any of their remarks you will know what credit to give to them.  Since my visit there, however, (it is about 30 miles from me) they have somewhat altered their tone.  All connected with the Government, among others the Colonial Secretary, were very civil to me, &amp; I lately had two very polite notes from Col. Wakefield.  I never have &amp; never intend to court the favour of men, but if, however bad, they are willing to live on friendly terms with me, I shall not draw back.  I met with some pleasing people among them.  I do not wish to be much connected with Government, as they have already appointed one Popish magistrate.  They, however, naturally apply to us for information etc. with regard to the natives, being ignorant of their language, manners, customs, etc.  When I came home I left as it were all comforts, &amp; everything connected with civilisation, &amp; I felt it no hardship; I was even thought by people here, rash and headstrong for coming here to the strait alone;  but now I have everything almost brought within my reach; however my wants are few.  I only mean that you need no longer fancy that I am where I was twelve months ago; I have not indeed moved, but the world has moved towards me.  There is not much beauty in the scenery here, a sandy shore and flat towards the sea, but the mountains at the back are fine &amp; I have the hilly Island of Kapiti, or "Entry Island" about three miles out at sea, just opposite me.  On a very clear day I see three immense mountains, the nearest of which is about 60 miles from me, &amp; they are always covered with snow, viz. "Taranaki", "Ruapehu", &amp; "Tapuaenuku"<!--Tapuae-o-Uenuku, formerly Mount Tapuaenuku, in the Inland Kaikoura Range--> this latter on the Middle Island.  I expect our vessel here in a few weeks when I intend crossing the Straits, &amp; visiting the natives on that Island, many of them I know, as they are the same tribe as my people here.  I intended crossing in my boat, but Mr. Williams, who is an old sailor, strongly urged me not; I therefore gave it up, it is rather dangerous, being about 25 miles across, &amp; there being very strong tide rips, but I have a great desire to go there.  I have been to Cloudy Bay on that Island at my first <!--previous editor's note: torn--> down here, but then I could not speak the language (and now speak it, I fear, very badly).  I have written a long letter about nothing, but you will, I suppose, get one of my sisters to read it to you.  I hope I shall soon hear again from you, &amp; hear good accounts.  I often think of dear Georgina who has gone before me.  May we all through the merits of a Saviour's blood, be delivered from wrath &amp; brought to glory.  Remember me, I pray, to all my friends, especially the Warrens, Griffins, and all others who, you tell me in your letters, ask after me.  I often think also of our poorer neighbours, John, etc.  &amp; now give my warmest &amp; most affectionate love to my dear mother, &amp; all my dear brothers &amp; sisters, not excepting Mr. Dawson, &amp; believe me, my dearest Father, </p>
      <p>Ever your most affectionate son,</p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      <p>Since writing the above I have recd. a paper sent to me by George concerning the ecclesiastical relations of the C.M.Society; will you thank him for it.  Tell him also it is not clear in distinguishing ordination from mission.  O.H.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
