<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0078">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1851 January 15: Octavius Hadfield to his sister Maria</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  "Letter 3."  Page un-numbered; between 234 and 235.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 9.12.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1851-01-15">1851 January 15</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/3619/">Wellington</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70928/">Maria Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1851 January 15: Octavius Hadfield to his sister Maria</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Wellington N.Z. January 15. 51.</p>
      <p>My dear Maria,</p>
      <p>Since I last write I have received your letter of May, &amp; those of my mother and George dated June.  Accept my best thanks for your letter; I shall hope to thank my mother &amp; George myself shortly.  I am always delighted to hear from you, as everything from home must interest me.</p>
      <p>I have been hard at work lately, doing, I think, as much as I used to before I was ill.  My old complaint is quite cured.  The only thing I suffer from is my chest, when I talk too much; but this I cannot help.  The natives are quite as attentive &amp; anxious to learn as ever, &amp; are improving.  I am much more engaged with the natives of this place than I used to be, as I find they get little attention from anybody else.  But my principal work is in the neighbourhood of Otaki.  Mr. Williams works hard, generally taking charge of the villages.  I have a school for instructing native teachers.  I had them during December, twenty-one of them, &amp; was very much interested in my scholars.  We are just going to build some good school-rooms.  We have all the timber ready, when these three rooms in one building- are completed we shall be able to carry on our school much better than we can at present. </p>
      <p>I saw Sir G. Grey last week: he promised to assist me in our school rooms.  We have been holding service in our beautiful new church at Otaki, it is not quite finished.  </p>
      <p>I must now mention to you one of my Otaki natives who is gone to England with Archd H. Williams, my old Waimate friend.  He is the only son of Te Rauparaha, who died the year before last.  His name is Thompson, or in Maori, Tamihana  His object in going to England is to see for himself what civilisation is.  He knows so little of English that I am afraid he will not profit very much; but he may learn it on the voyage.  He was one of the two young chiefs who, having heard of Christianity &amp; its effects, went to the Bay of Islands to learn more of it, &amp; who induced me to come down to this part of the country.  That is now near twelve years ago.  He was baptised by me about ten years ago, as was his wife.  He has always lived very consistently, &amp; is a right-thinking man.  He is not by any means one of our best &amp; most consistent Christians; but I believe him to be a sincere Christian; &amp; he has done much good by invariably using the influence which his rank gives him for good.  He has always been remarkably civil &amp; attentive to me, &amp; one of my most staunch supporters on all occasions.  His wife is now left under my charge, &amp; she has strict injunctions from him, which she very readily obeys, , to look after all my wants.  He has taken so many letters of introduction to various persons at home that I do not imagine he will be in any want of persons to show him the "lions" but I know he would like to see some of my family; if therefore any of you have an opportunity of seeing him or of showing him any attentions, I should be much gratified; indeed if it were necessary to incur any expense for his advantage or benefit in any way I would gladly bear it.  He made his will before he went away; I am one of his executors; &amp; all his property, about 6 or 700 &#163;. is in my hands.  I think he will prove to some at home that natives are not quite such savages as some of the wise people at home would have the public imagine.</p>
      <p>The new settlement Canterbury is now absorbing attention here.  Mr. Godley is gone there to direct the settlement.  I was very sorry to lose him &amp; Mrs. Godley, then were such very superior people.  I can hardly venture to predict any thing of the probable success of the settlement.  The great drawback to its speedy advancement is the high price of land.  In every thing else it is perfect, that is in its "idea".  And the spot selected is good, the land being so available for immediate use.  I was at Whanganui, Mr. Taylor's place, a few days ago; everything there is changing rapidly; the natives are improving; &amp; they &amp; the white population agree much better than they did.</p>
      <p>Another brother of Mr. St.Hill, who arrived at Auckland from Calcutta a few months ago, has just come down here; he intends to remain with the Bishop &amp; will probably be ordained soon.  The rest of the party here are all quite well &amp; as kind as usual.</p>
      <p>I read Mr. Fox's life a few days ago: it is very interesting &amp; edifying.  Our Bishop &amp; the Bishop of the adjacent colonies met lately at Sydney for missionary purposes.  I will send a Sydney Herald containing an account of the meeting.</p>
      <p>With love to all at home</p>
      <p>I am ever your affectionate brother,
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
