<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0056">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1846 February 6: Octavius Hadfield to one of his brothers</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  Page 132.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 1.12.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1846-02-06">1846 February 6</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/3619/">Wellington</name>
               </correspAction>
               
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1846 February 6: Octavius Hadfield to one of his brothers</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Wellington, N.Z. 6th. Feb. 1846.</p>
      <p>My dear Brother, </p>
      <p>I am afraid that I have been the cause of much anxiety to you.  Your letter of June, the receipt of which I acknowledged in a letter to my mother, leads me to fear that by informing you of the nature of the disease from which I have been suffering, you have been kept in a continual suspense concerning me.  I trust however, that it has not been of a painful nature.  We are apt to feel too strongly when sympathising with absent sufferers.  For sufferings, however acute, may, I trust, be patiently borne by looking up to Him Who has ordained them for us; and, if so, then we are not devoid of true happiness, though in suffering, and consequently should not be objects of undue solicitude to those friends who view truth in the same light as ourselves.  If sufferings are very intense, they must shortly terminate in death; from which nature indeed shrinks, but which is to living faith the mere bursting of the bonds that tie us to earth, and impede our entrance into the immediate presence of God.  I have been feeling better lately - suffering less pain, and able to rise more frequently from my bed and remain up for an hour at a time.  Any excitement causing more rapid circulation of the blood gives me great pain for the passage of the blood through a large artery being impeded by the aneurysm, causes an unnatural action of that organ which is very painful: but when I am quiet I suffer very little; and am able to spend many hours in reading, though I am obliged to vary it, as I am too prone to become inordinately interested in any particular study in which I may be engaged.  It is, however, a somewhat painful feeling which one occasionally experiences that the fascination of intellectual studies becomes too strong; and deadens our affections.  I feel strongly that I have in my past life neglected those studies which would have tended to expand the mental faculties, and to furnish the understanding with matter.  It is impossible to make a bold stand against the infidel if inferior to him in mental acquirements, if unacquainted with the past history of the world, especially since the christian era, if unable to point out to him all the difficulties and obscurities with which physical science is still encumbered, notwithstanding his most common objection to religion is that it has so many obscurities.  I make these remarks because there are several clever infidels in this part of the country, and I fear none of our clergy feel competent to encounter them. I, when in health, never shunned the contest, but still I could not help feeling that the more learned one is, the firmer and more confident tone one may take in the contest. I confess I was surprised lately in reading the "Cours de Philosophie Positive" of M. Comte, a first-rate French philosopher, to find him avow himself an atheist; his reasons were puerile.  He says that so far from "the heavens declaring the glory of God", they only disclose the glory of Kepler, Newton, etc.  Thus, no glory is to be ascribed to the Creator of the universe, but only to those who discover its laws!  As if the discovery of the laws whereby the motions of the heavenly bodies are governed, was the same as bestowing on matter those properties which enable it to obey those beautiful laws.  He confuses the acuteness of a lawyer who interprets the law with the wisdom of the legislator by whom they were devised.  In another place he says that science can easily imagine a better arrangement of the heavenly bodies!  Truly the wisdom of man is folly!  "Where is the wise?" etc.  God be praised that with intellects very inferior to that of M. Compte, you and I are not only preserved from such absurd folly, but enabled to believe in Jesus Christ! and to love and adore the wisdom and goodness of God!  But besides encountering infidels, a missionary, to be efficient, should be able to enter into the modes of thought of an uncivilised people, and this is more necessary than is generally supposed. Those who come as missionaries furnished only with a knowledge of the Bible, and with ideas formed in a civilised school, will be prone to judge harshly of a people like these, and to condemn prematurely most, if not all, of their maxims and habits; and this is a fault into which not only missionaries but those entrusted with the government of the country have followed. I have always endeavoured to investigate their language and their customs etc. with this idea uppermost in my mind, that they belonged to the genus man, and consequently that if their language, customs, etc., were investigated according to the fundamental laws which guide thought in the human mind, <supplied>[these]</supplied> must be found to guide theirs; But that I was sure to be involved in difficulties if I assumed the existence of any adventitious adjuncts which merely mark species, ie. civilised, semi-civilised, etc.  You will perceive what I mean; our rulers have endeavoured to enforce our laws without any investigation of their previous customs, endeavouring to mix what will not amalgamate, and missionaries have too frequently pronounced an unqualified condemnation of all their customs without any distinction, and I think in many cases erroneously.  I am convinced that such an empirical way of proceeding witll not succeed, either in religion, or in government.  I have entered into a long detail of my opinions on these subjects with the Bishop and he enters into my views, but laments the impossibility of finding men to act upon and carry out any system in this country at present.  I have also considerable hope of being able to do some good to the natives in a political point of view, by fairly and plainly stating, what has never yet been stated, - what their laws and customs are; this, I feel, would do good, as it will prevent laws being formed which would clash at once with old and inveterate prejudices, and inevitably meet with their determined opposition.  In this undertaking, on which I have bestowed considerable thought, I have hitherto met with much encouragement, my plan, as far as I have proceeded with it, having been much approved of by the judge and the legal adviser of the government; it of course depends upon the governor to give it any further encouragement or not, as he may think proper; it must, however, be some service to him as a new-comer; whether he approves or not.   The question was quite misunderstood at home in the House of Commons: the real errors of government were scarcely touched upon, and the real difficulties to be contended with out here were not alluded to.  The whole that was said on both sides of the House in reference to the Treaty of Waitangi was strangely confused and irrelevant.  International law sa it related to New Zealand, and which is as much the law of nations as the common law is the law of England, was left out of the debate, when it must have decided the question at once if brought to bear; - a strange omission on the part of the government.  The Right of Discovery only gives to the Crown a paramount title to all lands; but that the Crown possesses in England: that paramount title the Crown has whether a country is obtained by discovery, by treaty, or by conquest.  The confusion has arisen from the ambiguity of language - a common evil; the Crown claims a paramount title to all waste lands: if waste lands are interpreted as wild or uncultivated the crown has no title to them, but if as unclaimed lands, then the title of the crown comes in here and everywhere; but that is the difficulty; the natives do claim them; and moreover refuse to give them up, unless they are taken by force.  But I forget, I am tiring you with our politics.  We have not heard from the Bay of Islands for a long time, and know nothing of the proceedings there.  </p>
      <p>My old quarters at Waikanae and Otaki are now occupied by Mr. Govett, whom I like very well, and Mr. Tudor of whom likewise I have formed a very good opinion; he is not ordained, but will be ordained shortly, I believe.  The natives in those places are continuing to improve and though neither of their teachers know much as yet of the language, as they have not been very long among natives, yet they write to me frequently, and I perceive that they, as a body, are by no means declining in their religion.  Some of them, indeed, write me letters occasionally which are very satisfactory as indicating their present state of mind, - how changed from what it weas when I first went among them!  God be praised!  I was thinking of sending some translations; but without understanding their mode of thought etc. it would be no index to their real state, for, the other day, (one who had been a slave and subsequently my faithful servant for five years, and wholly free from cant of any kind) in writing describes himself as having been lately meditating on the majesty and goodness and grace of God etc., and then adds He inate!  He inate!  - Wonderful! Wonderful!.  I do not ever remember hearing the term applied in the same way before: it was a plain indication of his being really lost in admiration on these subjects, and then bursting forth in an expression of wonder.  I find I must conclude.  I have become so accustomed to writing in bed, that I go on without fatigue, forgetting that you have to read it.  My dear friends here are well, and as kind as ever.  I shall hope to hear soon from you,- though a ship came direct from London (Sept. 27th.) without a letter.  Pray give my kindest love to all at home.  I was delighted to hear you had got through the winter so well.</p>
      <p>Your affectionate brother,
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
