<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0048">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1844 September 17: Octavius Hadfield to his mother Amelia Hadfield (nee White)</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  Page 103.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 30.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1844-09-17">1844 September 17</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/71095/">Waikanae</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70719/">Amelia Hadfield (nee White)</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1844 September 17: Octavius Hadfield to his mother Amelia Hadfield (nee White)</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Waikanae</p>
      <p>New Zealand.</p>
      <p>Sept. 17. 1844</p>
      <p>My dear Mother,</p>
      <p>I feel at a loss, now that I begin to write, how to apologise for my long silence; I am afraid that I have allowed almost six months to elapse since I last wrote, which was at the end of March last to my Father.  I generally prefer writing by ships going direct, as I find that some of my letters which are sent via Sydney do not always reach their destination; &amp; owing to my distance from Wellington I do not always hear in time to write by homeward-bound ships.</p>
      <p>I have received five letters which I have not yet acknowledged - from yourself, Maria, Octavia, Caroline &amp; Henry - for these I beg to return my most sincere &amp; grateful thanks, as they are deeply interesting to me: I think that I have thought more of you all lately than I had previously done since I left England.  I had also the pleasure of receiving a letter from Alexander from India, &amp; as I presume that he is now in England, I must request you to thank him for his very acceptable letter.  I do sincerely hope that his health may improve at home.  It is very clear that India does not agree with him.  I forget whether I mentioned in my last letter that I was unwell; if I did, you will doubtless have been anxious to hear again from me; but if I had written since that period, I could not have given a very favourable account of myself, nor can I now; but I am persuaded, my dear Mother, that you have learnt to feel that resignation to the Divine Will is not only the wisest state of mind, to be in but also that the possession of it brings, at all times, &amp; under all circumstances, sweet peace to the soul &amp; enables it to rejoice under apparently adverse dispensations: - with this persuasion I hesitate not to tell you that I have been very ill, &amp; still am in very delicate health.  I have indeed cause to be thankful, that considering how weak my constitution was, when a boy, I have enjoyed so great a measure of health as I have, &amp; have moreover been enabled to devote a few years to the work of the Lord.  Few people probably have enjoyed a greater measure of happiness than I have.  I have been at times "sorrowful", "yet always rejoicing", - sorrowful indeed at times when I looked to myself, joyful, however, when I contemplated the Blessed Lord - the precious Saviour, the Holy Comforter; but I can truly say that the joy has predominated - nay "swallowed up the sorrow".  Hence, then, I attest, I have been highly favoured, richly blessed.  Praised be the Blessed God!! But to proceed; I must give you some account of myself.  In March last I was attacked with a complaint in my kidneys which confined me to my bed for some time; subsequently I recovered a moderate degree of strength &amp; attended to my duties as usual; but having a good deal of work about Easter, &amp; some time afterwards, I could not spare time to put myself under medical treatment &amp; consequently continued till the beginning of June without taking any steps to have the pain in my back removed, which was by that time rather serious.  On the 4th. of June I went to Wellington, having been previously visited by my friend Mr. St Hill, &amp; took up my abode at his house.  Dr. Fitzgerald, who attended me before, visited me &amp; having brought Dr. Featherston another very clever man to see me, they told me it was necessary for me to put myself entirely under their directions, as my complaint ought to have been attended to long before.  I continued at Wellington three months, &amp; was visited by Dr. Fitzgerald every day, who tried various remedies - bleeding, cupping, tartar-emetic applications, but without much success.  Having passed so much time at Wellington, I requested them to give me a decided opinion about my state of health, that I might be prepared to act accordingly.  They give me no hopes of an ultimate recovery, though they tell me that with great care &amp; by being very quiet, I may live tolerably free from pain.  I returned home about a fortnight ago, as they thought that with me that change of air might do me good, especially as the air of this place is better than that of Wellington.  I am strictly forbidden to exert myself, so I content myself with moderate duties.  I was nine Sundays without being able even to go to church, but I have preached once each of the last four Sundays, without suffering much by it.  I am not now in much pain but then I am daily using very strong medicines, which may be expected ere long to lose their effect.  I am determined to take care of myself, &amp; try every remedy that is in my power; believeing this to be my duty, &amp; as I am now in my new house which is very comfortable, I can do so: but to do this in New Zealand &amp; at the same time continue in the attempt to discharge my duties among my flock, seems impossible for any length of time.  If I find myself totally unable to do anything here I may be induced to attempt a voyage to England, especially as one of my medical advisors strongly recommended it: but I should take such a step with great reluctance &amp; consequently only mention it as a possibility.</p>
      <p>The Bishop happened to come into Wellington for an hour while I was there &amp; was much grieved to find that I was unwell.  He spoke &amp; acted with the greatest kindness.  He told me not to be anxious about my work, that he would send me somebody to assist me &amp; added that though I possessed but little strength I might still be very useful, especially in superintending matters at this end of the Island, which, being at so great a distance from him, he could not well attend to himself.</p>
      <p>Though I have written honestly &amp; candidly to you, my dear Mother, concerning my real state, yet considering how weak my constitution has always been &amp; yet how I have managed to live on hitherto &amp; even to work; I hope you will not gather from what I have said that I think it impossible that I may continue to live on for some time still; for I can assure you that I am not one who believes in the infallibility of doctors.  I will now neglect no opportunity of writing a faithful account of myself.  There is one fact which I know you must rejoice in &amp; that is that I am surrounded here with a host of kind affectionate friends: no language could express to you the kindness I have experienced, I may almost say from all who know me.  I cannot conceive anything to equal the affectionate love &amp; attention which I have experienced from both Mr. &amp; Mrs. St Hill: during the three months I was in their house they seemed to have no other thought than how to show kindness to me; &amp; now that I have left them they write as though they had suffered a loss by my departure.  I think I must ask Mrs. St Hill to write to you that you may judge for yourself what sort of friends mine are, lest you should imagine that I am ill here in a desert without a friend to sympathise with me.  The medical men who attended me would not hear of any remuneration for their attendance; &amp; requested me to send for them immediately in case I am taken suddenly worse.  Dr. Fitzgerald is a romanist, though unlike any that I have seen before.  He talks very seriously on religion but seem, as all romanists do, to confuse justification with sanctification; I have, however, a confident hope that he is resting entirely for his salvation on the Lord Jesus Christ.  He delights in conversing with me, &amp; says he considers me the greatest friend he has in N.Z.  He is himself in a very delicate state of health.  I feel very thankful to these two men.  It is very satisfactory to know you are in the hands of medical men whose only wish is to do all in their power to restore you to health &amp; who have no object besides that.  Mr. Cole, the clergyman of Wellington, has shown me great kindness.</p>
      <p>I do not think that they prospects of this colony are very encouraging at the present time.  The greater part of the colonists are very little acquainted with the various employments which would fit them to be useful settlers, &amp; even those who take the lead in matters here show great ignorance of the first principles of political economy: they are aware that N.Z. will not produce everything they require &amp; yet up to this time they have thought of no export in exchange for the necessary imports; though I am convinced that this country may produce many.  The consequence is that the little capital which was brought here has been drained out of the colony &amp; many of the settlers, I think, will shortly take their leave of it.  I regret this state of things as I am quite convinced that the resources of this place are various &amp; available.  Nor do I take a very cheering view of the condition of the native population.  I believe they are no longer on the advance but rather the reverse: but this idea I think I have previously expressed.  I attribute the change to the superficial nature of the system of instruction we have among them: we do nothing after bringing them to a certain point.  The standard of christianity presented to their view by European Christians is low, &amp; they think to attain that is beyond their power &amp; consequently they scarcely aim at doing so by which course they necessarily fall far short even of that - I mean the generality of them; whereas the truth is, being all of us subject to this weakness, it is our duty to set a very high standard of religion before our view; but more especially should those engaged in propagating the faith of the Gospel seek to have continually in them "the mind which was in Christ" &amp; endeavour to be continually "putting on the Lord Jesus Christ".  But I speak not altogether of missionaries - though I would take all the blame to ourselves which we deserve - but refer to the conduct of settlers &amp; others.  In addition to other evils I conceive the introduction of Wesleyanism has produced many evils.  Apart from its own intrinsic evil &amp; the errors contained in the whole system, its effect as a sectarian body in impeding the reception of the gospel among the heathen is very grievous.  I do not think that much can be done for the conversion of the heathen world until we who believe are more united.  The Oneness of the church was evidently to be the great convincing proof of the truth of the Gospel to the world (John XVII. 21)  I have never seen a good comment upon that passage; but to me it appears evident, that what is called love - union of sentiment, union of purpose &amp; feeling; while there is outward separation, is absurd sophistry, nay incomprehensible jargon.  What evidence is it to the heathen of the truth of christianity to say though we are separated - though we meet in different places though we have such different forms, though we pursue different systems, still we are one in purpose &amp; love?  Can any human being comprehend such nonsense?  Can any stumbling-block be thrown in the way of the heathen on which they are more likely to fall?  No, there are many things, it is true which we understand only by faith; but the evidences on which the Gospel rests its pretensions to a Divine origin, various &amp; manifold as they are, are all necessarily presented to our reason; &amp; one at least by which the All-Wise God has thought proper to convince the heathen, is the <hi rend="underline">outward,</hi> <hi rend="underline">visible</hi> oneness of His church: a tree is known by its <hi rend="underline">fruits</hi> - a christian by his <hi rend="underline">works</hi> - the existance <!--sic--> of love in the church by <hi rend="underline">visible</hi> <hi rend="underline">union</hi>.  Not all the sophistry &amp; specious argument in the world will ever be able to overthrow the force of this conclusion, which is evidently the indisputable inference drawn from the doctrine contained in that passage.</p>
      <p>The natives are not advancing in civilisation: not because they are not aware of its advantages over barbarism, but because there is no system used for effecting such an object: many talk upon the subject, but none use any efforts toward accomplishing it.  The introduction of christianity, they say, will not do it alone; they therefore throw impediments in the way of the missionaries, but in the mean time do nothing themselves.  </p>
      <p>I have received letters from India as late as April 27th. &amp; have been rather disappointed in not having a later date than March from home; especially as I was anxious to hear both of George &amp; Alexander, who I thought might perhaps have returned by that time, but I must wait a little longer.  I hope you will not be anxious about me; I will write again soon.  But above all may we all learn to feel more &amp; more, what we all acknowledge, that our Heavenly Father does all things according to the pleasure of His Own Will, &amp; causes all things to work together for His people's clearest welfare.  May our "faith" be indeed to us "the substance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not seen".  Give my affectionate love to my dear Father &amp; all my dear brothers &amp; sisters &amp; Believe me, my dear Mother, </p>
      <p>Ever your very affectionate son,
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
