<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0066">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1847 October 21: Octavius Hadfield to his brother Rev. George Hadfield</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  Page 175.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 7.12.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1847-10-21">1847 October 21</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/3619/">Wellington</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70976/">George Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1847 October 21: Octavius Hadfield to his brother Rev. George Hadfield</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Wellington, October 21st. 1847</p>
      <p>My very dear Brother,</p>
      <p>I know not why I have allowed so much time to elapse without writing to you, - unless it be that I have rather wished and partly expected to hear from you, - how you liked your new engagements at Malta before I did so.  I shall now enclose a letter to my father for you.  Through the mercy of God, <supplied>[contrary]</supplied> to my own, and the expectation of those acquainted with the nature of the disease from which I am suffering, my life has been prolonged to the present hour.  Who shall venture to enquire of the Lord a reason for His doings?  Sufficient for us it is to know that a God of wisdom and love and power reigns over all.  My thoughts dwell much on the invisible and eternal, that which is indeed the real, and which must be shortly to me all as indeed I trust in one sense it already is, to have life in Christ ,- Christ for our life-, to live in Him is to live an eternal life.  May I be daily made more meet for an admission into the everlasting presence of God!  It gave me extreme satisfaction to hear of your appointment at the college at Malta, for many reasons, but especially because I think you are highly suited for the work to which God has been pleased to call you, and because my mind year after year dwells more on the importance of education.  I can trace back to impressions derived from you all that is good in myself,; <!--sic--> you were, when I was a boy, the only person for whose character and judgement I always had the most sincere respect; you were, ere I knew God, the person whose advice I always desired to follow, and who prepared me, if I may so speak, to know God.  An expression which you once used in a note to me about 16 years ago, and which I have never forgotten, I think decided me, to determine to serve God; it was, "to be carnally minded is death, but to be spiritually minded is life and peace", but I must not allow myself to dwell on this, I shall only add that no lines of that splendid poet Coleridge ever <supplied>[obtained]</supplied> so much sympathy from me or could be adopted so fully as these.</p>
      <p>"He who counts alone</p>
      <p>The beatings of the solitary heart</p>
      <p>That being knows, how I have loved thee ever,</p>
      <p>Loved as a brother, as a son revered thee!</p>
      <p>Oh! tis to me an ever new delight</p>
      <p>To talk of thee." etc.</p>
      <p>May God continue, as I know He will, to strengthen and comfort you.  I do not know the precise nature of the object of the Malta College, but whatever it may be, I am quite sure that you will feel that to educated is not to impart instruction, but to educe from man's moral nature what exists, potentially at least in all, and what alone can make any knowledge acquired of any real service to man considered as an eternal being, or even I might say a member of society, a social being.  I look back now with great regret to that period of my life which I passed before I learned to appreciate the real value of learning.  I now know that it was only ignorance that induced me to suppose that learning ws not necessary; or rather, I ought to say, was not a real assistance, to the christian, at least if he is to bbe engaged at all in promoting the welfare of his fellow beings.  I have read much and thought much since I last saw you, and have likewise looked deeper into my own heart and considered human nature generally more profoundly than I had ever done then.  Its result has been to exalt my feelings of greater love for my fellow-creatures and to desire more ardently their improvement.  It is impossible for a thinking being to reside among a people like these New Zealanders and not to desire to fathom human nature, at least as far as it can be done, and to discover both the common ground for opinions held in common by all, and also the difference in the ground whence the differences arise.  What I mean is that the conscience of the most ignorant savage is as active,- points out the distinction between right and wrong-equally with that of the christian, though not in the same degree, but then the standard of right and wrong arising from the different degree of light in the reason constitutes practically an immense difference; I do not mean to say that many among savages as well as among so called civilised people have not by repeatedly slighting the admonitions of conscience actually so deadened it that it ceases to act; and they many probably be those whom the scripture describes as "given over to a reprobate mind,".  Conscience appears to be a testifying state of the coincidence or otherwise of the will with the reason /Voc/<!--slashes present in typescript-->; now as this latter faculty in a person brought up in a christian country must be more enlightened than in a savage, so a much higher standard of morality must be expected.  And I think that the Old Testament history confirms this, even were it not contained in Hosea 1 &amp; II etc.  Now the difficulty (speaking humanly) of converting the heathen, anticipated by, and dwelt upon by so many, from the wretchedly low standard of morality among them, is not so great as is supposed, for their consciences are as tender as ours /in an uncontroverted state.  But the standard of morality or the light of reason/ which is the ground of the conscience/ is low ,- they do not so much act against the conscience, as in accordance with a degraded standard; let this standard be raised by the Gospel standard, and they are in a more favourable position for christianity than the mass of unconverted people in a civilised country.  Now I think that the want of having considered this subject, if I may venture to use the word,-philosophically-,tends much to encourage people at home, and likewise leads many missionaries to condemn <supplied>[or rather]</supplied> the persons for the practices in a newly converted people which are not for them (subjectively) sinful,- and to expect more from them than ought to be expected.  Indeed I feel inclined to differ from all the expositions I have yet seen given on the Hosea V11 etc.  I have been writing some remarks on that part of scripture,- I will just say enough to let you see what I mean.  According to the language of St. Paul a man is under the law until he learns to serve God from a principle of love from within.  So long as his will is at variance with the will of God, of which the law of God - whether in the conscience or in the ten commandments,- is a copy; so long he is under the law. - - - - - - - - - <!--previous editor's note: 9 dashes here--> An external threatening, coercing power, no obedience to which/ even if it were possible for a fallen creature,/ could be a service acceptable to a God who is a spirit.  In man's low, fallen state, his will was not at variance with the law of God written on his heart; but by a mutual connivance of the will in the reason and the reason in the will, this law was a  <!--previous editor's note: left blank--> and he did spontaneously the will of God.  Now Christ has delivered us from the law - - that we should henceforth serve in newness of spirit, act from a holy principle of love and faith; so that the righteousness of the law is fulfilled in us "but not as a law- - - - - - acting from without; but it is perhaps - - - - for me to touch upon a subject of this kind in a letter, especially as I have already been writing this morning, a long letter to my father.  I have been studying for some time past the writings of Coleridge, and I must own that no human writings have ever afforded me so much instruction and pleasure; they certainly contain some exuberances of intellect, which one might not feel inclined to adopt, but I think he must certainly rank as the greatest Englishman who has lived for the 3 last centuries.  His "Aids to reflection" if you have not read them, would please you.  The Bishop is contemplating another college in this part of New Zealand; I hope it may succeed.  I had a great deal of conversation with him about it 12 months ago, about the affairs of the Mission.  He seems very anxious to do good and is a very talented man, but hs rather too much of the high church about him,- that is, he thinks more about forms than I do.  I think the whole theory of apostolic succession baseless, that is in the sense in which it is generally used, and therefore pernicious.  As in the state the authority of the executive is based/ in the idea, I mean in all states/ on, and is derived from the state, so I believe the authority of christian ministers is not derived from Christ through the ministers in a line of succesion <!--sic--> from the Apostles but through the church, of which I hold that Episcopacy was established in the time of the Apostles and by them; I do not think it necessary to continue as the only form of a ministry..  I am afraid I have tried your patience.  Adieu.  Ever your affectionate brother, 
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
