<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0070">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1849 February 23: Octavius Hadfield to his mother Amelia Hadfield (nee White)</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960. "LETTER 11".  Page 191.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 7.12.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1849-02-23">1849 February 23</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/3619/">Wellington</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70719/">Amelia Hadfield (nee White)</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1849 February 23: Octavius Hadfield to his mother Amelia Hadfield (nee White)</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Wellington Feb, 23 1849</p>
      <p>My dear Mother, </p>
      <p>I had the very great pleasure a few days ago of receiving your very kind &amp; interesting letter of Aug, for which accept my most grateful thanks, for I am sure it must now be some trouble to you to write so long a letter; it was quite refreshing to me.  It seemed, tho' I hope I never forget you, to bring you very vividly before me, &amp; also to give me a more clear idea of the measure of strength which both you &amp; my father still enjoy, than I had lately realised.</p>
      <p>May you both have your souls fixed by faith on God, reconciled through Christ, &amp; look to the Good Shepherd to conduct you in peace through the vale of death, &amp; bring you safe to eternal joy.  I was happy also to hear of you so late as Sep.17th. by your letter to Mrs St. Hill which she will answer by a ship which now sails direct to England.  Pray thank Octavia for her very kind letter of Sep.8th, I have heard also from Henry &amp; Charles, since I last wrote, &amp; shall answer their letters at once.  I am not sure whether I have yet acknowledged dear Caroline's letter of July.</p>
      <p>I am afraid it is a long time since I last wrote, (Oct.31 to Maria) but as there has been a vessel intending to sail for the last six weeks, I thought it better even to delay a little than to write by Sydney,.  I am happy to say that thro' God's mercy to me, I am now sitting up to write this letter, the first which I have so written to you for more than <hi rend="underline">four years</hi>.  The beneficial effect lately produced on my health by a new system of treatments, after all treatment had been hopelessly abandoned for years, is very astonishing,; I am now in the enjoyment of comparative health, but as I am still undergoing the treatment which has produced it, I am not quite certain how far I ought to regard my present improvement as likely to be permanent: still the change already produced is great beyond all human anticipation.  After being almost entirely confined to my bed for four years, &amp; suffering during that period almost incessant pain, living on a very low diet,- &amp; passing very restless nights, I am now, except when over-excited for a short time by mental exertion, almost free from it, - am able to eat meat with a good appetite - &amp; walk at different hours of the day 2 or 3 miles.  You cannot be more astonished at hearing this than those by whom I am surrounded.  When I went last to church about five weeks ago,- my appearance there seemed to people who had been constantly expecting to hear of my death, like a resurrection from the grave.  You can easily imagine how grateful I feel to my Heavenly Father for all his mercies vouchsafed to me.  He has ever been with me watching over me.- protecting me, providing for my every want.  Nothing, humanly speaking, but the unparalleled kindness shown daily, nay hourly, to me, during more than four years, could have kept me alive: &amp; how was this to have been expected in New Zealand?  But He who orders all things- He who cares for all- &amp; without Whom not even a sparrow falls to the ground, has more than abundantly provided all things for me.  And how could it be otherwise?  If Christ is ours, all things are ours,- angels &amp; men &amp; the whole creation: "the earth is the Lord's &amp; the fullness thereof", &amp; if Christ the Eternal Co-equal Son of the Father was not denied, what is any created thing in comparison to HIm- the Lord- Who is Lord of all in Heaven &amp; earth.  Praised be God for His unspeakable gift &amp; for all His gifts &amp; mercies.  </p>
      <p>The treatment by means of which my health has so improved, is, what is called the water-treatment or rather unscientifically - hydropathy.  It was first commenced in Germany, &amp; afterwards taken up by Gully, Johnstone &amp; others in England.  Dr. Fitzgerald, my kind, attentive, unwearied adviser, induced me to try it, after having performed many wonderful cures in the hospital over which he presides, &amp; which was built by Sir G. Grey at my suggestion.  The principle on which the treatment proceeds was perfectly clear to me for during my illness, as one style of reading wearied me so much, I have been used to amuse myself with scientific works, on, among others, anatomy, physiology, chemistry, &amp; especially Seibig's works on the latter, so that I was pretty well prepared to form an opinion on the subject, as well as from having had a good deal of medical practice myself while among the natives, but the inveteracy, the long duration of my disease, &amp; its being in the medical category of incurable ones, rather tended to discourage the attempt at a cure.  It proceeds slowly, I have been now more than three months undergoing the process, but the Dr. told me I need not expect even much relief from pain for that time.  Even if I am to continue to improved as the Dr. assures me I shall (D.V.)<!--Deo volente?--> I must continue it for a long time to come.  I shall say no more on this subject, as you will doubtless be able to obtain information as to the nature of the curative process which however laughed at by the ignorant &amp; prejudiced, is really an important discovery of modern times.</p>
      <p>Some of my good friens here, are, however, almost too sanguine, &amp; seem to imagine that I am quite well, which is not yet the case, among these the Bishop, who, upon hearing of my present improvement wrote to congratulate me on my recovery.  But he has done more than this,.  He says I shall probably never be fit for active missionary work, for which my strength, in his opinion, was never adequate, &amp; therefore proposes to put his contemplated college at Porirua (15 miles from this place, about 20 from Waikanae) under my charge, &amp; promises, if I will be the head, "to find me hands &amp; feet").  This suggestion was only made, in a letter a few days ago; so that I hve not yet given it much thought, but I think, for many reasons, if I have strength, Otaki, where there is a concentrated population, &amp; where among my old friends much might be done by me without much fatigue, would be my proper place.  Nor do I feel qualified, in point of education although the Bishop thinks otherwise, for such a post; I have doubtless improved since I left England, I have read much, on many subjects etc. but still my early education was so irregular, so broken in upon by ill-health, that I have <!--previous editor's comment: (page cut)--> readiness &amp; which is necessary.  Nor could I take the step which would tend to separation from the C.M.Society, but this need not do so: still I think Otaki is my proper place &amp; there I might direct others as well as work myself.  He has kindly intimated his wish that I should be Archdeacon of this district, &amp; in fact sent me a patent, but as my mind is at present, I have a firm determination to decline it, first because I have no eduational or other qualifications for a higher office in the church than I now hold; &amp; tho' he says he wishes me only to act as a referee in all matters for the clergy in this part of N.Z. &amp; requires nothing more of me, my bodily strength is not likely to enable me to do what the office implies; namely, visit the stations, especially those under the care of Deacons, &amp; moreover, tho' the Bp. &amp; I have hitherto agreed in all things, I am not quite sure that a close contact might not bring into view differences which when they are foreseen, are better avoided.  He is very kind, I will extract what he says; "The report of your returning health (given by Dr. Fitzgerald) encourages me to fulfil the long cherished wish of appointing you to the Archdeaconry of Kapiti, which has been kept vacant in the hope, however, faint, that you might be able to fill the offie.  I enclose the letter of appointment, which I beg you to accept for my sake &amp; much more for the good of the church.  You have already acted as my commissary &amp; adviser on all occasions, &amp; this will only give a formal &amp; legal sanction to the duties which you have already discharged."</p>
      <p>I was much obliged to you for what you told me about dear George, &amp; for the extracts from the "Record", tho' I subsequently got the papers.  Windle St Hill came here about three months ago.  He is going to school soon at Nelson to a son of Dr. Arnold's, an Oxford first-class man, so he will have a good opportunity of improving himself, but he has been badly spoilt by his father; I have had him in hand teaching him Latin, but tho' a clever boy he does not love books, but how few boys do!  The natives are all going on well at Otaki &amp; throughout my old districts, there are still a goodly number at Waikanae.  Mr. Williams is a hard-working, good man, &amp; does his duty well, so that I have had great cause for thankfulness on that head.  Mr. Cole the clergyman of this place has got an assistant in Mr. Hutton, a deacon ordained by the Bishop about two years ago.  He came here last week.  I heard him preach yesterday - a tolerable sermon, so that we shall do pretty well here, with God's help.  He is to marry a sister of Williams's.  And now, my dear mother, I must close this long letter.  You see I have said nothing about England, but if it were thought advisable, as my Dr. rather thinks it will be, when I become convalescent, that I should have a decided change &amp; thoroughly recover my strength, if such is the will of God, I may yet venture on a voyage to see you all, &amp; then return to my adopted country, &amp; my many children.  Give my kindest &amp; most affectionate love to my father and all others both at home &amp; away from you.  &amp; believe me ever, my dear mother, </p>
      <p>your very affectionate son,
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      <p>I will send you a few late numbers of one of our papers, there is not much in them.  I sometimes amuse myself by writing upon subjects connected with the interest of the native population as they have no protecter, &amp; as the Editor, Mr. Stokes, while he agrees with me does not know much about them, &amp; in order to counteract the mischievous intentions of their enemies who wish to defeat the Govt's wise plans.  There is rather a curious specimen of a native's letter which I translated.  The articles of the other papers were written by me.  You will see I am an upholder of Sir G. Grey; I should dread the consequences of his sudden removal, which some wish to accomplish.  However I have now done with papers as I find my head beginning to</p>
      <p>O.H.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
