<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0060">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1846 December 18: Octavius Hadfield to his brother Rev. George Hadfield</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  Page 149.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 1.12.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1846-12-18">1846 December 18</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/3619/">Wellington</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70976/">George Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1846 December 18: Octavius Hadfield to his brother Rev. George Hadfield</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Wellington, N.Z. December 18th 1846</p>
      <p>My dear George,</p>
      <p>I have not very lately had the pleasure of hearing from you; indeed, the last letter which I have received was dated in May, (from Amelia).  I am afraid it is some time since I last wrote; but, as the vessel which will convey this is going direct, it will probably reach you as soon as one written a month previous.  I have very little to communicate; my letters, now that I am reduced to inactivity can be little more than a monotonous reiteration of my thoughts which run very much on the same subjects <!--previous editor's comment: matter (crossed out)-->.  I doubt not, however, that you still value a few lines from me; quite independent of their subject matter.  My thoughts still dwell principally on the natives of this country, - their advancement in religion and their improvement socially and politically; but few does one meet who are prepared to think deeply on these subjects!  The natives have reached a certain point, by the use of certain means, which means are not inadequate to convey them to another stage in the march of improvement equidistant form the starting-point; other means are now required.  This simple truth many seem unable to perceive, and consequently their farther progress will probably be unduly retarded.  The Bishop's usefulness will be somewhat retarded, (I hope not ultimately impaired) but an apparent inability of seeing the difficulty which must always exist in applying general principles to peculiar cases, more especially where human beings are concerned.  To theorise on ideal notions of perfection which can never be realised in practice, from the necessity of the case, appears to me idle, and in some respects worse, because it tends to alienate the mind and energies from those things which are practicable.  In the application of <hi rend="underline">principles</hi> we must <hi rend="underline">always</hi> expect to meet some modifying circumstances, and some disturbing forces, and not to take these into consideration in forming <hi rend="underline">our</hi> plans, amounts to an absolute error,- as much so as if we were actually proceeding on principles totally false.  Had means been used to anticipate the present position of the natives in a religious point of view,- a position to which I called the attention of the C.M.S. and the Bishop three or four years ago, their uninterrupted progress might have been ensured; as it is they are very much at a standstill.  Though, I hope, not retrograding. - I perhaps look at the dark side of the picture,-as others do not altogether view it as I do; nevertheless, I must claim for myself a greater knowledge of the language than that possessed by many others, and thus a deeper acquaintance with their ideas and feelings,- and this leads me to fear that without far greater exertions on the part of their instructors than have been made in times past, very little improvement will be made in the natives.  </p>
      <p>May the Lord of the vineyard look down and visit this vine, and send into it some active and faithful ministers.  I often ask myself the question why so few go to instruct the heathen,- why visions of trials and difficulties present themselves to the imagination, why friends obstruct, why mens energies seem to sink within them when they contemplate a life spent among the heathen, in preaching the gospel of Jesus Christ?  If I look for reward while endeavouring to serve the Lord, what earthly reward can be conceived greater than the love and gratitude of hundreds of my fellow creatures who regard me as the earthly instrument the Lord Jesus has thought proper to use in dissipating some at least of the darkness in which they had been previously involved?  What richer notion of happiness can we have than that of employing our highest powers in the contemplation of God and His glorious gospel, and of holding communion with the highest parts of other men, that is, with their souls, while engaged together on one common object?  If I have been enabled to enjoy so large a measure of happiness.-  If I have been allowed to see so much fruit of my labour, what might not others have experienced who should have been more holy, more faithful, more diligent, more energetic.  The social and political condition of the natives is likely to improve rapidly, and with it, their moral and religious condition.  The Governor has been diligently engaged in endeavouring to frame some measures tending to advance these objects, which I think are good.  I lately had a letter from him, enclosing some draughts of these and expressing a hope that I should recognise some of my ideas embodied in them.  We are expecting a new Governor, either for the Northern division, or this division of the country.  I hope he will be a man accustomed to <hi rend="underline">think</hi>,- and who has some sense of the responsibility of his office.  I am not very well pleased to hear that the Lord Grey has become Colonial Minister, as I consider him given to crude, hasty measures, and the state of this country requires no more experiments, but sound legislation.  You will smile at my speculations on politics, (especially if they prove erroneous) but I cannot conceive that the Whig ministry can be very securely fixed in office, at least not till a new parliament shall give it security.  In the mean time the colonies suffer much from the constantly changing policy of colonial ministers.  But since the passing of the late free trade measures (good as I believe them to be) it will become absolutely necessary to reconsider all colonial question, and to establish matters on a thoroughly new basis. Very little attention has been given to ecclesiastical affairs in the colonies. While the Bishops have generally assumed high grounds they have very little real power. The common law of England extends to the colonies, but the ecclesiastical does not, nor does the jurisdiction of the ecclesiastical courts in England extend to offences committed in the colonies. <hi rend="underline">There</hi> is nothing but conscience to lead a man to obey the Bishop in matters on which they differ; and conscience is not likely to effect much in this way, when a man conscientiously conceives his own views of the subject in dispute to be the correct ones.  Mr. Taylor, the missionary at Wanganui has sent in to the Bishop a protest against the canons of a Synod held by the Bishop and some of the clergy.  I do not think Mr. Taylor understands the question, and the subject is too important to be treated in the superficial way in which he has treated it.   
      I have a strong impression that the whole of our ecclesiastical affairs require to be thoroughly examined and reformed, and moreover I would submit our prayer book — especially the calendar — to the same process.  The necessity of this might be argued <hi rend="underline">a priori</hi>, from a mere knowledge of the history - both civil and ecclesiastical - of England from the reign of Henry v111. to that of Charles 11 - than which a more unfit period for dispassionate investigation of religious truth can scarcely be conceived, besides, to suppose that any human laws and regulations, while circumstances are altering daily, can be suitable to society from century to century is absurd; but it is clear, and must be so to every unprejudiced mind, that many alterations for the better might easily be made;.  You will perhaps think me a radical in these matters, but you must allow that one is more able to take a dispassionate view of such subjects after having lived some years removed from an atmosphere of prejudice, which I must consider that of the society of clergymen in England is, for the most part, on these questions.  Have you ever read Arnold's works?  With all his crudities and hasty opinions, some very erroneous, I consider him one of those master minds, two or three, of whom a century furnishes.  If you have not read his works pray do, - and you will see a mighty intellect grasping a vast portion of truth and struggling to grapple with the remainder, breaking as Sampson did the new bonds, many of those chains of bondage and prejudices which have encumbered others all their lives.  The <!--previous editor's note: [illegible]--> on the church, with many minor matters to which I should object (non ego paucis offendor maculis<!--Horace: I will not be offended by a few blemishes [in a great work]-->) develop a great truth which must be acknowledged before many of the questions which now disturb christendom can be set at rest.  Excuse my crude incultation.  I was delighted to find that you were able to continue in your work.  May God protect and bless you all.  Pray give my kindest love to all at home. Ever your affectionate brother, 
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      <p>My health continues much as it was.  A very little exertion,-I mean mental, for I only leave my bed for a little exercise- causes me great pain, but when quiet I do not suffer very much.  I sometimes feel inclined to venture on a voyage but am always dissuaded by my friends.  I have not abandoned the idea, though I believe I am still useful in this country.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
