<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0052">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1845 May 2: Octavius Hadfield to his sister Amelia</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  Page 118.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 30.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1845-05-02">1845 May 2</date>
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/71117/">Amelia Hadfield (daughter of Amelia Caroline Hadfield, nee White)</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/71117/">Amelia Hadfield (daughter of Amelia Caroline Hadfield, nee White)</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1845 May 2: Octavius Hadfield to his sister Amelia</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>When I last wrote, I felt little prospect of being able to write again.  Since that period however, I have been much more free from pain, &amp; am now feeling stronger.  I gladly avail myself of the opportuniy afforded me by a ship going direct, to write to you.  I am not aware that I have received any letter from home since my last; the two latest that I have received were yours of Aug. &amp; my Father's of Sep.  I shall expect to hear again very soon, &amp; may I hear that you are all prospering &amp; in health.</p>
      <p>I am still confined to my bed, where I have been during the last four or five months, I am able however to sit up occasionally without much inconvenience or pain for a short time, which affords me relief. Had I expected to have lived till the present time, I should probably have endeavoured to reach home in order to have spent my last days with you, but as it was impossible to look into futurity, &amp; as it is uncertain what effect on me a voyage round Cape Horn would have had, it is useless to regret not having made the attempt to do so.  I feel that I am in the hands of God, &amp; under His direction, and not seeing my way clear to move, I concluded that I ought to remain patiently where I am.  I feel even now that I am not altogether useless, though as you must probably imagine, I must be approaching the verge of inutility: still, such is the lamentable ignorance among all classes here, of all matters connected with the aborigines that my advice, in this part of N.Z. is continually sought, both on questions more immediately concerning religion, and also by the government on secular affairs.  I am still residing in my old quarters, as Mr. &amp; Mrs. St.Hill positively refuse to let me leave them.  Various friends have wished me to go and stay with them, and have manifested the greatest kindness towards me, so that I do not want friends.  I have every want supplied by the dear friends with whom I now am, if you picture to yourself two kind and amiable persons, well-educated, with delicate &amp; refined feelings, overflowing with love and affection, &amp; always the same - then you see these two dear people.  Whatever, as a sister, you could wish either to do for me, or that I should have, that you may rest assured is now done for me, I now possess.  May God grant them every blessing.</p>
      <p>With respect to my complaint, tho' I am feeling much easier, I have no reason to believe that it has taken any favourable turn; the comparative ease which I enjoy rather arises from alleviating medicines having been administered, Prussic Acid etc.  I continue, thro' the grace of God, to enjoy that calm peace in my soul which the blessed religion we believe, is always able to afford.  What an inestimable blessing for a sinner to be able to look at his sins, without fear - at death without a doubt of the ultimate result at the judgement day, without consternation!  Oh the perfect security of a soul who believes in Jesus, of one whose life is hid<!--sic?--> - with Christ in God!</p>
      <p>The Bishop and Mrs. Selwyn have been during the last five weeks at Waikanae and Otaki. He has written to me several times to let me know what he is doing among my dear people. He seems very much interested in their welfare. He cannot remain much longer with them &amp; feels at a loss how to supply them with a pastor.  I shall expect to see him again in a week or two, when perhaps he may have formed some plan for supplying them with some person for a time.  He came to see me on his way there.  You would be surprised to see him when he is with me.  He seems to love me.  He talks about all the concerns of a church in the Colony.  He talks to me about my own soul; he prays with me and then with tears in his eyes gives me a kiss and leaves me.  He is a most remarkable man.  I never saw his equal.  He possesses talent of the first order, and comprises the most opposite qualities.  With a most acute intellect he unites the patience which will enable him to spend hours day after day catechising the most ignorant and stupid little native children.  With the greatest self-denial and indefatigable industry, he unites that feeling of charity which enables him to appreciate and value the very inferior labours of others.  He possesses a courage which no opposition can daunt; - a determination of purpose which no obstacle can arrest; - a resolute adherence to principle which no apparent advantage can for a moment interrupt.  He is appreciated by all who are at all able to estimate the character of a man so much above the ordinay standard of that <hi rend="underline">imperfect perfection</hi> which we have any grounds for expecting in any human being.  May the Lord in mercy preserve him many years.  </p>
      <p>Before this reaches you, the account of the disturbances of Kororareka &amp; the general excitement in the country will have appeared in the public papers &amp; you will doubtless be feeling some alarm concerning us all in this distant colony. I think the general tenor of my letters, as far as I have lately alluded to political affairs, must have led you to believe that neither the general management of ecclesiastical matters, nor the proceedings of government were in my opinion calculated to promote rapidly either the spiritual or temporal welfare of the natives; indeed, if I remember rightly, in my last letter I broke off abruptly when about to speak of the incapacity of the present Governor, &amp; the pernicious tendency of his measures.  The evil, which might easily, humanly speaking, have been averted is now commencing; &amp; where it may end, if the present vacillating policy is pursued by the Government, no human being can predict.  It is a difficult thing to think calmly &amp; with moderation while reflecting on the manner in which England always has mismanaged her colonies. I am no Radical; but if ever any radical change was requisite - such a change is necessary in these proceedings of the Colonial Office.  Nobody who has not lived in a colony can form the most remote conception of the pitiable imbecility of the colonial policy.  The history of colonial proceedings seems a history of egregious and contemptible blunders.  Never perhaps did an opportunity offer of establishing a colony with better prospects of doing so with advantage both to the aborigines &amp; to the colonists; &amp; never was such an opportunity so thoroughly lost.  In truth, when one reflects on the boasted civilisation and advancement in political science which the present generation arrogates to itself, one is lost in astonishment at the vast discrepancy between the theory and the practice, between the high-sounding professions and the deplorable facts—one would suppose that, now in the middle of the 19th century, N.Z. had been selected by political charlatans as a platform whereon to see who could best play the fool. The Governor is a cleverish, well-disposed man, but there is a vast deal of difference between wit and wisdom; &amp; it is never more visible than when a man is thrown upon his own resources in a responsible situation &amp; to be well-disposed without discretion, is no qualification for governing however amiable it may be in itself.  I very much doubt whether there is any one man connected with the Local Government who can even guess at the probable effect of any measure which concerns the aborigines.  What hopes can I then have that any of their acts will have the effect of ameliorating the natives, or of restoring the good feeling which once existed.  The only consolation in these times of doubt is that which is derived from looking up to Him who reigns on high.</p>
      <p>The Government &amp; the settlers have laboured under a misapprehension from the beginning - they have not known their real position in relation to the natives - they have mistaken a desire for peace, for cowardice - they have mis-imagined that combustible material because not ignited, were inorganic matter and would not burn; - in a word, that because the natives - who were under christian influence - did not steal and murder, that they were incapable of doing so, that because they submitted to insults that they would always submit to them.  Had the government &amp; settlers come further <!--should this have been transcribed as "hither"?--> before missionary influence had been exerted in a beneficial way, they would have at one seen the difficulties they had to content with, &amp; have determined at once on facing them boldly or declining to do so.  But as it is, the government have had no difficulty hitherto to grapple &amp; because they had now invariably assumed that there never had been any, and that there would be none.  They have in fact gone, hitherto on the assumption that the natives were naturally what they were thro' the influence of religion, placed too much reliance on it, assuming erroneously that the collateral effects of it were its direct effects: in other words, forgetting that where there is real religion in ten persons, their influence will make it appear that a hundred are religious in ordinary times, but that in extraordinary times, ninety will fall off, and only ten remain.  </p>
      <p>I have written, perhaps you will think, in an unusual &amp; censorious strain, but my object is to guard you against the probable assertion that the missionaries have done nothing &amp; that there is no real religion among the natives.  Those who assert most loudly the inefficiency of missionary exertions, are those whose practial immorality &amp; infidel principles, tend to counteract them.  They endeavour to unite the natives against religion &amp; the missionaries &amp; then say "look how little is done by religion."  As though when a physician is administering suitable remedies to a patient, a man should secretly give him antidotes &amp; then say see how little effect your remedies have!"  I am daily more &amp; more astonished at the imbecility &amp; unreasonableness of the human mind.  I shall say no more, you will gather my meaning from these remarks.  I hope I have not written quite illegibly: you must excuse me for I write in bed &amp; I now seldom write at all.  Give my most affectionate love to my dear Parents, &amp; brothers &amp; sisters, &amp; remember me kindly to all old friends, &amp; believe me, my dear sister, ever your affectionate brother, 
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
