<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0057">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1846 April 13: Octavius Hadfield to his sister Caroline</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  Page 136.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 1.12.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1846-04-13">1846 April 13</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/3619/">Wellington</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/71143/">Caroline Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1846 April 13: Octavius Hadfield to his sister Caroline</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Wellington, April 13, 1846.</p>
      <p>My dear Caroline,</p>
      <p>I was much delighted with your letter of October, the last which I have received.  The only thing which prevents my entire enjoyment of your letters is that I cannot but feel painfully sensible of how much anxiety I cause you all; - this I perceive in every sentence, still, I suppose did you not express some anxiety about me, I might fancy you indifferent, which I might like less,- such inconsistent creatures are we, for I suppose that our love towards an absent person must be the measure of our anxiety concerning that person.  Nevertheless, as Christians, though our love towards those who are dear to us is increased, and the ties of nature are rendered infinitely more permanent and therefore real by a new union with each other in a common Head and Saviour, we are bound continually to remember that in our present state of ignorance, it is our highest wisdom, as well as our greatest source of peace and comfort, to live in perfect acquiescence to the Divine Will, and in thankful resignation to the Divine dispensations - I am fully convinced that the first step to real happiness is to become sensible of our utter ignorance, I mean, of course, in matters of religion, for few people would be more ready than I am to acknowledge the powers of the human intellect when employed upon those subjects which are really within its grasp, those which are not resting upon hypotheses, but upon facts and self-evident axioms.  I have become more thoroughly impresed with the importance of continually bearing this truth in mind by reading the works of the greatest geniuses, such as Butler, Bacon, etc. who not only acknowledge it, but put it forward in a prominent manner.  Nothing can be really more absurd to a man who has accustomed his mind to think, than many of the foolish cavils of clever men, both against the evidence of christianity and its revealed truths.  Hume's argument against the evidences of christianity from the insufficiency of human testimony, equally applies against all history.  His metaphysical analysis of the laws of human thought, and his attempt to invalidate the principles on which reason rests, if it would prove anything would prove too much, for it would prove that we are not reasonable beings, but even this he must do by argument which according to his own showing is no argument.  I am surprised that he was thought so much of in his day.  When we have once received the scriptures as the Word of God, as a message from Heaven resting on good credentials, we are bound to believe all the truths which it contains.  Some people say they will believe what they can understand.  But I would say what can we understand?  Even in physical things we deceive ourselves by words,- we see lightning, we say it is caused by electricity, we see a certain attraction and we call it magnetism; but in truth, these expressions and a thousand similar ones are mere cloaks for our ignorance, they in no degree convey an idea of the cause which remains in impenetrable obscurity.  But in spiritual things this obscurity, from the very nature of the case becomes enhaned in proportion as the objects are removed from our view.  We talk of a spirit, but what a spirit is, no human language can define.  We may say what it is not, and by a tedious process of abstraction obtain an idea, a very obscure one at best,- of what we mean by it, but what it really is in itself we are and ever must <!--previous editor's note: "remain (crossed out)"--> while possessed only of our present faculties remain, in utter and hopeless ignorance of.  I confess I once attributed my ignorance on these subjects to my own obtuse faculties, but since reading the writings of Butler, Bacon, Locke, Hobbes and others, I clearly see that there are from the very nature of the case definite limits to the objects of human knowledge and that though the world were to last ten thousand years longer and the human intellect become more and more capacious, that there are some objects which never can be clearly brought within its grasp.  Now without alluding to innumerable controverted questions.  A Unitarian tells me that the doctrine of the Trinity is incomprehensible; I am quite ready to allow it, but I must reply that it is quite as difficult to comprehend God, in unity as it is in Trinity, that is that we can form no clear idea of either one or the other.  We can form an idea of God as a Being Who is good, wise, powerful, etc., but as to what His nature really is, - so as to be expressed in any definite form of words - we are, and ever must remain as utterly ignorant as new born babes.  We believe that man consists of body and soul; but can anyone understand this union.  We know from hourly experience that mind acts upon body, but can any philosopher, can any human being, form an idea of <hi rend="underline">how</hi> it acts; .  No-one has hitherto attempted such an impossible explanation, and yet every body firmly believes it.  I am every day becoming more and more astonished at both the ignorance and presumption of man; really, some people,- generally the most ignorant,- talk as if they knew something,-.  I am thankful that I have learned from scripture- and this has been abundantly confirmed by the most profound philosophers- that we really know nothing of things in themselves and that our wisdom is to express humility.  I find I am getting through my paper and have done no more than write down two or three commonplace remarks.  Notwithstanding, I suppose you like to have an idea of the style of thoughts that pass through my Head as I lie here exercising my memory on the past and my faith on the future; Still, I think I must ask for your indulgence for my dry style of writing.  I must now cross this, for hitherto I have really said nothing.  I must beg you to convey to Charles my hearty congratulations on his marriage, and an assurance of my earnest desire for his happiness, and that of his wife, and I hope to hear from him soon.  Tell him I have seen Horsbrook <!-- previous editor's note: (Horsbrooke?).--> <!--this editor's note: name written as MS annotation in both forms - could be Hoisbrooke--> who is in the Calliope and Harrison who is in the Castor, they both enquired very kindly after him  My old friend Craigy, who was master of the Pelorus in which I came to New Zealand, and is now master of the Castor enquired after Henry, for he went out to India with him once.  I was happy to hear Alexander was in better health.  Your account of George also was very satisfactory.  I trust he may continue in good health and be able to continue at work.  I am not quite certain whether I answered his last letter to me, which was a very short one.  I do hope you will not, any of you, allow my illness at this distance from you to be a cause of constant anxiety to you.  I really suffer now very little, and even in bed here, for I seldom stay up more than an hour at a time, I find I am of some little use; so that you ought not to grieve about me.  I have all and abound.  I rejoice continually, and live in peace and in the prospect of eternal happiness; why then on any account should I cause anxiety to others.  My friends here are all as kind as ever.  I am afraid in every respect I am over-rated very much by the Bishop and others from what you mention and from what I hear here.  But I know from whence that kind feeling emanates towards persons in sickness so that it does me no harm.  The state of New Zealand is by no means satisfactory.  The rebellion at the North has been quelled, but affairs there are not settled on a very firm basis in my opinion at least. Down here affairs are far from settled. Two whites were murdered by two natives here about ten days ago. The murderers are known but cannot be obtained as yet by the Government from the party who refuse to surrender them. About 200 are now in arms, but as the Government has a strong force here, and nine-tenths of the natives, with Te Rauparaha at their head are in favour of Government, I hope the question will soon be settled, though from want of a proper and systematic way of proceeding the Government sadly confuse questions. A native was lately tried for robbery and sentenced to ten years transportation. Subsequently I discovered that he was innocent and memorialised the Governor on the subject, and though the matter is not quite settled, I have no doubt...he...will be set at liberty.  Six white witnesses swore positively to him and yet he has proved a clear alibi.  You may easily imagine the state of feeling existing between the two races which could lead to such prejudice and blindness.  I have seen a good deal of our new Governor Captain Grey.  He is a very clever man but not a talented man.  He is very honest, unprejudiced and desirous of doing good, but not possessing very much decision of character or much judgement.  His intellect is rather acute than comprehensive, and more prone to see analogies than differences in things, and rather too ready to jump at conclusions; still, I have a very high opinion of him, and much admire the high moral tone that he assumes which is important in these colonies, where people generally retrograde on that point.  If I had a good opinion of myself, I ought to have a good opinion of him for he values my opinions very highly.  He has been with me a dozen times and has sat by my bed-side for two hours or more at a time, discussing questions of importance to the welfare of the colony.  I have carried some of my points.  I stated some of my opinions at some length on paper which he thanked me for.  But I do not flatter myself that my wisdom is so much in request as that he knows he can depend on the accuracy of all the information he obtained from me.  You may remember I was always very positive and dogmatical; I am so still on points where I know I am right, and I find this has the effect I wish.  Excuse this long epistle.  Give my kindest and most affectionate love to my father and mother and all my beloved brothers and sisters, ever your affectionate brother,   
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      <p>The Christian natives are all going on tolerably well.  Mr. Govett is still taking charge at Waikanae and Otaki.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
