<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0075">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1849 December 28: Octavius Hadfield to his sister Maria</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  "Letter 6."  Page 220.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 8.12.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1849-12-28">1849 December 28</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/3619/">Wellington</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70928/">Maria Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1849 December 28: Octavius Hadfield to his sister Maria</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Wellington Dec. 28. 1849</p>
      <p>My dear Maria,</p>
      <p>Since I last wrote, which I am sorry to say was so far back as Sep., I have had the pleasure of receiving your letter of June, also one from Henry &amp; one from Charles of about the same date, &amp; also one from George &amp; one from Julia of a few weeks earlier date.  Please accept my best thanks for your one, &amp; give them to those who have written me such gratifying letters.  I have just heard that a small man of war, (the "Swift") which came in here a day or two ago, after leaving Smith O'Brien etc at Hobart Town, is on her way to Valparaiso &amp; will send a mail home by way of Panama.  I wish I had more time than I have today, but I will try &amp; say a little about myself &amp; what is going on here.  </p>
      <p>When I last wrote I was just on the eve of making a trip up the coast with Mr. Lloyd to visit my previous sphere of labour, &amp; since that I have not written because there was nothing likely to get home soon: now at last an opportunity offers.  Mr. Lloyd was so pleased with what he saw; &amp; his own observations led him to such different conclusions from thos he had previously arrived at from the reports of others, that he thought he would state his own impressions &amp; give them to the public.  I sent you a paper containing his letter.  If it reached you it must have done as well if not better than a letter from me.</p>
      <p>Assuming then that you have already had an account of my first trip, I shall give some further account of my proceedings.  I was much gratified by what I witnessed all along the coast; but more especially by what I saw at Otaki.  The natives were delighted to see me again among them, &amp; received me with every token of love &amp; affection.  And I was delighted to see that they had changed in every respect for the better since I left them nearly five years before.  They have been under various disadvantages.  There was war going on here for some time which must have tended much to distract &amp; unsettle them.  They have had three different clergymen to minister among them, &amp; only one of these, Mr. S. Williams well acquainted with the language.  Moreover they have been exposed to very bad examples set them by those who ought to have known better.  Notwithstanding these &amp; many other drawbacks they have gone on steadily improving.  All things, I trust, have worked together for their good.  And I was able even in the darkest times, to believe this even when many were almost dreading a serious apostacy among the natives from the strength of the temptations which beset them.  I think that I impressed this conviction on you some years ago when writing on the subject.</p>
      <p>In preaching the Gospel, the great object to have in view, is to lay a right foundation, &amp; to erect a right superstructure.  To omit the first is of course fatal; but to omit the last will be no less fatal in its result, &amp; that at no very distant time.  To work as a missionary the mind ought to be able to grasp general principles, &amp; to apply them not according to rules drawn from experience in a civilised community, but according to the genius of the people among <supplied>[whom]</supplied> one works; &amp; I am surprised how few people are able to do this.  It has been always my object to fix the minds &amp; souls of the people upon the grand universal principles of the gospel, &amp; to refrain from littering their minds &amp; cramming them with minutiae.  The result, by the divine blessing, has surpassed my expectations.  The opposite course, such for instance as would be adopted by a high-churchman, would be necessarily a failure.  But I am forgetting that I am writing a letter, intended to say something about the natives.</p>
      <p>I was absent from Wellington a month with Mr. Lloyed.  I found Mr. Williams busily engaged with the natives &amp; working very hard with his whole heart in the work, &amp; speaking capital Maori so that there is no chance of anything he says to them being misunderstood.  I found all the young men I had left as teachers still retaining their positions &amp; going on well, which was very satisfactory to me.  And I found a better attendance at the services of the church than formerly; &amp; the children generally more attentive &amp; regular.  I administered the Lord's supper at Otaki, Waikanae &amp; Manawatu to large numbers, when Mr. W. &amp; I met previously on several occasions for conversation.  I likewise, assisted by Mr. W., examined and baptised several persons at these places.  </p>
      <p> The church that is building at Otaki is a very fine structure &amp; has been much admired by all competent judges.  It is eight feet long by thirty-six wid &amp; fifty high.  I am having some lancet windows with lead diamond panes made which will look very well.  Though they have had a great deal to do in moving from their old native Pa or village &amp; forming their new town, they have bestowed great labour on the church, freely admitting that was the chief work, nor have they flagged in their work during the whole period of their labour upon it.  I think I once mentioned that it would be difficult to estimate the amount of labour bestowed upon it.</p>
      <p>Mr. W. &amp; I have managed to scrape together some 50 or 60 pounds to pay for some of those things we are obliged to purchase - windows etc.  &amp; the Bishop has promised us something, still I am afraid we shall be rather short; but we shall complete it in time.  In a temporal respect also the natives have made great improvement, though there is still room for more.  They have now a great many horses &amp; cows, &amp; cultivate wheat &amp; also a good many vegetables.  I am continually endeavouring now to improve their clothing; but it is not easy to see my way in this matter.  They have quite means enough wherewith to sustain it, but they want discretion &amp; they are much imposed upon by those who deal with them.</p>
      <p>I returned to Wellington for a fortnight at the end of October &amp; then went to Otaki again for seven weeks whence I returned the day before yesterday.  On my first visit to Otaki I soon saw how I might employ a few weeks, &amp; Mr. W. agreed with me in my plan.  The teachers employed by us in the different villages labour under some disadvantages by their almost constant absence from our immediate instructions.  Without, therefore, interfering with Mr. W.'s own particular work, I proposed to have all the teachers in with me for a few weeks, which I had when I was last there.  I had only fifteen out of more than twenty, (some were absent from sickness-influenza, which has been very prevalent) but they were with me about three hours a day, in the fore-noon &amp; in the afternoon.  I had lectures with them which interested them very much; but being obliged to keep them only for a short time at this season of the year I could not carry them on very far.  The result however of my experiment has been highly encouraging, as they appeared to profit by what they heard, &amp; also to be well pleased.  What is now most wanted is some means of carrying the teachers somewhat farther than our ordinary general instructions go.  I propose (D.V.) to return to Otaki shortly &amp; to carry out some plan with this object in view.  I can find in this way more work than I can get through with.  And I should likewise, by being on the spot, enable Mr. W. to visit the surrounding villages more frequently &amp; with greater comfort when he knew I was on the spot- My health continues very good, though the warm weather at Otaki &amp; the necessity of attending to the numerous sik (from influenza) weakened me a little.  Dr. Fitzgerald tells me I must rest a little though it is a difficult matter.  I rode fortytwo miles the day before yesterday, so you may imagine I am pretty strong, &amp; I roughed the other day just the same.  I hope to be at Otaki again in a week or two.  I intended to have written to George but I find the vessel sails immediately.  I wrote to him in my last letter about our proposed college.  It is, I hear from the Bishop, delayed on account of some legal difficulty about a title owing to the N.Z.Company's agent's hostility.  I do not know whether the Bishop may have written to George, but since I wrote to George I begin to doubt from the tenor of his last letter whether he would agree well with the Bishop.  I am afraid the Bp. is very crotchety &amp; that G. would find it a hard matter to carry out his own plans.  Please tell him this if he should have given what I wrote any thought.  I was sorry to hear Alexander's health was so delicate.  The accounts, however, from home were as good as I could expect.  Please write often &amp; tell me what you are all about.  I am now too well to think of going to England, unless some mission business required it, &amp; my life is too uncertain to allow me to wish any of you should come here unless you came in a body.  </p>
      <p>Give my kindest love to my Father &amp; Mother &amp; all at home, etc &amp; kind remembrances to all friends, of whom I am always delighted to hear.</p>
      <p>Ever your very affectionate brother,
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
