<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0031">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1841 January 20: Octavius to Octavia Hadfield</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  "Letter 38". Page 69.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 25.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1841-01-20">1841 January 20</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70954/.">Kapiti</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key=" http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70767/">Octavia Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1841 January 20: Octavius to Octavia Hadfield
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Kapiti</p>
      <p>Cooks Straits</p>
      <p>New Zealand.</p>
      <p>Jan. 20th. 1841</p>
      <p>My dear Octavia,</p>
      <p>Expecting to have an hour this morn to myself, I cannot employ it more to my satisfaction than by writing to you.  The last letter I wrote was in Nov. addressed to Henry, since then I have had the pleasure of receiving one form you dated April &amp; two severally from my mother &amp; George dated June.  I feel very thankful for them, &amp; trust you will write as often as you can, two or three ships have lately arrived from England to this place without bringing any letters; I am in hopes of hearing again soon.  I was sorry to hear you had been such invalids last spring, but this latter letter gives better accounts.  I often think of you, &amp; sometimes wish to be among you again, but "the will of the Lord be done;" I have so much work here that I cannot even indulge the thought of ever paying you a visit, nevertheless we may hope, tho' it be but a faint hope.  I was glad to hear that Mrs. Squire had kindly remembered Charlotte in her will. I hope it may make them more comfortable.  May the Lord guide &amp; prosper you all &amp; dispose of you according to His will &amp; to His glory, &amp; may I continually hear that the God of peace is with you all, filling you with all joy &amp; peace in believing, &amp; what shall I say of myself?  It would well become me to be silent, &amp; to bow myself down in the dust when I reflect on my sinfulness &amp; unprofitableness; how apt are poor sinful worms of the earth to speak of themselves &amp; their doings, when they are only in the Lord's hand like the hammer &amp; chisel in that of the workman, yeah, while they are speaking in commendation of their work, the sentence of the righteous Judge may have gone forth that their "work shall be burned &amp; themselves saved, yet so as by fire", yeah, "I know thy works, that thou hast a name, that thou lived and are dead", may be the judgement of the heart-searching God.  I feel deeply that this may be my case, yea, probably is: Oh,! "the deceitfulness of the heart, Who can know it".  With these feelings then, it is with fear &amp; trembling that I speak or write; &amp; yet it is necessary to say something lest we give a handle for scoffing to infidels, or allow the saints to think that the Saviour's Kingdom will not, according to the promises, be extended thro' every land.  Dear George complains of the dearth of particulars concerning missionary proceedings, but is it to be expected that the missionary should give an account of his own? is it likely? is it decent?  I have only written two letters to the C.M.S. Committee since I have been in New Zealand.  I must however, now write again to state facts.  But to say something before my paper is fulfilled: I must give you some account of a very interesting trip I had to the Middle Island in December.  Soon after my arrival here the year before last, a large party from Queen Charlotte Sounds arrived here to see their friends &amp; relations, after the battle that was fought a few weeks before; these remained here some months &amp; constantly attended school etc. on their return I supplied them with books, slates etc. in order that they might carry on the same system on their returning home.  I occasionally heard from some of the teachers.  I promised, notwithstanding my multiplied &amp; daily multiplying engagements, to pay them a visit.  The windy weather being over, I started in my boat with five natives to cross the Strait, a canoe likewise accompanying me, I was detained a few days on this coast by contrary wind about twenty miles from this where I employed my time among the natives, who now in every direction pay me great respect.  I started at eight o'clock with a light breeze which soon died away, we then rowed for about three hours, the canoe left us, when a breeze sprang up, &amp; we were obliged to run for the north entrance of the Sound which from the ebb tide made the sea very rough, we however reached it at six o'clock in the even, when I was thankful to land safely.  I passed ten days in the sound, which is surrounded by mountains, with scarcely 10 acres of level land to be found anywhere.  I visited all the natives I could get near, &amp; was much pleased with the way they received me &amp; attended to my instructions.  I spent about a week at Okukari where there are a great many natives; there they have built a very large place of worship, &amp; are very regular &amp; attentive at school, &amp; are well behaved.  Some of them I found well informed in many of the doctrines of the Scriptures.  While here, a leading chief of the Ngatitoa tribe arrived from Kapiti to accompany me to Cloudy Bay.  Leaving Okukari with feelings of regret at parting with those interesting people, I went to Cloudy Bay, &amp; there I found that a Wesleyan teacher, a Mr. Ironside, whom I had previously seen at Waimate, had arrived the day before; at this I was not over well pleased, &amp; I found that another was going to Port Nicholson.  I remained there a few days; some of the natives join him &amp; others continue with me &amp; my people.  I had divine service also on Christmas Day with the English there, &amp; preached for the first time in English for the past fourteen months; they were very civil to me.  I returned to the Sound &amp; spent a few more days there among some natives I had not previously seen; &amp; then, taking leave of the Sound &amp; it's <!--sic--> inhabitants, with regret, with the purpose however, if the Lord will, of revisiting it.  I sailed, accompanied by four large canoes, at two o'clock with a fine breeze, &amp; reached the Island of Maria at 7 o'clock to my comfort &amp; satisfaction.  My boat is too small, several of the white men about this blamed me for crossing in it, but I had no alternative; I do not however, purpose venturing again in it.  I have now got Wesleyans &amp; Papists in my neighbourhood to my great sorrow.  I do not know which will do most harm, I think the former, as their notions &amp; ceremonies suit the native disposition well, &amp; they baptise all those <supplied>(who)</supplied> will join them, whereas I look for faith &amp; repentance ere I will administer that sacrament, this naturally draws the weak-minded the vain &amp; the ignorant into their ranks.  I do not, however, &amp; cannot acknowledge the validity of lay baptism, &amp; therefore do not acknowledge theirs.  It requires more talent &amp; power of reasoning than either Hooker or Milner have shown to convince me to the contrary; indeed the imbecility of the latter writer manifested on the subject in his life etc. of Cyprian is remarkable.  I consider that Bishop more sound in his view of the subject.  The papists on the other hand can only make converts when the Gospel has not been preached.  Their profanation of the Lord's Day, their withholding of the second commandment, their image worship, etc. are too glaring marks of the man of sin not to be perceived by New Zealanders.  Their publications also, small as they are in the language, are so wretchedly written that I will defy any native to understand one single sentence, I conceived at first that it must be a burlesque, but afterwards saw that it was really theirs.  Peace is now fully established between the two tribes among whom I live; the sons of the leading chiefs of both sides have respectively visited the opposite party.  This at least is one point I have gained; so far the Gospel has displayed its power.  I yesterday added up a list of my schoools in different places around me &amp; found that about 600 this is under the mark meet daily to learn to read &amp; write &amp; also to learn the catechism they have in use; about one half of these can read &amp; write tolerably, but there are many hundreds who have learnt without any regular school.  These are my weapons against wesleyans &amp; papists, &amp; while they glory in the sight of men, &amp; boast of the numbers they have baptised "verily they have their reward" may I look forward to the great day of account, &amp; labour diligently, trusting that a "few" sealed by the Holy Ghost will be my "crown of rejoicing and glory".  In outward labours I think, tho' here I may err, I am not deficient, as I give myself but little rest &amp; am nearly always among these people talking of divine things.  I this time of the year attend school at four o'clock in the morn daily, &amp; my evening lecture closes at about nine; during all this time I am liable to be interrupted.  I have also the hearts of the natives who see that I give myself a great deal of trouble in their behalf.  But with all this, "My heart condemns me", I preach &amp; I teach etc. but I pray but little, &amp; that in truth is the great secret of ministerial usefulness.  My love has grown cold &amp; my faith weak.  I will not attempt to excuse myself, but oh, what would I now give for one Sabbath in the midst of some holy congregation at home; you can perhaps enter into my feelings.  Pray that the Lord may be with me, that a precious Saviour may be daily becoming more precious &amp; that I may live nearer to my God; &amp; now my beloved sisters, praying to you to give my affectionate love to my Father &amp; Mother &amp; all my dear brothers &amp; sisters, &amp; likewise to remember me to all friends.</p>
      <p>Believe me, with everlasting love,</p>
      <p>your affectionate brother,
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
