<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0073">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1849 September 15: Octavius Hadfield to his brother Rev. George Hadfield</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  "Letter 8."  Page 210.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 8.12.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1849-09-15">1849 September 15</date>
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70976/">George Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70976/">George Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1849 September 15: Octavius Hadfield to his brother Rev. George Hadfield</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Wellington Sep. 15. 1849</p>
      <p>My dear George,</p>
      <p>By a letter which I recently received from Octavia dated April 13th. I learnt that you had finally resolved to settle your differences with the Committee who originated the College at Malta by resigning your post.  Of course when a decided difference exists, that is the only course left for one to pursue.  I learnt, however with regret your removal from a sphere of labour for which I knew you were so well suited.  Octavia was kind enough to send me a few extracts from your letters, enabling me thus to see how your resignation of your charge was forced upon you.  She mentions likewise the prospect of your again going to assist your friend Mr. Churton,.  On hearing that you had resigned your Charge at Malta the thought struck me that you might be directed to this country.  I have already mentioned in some of my letters home that a college is to be established in this neighbourhood, about 15 miles from this place, &amp; that the Bishop had wished me to take charge of it.  I can hardly tell what induced him to offer it to me  But I believe his chief object must have been to make me a beginning, &amp; he at present has nobody to whom he could entrust it.  Besides, I believe he thinks my name would be a sort of guarantee to our Missionaries &amp; the Ch.Mis.Soc. that it would be conducted on such principles as they approve.  And I suppose he only expected from me a general superintendence as he places great confidence, much more than I deserve, in my judgement.  I lately wrote to tell the Bishop that I really could not undertake it, as I felt myself incompetent for the position, &amp; I was quite sure I should disappoint others; but the only reply I received was that he purposed being down here in Decr. &amp; that we could again talk over the matter. </p>
      <p>The College must necessarily I suppose be begun in a very small way, both because I am not aware that any large amount of funds are in the Bishop's hands for the purpose, &amp; because there are not many subordinate teachers to be had; preparations are however, already being made for the erection of temporary buildings that a beginning may be made at once.  The idea of the College is that it should contain, as it were, two schools &amp; two Colleges: a school for English boys where they may begin their education, &amp; then a higher department where their education may be carried on with a view to ordination, which may of course be entered without their having gone through the lower school by those whose education qualifies them for it: also a school for native children where they will receive English education.  This will be composed of children carefully selected from all the district schools. ; &amp; then a higher one in which their education may be proceeded with, which may be made instrumental in qualifying them to act as teachers, or even to becom eligible for ordination.  I look upon this projected college as of the highest importance, both as respects the future well-being of the native race &amp; the prosperity of the Colony generally.  We are not, as you know, rich out here, but the natural resources of the country are great: to obtain a decent subsistence is not difficult.  The Bishop therefore proposes to combine with the educational department an industrial system by means of which much may be done towards supporting the Institution.  This, if not carried to excess, I highly approve of, as it tends to impart habits of industry &amp; co-operation which are highly essential everywhere, but especially in a country like this, &amp; so far as concerns the native population, must prove beneficial.  As I have already remarked, it must be small in the beginning; but if founded on right principles, &amp; carried on wisely, its ultimate good effect on the country would be very great.  I have thought much on the subject, &amp; if I were competent for the management of the Institution there is nothing which I think would be likely to be a more useful sphere of labour.  What should you think of coming to be the head of it?  <hi rend="underline">I</hi> think it would suit you &amp; you it, but what may my opinion after all be worth?  And how can I be sure that a desire to have you again with me may not bias my judgement?  You know how highly I have always expressed myself as to this country &amp; its lovely climate.  You could not do otherwise than improve in health here, I of course mean as respects those ailments from which you have suffered in your Chest &amp; stomach.  The surgeon of the 65th. Regt. which has been two years in the country, said he had never heard of any climate in which there was so little sickness; that with the charge of 1000 men he really had scarcely anything to do.  When thoughts come into my mind I like to come out with them, &amp; so I now write to you upon this subject; &amp; I wrote last week to the Bishop upon it.  I told him I could not of course say what you might be engaged in by the time a letter reached you, but that I thought it would be as well for him to write to you &amp; state his own views to you, &amp; that it would be as well to refer you to his brother that you might fully understand his plans, &amp; ascertain whether your views of education agree with his.  There are some things to be taken into consideration: I will mention them.  Up to the present time the College at Auckland has not succeeded.  I know very little of the cause of this.  It is ascribed by some to the Bishop's High Church notions which have given offence;- to his being crotchety &amp; adhering to plans which are abstractedly good in themselves but unsuited to the people he has to deal with; &amp; to the fact of his never having had a proper head to the College, he himself being necessarily much absent from it.  As the Bishop is now absent from N.Z. &amp; will not be at Auckland until the beginning of next month, he will not receive my letter until then, when I have very little doubt he will write to you.  I am sure you will think of the subject.  May the Lord direct you.  Should you come, &amp; any of our sisters like to come with you, let them come by all means, there is something to be done by all here who feel inclined to do anything, &amp; it is very easy to live here.  On Sunday last, just as I left the Pulpit in the English Church, I was delighted to find myself addressed by a Clergyman who had just landed from a ship which had come to anchor while we were in Church, having come from England.  His name is Lloyd.  He brought me a letter of introduction sent through Geo. Dawson.  He is come out unconnected with any Society, having private means for his support, &amp; brings letters from the primate of Ireland to the Bishop.  He wishes to labour among the natives, but will be disposed of as the Bishop may think fit.  He appears an excellent man; very well educated: unmarried &amp; about 35 years of age.  I have not been in such high spirits for a long time.  He tells me he knows several men who are ready to come out, among others, Henry Cobbe who was at Charterhouse with me and worked with him in a parish <!--previous editor's note: (incomplete)-->  
      </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
