<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0039">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1842 November 19: Hadfield to ?</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960. (page 90)</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 20.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1842-11-19">1842 November 19</date>
                  
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1842 November 19: Hadfield to ?
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Nov 19th 1842</p>   
         <p>“I have two clergymen now come into my part of the country, one is at Wellington, the Rev R Cole, he I fear will do little good; he was sent out by the Gospel <!--[blank]--> The other is at Nelson, the Rev C L Reay <!--[marginal MS annotation: Reasy?]-->, belonging to our society; him I have not seen, but trust that he is an active man who will do good.  I am not however much relieved by them at present as the former is still quite ignorant of the language, &amp; the latter at too great a distance from Queen Charlotte’s Sound to take charge of the natives there.  In Septm while I was at Wellington with Mr Mason the bishop ordained him; Mr Cole &amp; I assisted in the service.  This ordination took place before a large congregation of Natives &amp; was performed in the Native language, I having translated that service into the Native for the occasion.  It was highly interesting to me, as well as to the Natives.  The bishop will admit several of the catechists to deacons orders: thus we may expect something like a church here in the wilderness- I have had much conversation with the bishop.  He is a man, I think, well suited for the work to which he is appointed.  He is devoted to his work, &amp; is a pattern of self denial diligence &amp; activity.  His great talent is too manifest to be questioned by any body.  He delights in being with Natives; &amp; enters into all their concerns &amp; wants, with unwearied attention &amp; patience.  The knowledge which he has already attained of the native language is surprising.  He talked to me about his own appointment to his present office, &amp; said that he was objected to as a Puseyite by Lord J Russell, &amp; that was stated to him by the Archbishop.  He however told the latter that he had never so much as read one of the Oxford tracts, that he held opinions of his own derived from Scripture &amp; belonged to no party- He told me moreover that he was told very positively at Sidney that I was a Puseyite – The bishop of Australia had however given him a correct account of me- He spoke in very high terms of Simeon &amp; the good he had done in exciting an evangelical spirit in the church; but objected to his intercourse &amp; c with decenters <!--sic--> – And speaking of Puseyism he said, that it might have been most pernicious, had it not been preceded for years by the revival in godliness which had taken place under the instrumentality of Simeon.  He complained much of the inefficiency of the clergy of our church, &amp; of his bitter disappointment on opening letter after letter in answer to an advertisement  when in England, wherin the first enquiry was “What is the salary”   He said that he felt that he would sooner have come alone than to have been accompanied by any such persons- He has passed through my place twice, once on his way to Taranaki (New Plymouth) and then again on his road to Hawks Bay – On this latter occasion he was accompanied by the Chief Justice Mr Martin – I went with them about a hundred miles up the river Manawatu &amp; then having procured about thirty natives to accompany them to Archdeacon Williams’ at Hawks Bay I took leave of them.  I was with them a week and left them with regret; thankful however that I had enjoyed the society of the two most talented men in N. Z. for so long a time – They are both attached in a most extraordinary way to the natives, &amp; seem determined to defend the Natives interests &amp; as they have the power to do so, being joint trustee for all native property &amp; much good will no doubt be done by them- I cannot express how delighted I have been with them both- I returned last week- The bishop seems to feel some pain at the suspicious conduct of the C.M.S. towards him.  He said that he believed they thought that a bishop could not be an honest man; &amp; indeed one connected with them told him previous to his consideration, when speaking of the bishop of Calcutta that a mans heart becomes changed on his becoming bishop- He seems to like all but Mr Coates- I do not know whether I am tiring you with these matters, which I forget may not be as interesting to you as they are to me.  I felt very much interest in my English congregation at Wellington, on giving them up to their new pastors, in whom I must confess I have not very much confidence.  Several of them wanted to know why I could not live there- I have received one or two very pretty letters from our dear friend Mrs. St Hill.  She seems full of gratitude to the Lord for having directed me to Wellington &amp; especially to their house.  God’s ways are mysterious in accomplishing his own blessed purposes.  She now delights in reading the Bible &amp; Simeon’s sermons.  Mr St Hill accompanied the Bishop to Taranaki &amp; has returned unwell.  He is now a little better- These are my friends who kindly endeavour to supply the places of Father &amp; Mother &amp; brothers &amp; sisters- There has been this last weekend a very disastrous fire at Wellington 59 houses having  been destroyed &amp; many poor creatures consequently involved in misery &amp; want- A considerable sum of money has already been raised for the relief of the sufferers &amp; I was gratified to learn that a small native congregation had given 4£ towards the fund, thus shewing a kindly feeling towards their white brethren- The bishop has given me more works to do; but whether I shall obey him or not I have not yet determined.  He wished me &amp; Mr Maunsell to go through all the Native New Test: &amp; correct all the mistakes, &amp; then to have a large quantity printed by the Christian Knowledge Society- I endeavoured in vain to persuade him &amp; the Judge that I knew but little of the language, nothing would do, but I must give myself to the works.  I know however that I am unequal to the works &amp; therefore shall leave it for Maunsell- A little fluency in speaking with a tolerable pronunciation is mistaken for a knowledge of the language, when in truth there is no real connection between the two <!--[do these dashes represent blanks, or a row of dashes in the original?]--> OH
</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
