<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0034">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1842 January 5 [first typescript: January 25; amended to 5]: Octavius to Octavia Hadfield</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960.  Page 78.</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 26.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1842-01-05">1842 January 5 [first typescript: January 25; amended to 5]</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70954/.">Kapiti</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key=" http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70767/">Octavia Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1842 January 5 [first typescript: January 25; amended to 5]: Octavius to Octavia Hadfield 
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Kapiti,</p>
      <p>Cooks Straits</p>
      <p>Jan. 5th.<!--first typescript: 5; amended to 5--> 1842</p>
      <p>My dear Octavia,</p>
      <p>It is a long time I fear since I have addressed a letter to you, tho' I think I have received more from you than anybody else.  I feel thankful that I have health &amp; strength today sufficient to enable me to write to you.  The last I wrote was to Caroline &amp; Henry, Nov. 1st. &amp; 16th. &amp; as the vessel by which they were sent went direct home I hope you will get them soon.  I received a few days ago dear George's of April 19, (enclosing one from Amelia), I had received one from Maria of June 14 previously, to writing my last.  I have received some papers <supplied>[as late as]</supplied> July 19th.  I am much obliged for them, I only regret that they were not accompanied by a letter.  I fear there has been great neglect at the Post Office Port Nicholson.  I trust however that matters will mend as they acquire more experience.  I have heard nothing of Aleck for an age, the last letter that you mention from him is <hi rend="underline">Oct. 1840</hi>, &amp; that is the latest information I have of him. </p>
      <p>And now I suppose I must say something about myself &amp; how shall I begin, if I keep silence I shall lose your confidence, &amp; if I tell you the truth I shall perhaps give you pain, but if my letters written lately have reached you, you will have heard that my health has not been very good within the last four months, but as I am always complaining you would not perhaps think much of it. I suffered for some weeks from pain in my left side accompanied with very disordered bowels and great weakness, but tho' confined to my house some days, on others I was enabled to go through some of my duties. Feeling rather better on the 8th. of Dec., I started in my boat to go across to Queen Charlotte Sound, but having gone down the coast about 20 miles I felt so ill that I was obliged to land, have my tent erected and go to bed; I then found myself in a violent fever; which increased so rapidly that in the night at about 11 oclock I told my boat's crew they would have to cover me with blankets and take me back home, which we reached about the dawn of day, I was then put to bed, where I lay till Jan. 2nd.  Mr. Mason kindly came from Wanganui as soon as he heard of my illness &amp; remained with me for a week till he thought me recovered, &amp; Mr. St. Hill a particular friend of mine likewise came from Port Nicholson, &amp; wished much to convey me to his house, but I thought it too far to be carried, (about 40 miles). Col. Wakefield and others called &amp; were very civil. I as usual would not have any medical man's advice, tho' now that I am better I hope that I shall consult somebody. One called in passing whom I had seen before &amp; told me he thought there was an absess forming in my left side, and advised me to use calomel &amp; blisters. I had previously taken calomel rather freely, &amp; I applied a blister which relieved me for the time, but the pain has since returned tho' not with violence. I think he made a great mistake about the formation of an absess, I am not however certain as I am not well yet tho' I now sit up &amp; yesterday walked out a few yards from my house. I however, hope, &amp; my friends who judge by my improved looks, etc., think the same, that I am now getting well. Mr. Halswell whose name is connected with N.Z. matters you may have seen in the papers, sent me a beautiful goat, which supplied me with nice milk &amp; I have since lived almost entirely on arrowroot, which is the only thing that has agreed with me. I have not, you see, been destitute of friends even here, but have had them to minister to my wants &amp; necessities. My native lad also, Coleman Davis <!--note added in 1969 Macmorran biograph: (Te Kooro)-->, has been very assiduous in his attentions, so I might say that in this respect I have need to be thankful.  You will probably by this time wish to know what effect this illness has had on my soul, and expect a full account under this head than I have given concerning the body. Should such be the case, I fear you will be disappointed. Never has sickness been less sanctified to the good of my soul. The powers of my mind &amp; soul seemed proportionably weakened with those of my body, &amp; I have enjoyed but little of my God.  I have, however, felt happy &amp; comfortable in depending for everything on my Covenant God, &amp; in looking to Jesus as my surety, at whose hands the debt which my sins incurred has been required.  On Christmas Day, my mind was much occupied in reflecting on the great majesty "God, manifest in the Flesh", man is lost, is dead, none but God can recover him, &amp; restore him to the favour of God.  Man has sinned, none but man can pay the debt, due to Divine Justice.  How then can the reconciliation be effected - God became man, the two natures are united in one person, Christ Jesus, "He died that we may never die, &amp; lives that we may live with Him for ever".  What most distressed me is that while I have some acquaintance with these glorious truths, my soul feeds so little upon them, &amp; my affections are continually drawing to this dust.  There is one thought that always humbles me, &amp; it is this, that while I acknowledge God to be the only object concerning which my soul can occupy itself with profit, comfort &amp; delight, I nevertheless am prone to let my thoughts fix on any other object.  I know nothing that so fully demonstrates the total depravity, yea depraved nature of my soul so forcibly, that instead of saying with the Psalmist "I hate vain thought but Thy law do I love", I may almost reverse it.  Oh Holiness, 'is it to be found on earth? Yes, but in me? No! never'.  May the Lord have mercy on my filthy &amp; polluted soul' - &amp; shall I doubt? No. what soul is there among the glorified saints above, that has been saved in any other than a way of grace, mercy, favour freely bestowed, &amp; which was not in itself corrupt, depraved, polluted &amp; sinful.  May the Holy Spirit sanctify &amp; purify my soul, &amp; make me meet for glory.  I feel however, that all things are ordered for my good, by Him Who has "loved me with an everlasting love", &amp; I cannot wish that anything but "His will should be done". </p>
      <p>My dear people have been much grieved at my sickness, expecting to lose me, &amp; if there was anything which tied me to this world it was a wish to be with them; (be not angry with me if I confess I had almost forgotten you) though I could feel that I had a desire to depart &amp; be with Christ which is far better. A report having gone abroad among some at a distance that I was dead, they were all in tears. Whether their love is to me personally, or to me as a minister &amp; ambassador of Christ, I know not, - God grant that it may be this latter. I can however, look upon many souls who, I trust, will be found precious among Jesus' jewels. I feel more &amp; more my own incapacity, bodily &amp; more especially mentally, &amp; spiritually in this great work in which I am professedly engaged. I differ in opinion with most here concerning baptism, &amp; with regard to solemnising marriage between persons baptised &amp; those who are not etc. &amp; as we are expecting a Puseyite bishop I see no prospect of mending matters.  I wish I could spend my few remaining days as a hermit, but how to proceed I know not.  I hear 20 Popish priests have lately landed. May the Lord raise up instruments to do His work. Political matters are very prosperous here.  I feel that there will be dreadful bloodshed before many years. May it be ordered otherwise!  I am glad to see that Whig influence at home was on the decline.  George says my father wants a stated account of how I pass a day etc., the truth is I never pass two days alike, &amp; never two weeks together in the same place. I sometimes have a dinner, &amp; sometimes go without, in fact you cannot well imagine anything more irregular than the life &amp; adventures of O.H.  I trust that I have the benefit of your prayers, tho' I confess that mine in your behalf are not worth much.  Give my kind love to my father, mother &amp; all my dear brothers &amp; sisters, &amp; believe me, my dear Octavia,
      </p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      <p>P.S.</p>
      <p>I am sorry George did not come out here to <hi rend="underline">pay me a visit</hi> - it would I think have done him good.  He might even do so now.  Should the climate agree with him, he could easily take some duty and return at any time, when he got tired of me &amp; New Zealand.  It is a fine climate, no cold.</p>
      <p>Remember me kindly to all old friends.  I like you to mention those who take an interest in me, that I may love them and pray for them.</p>
      <p>I think I mentioned in my last that I saw James Hannay<!--previous editor's note: (Haneray?)-->.  Maria said that Godfrey Hult was coming out, but I have seen nothing of him. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
