<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0029">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1840 October 22: Octavius Hadfield to one of his sisters</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960. (page 64)</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 25.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1840-10-22">1840 October 22</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70954/.">Kapiti (Otaki)</name>
               </correspAction>
               
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1840 October 22: Octavius Hadfield to one of his sisters
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Kapiti,</p>
      <p>Cooks Straits,</p>
      <p>New Zealand.</p>
      <p>Oct. 22nd. 1840</p>
      <p>My beloved sister,</p>
      <p>I have lately been put into good spirits by the hope that our correspondence may henceforward be more regular &amp; expeditious, for certainly next to the pleasure of being with you, that of hearing from you is the greatest I have.  Your letter, &amp; that of dear Charles dated May reached me three weeks ago, being directed to me at this place.  I beg to thank you both gratefully.  I yesterday recd. one from my Father dated March 20th, crossed by my Mother, by the old route; I was sorry to hear by that that so many of you had been sufferers from influenza.  I hear of other letters; &amp; the bearer of the one I recd. yesterday told me there were more &amp; newspapers for me at Port Nicholson, (which for some unaccountable reason have not been sent on but which I suppose I shall see in due time.  I am afraid my letters since I have been down here have been very dull &amp; stupid, but living in England you can scarcely imagine the difficulty one feels here of getting a little quiet time when an opportunity presents itself of writing.  I will try henceforward to be more regular in writing, &amp; my letters must wait for a ship at Port N.  I have not recd. a letter from Alexander since his arrival in India; I was glad to hear thro' you concerning his health etc.</p>
      <p>Your letter &amp; dear Charles' came to me much to my refreshment &amp; soul's edification many sentences in both afforded me much comfort, to hear of you is my delight, but to hear that your souls advance in holiness &amp; in conformity to the great Head, Christ Jesus, greatly enhances my delight in reflecting on you; this impression, unintentionally to yourselves, your letters made, &amp; I trust also were the means of exciting within me some feelings of love &amp; gratitude to our common Lord &amp; Master.  I feel what others have felt before me, the bad effects of living alone, without a christian brother to speak from one mouth to another; I do not feel dull, or find time hang heavy, etc, etc but my soul insensibly sinks lower &amp; lower, &amp; I seem to gaze on Jesus &amp; behold Him unaffected, without a spark of holy love being kindled within my soul.  Alas my hard heart, how long shall thy vain thoughts lodge within thee?<!--MS corrections to previous typescript are unclear to me regarding the punctuation of that sentence - possibly "how...thee" is enclosed in quotation marks?-->  I feel that there is much to call forth every energy &amp; leads me to cry for every grace, situated as I am in the midst of the poor heathen, some of whom are being daily taken away to the flames of hell, perhaps to rise up against me at the judgement day, &amp; "whose blood may be required at my hands"; &amp; yet, strange inconsistency, I feel careless &amp; cold.  Oh, the awfulness of the ministry!  May I not be found at the last day to have been a soul-damning minister.  I feel that I have not taken it upon myself inconsiderably or without years of prayers; but alas, my incapacity, my unfitness, is as manifold as the noon-day.  Oh gladly, but then the dear souls around me forbid the thought, would I leave the work I am engaged in, &amp; spend the remainder of my life unnoticed &amp; unknown.  What that can be found on earth can afford any delight or pleasure equal to that of one hour spent in earnest fervent prayer to the Lord Jehovah, a Covenant God in Christ, &amp; yet that is what my soul now seldom realises.  When I strive to escape from all that can distract me by setting apart a day for fasting &amp; prayer, my soul, as tho' chained by the power of hell refuses to soar above, &amp; still cleaves to the world which the Lord in wisdom had place beneath my feet.  "Oh wretched man that I am", etc.  Thank God "thro' Jesus Christ my Lord" - Oh the preciousness of a most precious Christ!  But why do I say so much of myself &amp; my sinfulness?  is it to distress you?  no!  but to excite pity for a poor brother who dwells where Satan's seat is, that you may be led to prayer in my behalf, that I may be more conformed to Christ &amp; strengthened for His service.  Remember that I am in the midst of a sinful people, who have been accustomed to sin uncontrolled from their youth &amp; speak of it with levity.  By the by, in answer to an observation of my Father's, tell him his preaching would have no effect here; he says "the first instruction should be the most plain &amp; obvious duties of a Christian, founded on the precepts of the Gospel," etc.  This will not do, if I speak to a native on murder, infanticide, cannibalism &amp; adultery their hitherto glaring sins, they laugh in my face, &amp; tell me that I may think them bad, but they are very good for a native, &amp; they cannot conceive any harm in them, but on the contrary, when I tell them that these and other sins brought the Son of God, the great Creator of the universe from His eternal glory, to this world, to be incarnate, to be made a curse &amp; to die, they open their eyes &amp; ears, &amp; mouths are silent, &amp; wish to hear &amp; shortly after acknowledge themselves sinners, &amp; say they will leave off these sins.  Further, he accuses me of speaking strongly against Papists &amp; Wesleyans; if this were the case when I wrote from Waimate, what must my subsequent remarks have been.  But, to be short, I look on both these, (as I find them in N.Z.) as the "enemies of the <hi rend="underline">cross of Christ</hi>", &amp; as such, as a minister &amp; servant of Christ I oppose them with every faculty of mind, soul &amp; body.  If this appears harsh, I must plead my ordination vows.  I am happy to say that by help from on high I have been able to upset my Wesleyans at Waikanae, &amp; now they all join me.  I have much when I look out of my sinful self to cheer &amp; refresh me.  The people of this tribe, (I am writing now from Otaki) who, the leading men at least, have hitherto resisted the Gospel are all coming round to attend to the preached Gospel, &amp; in form daily to worship Jehovah.  I returned about a fortnight ago from an interesting trip among some people of this tribe living on the banks of a most splendid &amp; beautiful river, Manawatu, which empties itself into the sea about twenty miles from this.  I was as high up the river before, last summer, about forty miles, but I this time came all the way down in a canoe, visiting the natives on the banks, nearly all of whom I found much improved, &amp; seeming to welcome me from their hearts.  I was much interested.  The people of Waikanae are outwardly doing well; on the Lord's Day, tho' the building we have service in contains about 500, many go a half an hour before service to get admittance, the rest remain outside.  But does this all arise from love to Christ?  no, but as Archbishop Leighton remarks, where there are hypocrites, there are believers, &amp; so I trust there are some among them who are the salt as it were which preserves the rest.  I am also expecting a vessel to take me to the opposite Island, to Queen Charlotte Sound, where there are many hundreds who in their simple way call themselves my children; I have much love for them; nay the children of the Lord Almighty.  A party of another tribe lately visited me for some days (Rauparaha's people) with all the nobility of the tribe; I was much pleased with some of them.  There is some talk of their coming to me from all parts of the Straits in the summer, but I do not know whether it will be the case.  I am afraid I repeat the same things over &amp; over again in my letters.  I am glad to hear of my friends at home; remember <supplied>(me)</supplied> to the Griffins, Colemans, Warrens &amp; all others rich &amp; poor; I should like to hear of Mr. Douglas, &amp; Mr. Hailstow if you have heard of either of them lately.  My mother kindly asks me whether I want anything in the way of clothes, &amp; I think I will trouble you as everything I get here is very dear &amp; bad.  What I chiefly want are some books which perhaps George will be kind enough to get for me at his leisure, &amp; besides two or three articles may as well come at the same time...one dozen flannel waistcoats such as my mother made before for me, (my native damsels do not know how to wash flannel well, &amp; spoil mine), one dozen pairs of strong <hi rend="underline">worsted socks</hi>.  One dressing or reading gown of some kind of common drab cloth which any tailor can make, three or four small tablecloths, six small window curtains of any kind of material, my windows contain six panes of glass!  &amp; four pair of <hi rend="underline">boots</hi>, well made to keep out water but not thick as I have nothing but sand to walk on &amp; a stone is not to be found within many miles of my abode, which Charles perhaps will be kind enough to get for me, a good tight fit for him will suit me very well.  A list of books I wrote on the other side that it may be plain.  I send a check for what I hope will cover all, if not it must remain over till another time.  I draw it in George's name as perhaps it will be more convenient.  I feel quite sorry to give you so much trouble but I must not treat you as strangers.  For me to get them safe they ought to be packed in tin.  The box must be sent to the Church M.S. House with a note just mentioning the value of the contents.  They will pay insurance, freight etc. with which I shall be charged in due time.  Give my love to every one of the dear family, &amp; believe</p>
      <p>me my dear sister,</p>
      <p>Ever yours most affectionately</p>
      
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      <p>List of books:</p>
      <p>Charnock <!--previous editor's note: [Stephen 1628-1680]--> "On the Excellence, Attributes &amp; Providence of God".  By Owan <!--previous editor's notes: [John, D.D. 1616-1683]--> Folio, "Of the Saint's Perseverance"; "A Discourse of the Holy Spirit".  Quarto, "A Display of Armenianism"; "Salus Electorum Sanguis Jesu;" or "The death of death in the death of Christ"; "Of the death of Christ"; unabbreviated or corrupted.  Then at any cost, if to be found, Usher on "The extent of Christ's satisfaction".  Memoirs of H. Martyn; Brainerd's Life.  Some book on eccesiastical forms, regulations &amp; relations as a guide in the absence of advice from others; also "canons"; "Oliphant's analysis on History of the Gospels"; &amp; second edition of Leo's Hebrew Gram.; Stewart's Hebrew Gr. or any others, I have Lee &amp; Buxtorf.  If my list has not exceeded the cash "Dr. Hawker's Commentary on the Bible".  </p>
      <p>I wrote to my father last month.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
