<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrLHadfld-0026">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1840 April 28: Octavius to his brother Lieut. Charles Hadfield</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70582/">Octavius Hadfield</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Wellington City Libraries book of typed transcriptions.  Spine title "Hadfield, Typescript (amended) letters 1833-1854".  Corrected by Gillian Ryan 1960. (page 53)</p>   
         <p>Re-typed and encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 24.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1840-04-28">1840 April 28</date>
                  <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70954/.">Kapiti</name>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70819/">Charles Hadfield</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1840 April 28: Octavius to his brother Lieut. Charles Hadfield
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Kapiti</p>
      <p>Cook Strait,</p>
      <p>N. Zealand.</p>
      <p>April 28th. 1840</p>
      <p>My dear beloved brother, </p>
      <p>Tho' one of my last letters was addressed to you, (dated Jan. 6th., sent via America) I again take up my pen to endeavour to express the feelings of my heart towards you, no longer only a brother in the flesh (an enduring relation) but now a brother in the Lord, even in Jesus, in Christ a precious, a most precious Saviour, &amp; oh what a blessed tie is that new relation, we become united in our Saviour, never to part; oh, it is indeed a relation sweet, blessed, holy, everlasting, &amp; may I not say Divine, inasmuch as in Christ both God &amp; man, we are one with God; yes, God has become united to our nature, never to be divided, in the person of Christ, &amp; all who are in Christ are one, &amp; must be one for ever &amp; ever in spite of sin, men &amp; devils,- &amp; oh, with what gratitude &amp; praise ought my soul to look up, to God, the prayer-hearing &amp; prayer-answering God, "Who dwelleth between the Cherubim" when I recall to mind that evening which we spent together for the last time at Ventnor; your thoughts were, I believe, fixed on me, &amp; mine were engaged with you.  My soul was then melted within me, &amp; when I retired to my room, I spent <hi rend="underline">some hours</hi> in earnest, fervent prayer, to the Lord that should my eyes never behold you again, we might nevertheless spend together a blessed eternity in Jesus' presence; yea, &amp; I fancied then, I was persuaded (tho' my unbelieving heart would fain have induced me to believe it was a delusion) that the Lord answered me &amp; said it shall be so.  Oh, how unsearchable are the riches of divine grace, how wonderful is the thought that Jehovah, a righteous &amp; Holy God should look with any pity upon sinners, rebels against His Divine Majesty; but oh, He is infinite in all perfections or He would not be God.  Dwell much in contemplating the Father's sovereign grace who wrote your name from all eternity "in the Saints' book of life", as a vessel of mercy afor prepared to glory; on Jesus' dying love Who redeemed you &amp; all the elect of God, the Father Who now lives &amp; reigns on high praying for you, "not for the world" as some would have you suppose "but for them which the Father has given Him" John XV11: 9.  also on God the Spirit Who has enlightened you, regenerated and sanctified &amp; sealed you to the day of redemption, that you should not go whither you &amp; I deserved to go, to the eternal damnation of hell, where millions of our fellowmen will dwell forever with Satan, but that you should be made <hi rend="underline">a king &amp; a priest to God</hi> to reign with Christ for ever.  Dwell, dear brother on these truths, as I am sure you do, they will draw your soul up to heaven &amp; support you in your hour of trial trouble &amp; affliction, until you have fought the good fight &amp; finished your course, &amp; kept the faith &amp; are covered with everlasting glory &amp; clothed with bright &amp; brilliant righteousness, far out-shining that of angels, even the righteousness of your Saviour God.  Dear Charles, I give thanks to God on every remembrance of you, - but I must turn to another subject, &amp; that our dear beloved Georgina's - I had well nigh written death, but ought I not rather to say birthday of Glory. </p>
     <p>On the 25th inst. up to which day your letter of May was the last I had received (being nearly twelve months) I received from the Bay of Islands a <hi rend="underline">letter from Amelia dated July, from my Father &amp; Henry, Aug.  One from yourself &amp; one from Julia, &amp; one from George of Oct.,</hi> for which letters I must trouble you to give to each of them &amp; those also who filled up the ends, my most grateful thanks; there was a sweet spirit of love conveyed in every sentence of each of them which delighted and refreshed my soul.  So long a letter from my father was indeed acceptable, one however, &amp; that from its contents, describing more particularly the last hours of our dear glorified soul, I should have prized most, has not reached me, &amp; oh, what shall I say, three days ago I supposed that dear Georgina was alive in the flesh, &amp; then suddenly learnt that she had been taken from this world of sin &amp; trouble for <hi rend="underline">more than eight months, I did,</hi> &amp; perhaps you who are at home will pity me, I did wish &amp; <hi rend="underline">perhaps sinfully</hi>, but it was only for a minute, to have been with her in her last hours in this world; <hi rend="underline">but on that very day</hi> I did from my inmost soul yield hearty thanks both to the Lord of the living &amp; the dead that He had been pleased to take to Himself the soul of one whom He had redeemed with His own blood &amp; with whom He had permitted me to enjoy so many days of sweet &amp; holy communion.  Let us be looking forward to that day when we shall be taken hence, &amp; remember that even she who is now in glory without us will not be made perfect.  I feel much for poor Dawson, but doubt not that the Lord which supports me, supports him also, as I rejoice to hear he has you.  But why should I say more, &amp; yet you will perhaps think that I have little feeling.  But in truth this trial has come to me with power, it has come to me from the Lord.  I wrote on March 31. to my mother, &amp; if my letters of late have been received, you must have perceived a deadness in them, or rather indications of deadness in me to the things of God, but now I am called upon to think &amp; examine myself, &amp; alas, after examination, "my heart condemns me".  Oh, dear brother, pity the anguish of my soul, "my heart condemns me".  I have been for more than five months living alone without a christian brother, save two natives who are sometimes a comfort to me, but little time for reading or prayer or fasting, &amp; I feel that my soul has declined, I feel I hear Jesus saying to me in the midst of my labours &amp; works "I have somewhat against thee because thou hast left thy first love", &amp; this pierces my soul; oh, how much easier it is to preach than to pray, how much easier to endure hunger, thirst, cold &amp; bodily fatigue than to love my God, my Saviour, my precious Christ.  There was a time when hours spent in prayer was my delight, but now I am grown faint, my faith is becoming too weak, &amp; tho' some, even here I find by these letters look upon me with surprise as one who has left all the rest to labour here alone among this people, I who see &amp; know my heart, its corruptions &amp; depravity, seem to wonder how anybody can notice me.  Oh, may I now live at a higher rate.  But who can tell the trials of a missionary, I should say temptations.  He goes to storm the stronghold of Satan &amp; is it to be wondered at that the god of this world puts forth all his power to oppose; living also in the midst of sin, in its grossest &amp; most manifest kind is not favourable to the growth of spiritual life; this much I have written to lead you all to pray for me that I may be blessed.  I gave some account in my letter to my mother of my trip to Taranaki, a walk of about 350 miles for 4 weeks, during which I went over land, &amp; among natives that had not seen a missionary before., &amp; had an opportunity of preaching the glorious Gospel of my Master. I am disposed to take a different view of the natives from that generally taken by the missionaries here, I think them a most pleasing, interesting, intelligent set of people; if a <hi rend="underline">Londoner</hi> comes out here expecting to find Cockneys he will be disappointed, but I admire them.  I have some who had not looked into a book when I began school in Dec. (especially a leading chief) who can now read and write well.  I am beginning to speak rather freely in native in preaching but having to learn the language without grammars, dictionary etc. it is difficult. The natives however understand me &amp; I trust I shall shortly improve. I have many interesting enquiries concerning Jesus, but all, hitherto (the fault is perhaps with me) rather ignorant, one is evidently under the influence of the Spirit &amp; I shall shortly baptise him, they are for the most part young men from the age of about 18 to 20 who are disposed to give up sin of every kind &amp; serve Jesus. My place of labour from its vicinity to shipping is bad but the Lord has brought me, &amp; I trust, through prayer, will bless me. I have no certain dwelling place, but two small houses at about ten miles apart.  My congregation at one place is about 400 &amp; the other 150, but numbers of others in villages all about me. It is surprising to see the attention with which they attend to the preached Gospel &amp; their reverence for the Word of God, the Bible says so and that is enough.  My greatest trial are the Wesleyans who have a separate service in the place where I live, &amp; propagate the most damnable heresies.  I show them the most determined opposition.  Port Nicholson, the new settlement, is within 30 miles of me, so that I am no longer out of the world.  I have not heard from Aleck since his arrival in India.  I shall try &amp; persuade him to come &amp; see me here.  I must beg you to remember kindly to all my friends you may have an opportunity of seeing etc. &amp; give my kind love to my dear father &amp; mother &amp; all our dear brothers &amp; sisters, assuring them they cannot write too often to me.  I ought to say something about my health but I scarcely know what.  I am enabled to go through a great deal of work but I am not very well.  I suffer from worms in my bowels, which my medical skill has not yet succeeded in destroying, but this I know, that as my day so shall my strength, be "for the mouth of the Lord, hath spoken it" &amp; now and ever,</p>
	<p>Believe me, with affectionate love, your brother,</p>
      <p>Octavius Hadfield.</p>
      <p>May 14.  I have not had an opportunity of sending this before.  But have nothing of importance to add.  Let my letters be directed as above, without reference to Sydney.  Will you thank my mother for her offer of making anything for me &amp; tell her that I am in want of nothing.  "I have all &amp;  abound".  I once, I believe, expressed a wish that some of you, that is, my sisters, were here with me, but now, to tell the truth, I believe I can be more useful alone, as I am continually moving about among the natives which if I had anybody with me I could not do.  I am convinced  that a single man as a missionary can do much more than a married man provided his faith &amp; grace are equal.  I trust you and all at home will pray much for me, the mere thought of it comforts me much.   O.H.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
