<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1099">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>24 August 1863: Hooker to Haast.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>ATL MS-Papers-0037, folder 238-9 &amp; folder 105-01.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "The Correspondence of Julius Haast and Joseph Dalton Hooker, 1861-1886", by Sascha Nolden, Simon Nathan &amp; Esme Mildenhall.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133H, 2013.  ISBN 978-1-877480-29-4. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133H.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1863-08-24">1863 August 24</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9511/&gt;Sir Julius von Haast">Sir Julius von Haast</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hooker to Haast, 24-8-1863 ATL MS-Papers-0037, folder 238-9 &amp; folder 105-01.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>Kew</p>
            <p>Aug 24th 63</p>
            <p>My dear Haast</p>
            <p>I have now to acknowledge your just arrived packet of plants, &amp; letter of June 11th, 
both extremely interesting to me. 
The packet contains many very nice &amp; a few, very few, new 
plants 
–
one a small 
Raoulia
No. I have today described as 
R. youngii
, which you describe 
as forming large white patches on the earth of Mts near Lake Hawai <!-- editors note: Hawea? -->
–
I was particularly 
plea
sed with the 
Celmisia
s having only
last week completed my study of that most 
troublesome genus &amp; found that your fine species all came well into my descriptions; most of 
them were discoveries 
originally 
of your own. You will I fear to be much disappointed to 
hear that 
there is not a novelty amongst your G
rasses
&amp; Cyperaceae. I do not
at all understand 
it. Whereas 
you have added so many, perhaps 150 species!, not known when the Flora of NZ 
was published; neither you nor any one else has
[2] added materially to any 
monoco
tyledonous
order! 
–
I suppose that your 
M[
oun
]
t
[
ain
]
s
are not rich in Grasses
&amp; 
Cyperac
eae.
I do not think you have gathe
red more than 3 or 4 of the NZ Carices! &amp; still 
fewer Junci, Eleocharis
, 
Sonchus
etc
etc &amp; scarcely a Restiac
ious
plant; can it be that
these 
orders are much more prevalent in the Northern Island where Colenso has gathered many.</p>
            <p>As to
the rest of your last collection, I have had no time to do more than throw these 
into genera &amp; must work them up as I proceed with the N.Z. Manual which now -------- all my spare time day &amp; night. I send herewith a list of the species as far as I have gone since 
they arrived, &amp; shall continue sending you the names as I proceed. As I said before they do 
not present much novelty, but are most important, so ma
ny of them being undescribed though 
gathered before by yourself or Sinclair. Hector has also 
[3] 
sent a few of them from the Otago 
Alps.</p>
            <p>I have withdrawn my paper on the N.Z. plants from the Linnaean as I find that the 
descriptions will also appear so soon in the N.Z. Manual, &amp; I would prefer having these 
numerous interesting novelties to appear for the first time in a work to which the N.Z. Govt 
has been so liberal &amp; you &amp; others have contributed so largely. I still hope to get vol I out 
this year with the Phanerogamia
&amp; Ferns. I find the additions to
the old Flora much more than 
expected, &amp; as I am reexamining every specimen with far more specimens than I then had, &amp; 
making new descriptions of every species, the result will be widely different, &amp; I hope m
uch 
better work. Some of the genera are very laborious, &amp;
took me several weeks, as 
Celmisia
, 
Eurybia
(which now goes all with 
Olearia
), 
Coprosma
etc. 
Veronica
will be a terrible job &amp; I 
quite dread it. I see no limit 
[4] 
to the species, subspecies, variet
ies, &amp; I fear hybrids!</p>
            <p>Your fine
tree No. 13 is I think 
Thuya doniana. </p>
            <p>The 
Phormium
s are great puzzles, there are certainly 2 distinct forms in the plants, but 
connected I fear by many intermediates.</p>
            <p>A thousand thanks for your splendid &amp; most useful ma
p. I shall take care to keep it to 
myself as you direct. The mountain ranges, valleys, &amp; glacial distributions &amp; channels are 
most curious. I hope to see Tyndall
out here soon &amp; will show it to him. I must take it to 
Darwin (who never leaves his home) when
next I visit him.</p>
            <p>Many congratulations 
up
on your marriage, may you find every comfort &amp; blessing in 
your new &amp; enviable state 
–
may you soon have as many children as I have 5 
–
&amp; all healthy 
&amp; good!</p>
            <p>After a long fruitless search in the bookstalls, &amp; 2d
hand catalogues, I have
[5] 
abandoned hope of getting you a copy of Ed 1 of my Himalayan Journals, &amp; have been 
obliged to send you the 2d
or smaller only, 
–
this wants the maps, which I will try &amp; get for 
you somehow.</p>
            <p>I sent the book (Australian Essay
etc
) with some others for your kind acceptance to 
Mr Marshman, &amp; hope that they will be forwarded by this mail.</p>
            <p>Thank you much for the promised Diploma of your Society. I am very proud of my 
Bengal &amp; Tasmanian honors &amp; shall have yours of Canterbury entered 
with the others in the 
Linn. Soc. list, which is my official depot for all such honors.</p>
            <p>I am much interested at hearing of the Red Snow on your Alps! I do not think it had 
heretofore been found in the S. hemisphere.</p>
            <p>The Conferva? from the boiling spring 
was I think collected by Colenso &amp; sent to 
Berkeley, but I do not think he could [2] make any thing of it. He says that without specimens 
it is almost impossible to describe your Fungi from drawings, so much depends on the spores, 
or texture &amp; surface etc.
I doubt any thing being done of consequence to elucidate them till
some one can give 3 or 4 years to a continuous assiduous study of them. Your drawings will 
one day prove useful I hope, 
&amp; they do your energy &amp; good taste great credit. As to the 
confervae
etc
,
these too Dr Harvey says can not be studied satisfactorily except in a living 
state by observers having some 
knowledge of their structure. 
I collected them largely in the S. 
Pole
Expedn
&amp; in Himalaya, but my labor was well nigh lost. </p>
            <p>By next mail I
shall send you [3] a copy of 
Jamieson’s
paper on the Parallel roads of 
Glen Roy, which he attributes to glacial action &amp; which will interest you much.</p>
            <p>The Intellectual Observer, is not the Nat. Hist.
Review, but a more popular work
very 
interesting &amp; well done.</p>
            <p>You will find in the N. H. Review, a resume of th
e whole 
Moulin Quignon Case
, 
–
in
so far as it is published. I may however tell you privately that there is no doubt whatever, that 
the Jawbone is a “Romano Gallic” one from an ancient Tumulus open
ed some years ago in 
the neighbourhood by the same man who is supposed to have fraudulently introduced the jaw 
bone into the gravel! The evidence is cumulative &amp; almost irresistible.</p>
            <p>And now my dear Haast I must break off. I find I must close
this
[4]
to 
catch the 
Marseilles without adding the list of your last plants so far as named: 
–
but few were done &amp; 
only the 
Celmisia
s &amp; 
Raoulia
s; all before that must wait now till
I have finished the 
Sup
.
of 
Vol. 1 when I will return upon these &amp; all new arrivals &amp;
go over them previous to print
ing.</p>
            <p>Ever my dear Haast
,</p>
            <p>Most sincerely your
obliged</p>
            <p>Jos. D. Hooker</p>
            <p>Justicia carnea <!-- editor's note: Brazilian plume flower – presumably this was added as a reminder--></p>
            <p>F.L.S.</p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>