<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1100">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>18 January 1864: Hooker to Haast.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70468/">Joseph Dalton Hooker</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>ATL MS-Papers-0037, folders 097-1 &amp; 105-02.</p>
         <p>Transcription published in "The Correspondence of Julius Haast and Joseph Dalton Hooker, 1861-1886", by Sascha Nolden, Simon Nathan &amp; Esme Mildenhall.  Geoscience Society of New Zealand miscellaneous publication 133H, 2013.  ISBN 978-1-877480-29-4. Openly available at https://securepages.co.nz/~gsnz/siteadmin/uploaded/gs_downloads/MP133H.pdf</p>
            <p>Encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 12.11.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1864-01-18">1864 January 18</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9511/&gt;Sir Julius von Haast">Sir Julius von Haast</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>Hooker to Haast, 18-1-1864 ATL MS-Papers-0037, folders 097-1 &amp; 105-02.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p> Kew </p>
            <p>Jany 18th/64</p>
            <p>My dear Haast</p>
            <p>I have just received yours o
f 12th Nov. 
–
I think I did answer 14th October 
–
lest I did not I 
may say that the maps of Nelson &amp; Canterbury are both most valuable to me &amp; I am 
exceeding obliged for it. I have not had time yet to go to Geog. Soc. &amp; see the sketches you 
have sent there
. </p>
            <p>My father has been ill for a fortnight with head cold, &amp; it will I fear be long before he 
gets to town again; so I shall ask Murchison to lend me his “Hooker Glacier” for a day to take 
out to Kew.</p>
            <p>
I am now busy printing the “Handbook of N. Z. Flora” 
–
this name [2] elected by 
Knight 
–
&amp; have 
gone
on to p.
40 
when
a splendid collection arrived from Hector &amp; 
Buchanan containing several new things &amp; of course many of your discoveries. They send far 
more grasses &amp; Carexes than Canterbury seems to afford, e
specially small ones, such as grow 
in alpine marshes, river banks etc. Have you Areca in your province. The map of the 
Phanerogams is now complete &amp; I had begun the Cryptogams when this collection arrived &amp; 
stopped the way. Still I hope that Part I will be
printed in about 6 weeks. I am working hard 
all my spare time at it day &amp; night 
–
certainly your collections cut a very handsome figure 
–
as I only give authorities [3] for habitats of the newer species. I think your work second to 
Colenso, (after Banks &amp;
Solander), who being the first to explore the island, I usually 
always mention.</p>
            <p>There is still 
some
novelty amongst your Grasses &amp; I have named two after your 
excellent assistant Young. I send too by (this mail I hope) a list of all your last collection
s.</p>
            <p>I shall say no more about the Monocots &amp; Dicots till I can tabulate results of N &amp; M. 
Island containing there all grasses which are found in 
---
Auckland Pr. &amp; in the N. Island, but 
not hitherto on the Middle, whence they must either be overlooked or e
xterminated in the 
latter! [4]</p>
            <p>I hope ere this you have received the 1st Ed. of my 
Himal. Journals
. Your account of 
Mr Potts garden at Otago is quite interesting. I wish he would send a little account of it for 
the Gardeners Chronicle. I shall send you a 
bundle of miscellaneous garden seeds by an early 
opportunity to distribute as you wish.</p>
            <p>I do not wonder at Fenzl being delighted with the plants you sent him; 
–
he &amp; his 
family are intimate friends of ours; but I do wish he would publish! 
–
They have a splendid 
Herbarium &amp; Botanical Library at Vienna, but very little is published by them.</p>
            <p>I have no Geological news for this letter. This is our dead 
------- season, &amp; I get more 
[5]
engrossed in the Gardens &amp; my Flowers.</p>
            <p>Lyell is well, Darwin still very ill
, vomiting after every meal: how he lives is a 
mystery to me &amp; all his friends.</p>
            <p>It was very stupid of me to address you prematurely as F.L.S. but I suppose you are so 
now. I had quite forgotten that your name was proposed too late for ballot last session.
It has 
to have 3 clear meetings of the Society. The misfortunes in my family prevented an
y 
attending to the Society for several months. 
I will see that all is right next Thursday when I 
shall go in to the Society’s meeting.</p>
            <p>Kindest regards to Mr Travers 
he has sent me a great number of excellent things &amp; 
will find his name very often in the Handbook.
[6]</p>
            <p>I wrote to him about a month ago. 
–
I think your 
Thuja
may 
be different from the 
Northern 
T. doniana, if so they have always hitherto been confounded. I
will look closely to 
them. I hope it is different if so it must be called 
T.
haastii
.</p>
            <p>I am eager for you
r Mt
Torlesse plants.</p>
            <p>Ever my dear Hector [sic]</p>
            <p>Most sincerely yrs</p>
            <p>J. D. Hooker</p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>