<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0617">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1885 December 1: to Balfour</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
        
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73378/">Balfour</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1885-12-01">1885 December 1</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <front>
         <p>1885 December 1: to Balfour<note xml:id="ftn3-332" place="foot" n="332">ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">NAPIER DEC 1/85</p>
         <p>Mr D.P. Balfour<lb/>Glenross</p>
         <p>My dear Sir</p>
         <p>Being in town this mg, I early got your kind note of the 29th Nov, &amp; the packet of <hi rend="italic">Pterostylis</hi>, which, (though you had done your best by writing on the outside) was all in <hi rend="italic">pieces</hi>; crushed to smitherines!! no doubt in carriage to Puketapu. I brought it away, and on reaching here opened it, (or, it fell to pieces) and I got <hi rend="italic">one</hi> good &amp; perfect flower out of the lot. Don’t trouble yourself about any more of this genus—unless something very curious should turn up.</p>
         <p>I don’t know if I told you of a peculiar species Mr Hill found between Waipawa &amp; Ongaonga, on the open dry plain among the low <hi rend="italic">Manuka</hi> bushes; he brought away a big tuft of Moss, &amp; in it were 2 or 3 little grey leaves thus,</p>
         <p>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="Pictures/100002010000005200000050B257D14C.png"/>
            </figure>, or scarcely as big; I saw they were <hi rend="italic">Orchids</hi>, partly from their little tubers, and carefully planted them before I went inland in Oct &amp; they grew fast; on my return they were 3–4in in height &amp; about to flower (2 on one &amp; 3 on tother)—flowers small thus</p>
         <p>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="Pictures/10000201000000770000004F1A993471.png"/>
            </figure>; At first I supposed a <hi rend="italic">new</hi> genus; and <hi rend="italic">more trouble</hi>. However on dissecting carefully <hi rend="italic">one</hi> fl, I found it was a true Pterostylis, &amp; allied to an Australian one, (or two), small &amp; reddish (like this) and <hi rend="italic">without tails</hi>. I was much pleased with this novelty.<note xml:id="ftn3-333" place="foot" n="333">
               <hi rend="italic">Pterostylis tristis</hi> Col. = <hi rend="italic">Tanypoda tristis</hi>.</note>
         </p>
         <p>I hope now that your shearing (as you say) is over today, you may find tine to look about you—in nooks &amp; <hi rend="italic">unvisited</hi> spots. I mean by sheep—if there are any such left—and obtain that long-stalked Orchid. However Dinna forget the <hi rend="italic">one</hi> with a red open mouth, and <hi rend="italic">long narrow</hi> stiff leaves you sent me whilst at Norsewood last <hi rend="italic">autumn</hi>, I should much like to see more of it.</p>
         <p>Last night a fine packet of <hi rend="italic">sorts</hi> came from Mr Hill (who has been up to Makaretu &amp; the slopes of the Ruahine) among them a new <hi rend="italic">Ranunculus</hi>—at all events, new <hi rend="italic">to me</hi>—but as there are nearly (or more than) 200 known species of this extensive Genus—I must overhaul warily, &amp;c, &amp;c. The worst is, I have <hi rend="italic">not time</hi> now to spare—though I work night &amp; day—&amp; very rarely go down to town; I was there this mg on business, but don’t go again this week.</p>
         <p>Another <hi rend="italic">new find</hi> (causing labour) was the bones of an animal in the quarry below, 45 feet, or so, under surface, and in <hi rend="italic">excellent preservation</hi>. Unfortunately from their being very small (I could put all I have in a wine glass) they were not soon discerned, &amp; so <hi rend="sup ">4</hi>/<hi rend="sub">5</hi>ths or so are missing. These will cause another short paper for our next meeting.</p>
         <p>I wrote on Sat to Dr Hector, to borrow a work from the library—which I require; will he lend it?.</p>
         <p>Do you take in our “Dy.T.” &amp; did you note Mr Editor Prices sapient quotation from a little pamphlet of mine I have sent him?.</p>
         <p>Bless my soul; what a <hi rend="italic">long</hi> letter to you again; and I up to the neck, in work, w Eng Mail closing on Saturday.</p>
         <p>It is no use sending spns in <hi rend="italic">Paper boxes</hi>—better perhaps in <hi rend="italic">soft rolls—</hi>better still <hi rend="italic">in tin</hi>. I shall send you 3 empty tins of a very <hi rend="italic">good size</hi>, and they weigh <hi rend="italic">light</hi>.—I have a lot of them—<hi rend="italic">I forage down in town for old tins, &amp; old bottles &amp;c &amp;c.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Winklemann sent me a thumping lot of Orchids (all large size) from Kaipara—in a very <hi rend="italic">stout</hi> &amp; big tin box (larger a good deal than this page) and that was crushed out of all shape, askew, like a billy cock hat. I never saw such a crushed, &amp; twisted <hi rend="italic">stout tin</hi> article ; the plants were all utterly useless, owing to his sacking them up, tubers &amp; <hi rend="italic">earth</hi> as they came out of the ground. I gave them two hours, but not <hi rend="italic">one flower</hi> could I make anything of—<hi rend="italic">rotted</hi>—<hi rend="italic">sanded</hi>—&amp; crushed. However I got a large supply of tubers, some nearly 1¾ʺ long &amp; ¾ʺ thick, &amp; I have planted them in pots.</p>
         <p>What of your <hi rend="italic">divot</hi> Orchid.</p>
         <p>I have neither seen, nor heard from P.D., though, <hi rend="italic">like D.P.B</hi>. he has been in town attending meetings. I wrote him ten days ago,—no reply—too bad.</p>
         <p>10 o’clock P.M. Goodnight. Kind remembrance to all at Glenross.</p>
         <p>             Believe me ever</p>
         <p>                             Yours truly</p>
         <p>                                             W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. Pretty well but too much Rheumatism.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>