<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0867">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1893 May 1: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1893-05-01">1893 May 1</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1893 May 1: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-642" place="foot" n="642"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Waipukurau<lb/>“May Day”, 1893.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>Being here this mg. <hi rend="italic">idle</hi>—I have determined to write to you—if only to begin my letter, for I know it is some time since I last wrote to you, and I think that since then I have heard from you.</p>
         <p>Events thicken—here in N.Z. as well as at Home (Europe!) With <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, there in Wgn., prominently the deaths of Didsbury (whom <hi rend="italic">you </hi>knew so well!) and of Ballance, and I may add a 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi> of <hi rend="italic">note</hi>—Te Kooti! and then the weather!—strangely &amp; persistently <hi rend="italic">wet</hi>—and this just the same with us as with you. The sun <hi rend="italic">is shining </hi>this mg. but only through fog &amp; mist, and on a <hi rend="italic">wet </hi>world!!—We had a <hi rend="italic">tolerably </hi>fine day on Thursday last (I then in Napier), but with that exception more than a fortnight of continued rain!—–</p>
         <p>This is my <hi rend="italic">3</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">rd</hi> Sunday in succession <hi rend="italic">here</hi>—I came for 16<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. ult., then the Bp. wished me to take 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi> &amp; this I agreed to do—as I was desirous of seeing Dannevirke <hi rend="italic">once more</hi>; also of saying “Good-bye” to Gow &amp; wife, leaving on 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> for Scotland, so we travelled together to Dvk., on 8th., I remained there till 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>., when I returned to this place, &amp; to N. on 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., but before I had gone from here, I recd. a note from Bp. asking me to take duty on 30<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. so I came back on Saty. 29<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., in rain; and on platform was accosted by Mrs. Winlove to bury a youth at iv. I was obliged to assent, of course, and at iv.30, in <hi rend="italic">open </hi>buggy &amp; <hi rend="italic">in rain</hi>, we wended our <hi rend="italic">slow </hi>course to cemetary!—and there <hi rend="italic">in rain </hi>I did the duty;—retg. very wet, and cold, and I almost feared the consequences, but though such exposure brought back Rheumatism &amp; semi-Lumbago, and made me feel uncomfortable yesterday, (no doubt increased by the weather.) I am pretty well again today, only my hand is getting more &amp; more shaky! </p>
         <p>The youth (16) I buried, is called Newman (son of a N. here on the line), has been in Nap. Hosp. since July ’92. Went thither, first, for his knee, which had largely swelled &amp; diseased, by &amp; by his leg was amputated, he got over that &amp; was on crutches, then dropsy &amp;c. followed, &amp; he lingered <hi rend="italic">long </hi>&amp; in pain. I saw yr. Cousin Rechab here, in <hi rend="italic">passing</hi>, last week, he seemed very well. Mrs. Russell &amp; Gaisford were again at Ch. yesterday mg., notwithstanding weather! (Congn. <hi rend="italic">very small</hi>—G. being the 6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. man present, &amp; of remr. 3 were Ch. officials;)—but it was <hi rend="italic">still worse</hi> on Sy. evg. 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>, when the Bp. drove over in pelting rain from Waipawa! then the <hi rend="italic">whole </hi>Congn. only numbered 8!!! and the poor Bp. was <hi rend="underline italic">dripping wet</hi>; and I got enough of water &amp; mud, in going &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">in returning</hi>—it came down in torrents.—</p>
         <p>The Rev. R. Fraser was, also, here then, (he came on 17<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. &amp; staid till 24<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) and as he lodged here w. me, we were pretty much together: Mr. Grant was at Dvk. on 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. I had previously spent an hour w. him at “Manse”. With your old friend Mrs. Trestrail I also spent a nice hour, I caught her at work (as usual) in her garden <hi rend="italic">down </hi>among her <hi rend="italic">flowers</hi>, almost hidden! &amp; there is a fine show. Unforty. she was going to Napier, &amp; so I have not seen any more of her, neither has she seen or heard Mr. Fraser.</p>
         <p>Late—I suppose you will have heard of Hon. Secy. G. White’s marriage—to a Miss Baker (neice of H. Williams) perhaps known to you and to Mrs. Harding. In town last wk., Large <hi rend="italic">besought </hi>me for a Paper! Hill came hither on Friday last from Waipawa to give a Lect. in Tn. Hll., but attendce very poor, he retd. to N. on Saturday. The repairs at Parsonage taking some time, Tuke will not be well able to come for at least a month.—–</p>
         <p>3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. (viii p.m. Napier) I go on w. my letter.</p>
         <p>On May Day afternoon, Hill returned from Napier, dined, &amp; was going on to Wallgfd. &amp; E. Coast Schools, &amp; to Dvk. by Sunday: I tried hard to dissuade him from it in <hi rend="italic">such </hi>weather—not merely for himself but the poor children—but no avail. It is <hi rend="italic">still raining</hi>—all this day heavily! &amp; I think H. will have enough of it.—</p>
         <p>Before I left Waipu. I had the pleasure of meeting &amp; speaking w. yr. cousin R. he was well &amp; so Father, now at Home: we 2 had a good laugh at “own correspdt.” (plaguy <hi rend="italic">S.J.</hi>) who had inserted in “Herald”, of a “₤100. damage done at Mt. V. by earthq.” in wk. before last. I have since seen a short letter in “H.” from yr. Uncle, denying it! But <hi rend="italic">all one </hi>to <hi rend="italic">that </hi>pachyderm! I halted on Monday nt. at Waipawa—arrd. here last nt., not <hi rend="italic">over well</hi>: wrote (<hi rend="italic">again</hi>) to Tuke, I should <hi rend="italic">not </hi>be at their social tomorrow nt., <hi rend="italic">neither out there on Sy. next</hi>—I have a <hi rend="italic">slight</hi> cough, &amp; plenty of flying rheumatism, and must take a little care of myself.—–</p>
         <p>Hill told me of a “row” he had last week had w. Large &amp; new Council: they were detd. to appoint a Librarian,—no books to be taken out by a Mr., but only thro’ L. who was/is to be there once a day!!—I found here a copy of <hi rend="italic">their </hi>“Report” just issued: I send it. I also add—2 scraps from Sta. Barbara (one, most strange!) and a leaf from a “Hansard” cover—I was not aware of <hi rend="italic">so many </hi>books (by outsiders) pubd. by Gt. and I see, “Thompson” Dunedin, adds “<hi rend="italic">F.R.S.</hi>”—re <hi rend="italic">same </hi>I shall enq. of Hamilton. Hill also told me, that <hi rend="italic">young </hi>McLeod’s paper on electricity <hi rend="italic">has been</hi> pubd. by Sir J.H. in forthg. vol. Two things I noticed in <hi rend="italic">Wgn. </hi>p. this day— “S. Costall” was filling Didsbury’s place (<hi rend="italic">pro tem</hi>—perhaps): and St <hi rend="italic">Patrick’s </hi>was in “<hi rend="italic">Boulcott</hi> St.”</p>
         <p>I called in at Crerar’s last wk, &amp; was much pleased to find <hi rend="italic">yg. C. so well</hi>: I spoke of <hi rend="italic">you </hi>to him, &amp; that I shod. <hi rend="italic">report. </hi>I have also been looking into Field’s book of Ferns—&amp; find many strange things in it—besides a certain <hi rend="italic">animus </hi>v. the writer of this (which <hi rend="italic">I had expected</hi>)—and the most sickening <hi rend="italic">egoism re self</hi>!! I think I must have told you I had been reading Froude’s “Cath. of Aragon”—a curious thing in it—is, that in the whole Title p. not a single stop! not even a period at close! I have recently recd. a <hi rend="italic">very long letter </hi>(fol. pap.!) from Hamilton (in almost Diamond type!) about his “finds”, &amp;c, &amp; askg. questions—<hi rend="italic">great many</hi>! I almost fear—I shall <hi rend="italic">never </hi>ansr. them. I lent Mr. Fraser my copy Morris’ poetry, F. <hi rend="italic">most </hi>pleased, &amp; going to purchase a copy: I see <hi rend="italic">another </hi>vol. of <hi rend="italic">his </hi>lately advd.—“Songs of Legends” (I think): I cut out the Review for you, &amp; mentg. it last wk. to Craig, he wished to <hi rend="italic">see </hi>it, to order (?) &amp; has not yet retd. it—pubd. by Cassell &amp; Co. but as it is largely &amp; “<hi rend="italic">superbly</hi>” illd.—I suppose it is <hi rend="italic">dear</hi>.</p>
         <p>I notice, a Teacher is advd. for Makotuku School, and I hear that one will be required for Takapau School: I don’t know the <hi rend="italic">real grounds</hi>. On the platform Ry. Stn. Waipawa, last evg. I saw 11 big (3-bushel) sacks <hi rend="italic">filled </hi>w. fine cabbages <hi rend="italic">for Wgn</hi>, all bearing an address in <hi rend="italic">Chin. chars. </hi>written on calico; these were grown in Waipawa Bush, and (of course) sent by a Chinese; their total weight was nearly a ton.</p>
         <p>I omitted to mention that Field has actually <hi rend="italic">figured </hi>some of my rare described ferns (in N.Z.I. Trans.)—which, he says, he has <hi rend="italic">never </hi>seen! but “from my descriptn.” &amp;, of course, erroneously—but to upset them himself! and worse still, Mr. Baker of Kew, in a <hi rend="italic">very recent </hi>paper on Ferns, brings them also forward <hi rend="italic">from Field’s</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">drawings</hi>, and disallows their specific differences. Really it is too bad. Kirk, in a letter 2 yrs. ago, told me of Field’s wonderful doings! in that way.—</p>
         <p>Now I must close. I hope you &amp; yrs. are all quite well: and (shall I say?) <hi rend="italic">you </hi>busily &amp; <hi rend="italic">profitably </hi>employed?—If R. Stout becomes P—r, I will try <hi rend="italic">him </hi>again <hi rend="italic">re </hi>ptg. “<hi rend="italic">A</hi>.” I saw in a paper yesty. in train that Ly. &amp; Bl. had got the Bor. Council <hi rend="italic">printing</hi>, &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>             With very kind regards,</p>
         <p>                                     Yours truly, W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. I have recd. a nice note from Mr. Maskell <hi rend="italic">re </hi>that <hi rend="italic">Coccus </hi>already described by him.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
