<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0351">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1877 December 9: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1877-12-09">1877 December 9</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1877 December 9: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-302" place="foot" n="302"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand, Sunday,<lb/>December 9, 1877.</p>
         <p>A. Luff Esq.,</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir,</p>
         <p>Four days ago I had the pleasure of receiving your long &amp; friendly &amp; welcome letter of Octr. 10–17, &amp; I was much pleased to find you were all then well. My last to you (a bulky one) was closed, I think, on 14th. Novr. I was not then very well, &amp; since that I rallied &amp; went to work &amp; got laid up again—another 7, 8 days!! I am going to make another attempt tomorrow (at Campbell’s) &amp; so on to 24th. inclusive, if I can, &amp; even then I have not time enough left to visit all <hi rend="italic">before</hi> Xmas: so I write you <hi rend="italic">today</hi>.</p>
         <p>First, Business: I enclose Black’s last note, which will speak for itself. Witty I write to by to-morrow’s mail to let him know that his Deed is ready &amp;c. I thank you for paying Trubner &amp; Wesley those two sums for me. I ought to have heard from them both but didn’t: they may, however, have written by Suez mail.</p>
         <p>Of <hi rend="italic">news</hi>, there is plenty: Parliament, I believe, prorogues <hi rend="italic">tomorrow</hi>. Gray Ministry still in: 2½ m. to be borrowed.—see the papers I send you; O., S., &amp; Russell (W.) returned yesterday. I saw S., who was looking pretty well. Education Act will pass, with a few of the Amendments of the Leg. Cl.—one, the <hi rend="italic">Inspectors</hi> to be appd. &amp; removd. by Governor; &amp; <hi rend="italic">this</hi> Edl. District to comprise from S. Boundary of H. Bay on to the <hi rend="italic">other</hi> (N.) side of E. Cape!! in Bay of Plenty! Sup. Ct. opens here tomorrow—Prendergast is come, &amp; the Calendar <hi rend="italic">heavy</hi> for <hi rend="italic">us</hi>!, a sad case of murder at Woodville, a fortnight ago—&amp; the man taken up on <hi rend="italic">suspicion</hi> (though the sapient Coroner’s Jury at W. draught him in <hi rend="italic">guilty</hi> of <hi rend="italic">w. murder</hi>!) there is little or no <hi rend="italic">evidence</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">against</hi> him but, as somebody did it, a great <hi rend="italic">furore</hi>!—Mrs. Shepherd (Havelock) is dead. Bp. Williams is still very low, gradually sinking:—The <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Bishop of Waiapu is to be “consecrated” today: to do this the Bps. of Christchurch, Auckland &amp; Wn are here.—So that altogether we have a whole Bench (5) Bishops; may they be the means of doing us good. Sidey is still in N.S.W., &amp; Fraser (senior) is gone to <hi rend="italic">their</hi> Assembly at Wgn. Berry too, is gone to Pov. Bay on a visit.—G.P. Donnelly is just married to Renata’s <hi rend="italic">grand</hi>niece (great fuss!—we shall see!—it would have <hi rend="italic">looked better</hi> had <hi rend="italic">D.</hi> waited his trial for horse-stealing which is to come off in a day or two. “Helen Denny” (our <hi rend="italic">first</hi> wool ship) is gone, and in her <hi rend="italic">several</hi> passengers (about 24 I think) &amp; among them Edwards &amp; wife. I did not know of their going till the ship had sailed; but had I known, say, a few days before, I <hi rend="italic">could not</hi> have seen them, being ill. David Hunter is <hi rend="italic">leaving</hi> Station! It is <hi rend="italic">said</hi>, some great falling out w. his brother George. Wellwood (it is said) is going to England.—Fannin has been unwell “gout, toothache, and neuralgia”: he does not take care of himself. Tel. Off. opened at Mohaka: <hi rend="italic">2</hi> mails a week to be hence to Wairoa overland &amp; £10,000 voted for Ahuriri bridge (Sheehan &amp; G. Grey!)—we shall see, if it be spent. They are shortly to be <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, &amp; the Catholics &amp; “working men” (w. Knight &amp; Lindsay!! at their head) are <hi rend="italic">moving</hi> &amp;c., &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>Troy has retd. to his old post at bank &amp; seeks to part w. his place! H. Williams as trustee to R. &amp; Drummond refused to pay me <hi rend="italic">¼th</hi>. of interest due—£20, saying my name was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> in Deed—so I have to wait 12 months for them to be paid, before I can think of getting a 1d!! D. brought me L’s account—it was simply <hi rend="italic">fearful</hi>: L, so D said, had said “it would only cost a <hi rend="italic">trifle</hi>”. D said “say the sum”. “Well about £5”. D. said “say exactly; will £10 pay <hi rend="italic">you</hi>”?, “Yes, completely”. The acct. was nearly £40! &amp; <hi rend="italic">thus</hi> run up “Consultation £1.1.0, D. 10/6 (these often repeated); writing advt. for D.T. 6/8; copying for “Herald” 6/8; sending ditto to D.T. 6/8; do. to “H.D.” 6/8; altering do 6/8; payg. for­ advtg. 6/8 (<hi rend="italic">besides</hi> the full charges for advertg.)!! loan of room &amp; chairs (4!!) for meeting £5.5.0. (we were in his outer or clerk’s room 2 hours!!!). I begin to fear that L. will also have a long &amp; heavy acct. against <hi rend="italic">me</hi>. Poor old Groom is dying &amp; his old wife not much better—both in a sad state. J. Hamlin has had another portion of his lower lip cut away by Dr. S.—but, I fear, with <hi rend="italic">little benefit</hi>. J.H. is now obliged to give in from any work. Young Irvine, too, is gone in H. Denny: some say <hi rend="italic">he</hi> will never reach England, &amp; that it is doubtful if Edwards will. I hope nothing very serious will happen for Mrs. Ruth (Vaughan’s daughter) <hi rend="italic">must</hi> be confined on board during voyage. Read G.T.C. Chapman’s account of <hi rend="italic">his voyage</hi> to Eng. in “Auckland Weekly News” which I send.</p>
         <p rend="end">Decr, 11th.</p>
         <p>I recommence. Yesterday &amp; today I have been at Campbell’s large school (over 100) &amp; am <hi rend="italic">rather</hi> tired; however I held out better then I had anticipated—glad that it is over.—Grey, Sheehan &amp; Macandrew are to be here this week, &amp; are to have (I hear) a “perfect ovation”. Our own 3 members landed in silence. Good has, already, come through the Grey Ministry—<hi rend="italic">viz</hi>. the Colonialization of the Land Fund, which the former My., I think, would not have <hi rend="italic">attempted</hi>! and I look for good to come to us, through the Maoris being driven to see, that they <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi> have <hi rend="italic">their wishes</hi>—not even from <hi rend="italic">Sheehan</hi> &amp; Co. Mr Orr brought a <hi rend="italic">big</hi> N.Z. (<hi rend="italic">forest</hi>) Beetle, thinking it was the <hi rend="italic">Colorado</hi>! I was happy to undeceive him. I see a large lot of timber &amp; several carpenters at work on T.S. 169 (opp. Church Lane). The poor girl accused of <hi rend="italic">stealing</hi> an old 12 year old child’s garment was acquitted yester­day. (She never ought to have been tried for such a <hi rend="italic">trumpery</hi> charge). In today’s Herald is a letter of Sealy’s (from Jersey to Home Paper), in which <hi rend="italic">I quite agree</hi>. I marvel at <hi rend="italic">that</hi> Jury in the “Penge” murder case! I don’t at that butcher Hawkins! (a second Judge Jefferies!)—he got his (<hi rend="underline italic">Govt</hi>.) reward for his atrocious conduct in the Tichborne case, &amp; is capable of anything! I have no doubt but that <hi rend="italic">he</hi> would gladly have hung those 4 for Harriet Stanton, who died of <hi rend="italic">disease</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I have just been to the “<hi rend="italic">brow</hi>” to look at the works below: Monroe Street is advancing, the N.E. side is carried out beyond our sales to Scandins. &amp; Pocock’s Sn., &amp; one (next to Watt’s) near Railway are now nearly filled in: 4 in Carlyle Street (see advt. in paper.) are <hi rend="italic">1</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">st</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi> for filling-in, cont. taken. The worst is they are getting stuff from all around my hill; so that I have been obliged to send out two letters again, this past weak, warning them of the consequences.</p>
         <p>Our <hi rend="italic">first </hi>rain fell on 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Novr.; I was at Waipukurau, of course shut up all that day—but <hi rend="italic">willingly</hi>: it was delightful<hi rend="italic"> to see </hi>the good<hi rend="italic"> </hi>arising from that rain. It has also rained since—2–4 times, but all good &amp; serviceable: it now seems drawing that way. In this day’s <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> you will see a highly <hi rend="italic">characteristic </hi>advt. by my neighbour!</p>
         <p rend="end">Sunday. Decr., 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>I now proceed to close, having had a day longer for writing, through detention of steamer, S. First, let me tell you I got through my heavy week’s work! (<hi rend="underline italic">again</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">better</hi> than my fears!) &amp; tomorrow I take Hastings;—Tuesday, Havelock;—Wednesday, Kaikoura,—Thursday, Patangata,—&amp; Friday, Tamumu: so that if I can do this &amp; return on Saturday from Waipukurau I shall be both glad &amp; <hi rend="italic">thankful</hi>.</p>
         <p>I send you yesterday’s 2 papers, from which you will learn a <hi rend="italic">little</hi> of <hi rend="italic">our</hi> doings! Of course <hi rend="italic">I had</hi> a good <hi rend="italic">view</hi> of all from the brow; there were <hi rend="italic">very few</hi> (if any) of our old first settlers present; &amp; so of our <hi rend="italic">principal</hi> shopkeepers, old hands,—I saw none. The day (weather) was splendid (as usual) &amp; mob great—(partly owing to the 3 Boys’ Schools (town) having broken up that morning!)—but great <hi rend="italic">at Spit</hi> owing to Natives, who did not <hi rend="italic">stay</hi> in Cl. Sq. I fancied they had been told to clear out, as Sir. G. &amp; Co. would meet them all on <hi rend="italic">their own</hi> ground yesterday; there were not 500 in Cl. Sq. &amp; many of these were boys &amp; servant girls. Grey made a sad error in his speech (which you will see <hi rend="italic">marked</hi> by me), &amp; I find that Price, <hi rend="italic">last evening</hi> took him up for it: but Price is also a little out in his statement.—</p>
         <p>Rev. S.W. told me on Friday last the old Bp. was sinking fast—calm &amp; collected: I should greatly like to see him again, but he is to be “<hi rend="italic">kept very quiet</hi>”. Donnelly has been acquitted: I fancy, however, it is not wholly over. D. Galbraith is dead, died suddenly at Clarendon. Miss Sproule (who kept Port School) was married an 10th to the Capt. of the “Manaia”, a quiet nice man. Irvine, I hear, is going to keep on his school, which I <hi rend="italic">regret</hi>—unless he will teach his unruly ones how to behave, but I will hope for the best, because J.D. O—d is going to live in his old Town Quarters. J.N. Wilson is now a Lord! hope he, too, will polish up a bit! he needs it: I have no faith in <hi rend="italic">his</hi> law, should he become Attorney-General! he can never <hi rend="italic">lead</hi> in the Leg. Council.—</p>
         <p>While selecting prizes for Cy. schools at C. &amp; <hi rend="italic">Craig’</hi>s yesterdy I saw Witty who told me he had got my letter <hi rend="italic">re </hi>your Deed, thanked, I said that wod. be “all right”: we were <hi rend="italic">both too busy </hi>to talk. Grubb I hear has been unwell from diarrhoea. From the hill I see a frame house (decent size &amp; high) just up <hi rend="italic">opp</hi>. U.M. Chapel &amp;, I believe, on Mrs. Tuke’s land. Bryson is going to build a fine Hotel on his corner <hi rend="italic">Section</hi>. Not <hi rend="italic">seen</hi> P.D. since my last. <hi rend="italic">We must</hi> come to some <hi rend="italic">real</hi> conclusion shortly. Barry (R. &amp; Drummond’s <hi rend="italic">trustee</hi>) is in an awful way <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Lascelles’ <hi rend="italic">infamous</hi> Bill! Mr. Sidey is to leave N.S.W. on 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.—</p>
         <p>The “Lochnagar” (our 2nd. wool ship) is to leave next week. I posted, last evg. a <hi rend="italic">lot</hi> of papers for you, contg. many matters of interest, also a vol. of N.Z. Institute <hi rend="italic">Proceedings</hi> for last year—omitted in the “Transactions” vol. The <hi rend="italic">Red Kowhai </hi>is bearing <hi rend="italic">green</hi> pods before my window, which, when ripe, will be for you. I hope to have a little spare time after Jany. 1st. as I have still all the Teachers’ Quarterly Registers to go through, &amp; make out all their vouchers &amp;c., &amp;c.—&amp; then, all for the Board, &amp; the Govt.—and I hope, the <hi rend="italic">very last</hi> time, after this fashion; for all this work is (or should be) <hi rend="italic">Fannin’s</hi>. Inglis—who was nearly starving here—has got the billet of Clerk to Waipawa Cy. Council @ £200.—</p>
         <p>And now I must say Goodbye, with best wishes for you &amp; yours &amp; a Happy New Year &amp; <hi rend="italic">many of them</hi>.</p>
         <p>Bel. me,</p>
         <p>Yours truly,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>J. Hague has broken his leg! his wife is now in service at W. Clive Hotel.</p>
         <p>“This case was tried in H.B. some years ago, &amp; was that of P. Torotoro &amp; Rewi v. Sutton, If hon. members will read the report (which I now lay on the table) they will find how land <hi rend="italic">not</hi> intended to be included in a claim has come to be included in that claim, and how land which clearly on the evidence should not have been included in the original trans­action, has been found by a Jury of the Supreme Court to have been included in that transaction. The perusal of that report greatly shocked me. – – – I have submitted it to the opinion of another hon. member of this Council, &amp; he agrees w. me that in that case <hi rend="italic">there has been a grievous miscarriage of justice</hi> &amp; that it becomes the duty of the Government of this country, if called upon to enforce the judgment of the Supreme Court in that instance to purchase the rights of the natives in the possession of that land…. I am satisfied, that, in that case there has been grievous miscarriage of Justice.”</p>
         <p>From “Hansard”!! (Hon. Mr. Hart, in Leg. Council, Oct. 18/77 in speech on “Native Lands” with a good deal more to same effect).</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">re Wairoa Land</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="center">Extract from D. Black’s letter.—</p>
         <p>—“As regards the land, I may say that Mr. Luff bought it about 4 years ago from Mr. Routledge at £5: 5: 0 per acre, and I believe when he left for England, some 2 years ago, he offered to sell for £6: 6: 0 per acre. I think £7 per acre would pay him good interest since that time; this I would give for it. The land is very rough &amp; expensive to clear, and will need to be drained, as it is very wet in the winter season.—</p>
         <p>I will trouble you for another line or two on the subject.</p>
         <p>Wairoa Nov. 3/77                             (signed) D. Black.</p>
         <p rend="center">Extract from my reply:</p>
         <p>—“I am now writing to Mr. Luff by this outg. Eng. Mail. (closing here, on 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. at 8 p.m.) and I will let him know of your offer—but I don’t think he will sell it at that price. I wish, for your sake, that you had increased, for I believe it is worth more.—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">It is nothing to the purpose</hi> what Mr. Luff gave for it: the only question is, what is it worth now? Many sections in this Town were bought for £3 each—yet now the owners ask £500 to £800 each for them.</p>
         <p>If you should get this <hi rend="italic">in time</hi> (<hi rend="italic">before</hi> our Eng. mail closes) and you will increase your offer, you can do so by telegram: just say the gross amount of the money you will give, that will do. I will keep open my letter to Mr. Luff till the last hour.—</p>
         <p>(signed) W. Colenso. </p>
         <p>Napier, Novr. 10/77.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>