<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0767">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 February 5: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0495.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-02-05">1891 February 5</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 February 5: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-511" place="foot" n="511"> ATL qMS-0495.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Thursday night,<lb/>Feby. 5/91:—at the <lb/>well-known old Corner!</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding,</p>
         <p>Altho’ I wrote to you recently, I am inclined to do so again: (1) a letter your brother left here yesty. mg. early, on his way to pg. off.—I, in going to town, afterwards, returned it to him—to forward to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>.—as you could <hi rend="italic">well</hi> ansr. (N.B. “2/6 P.N.”! a good joke: had it been 20/-<hi rend="sup "> </hi>it wod. have been nearer the mark: I have but a <hi rend="underline italic">few</hi> copies of “<hi rend="italic">3 Lity.P.—</hi>” left, &amp; these are 5/- each.) (2) a letter again from you, of the 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi> inst. (crossing mine! of course): its contents <hi rend="italic">most </hi>interesting:—I marvel at yr. remark <hi rend="italic">re</hi> “<hi rend="italic">Skein</hi>”—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> at <hi rend="italic">your</hi> lack of memory!—and as your enquiry was a <hi rend="italic">long one</hi>, return it—Then yours from Archdn. <hi rend="italic">L</hi>.W.—re Yate &amp; the pg. p. I suppose that <hi rend="italic">settles</hi> the matter, <hi rend="italic">so far</hi>: but what became of it! or, rather, how come it to pass that <hi rend="italic">I</hi> (<hi rend="underline italic">we</hi>) never knew anything of it! What J. Smith a Col. youth of <hi rend="italic">that</hi> day/aged <hi rend="italic">15</hi>) could <hi rend="italic">do </hi>in the way of ptg.—I have yet to learn. </p>
         <p>see slip marked *——</p>
         <p>There is one <hi rend="italic">ludicrous</hi> bit in the Arch-deacon’s extracts, about his Uncle—this I have pencilled: he only came to N.Z. in <hi rend="italic">Augt</hi>./23, w. wife &amp; family, &amp; this land was <hi rend="italic">then</hi> indeed wild: fancy <hi rend="italic">his</hi> writing to Mr. Pratt (about 4 months or so after landing) about a <hi rend="italic">pg. press</hi>! Of all our Misss.—<hi rend="italic">H.W.</hi>, was perhaps <hi rend="italic">the least fitted</hi> (naturally) for <hi rend="italic">anything</hi> of that kind. He <hi rend="italic">never</hi> attempted translation!—indeed, the lang. was little known: but this small incident truly shows <hi rend="italic">the char.</hi> (not so much of <hi rend="italic">H.W.</hi> as of his <hi rend="italic">wife</hi>—who was (the <hi rend="italic">sole</hi>?) writer of <hi rend="italic">all</hi> that awful scribble used by son-in-law Carleton, in “Life of H.W.”) The diff. between <hi rend="underline italic">H</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi>W. &amp; his brother <hi rend="underline italic">W</hi>.W. (the late Bp.) was immense! <hi rend="italic">in everything</hi>—phys. &amp; mentally!! There is a <hi rend="underline italic">fine</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> portrait</hi> of <hi rend="italic">H.W.</hi> in “the Early Histy”—but <hi rend="italic">no more like him</hi> than it is of D. Sidey! it is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> a photo: &amp; perhaps <hi rend="italic">done by himself</hi>. (There are <hi rend="italic">2 other</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">highly</hi>
            <hi rend="underline"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">flattered</hi> portraits in that work, Heaphy (w., of course the I.V.P.) &amp; <hi rend="italic">Pompallier</hi> to this last, almost a full page, abounding in French decoration &amp; (as in <hi rend="italic">H.W.) </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">not like the man</hi>.—</p>
         <p>In your last written (<hi rend="italic">bad</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">pale</hi> ink on <hi rend="italic">green</hi> memo. paper! scarcely legible,) you quote Archd. W’s. remark on the “Maori’ Catms, Kerikeri, 1825”.—[I would here observe, that <hi rend="italic">he</hi> quotes from “Mr J. Kemp”—re “<hi rend="italic">press</hi>”, &amp;c—now <hi rend="italic">J. Kemp</hi> resided at “<hi rend="italic">Kerikeri</hi>”, &amp; <hi rend="italic">only there—</hi>(J.K. was at KK. before 1825.)] L.W. asks “where is such to be found?” I copy—“Races Bibliography Committee. <hi rend="italic">Rarotongan – – – Hawaiian</hi> – – – <hi rend="italic">Maori</hi>.” M.Catm. (the first book printed in N.Z.)<hi rend="italic"> </hi>12mo., Kirikiri, 1825; the Pilgrim’s Progress; Robinson Crusoe: Poems, &amp;c., edited by Sir G.Grey, &amp;c, &amp;c: &amp; other books, pamphlets, very numerous.”<lb/>(“Report, 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi> meeting, Australian Association of Sciences,” p.309.) [not a sound, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> any I had printed!!]</p>
         <p>Another <hi rend="italic">laughable</hi> item! Archdn. says, re “’25”—“more likely to be 18<hi rend="underline italic">3</hi>5”—why I landed in <hi rend="italic">Decr. ’34</hi>!!!——</p>
         <p>Should you write to <hi rend="italic">him</hi> again on this subject,—copy what I sent to you from Dr. Marshall’s book, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> those 2 ladies working hard at translating for him to take to Sydney, to be <hi rend="italic">printed</hi>—small lessons for schools.—Why were <hi rend="italic">such</hi> not printed here in N.Z.? the Archdns. Mother, now here with us, is one of those <hi rend="italic">2 ladies</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="center">————</p>
         <p>Am <hi rend="italic">glad</hi> you are sending for “Roving Printer, N. York ’61.—</p>
         <p>Yes, I have seen “Angas’ N.Z.” there are some good Mao. things in it.—Capt. Reece, the other day, told me in train, of his having seen it—once and lately, &amp; was surprised—I have noticed it advertised at a <hi rend="italic">high fig.</hi>.</p>
         <p>There are <hi rend="italic">many</hi> quasi similar works I should much like to see—but am <hi rend="italic">too old</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">now</hi> to order any more.—</p>
         <p>I know a little of Lord, &amp; we were, latterly, friendly: I visited him in his quaintly fitted up room at “Clarendon” H., and at one of my pol. meetings, in P.C.C., L. was Chn. &amp;c.—He also sought out a small work on N.Z. for me when he retd. to England, &amp; he sought about for <hi rend="italic">another</hi> I much wanted (<hi rend="italic">Bidwell’s ascent of Tongariro</hi>) but failed: I knew <hi rend="italic">B</hi>., he stopped at my house on his <hi rend="italic">return</hi> jy. <hi rend="italic">w. his plants</hi>. Should you ever notice B’s book,—try to get it—it is a small one,—</p>
         <p>I thank you for the “Circular” re Tregear’s Dicty.—I shall purchase one if T. does <hi rend="italic">not</hi> send me a copy!! (He <hi rend="underline italic">may</hi>, as he did his “<hi rend="italic">Aryan</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Ox</hi>.” one.) Be sure you <hi rend="italic">do not</hi> slip out, that I am on the look-out for one. I notice T. says—“<hi rend="italic">several years in prepn.</hi>”—I <hi rend="italic">was sorry to see that</hi>, bearing in mind <hi rend="italic">his first</hi> letters to me.—What <hi rend="italic">is he? </hi>How<hi rend="italic"> does he live?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Hill, yesty. gave me an astonishing account of the great XtCh. meeting,—His own Papers were <hi rend="italic">not read</hi>, because he did <hi rend="italic">not send</hi> them in! Hamilton was very well—&amp; “<hi rend="italic">recd. H. gladly</hi>.”</p>
         <p>I enclose 10/- P.N. subsn. to “Typo” for 1891, <hi rend="italic">2 copies.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Evg. Mail arrived here yestdy. and I <hi rend="italic">am vexed</hi> to find, that my letters, papers, &amp;c. posted at Dvk. on 31<hi rend="sup ">st</hi> Octr., were <hi rend="italic">not sent on</hi>! I purposely visited the P.O. there, and the P.M. too, about the mail on that day; as he had <hi rend="italic">before</hi> made a mistake, in persisting to send <hi rend="italic">to Wgn</hi>—a mail too late! He assured me, mine should go to N. on <hi rend="italic">that evening</hi>—which they <hi rend="italic">did not</hi>! And so all my family, &amp;c, &amp;c, were in anxiety!—</p>
         <p rend="end">(<hi rend="italic">Good night</hi>)</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">6</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>. Having you or the pg. press (or <hi rend="italic">both</hi>) on my brain! I commenced scribbling again this mg. (See slip,*) and <hi rend="underline italic">I commend that to your considn, &amp; custody</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>You will recollect Saunders’ quaint text— “<hi rend="italic">this is</hi> a great mystery”(?)—I think <hi rend="italic">this</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">ours</hi>, is <hi rend="italic">far greater</hi>: but <hi rend="italic">Tempus revelat</hi>.—</p>
         <p>A postcard to hand this mg.—from White, to attend meeting <hi rend="italic">tonight</hi>, at VIII, to consid. Report, &amp;c—<hi rend="italic">drafted:</hi> Annl. Mtg. on 9<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I enclose a memo from Large—how <hi rend="italic">could</hi> he use <hi rend="italic">such</hi> a paper?——</p>
         <p>Hill told me, my <hi rend="italic">non-</hi>appce at XtCh. was much regretted, &amp; <hi rend="italic">enqs. after me from strangers were many: </hi>it is a notable fact, talked of there, that I should have<hi rend="italic"> personally known</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">&amp; recd.</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">into my house</hi>—<hi rend="italic">those 3 pakehas</hi> who alone had <hi rend="underline italic">early</hi> ascended Tongariro—Bidwell, Dieffenbach, &amp; Dyson! I have a fine <hi rend="italic">Australian</hi> plant now here in my garden, sent me from Sydney by B. on his return:—it was 25 years w. me before if flowered, but since, it has flowered every year! The tuber, when sent, was of the size of a <hi rend="italic">small</hi> walnut,—now it is as big as a man’s head.—</p>
         <p>3 <hi rend="italic">p.m</hi>. And now I think I will close my <hi rend="italic">long</hi> letter: <hi rend="italic">You</hi> will note that I have written it much as if you and I were talking! It has filled up a few <hi rend="italic">vacant hours, </hi>which<hi rend="italic"> I ought not to know</hi>.—Of late <hi rend="italic">I cannot settle down to anything</hi>, <hi rend="italic">mainly</hi> because I <hi rend="italic">don’t know</hi> what I may have to do in the <hi rend="italic">near future</hi>. It is much like as if you had a long and heavy work in expectation, and you don’t like to begin on others—save small ones. I have had no visitors, I do not wish to enter microscopl. Botanl. work (Mosses, Hepaticæ, &amp;c) unless I <hi rend="italic">could go</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">on with it, stick to it: </hi>otherwise time <hi rend="italic">is wasted. </hi>If the Dean is pretty well<hi rend="italic"> </hi>&amp; returned the Bp. too being back from Py. Bay.—I may get away next wk. to the Bush—but I do not intend to remain there unless I have some <hi rend="italic">Ch.</hi> work to do—I mean such as is <hi rend="underline italic">really</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">required</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I wrote to Parkinson yesty. and I ought to have had his reply: maybe I shall hear tonight. On Sy. mg: I go to Clive for St. Hill, who has taken his holiday at Erewhon, &amp;c.</p>
         <p>This day I recd. a terrific Ms. from Kew (thro the Governor’s P. Secy.), containing the examn. by Stephani of Leipsic <hi rend="italic">of all the Hepaticæ</hi> last yr. sent to Kew. (some thousands of <hi rend="italic">spns</hi>.—many new). This is Ms. No.2—the Mosses, &amp; Phænogams have yet to undergo the Ordeal of exam. by <hi rend="italic">experts</hi>. (My lichens &amp; f.w. Algae not yet sent—also, <hi rend="italic">lots</hi> of mosses! To put those up, w. notes, would give me employ for the winter.)</p>
         <p>I am in <hi rend="italic">good</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">health</hi>—i.e., free from Rheumatism, a <hi rend="italic">new feature</hi>; though I believe <hi rend="italic">him</hi> to be near &amp; <hi rend="italic">vilely</hi> waiting, tiger-like: and feeling so well <hi rend="italic">I want work</hi>. I shall post this tonight, that you may get it <hi rend="underline italic">before</hi> you again write, &amp; so bring our X correspce. regular. I hope your son is steadily improving: &amp; with kindest regards &amp; best wishes, I am, Yours sincerely, W.Colenso.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">* Slip to p 1—(addendum)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Re</hi> Mr Yate &amp; James Smith: as per extract furnished by Archd. L. Williams.</p>
         <p>On again reading this—I am inclined to think there is <hi rend="italic">more</hi> here than appears at first sight.</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>Yate, Mr &amp; Mrs Chapman, &amp; I.S. left Sydney <hi rend="italic">19</hi>
               <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>. July. “Y. took with him a Pg. P., &amp; a <hi rend="underline italic">lad</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">named S.,</hi> to assist him in the use of it.” (<hi rend="italic">C.M.S. publication</hi>—“Record.”)</item>
            <item>Mr Y., <hi rend="italic">in his letter</hi> to the C.M.S. from Sydney in July, says:—“I am about to take with me to N.Z. a <hi rend="italic">youth</hi> aged 15 yrs., <hi rend="italic">very strongly</hi> recommended by Mr Marsden: he is to assist me in printing: <hi rend="italic">for which purpose I have put him in the Gaz. Off. till we sail.</hi> – – – <hi rend="italic">I send by this conveyance a few copies</hi> of the work which I have been superintending. </item>
         </list>
         <p>                                                             (“Record”, Jany. 1831.)</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>Mr Marsden lived at Paramatta—then a country township ___ miles from Sydney: <hi rend="italic">there</hi> was the “factory” of State prisoners under Mr Marsden’s charge. N.B. There were then but <hi rend="italic">few free</hi> settlers <hi rend="italic">there</hi>:—</item>
            <item>Was J. Smith a “factory” lad?—or, one of Mr Marsden’s numerous <hi rend="italic">assigned</hi> servants (?slaves).</item>
            <item>There was <hi rend="italic">no</hi> Pg. off. at Paramatta.</item>
            <item>Y., writing <hi rend="italic">in</hi>
               <hi rend="underline italic">July</hi> says, “I have <hi rend="italic">put him into the Gaz. P. Off. till we sail.</hi>” At that time, Y. had <hi rend="italic">finished</hi> ptg. what he went to Sydney for, and probably had <hi rend="italic">left Paramatta</hi>, bringing the boy with him to Sydney.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">That ptg,</hi> was the<hi rend="italic"> first </hi>Maori work done in Sydney: a small thin 12 mo. (I have seen a copy),—<hi rend="italic">not the larger one,</hi> to execute which, Y. retd. to Sydney, 3 years after<hi rend="italic">.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>Mr &amp; Mrs Chapman were<hi rend="italic"> intimate </hi>friends of mine. We lived together at Paihia for a long time; and when they removed to the S. (Rotorua) we corresponded: I have <hi rend="italic">lots</hi> of his letters! How came it to pass—that <hi rend="italic">this </hi>
               <hi rend="underline italic">lad</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">,</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">J.S.,</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">the pg. p.,</hi> was <hi rend="italic">never once mentioned!!</hi> x x x x x</item>
         </list>
         <p>     (“Oh! for a tongue to utter—<lb/>               The thoughts that arise in me!”</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>Mr Chapman was a great talker—I mean, chatty, fluent, open; (he was a great chum of Dr Marshall’s, &amp; the officers of H.M. Ship:—I did <hi rend="italic">hear</hi>, that Chapman had been a “<hi rend="italic">Steward</hi>” in the Service: I <hi rend="italic">know</hi> he was a <hi rend="italic">first-rate</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">cook</hi>!) and in my early travelling I stayed at his house at Te Ngae Rotorua: all this tends to make that <hi rend="italic">reserve</hi> (?) the more mysterious. </item>
            <item> Rev. Mr. Marsden, also, was a very chatty (garrulous) old man:—how was it—that when I was with him at Paramatta,—and in Sydney—and afterwards, at Paihia, on<hi rend="italic">his</hi> visiting the P.O., &amp; <hi rend="italic">seeing</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">the N.Z. &amp; other books &amp;c, &amp;c</hi>.,—and on my walking up &amp; down w. him, he leaning on my arm, on the gravel walk at Paihia, he talking over old Mission matters, (we 2 had nothing else to talk about!)—<hi rend="italic">that he never alluded to </hi>
               <hi rend="underline italic">his lad</hi>
               <hi rend="italic"> J.S., nor to that Pg. Press??—</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>Moreover:—1. They <hi rend="italic">had printed</hi> “a Hymn”—a copy of <hi rend="italic">it</hi> forwarded to England by Y., in Septr./30: and, 2, they “<hi rend="italic">had looked forward to receiving great benefit from the Press for the schools; through getting portions of the Scriptures printed as they are wanted</hi>.”—</item>
         </list>
         <p rend="end">(Mr J. Kemp’s letter.)</p>
         <p>j) Yet, in 2 years, or so, we learn from Dr. Marshall—such were <hi rend="italic">not realised</hi>! And he took to Sydney <hi rend="italic">School lessons</hi> to be <hi rend="italic">printed</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">there!—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Explanation</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">wanted</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">k)  </hi>Have just been looking into my old Diary (1835): well do I remr. <hi rend="italic">the day</hi> when <hi rend="italic">the 1</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">st</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. proof sheet was taken</hi>! all the mission folks of the station present, and I have no doubt their children—the 2 Archdns. among them! &amp; several Maori chiefs: Mrs. <hi rend="italic">H.</hi>W. was accomdtd. w. a chair sent for (I see her now!) &amp; she insisted in having the <hi rend="italic">first</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">sheet</hi>! to keep &amp; <hi rend="italic">hand down</hi>, &amp;c. I fancy, <hi rend="italic">all that,</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">much more</hi>, has been <hi rend="italic">omitted</hi> by son-in-law, Carleton!! I was also informed—that a prominent member of the My. had said,—“I had been very badly treated.”——I did not tell you, while here, of this, as it was “<hi rend="italic">doubly private</hi>,”—more anon.—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Don’t forget—</hi>a copy of J. White’s works—vols III—IV: had I better write to Blair? or to Dy. about them? as the bulk was burnt, I am <hi rend="italic">very anxious.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I have <hi rend="italic">no</hi> reply from Sir J.H. I see, McGlashan has <hi rend="italic">at last</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">cashed</hi> his £7.10. Chq.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Re</hi> Andrew Tuer &amp; engraved plates N.Z. Boty: see p.9*, par.2, in yr Hd.Bk. N.Z. Flora.</p>
         <p>Glad to know you were at the Phil. Mtg.—I await impatiently (!!) Blair’s Monthly w. <hi rend="underline italic">Your Review</hi>! (good:) be sure you send me a copy. </p>
         <p>No: long Mss. of <hi rend="italic">dry names only from Kew</hi>—much as those <hi rend="italic">Lists</hi> of fungi already pubd.—but put into order by me. My <hi rend="italic">heavy</hi> work in that direction is ended.—</p>
         <p>Yesty. Smythe kindly sent up a copy of a <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Australn. Serial, “<hi rend="italic">Spectrum</hi>,” w. coloured plate, if I would subscribe—6/- yrly. No—I reply tomorrow.—Don’t admire its “get up”.—</p>
         <p>Did you rec. Copy of XtCh. Press I sent you last week?—</p>
         <p>Weather here <hi rend="italic">very wet </hi>and <hi rend="italic">great</hi> dam. done breakwater, &amp;c. do read “<hi rend="italic">Herald’s</hi>”<hi rend="italic"> </hi>art. of this day!</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Very glad</hi> to hear of Mrs H. &amp; baby doing well, &amp; boy “<hi rend="italic">improving</hi>”<hi rend="italic">—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Endeavour to make up my lot of “pie”—of last week, &amp; again something from it.<hi rend="italic">—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>With kindest continued regards, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">often</hi> thnkg. on <hi rend="italic">you</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I am, my dear Sir,</p>
         <p>Yrs truly &amp; affy., W.Colenso</p>
         <p>PS: Have you a copy of Yates’ N. Zeal.?</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
