<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0764">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 January 18: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0495.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-01-18">1891 January 18</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 January 18: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-508" place="foot" n="508"> ATL qMS-0495.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, 18 Jany.’91<lb/>(3 p.m.)</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Your (dateless) memo of Enqy. <hi rend="italic">re</hi> J. White came to hand yesty. mg.—and, as a matter of course! nowadays! crossed my big budget to you, which I suppose you recd. a few hours after.—</p>
         <p>In that last letter I, also, mentioned, that <hi rend="italic">startling</hi> telm. of J. White’s death, but I don’t recollect saying that in <hi rend="italic">the same</hi> in “Evg.N.”—they had <hi rend="italic">3</hi>9 instead of <hi rend="italic">5</hi>9—but “Herald” subsy.—<hi rend="italic">5</hi>9.</p>
         <p>Last night, at IX, my man retd. from town, &amp; brought me a copy “N.Z. Herald,” sent from Auckland: at <hi rend="italic">first sight</hi>, I supposed, it was sent from its Contg. some notice of J.Wh.—but <hi rend="italic">not so</hi>, but from Rev. G.H. Preston, to inform me of the birth of a daughter on 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>Fortunately it contains a notice of J.W. which I cut out &amp; enclose; my having <hi rend="italic">this </hi>is the reason of my now writing.—</p>
         <p>I knew a good deal about him, mainly however from his own convns. w. me, when here in N., &amp; often <hi rend="italic">upstairs</hi> in your office! but I regret to say I have <hi rend="italic">forgotten</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">much</hi>!! (1) He was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> the son of a Missy:—but his Uncle, Wm. W., was a Wesleyn. Missy. and was early stationed at Hokianga (before Buller’s arrival),—but he became <hi rend="underline italic">dissociated</hi> from the W. Mission, went to N.S.W., &amp; returned bringing his brother (a Blacksmith, I think) w. a family with him, &amp; J.W. was one of them. That is <hi rend="italic">generally</hi> correct in the clipping enclosed—as to “½ a centy. ago at Hokianga” (or thereabouts: possibly J.Wh. was “59”—but I doubt his being so old.——</p>
         <p>It seems to me a curious coincidence—my finding his writing in that book of his, &amp; my writing about him to you on the day of his death! This opens up a world of thought—which <hi rend="italic">you &amp; I</hi> might <hi rend="italic">talk</hi> about.—</p>
         <p>I mentioned to you <hi rend="italic">re</hi> vol. II “Australn. Assn.” Book, &amp; gave you an extract therefrom: looking into it again, I find in the “Report of Comee. No.11. the Bibliography of the Australian Papuan &amp; Polynesian Races”—amg. whose names as Members of Commee.—is that of <hi rend="italic">Sir James Hector</hi>,—that they give in their <hi rend="italic">N.Z. List</hi> (No.8) <hi rend="italic">J.Wh’s</hi> “Te Rou,” &amp; “Anct. Hy. of the Maori:”—also several other old pamphlets, as by W.Brown (’45) Polack, Shortland (’51), Angas (’47) Johnstone “Maoria” (’74) Taylor, Trenton, J.G. Wood (In “Wood’s Natl. Histy. of Man”—1868), &amp;c &amp;c but <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> of mine, nor any reference, or remark, concg. me.—and so in the great long <hi rend="italic">List</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Members</hi> (some hundreds, mostly Australian), who have <hi rend="italic">plenty</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Caps</hi>. after their names—generally—this <hi rend="italic">child</hi>, however, is therein placed remarkable for its <hi rend="italic">simplicity</hi> of 3 words, “Colenso, W. N. Zealand”—I fancy the Syd. Comee. was early vexed w. me, because on their <hi rend="italic">commencement</hi> they wrote to me, asking me to join, &amp; also, <hi rend="italic">to contribute papers</hi>—&amp; this latter <hi rend="italic">I refused</hi>.</p>
         <p>This mg. I took the whole S. at Augustine’s—Parkinson at Cathedl. Weather <hi rend="underline italic">delightful</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">this day</hi>, but <hi rend="italic">windy</hi> yesterday &amp; also Friday, &amp; <hi rend="italic">precious</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">rain</hi> all day on Thursday—doing much good. Hill left yesterday for Nth. I am pretty well today.</p>
         <p>             Kindest regards.—</p>
         <p>                             Yours ever.</p>
         <p>                                             W.Colenso.</p>
         <p>Have <hi rend="italic">lost</hi> my chance by Return to DVK!</p>
         <p>When you ptd. Jubilee paper, at your suggestion I sent copy to “NZ Methodist,” but it was never acknowledged. Did you note “Herald’s” apology, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the Maori letter against Smith.</p>
         <p>Post Card</p>
         <p>     Mr R.C. Harding,<lb/>   Boulcott Street,<lb/>   Wellington</p>
         <p>19/I/91. After postg. this mg., saw <hi rend="italic">at</hi> Craig’s long obity. of J. Wh., in “Weekly News,” Auckland, of <hi rend="italic">17</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>.—look it up: I merely glanced over it, but think it correct, espy. as respg. <hi rend="italic">old matters</hi> in N.Z. Surely Buller (senr.), as one of them, would have all about P—ss, he residing <hi rend="italic">there</hi>—at that time. W.C.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
