<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0538">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1883 June 29: to Balfour</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73378/">Balfour</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1883-06-29">1883 June 29</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1883 June 29: to Balfour<note xml:id="ftn3-187" place="foot" n="187"> ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier June 29 (83) (night late)</p>
         <p>Mr D.P. Balfour</p>
         <p>My dear Sir</p>
         <p>Tired &amp; weary, I will not drop tools without first writing to you. I now have open before me your two kind letters of 4th &amp; 16th. Before however I answer them, I will tell you a little of myself. As you know, I wrote to you from Norsewood. I only returned on the 8th, and found that Dr Sp had <hi rend="italic">not</hi> advertised our monthly meeting for June. He has since called on me, and told me, that my letter of Sunday 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi> (posted, as I was told, that day, &amp; should have been at N on Monday night, 4th,) only reached him on <hi rend="italic">Thursday night</hi> (like yours it seems) so he did not advertise. I have been waiting our Presidents return to town, also Holders, &amp; now they are back.</p>
         <p>I purpose calling an early Cl meeting to decide what is to be done. I suppose you will have noticed that 3 of my papers were <hi rend="italic">omitted</hi> (“rejected”) and, as a matter of course, I am not going to write for our Inst to be so served. Those 3 papers (see ‘S.542’ Vol. xv) too, were the <hi rend="italic">popular</hi> ones <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, a special vote of thanks accorded to me for each.<note xml:id="ftn3-188" place="foot" n="188"> Colenso published them himself that year: <hi rend="italic">Three literary papers read before the Hawke’s Bay Philosophical Institute during the session of 1882:—I and II, On Nomenclature; III, On ‘Macaulay’s New Zealander.’ </hi>Daily Telegraph Office, Napier. 41p.</note>
         </p>
         <p>I have been most diligently employed since my return from “Bush” in sorting &amp; packing specimens; only this afternoon despatched my <hi rend="italic">last</hi> lot (2 cases) living &amp; dried, to Port, to go tomorrow to Lyttleton, thence per “Ionic”, Home. Among the living ones are your 2 “Divott” plants. I had sent also, 2 small boxes by last S.F. mail &amp; 1 case on May 30<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. per “Brit Queen” also 2 boxes, 1 Mosses, to a German Professor last week, altogether sorting &amp;c about 1000 specimens. P.D. will be able to tell you how he found me engaged, &amp; of his <hi rend="italic">not</hi> having from me a Hieland Welcome.</p>
         <p>Now to your letters—Your little Fungus, from the butt of a dead standing Matai, is a pretty little thing. I found a tolerably large patch of it on a fallen log in May; it may be a species of <hi rend="italic">Diderma</hi> (though not the described one.) The Moss in your letter, is a sp of <hi rend="italic">Polytrichum</hi> , but yours have <hi rend="italic">lost</hi> their <hi rend="italic">caps</hi>. These (sometimes they fall off with the most careful handling—if so, preserve them) are always <hi rend="italic">necessary</hi> with Mosses; it is, however, of no consequence, as the species is common &amp; well known.</p>
         <p>The “Red river” curio, has pleased me much, especially your last sample in fruit; <hi rend="italic">this</hi> I have sent to England,—whither I had also sent the barren stems of it, that I had found on W. Ruahine 35 years ago; I hope to hear something of this.</p>
         <p>I did not know until now, that you had a library at Glenross; Capital, I am greatly pleased at this, &amp; think how those round you are indebted to you. Go on &amp; prosper; Mr Kinross told me, he had been to see you, &amp;c., &amp; pleased me much with his remarks.</p>
         <p>How I <hi rend="italic">go with you</hi>—when you speak so feelingly of this <hi rend="italic">want</hi> of a “Kindred spirit” &amp; or your therefore, “living in a world of your own entirely alone”;—Ah; <hi rend="italic">I do</hi> understand you; but do, for a moment, think of <hi rend="italic">me</hi>. No wife, no bairns, no visitors—I, too, am living in a world “<hi rend="italic">Entirely alone</hi>” as to human <hi rend="italic">society</hi>; I had however a beautiful letter from a member in the Country (almost a stranger to me) on his reading my paper in Vol. XV. on my feeling in the forest, &amp;c. It has done me a deal of good, so, also, <hi rend="italic">your</hi> letters.</p>
         <p>Your letter of the 17th &amp; box, from the look &amp; feel of the <hi rend="italic">latter</hi> I augured mischief. My table was crowded with specimens (of 80, 81) which I was going over for a friend in Australia<note xml:id="ftn3-189" place="foot" n="189"> Colenso sent mosses to Felix Reader in Melbourne.</note>—but I cleared all aside, &amp; cleared decks, and went in for your wet package. Really it <hi rend="italic">seemed</hi> to look at—as if some 6 ft Irishman had set his long big foot on it &amp; gave it a squelch; I unlaced, &amp; undid, &amp; did what I could—cleaning out mud &amp; wet paper &amp; mosses—such a mess; as if all had been in a cheese press.</p>
         <p>This day I got up early, &amp; resumed my work; I have been some hours over the plants, washing everything that seemed worthy, in 4–6 waters, and with a camel hair brush, but, I fear, to little benefit, for I do not think there is <hi rend="italic">one perfect good </hi>spn in the whole lot, though there were many, (and then what makes it <hi rend="italic">all the worse—by comparison</hi>—was the fact that yesterday afternoon I had been closely engaged, in washing, dissecting, &amp; examining, that <hi rend="italic">very nice</hi> lot you had brought me only a week ago, and which contains another <hi rend="italic">new</hi> species. And then to think, you had been out in the heavy rain to get them. It vexed me <hi rend="italic">much</hi>—for I feared that I must have written <hi rend="italic">far too strongly</hi> in my letter to you about them. However, I must ask you to get me some more (if you can do so conveniently) only in fine weather, and to put up in a <hi rend="italic">tin</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">wooden</hi> box, or <hi rend="italic">loosely</hi> in a parcel (if you should be coming to town, or Puketapu), with light dry mosses between them. These plants must not be squeezed the least, while fresh; if they are, they are ruined.</p>
         <p>In this <hi rend="italic">last</hi> lot—I see, there is another <hi rend="italic">new</hi> one, (I have often seen it, and gathered it, &amp; have it here, but <hi rend="italic">not</hi> in fruit; as I have not been in the woods &amp;c., in the winter-spring season for some years;)—This new one, a long narrow leaved plant, adhering to soil, &amp; <hi rend="italic">very tender</hi>. I should like some more of those you brought me in a tin box—the larger kind; also some of those of last year, (described in Vol. XV). I have not a spn (of yours) left, I only had 2 or 3.</p>
         <p>Besides all this, I am sure you have <hi rend="italic">lots</hi> of similar good wee things there, and now in flower.</p>
         <p>I note what you have said <hi rend="italic">approvingly</hi> of one of my papers. I fear I shall <hi rend="italic">not</hi> get that aid I <hi rend="italic">ought</hi> to have (am I right?) from our members; only a <hi rend="italic">few</hi> have responded to the circular. Today I was told in town, by some—“Who would care to <hi rend="italic">write</hi> about 3/-;”—meaning, that I should go round <hi rend="italic">asking</hi>, or, print a large lot for common sale, but I’ll do <hi rend="italic">neither</hi>. I quite expect that some will be disappointed. Well, I have written you a long letter. I hope you are well at Glenross.</p>
         <p>             Kind regards to Mrs Balfour, and believe me</p>
         <p>                             Yours truly</p>
         <p>                                             W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>