<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0190">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1865 May 10: to Hector</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Museum of New Zealand Te Papa Tongarewa MU000198/001/0033</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">Hector</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1865-05-10">1865 May 10</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1865 May 10: to Hector<note xml:id="ftn2-104" place="foot" n="104"> Museum of New Zealand Te Papa Tongarewa MU000198/001/0033</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, May 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., 1865.</p>
         <p>My dear Sir</p>
         <p>Since I dispatched my last to you I have received no less than 5 notes from you!—dated, 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>., 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. (2) ult., the last 3 (with proofs of first 2½ sheets of Essay, &amp; lith. of Bell) by steamer 2 days back: for all which I am not a little obliged &amp; indebted. I should have written to you 10–12 days ago, in reply to your notes of 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. &amp; 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. ult., but I waited the arrival of the “proofs” therein mentioned. I find I have nearly a doz. subjects to write on, and I scarcely know where to begin—although I am determined to get out of your debt for letter writing. 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. then, I observe your last 3 notes are headed “Geolog. Survey <hi rend="italic">of N.Z.</hi>”—May I not congratulate you on some new &amp; good appt.? I hope so. I had <hi rend="italic">heard</hi> (from—Wellingn.) of something of the kind being on the <hi rend="italic">tapis</hi>: and now I hope, for the sake of the Colony &amp; of Science (as well as of yourself) this is <hi rend="italic">au fait accompli</hi>: and I hope this may bring you into our neighbourhood. 2. I am sorry to find, that you are obliged to use funds reserved for Essay printing, &amp;c, for other purposes; hence, you say, you will have to shorten some of the Essays, and among them my Bot. one—<hi rend="italic">i.e. </hi>omitting the more systematic part: I leave all that, my dear Sir, entirely to you—cut out what you please. I see, however, by “proof” (“<hi rend="italic">Analysis</hi>”) sent, you intend giving the <hi rend="italic">whole </hi>of the 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. Essay, which (as you justly say) <hi rend="italic">is long</hi>, yet (in some parts) almost painfully (spasmodically) contracted. If you are “<hi rend="italic">hard up</hi>”, I am willing to give your exhibn. this Essay also: I have been thinking of doing so ever since I got your intimation of the state of your funds, &amp;c. [<hi rend="italic">Entre nous</hi>: My writing that Essay (or both) has already been a means of much official scribbling between our N.Z. Nat. Minister Mr. Mantell &amp; myself, and will (I have little doubt) end in my throwing up the Anglo-Maori job I had commenced, (which if I do I must also refund £150. “advanced” during 17 months)—The Maori <hi rend="italic">Lexicon </hi>(on which my heart <hi rend="italic">was</hi> set, and about which, I think, I must have written to you,) is already <hi rend="italic">in nubilus</hi>!—but more anon.]  3. As to the “proofs”:—allow me to say, I am not over well pleased with them; your Printer evidently slops his work; indeed, I should say, he is not used to<hi rend="italic">Book</hi> work,—perhaps to Composition on Newspapers only. The “Analysis” is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> well-done—why the word “Analysis” should be in the <hi rend="italic">biggest</hi> letters I am utterly at a loss to know. The line “<hi rend="italic">Ethnology</hi>”, or, “<hi rend="italic">the</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">M. Races of N. Zealand</hi>,” should have been the leading one—&amp; so throughout all the Essays.—By compressing the “Analysis” a <hi rend="italic">little</hi> (which it would well bear) he could have put it in 3 pps., and have begun his 4p. with the body of the work, which would have looked vastly neater. I have noticed a few ugly typographl. errors (which I enclose on a slip) and lots of deviations from proper (or my own) punctuation. I, perhaps, notice these things the more, from having had practically and critically to superintend the C. Mission Book press for many years. I fear my “Copy” (Ms.) was <hi rend="italic">too well written</hi>; hence it has been placed in the hands of an apprentice or inferior workman:—a common trick w. printers. Since you have determined to print the 2 Tables (Appendix), and as the little type in them cannot be immedy. wanted,—could you not forward corrected proofs of these to me, for final revise &amp; correction? as if not <hi rend="italic">wholly </hi>correct—especially the 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. one, they are useless.  4. I notice that, both<hi rend="italic">in </hi>Essay and <hi rend="italic">on</hi> one envelope, you add F.L.S. to my name. I would ask, is this correct, were I not sure you would not have done it if it were not so. Yet, perhaps, more <hi rend="italic">in posse</hi> than <hi rend="italic">in esse</hi>. If I do not mistake I shall ever remember this delicate &amp; fresh proof of your kind attention. <hi rend="italic">Hitherto</hi> I have never sought, nor greatly cared for any thing of the kind, but, <hi rend="italic">since I wrote the Essays</hi>, I have corresponded with Dr. Hooker about it, &amp; expect by next Mail to hear it is so. Had I listened to the overtures made to me 25 years ago, by French, German, &amp; Belgian men of science &amp; their patrons, I suppose I should by this have had a tail of nearly half the alphabet!  5. I also feel much indebted to you (and to Mr. Thompson) for the charming<hi rend="italic">lith. </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">phot.</hi> of the Bell. I think them excellently well done—especially the <hi rend="italic">lith.</hi> part. I shall not fail to write Mr. Thompson a warm letter of thanks for his exertions: Dr Hooker, I am sure, will be delighted beyond expectation. I feel a double amount of satisfaction, at such good lithography being done among us. I tried hard when in Auckland (twice) to find a <hi rend="underline italic">good</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">artist</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> lithographer</hi>, but failed; and I have often dwelt with delight (dashed with regret) on those few plates of Müeller’s Chatham Isld. plants executed in Melbourne. Surely we shall eventually have such a clear Inscriptn. deciphered!—Boyle wrote meditations on a Broomstick—Byron on a skull,—&amp; Burns on a Daisy, &amp;c, &amp;c,—what depths of thought are stirred, what reveries may not fairly be indulged—on that old Bell:—would that we could make it <hi rend="italic">speak</hi>!  6. Three days ago I recd. a Copy of your Offl. Catalogue from our Mr. Wilkinson, (I believe he had had them some time before, but had supposed I also had received a Copy.) Mr. Wilkinson told me, he had paid you for the<hi rend="italic">outlay</hi> on the Exhibn. Case, which I was glad to hear. I have not yet gone through <hi rend="sup">1</hi>/<hi rend="sub">6</hi>
            <hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of the Catalogue, still I feel greatly pleased at your having such an Exhibn., and <hi rend="italic">now</hi> feel considerably vexed with myself for not visiting it; (particularly since the principal matter for which I had absented myself—viz. the Anglo-Maori books for the Govt. is likely to be abandoned) I have heard it highly spoken of by many,—and, in particular your numerous &amp; valuable exhibits. I am delighted to find <hi rend="italic">you</hi> had so many good &amp; interesting Colonial subjects from almost the whole Circle of Natl. Science—and am particularly pleased with your <hi rend="italic">fine provincial </hi>Colln. of Ferns, and of Birds. (See Postscript).—Among the latter I am right glad to find my dear little owl (whëkåu), which I discovered in 1845, in the Tararua mountains, and have never before, nor since, heard of. I do not see, however, in the Ornithologl. List, the prized <hi rend="italic">Huia</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Neomorpha Gouldii</hi>), or the elegant <hi rend="italic">Fulica N.Z.</hi>, but I have not yet gone closely through all. If Buller’s nomenclature is correct (which, in some few cases at least, I venture to doubt) much of it is wholly new to me. However, the portion of the Cat. printed at Dunedin is full of typographical errors, especially in scientific spelling, which is anything but ornamental or pleasing: if it were to be printed I would willingly set about correcting it. It is so much the more conspicuous owing to the English printed portion being free. I notice, with regret, how conspicuously our J.A. White has placed himself (see, p.156,)—for, setting aside the fact that those sps. of flax (<hi rend="italic">Phormium</hi>) did duty before at the old European exhibitions, (J.A.S. then being a kind of <hi rend="italic">quasi </hi>Collector for Auckland Museum,) his “<hi rend="italic">Linum perenne</hi>, or perennial flax” (!!) is our common N.Z. <hi rend="italic">L. monogynum</hi>, which is well-known (comparatively) to be utterly useless as a fibre-producing plant, particularly as to <hi rend="italic">quantity</hi>: and his “Yellow Kowhaie, a substitute (??) for Quassia”, is the common <hi rend="italic">Edwardsia </hi>(or <hi rend="italic">Sophora</hi>)—concerning which “Substitute” J.A.S. has been regularly roasted! And his s-speaking of the “Error of the local Agent”, is far from gratifying.</p>
         <p>There are a few <hi rend="italic">small </hi>Ferns mentioned in <hi rend="italic">your </hi>lot, I should much like to have specimens of,—that is, if you have any to spare—<hi rend="italic">e.g. Cystopteris fragilis, Hymenophyllum unilaterale, minimum, </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">Lyallii, Trichomanes strictum, Colensoi, </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">Malingii, Aspidium cystostegia, Asplenium Trichomanes, </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">Richardi</hi>:—perhaps, by and bye, I may be able to return in a few <hi rend="italic">N. </hi>Island ferns.—From our local paper of this day I find your Exhibition closed last Saturday, 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.—I feel somewhat sad at this: (much as I have felt at beholding the melting away of the gorgeous Mexican Day Lily:) I cannot help thinking its sun has set too early. You kindly inform me, that you will see to the careful repacking of my exhibits, for which I shall be still more indebted to you—indeed, I fear more altogether than I shall ever be able to repay. You mention some as being desirable for a Col. Museum: but you do not say <hi rend="italic">what</hi>—or <hi rend="italic">where</hi> this C. Museum is to be. Had you not better let me know what you wish <hi rend="italic">before</hi> you pack them? Should any one wish to have the Flora <hi rend="underline italic">N</hi>.<hi rend="underline italic">Z</hi>. they can have it at Cost price, with what I paid at Auckland for binding; or, if preferred, in <hi rend="italic">parts</hi>, I have a colored copy at Cost price, (although I paid W. Lyon, Wellington, considerably more for some of them).</p>
         <p>Hoping you are well, and assuring you, that I am often thinking of you and your Temple of Science.</p>
         <p>I am, my dear Sir,</p>
         <p>Yours ever sincerely</p>
         <p>Wm. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. (May 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.) Since writing the foregoing I have been dipping deeper into the Off. Cat.—The more I do so, the more I regretfully know of <hi rend="italic">what I have lost</hi>! I note with fresh pleasure, your <hi rend="italic">numerous </hi>fossils, geologl. &amp; mineralogl. specimens, alpine plants, &amp; extensive herbarium, &amp;c., &amp;c. and shall still hope to see them somewhere as a “<hi rend="italic">Museum</hi>”. Ten years ago I endeavoured to stir up Dr. Featherstone <hi rend="italic">our </hi>then Superintendent; and, subsequently, the Genl. Govt. of that day, on this point,—but without avail.</p>
         <p>—In going closely over the lithog. of the Bell I find a <hi rend="italic">slight</hi> deviation from my words in Catalogue, which, I have little doubt, will cause many enquiries to be made. I had said— “I have, somewhere, written but I cannot tell where (<hi rend="italic">if existing now</hi>, after 28 years,)—and when at Auckland I wrote to some old chiefs, but, thanks to the troublous times, hitherto without answer. The words in lith. make it <hi rend="italic">more certain</hi>, &amp;c.— <hi rend="italic">Vale</hi>!  W.C.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
