<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0942">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1895 August 6: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1895-08-06">1895 August 6</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1895 August 6: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-754" place="foot" n="754"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Augt. 6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>/95</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Late last night I recd. your long, kind, chatty, &amp; intg. letter of 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. &amp; thank you for it. And having got rid (once more!) of Frisco Mail, and not greatly caring to go <hi rend="italic">to work </hi>at any thing fresh—I have concluded to write to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>—seeing I cannot have you here <hi rend="italic">in prop. person</hi>. One thing I wished to lay before you, is a <hi rend="italic">note </hi>recd. from Wgn. some time ago (from, I suppose, a <hi rend="italic">Jew</hi> dealer) <hi rend="italic">re </hi>vols. Trans. for sale to ask you, If you have time, and inclination (&amp; place not very far from your “beat”), to look-in, see the vols. (XII, XIII, XIV,) &amp; offer him ₤1. for them, if perfect &amp; clean: I don’t greatly care about them (I have already some spare ones purchased here) but if to be had for price named—all right. I wod. pay carriage hither.—–</p>
         <p>I shall also send you a rare lot of “odds &amp; ends”—mainly that you may see some typographical display home &amp; foreign, some being peculiar: and a dear little book of <hi rend="italic">your own </hi>(how happy shall I be—if you have <hi rend="italic">not </hi>a copy!) and a clipping from “Evg. News”, to which Hill called my attention a few days ago—&amp; so I bought one. Neither “H.” nor “D.T.” cared to say much or anything, this time, about our last Meeting, which makes <hi rend="italic">this</hi>, of “Evg.N.” so much the more worthy! I had worked <hi rend="italic">very hard </hi>for that <hi rend="italic">paper</hi>, also in looking-up my <hi rend="italic">old </hi>collection of Cornish Minerals (recd. somewhere in the ’30’s, from my Uncle, Bp. Natal’s father,)—packed by me in ’44, and only <hi rend="italic">now opened</hi>!! For some time I could not find the case, &amp; had opened <hi rend="italic">another </hi>such an one! but was <hi rend="italic">vastly pleased </hi>with what I <hi rend="italic">found</hi>: many specimens of plants, especially <hi rend="italic">Ferns</hi>, all in <hi rend="italic">good </hi>preservation, and among them (<hi rend="italic">recently fixed</hi>, and closely examd. &amp; descriptions drawn up) <hi rend="italic">3 new ones</hi>! several spns too: I was astonished; these must have been collected in ’43, ’44,—return jy. to the N., and from notes, pamphlets, &amp;c, &amp;c, in the lower Waikato, or between Manukau &amp; the Bay,—and then on my return to the Bp’s. College, having to prepare for Ordination, with other heavy work, set aside, and on my finally leaving for the Hawke’s Bay, put up any how—and forgotten!!! But, the strangest of all is, that <hi rend="italic">no one </hi>(as far as I know) has since found <hi rend="italic">one of them</hi>! and I have <hi rend="italic">no certain </hi>recollection of their habitats. These have given me <hi rend="italic">several days </hi>of close labour, (having more than 30 books of reference—Ferns of the world, new &amp; old—to look into—aye to <hi rend="italic">study</hi>, &amp; to bring them all into this warm parlour from the <hi rend="italic">cold back </hi>room, and poor thumb “in the way,”)—I confess, I should not like to have to do a similar job!—</p>
         <p>Our Society’s Meeting on 15<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst. postponed for a week, was not a success—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> few of the Dons present, <hi rend="italic">so </hi>no discussion, nor indeed any proper votes of thanks—to any of us! Hill commenced his <hi rend="italic">long paper</hi> too late, and made it <hi rend="italic">doubly long </hi>through <hi rend="italic">explaining</hi> (or repeating, over &amp; over from map, and diagrams which he ceaselessly drew on B. Board), <hi rend="italic">all hands</hi>—save himself! <hi rend="italic">tired</hi>.—I got back by xi.15! the next mg. I went thither, &amp; packed my jewels! Lund’s paper (a <hi rend="italic">good one</hi>, &amp; w. coins illustrating it) was <hi rend="italic">not fitted </hi>for <hi rend="italic">that audience</hi> I fear there are <hi rend="italic">some</hi>, who attend for the cup &amp; cake, as <hi rend="italic">some </hi>used to attend auctions for the “luncheon provided”—I am about to write a letter to our Secy., <hi rend="italic">re </hi>omission of 2 of my papers, seeing they contained some highly interesting reminiscences of the <hi rend="italic">old times</hi>, only known to myself, and Hill (warm on the subject) is going to fight the gods!—I shall seek to get them <hi rend="italic">back</hi>, and it <hi rend="italic">may </hi>be printed here: I cannot help thinking that, in this case, as in a <hi rend="italic">former </hi>one (at least), some persons in Wgn. may put by in reserve for a <hi rend="italic">future day</hi> those <hi rend="italic">early </hi>memorabilia—but after this treatment I don’t think I shall essay any more especially when I see Taylor White’s <hi rend="doubleunderline underline italic">3</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>(!!) wretched papers—on old old matters, published in vol. XXVII. However, “Comparisons are _______”.</p>
         <p>Of the Sundays (since my last) I have little to report: only, I was at Cathedl. on each; &amp; on <hi rend="italic">2 latter </hi>read Lessons there. Our Bp. was <hi rend="italic">again </hi>“Bar-bound” at Wairoa, 16 days this time. The Dean is going to Xt.Ch. for next Sy., special Invitation, and the Bp. is to be in charge here. I have been out but little since my last, weather however <hi rend="underline italic">fine</hi>: on Friday last I went to Hill’s, to spend aftn. (<hi rend="italic">long </hi>promised) and while there Eccles arrived from Woodville! &amp; took us all by surprise. E came to attend meeting of Select Ch. Committee, Hill also being one. It is astonishing the number of applications for <hi rend="underline italic">money</hi>! day after day—even from Australia, Wellgn., Palmerston, Auckland, and all the Country round! Have been obliged to tell them, “<hi rend="italic">I am come to the bottom of the bucket</hi>!” <hi rend="underline italic">all gone</hi>. <hi rend="italic">The whole of proceeds of Auction sale of T. Sns. </hi>(aided, <hi rend="italic">pro tem</hi>. by Bank), together with <hi rend="italic">£300 more</hi>, has been spent; and my income is <hi rend="italic">much less </hi>than it has been for many years, and may yet become less! I suppose I shall not be visiting Bush until <hi rend="italic">after </hi>Synod meets—mid. September, if indeed then! Of course you will have heard of the death of Mrs. Hugh Aplin, organist at yr. old Ch.—and since of the death of Judge Richmond! I agree w. <hi rend="italic">you </hi>in your high opinion of him; we were in <hi rend="italic">the House </hi>together 1861—and I often had great pleasure in hearing him there.—–</p>
         <p>I note your remark on Tregear &amp; his conduct &amp; words at your late Socy. Mtg., <hi rend="italic">you </hi>will know him <hi rend="italic">better </hi>by-and-by. Was not Buller there? By the way—I also found in that old case a rare lot of <hi rend="italic">fine Cordiceps Robertsii</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">good</hi> dry preservation: what a <hi rend="italic">wretched </hi>plate that is, given in vol. XXVII, from Buller’s specimens. I have not yet found time to look into your Polyn. Jl.! I unrolled it, &amp; put it (w. copy of Seddon’s ponderous one!) under heavy vols. here, to get it <hi rend="italic">flat</hi>, &amp; so have forgotten it—for <hi rend="italic">the time</hi>. “Anon, Sir, anon.” Have recd. several strange letters, to ansr. <hi rend="italic">peculiar </hi>questions! from all quarters—some I have endeavoured to reply to—but ? satisfactory. With Sir J. Hector, I, too, supposed Lyall to be dead long ago. A long (tedious) letter from Howlett; I fancy, he <hi rend="italic">may </hi>not relish my ansr. Somehow, I can scarcely think that <hi rend="italic">McD.</hi> writes <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the <hi rend="italic">Articles</hi> that daily appear in “D.T.”—always several columns of good solid research &amp; reading, and that too on fresh matters, exhibiting much of head labour with quotations in French &amp; Latin &amp; sometimes a word in <hi rend="italic">other</hi> tongues with often much of figures, &amp;c &amp;c. I don’t care for his <hi rend="italic">political </hi>ones, neither for his theological remarks though sometimes good—to the point. I am much pleased in knowing of your own good health and plenty of work in Pg. Off., and of family being well. I am keeping well, thumb easy, but still bandaged, &amp;c., &amp;c, of course, “<hi rend="italic">in the way</hi>”! I think I must have told you, of my son having had his diseased eye extracted by Dr. Nettleship: by last letter he was still in London being <hi rend="italic">fitted </hi>up w. a glass eye, which takes some time as to size, right colour, &amp;c., must take 2, price 4 guineas, &amp; <hi rend="italic">every 2 yrs</hi>, seek to maker, owing to shrinkage of orbit, &amp;c. Now Good bye! Kind regards to you, &amp; all yours,</p>
         <p>Yours ever,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
