<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0860">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1893 March 4: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1893-03-04">1893 March 4</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1893 March 4: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-633" place="foot" n="633"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier,<lb/>Saturday night,<lb/>4/III/93.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I have been (as usual) thinking much on you <hi rend="italic">this day</hi>, &amp; so I have determined to commence my letter to you: my last was on the 22<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. ulto.—&amp; sent with it a few scrap extras. Two or three things in “Herald” of this mg. served to increase my thoughts to you-ward, &amp; these I will mention first,—(1) In “Supplt.” a <hi rend="italic">long </hi>&amp; most atrociously lying story respg. Bp. Selwyn &amp; the Chief Tiakitai—in which <hi rend="italic">as far as they two are brought together</hi> there is not one atom of truth, and I think I <hi rend="italic">am bound</hi> to contradict it, being the <hi rend="italic">only</hi> European who can probably do so: I wod. give something to know the writer. 2. a kind of report of the H.B. P. &amp; Ag. Sy’s. mtg. (still further <hi rend="italic">erroneously </hi>given in D.T.) <hi rend="italic">re </hi>those circulars issued by Govt. respg. the Sparrow, as far as I can make out, <hi rend="italic">no notice </hi>is taken of mine (perhaps, pooh-poohed ’mong the rest?) but then D.T. says, “only 8 replied”!!! and “<hi rend="italic">none </hi>gave n. &amp; address”—I, however, did both.– – I <hi rend="italic">know</hi>, too well, that both McD. &amp; Wilkn. have <hi rend="italic">no love </hi>for me!—no doubt, this feelg. increased w. McD., as, a short time ago, in reply to his pressing letter, I refused to join, or to subscribe to, the Assn. of which <hi rend="italic">he </hi>is Secy. (3) In a par. in “H.” mention is made of a party going to ascend Ruahine range, &amp; to get to “Park’s Peak” (!!!) why P.P.? He was never there: the <hi rend="italic">first </hi>settlers called it “Colenso’s Pk.”, or “Mt.C.”—from the Maoris who had previously named it “Te Taumata-a-Neho”, and so it has been both written &amp; printed. I shall send you my copy of this day’s “Herald”.</p>
         <p>Last nt. I recd. from Gore, a copy of <hi rend="italic">Report </hi>of Wgn. Ph. Sy., which I am <hi rend="italic">glad </hi>to find is <hi rend="underline italic">printed by you</hi>. My copy howr. is much <hi rend="italic">too pale</hi>—some pp. scarcely legible (your <hi rend="italic">old </hi>fault here; Don’t be angry.) Your Socy. seems to read a large no. of papers. I notice you have T. Kirk, <hi rend="italic">rightly </hi>down—no “Profr.”, but some letters should have followed Tregear’s name, &amp; should you ever pub. another Report, see that (w. me) F.R.S. comes <hi rend="italic">first</hi>.</p>
         <p>Our Socy held their mtg. on Mony. nt. (27<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. ulto.) a ppd. one, on account of Hill, &amp; he <hi rend="italic">was not</hi> present! I did not go being sick of their contd. <hi rend="italic">breach of rules</hi>, but I wrote a note to Chn. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>hearty vote of thanks to G. White on resigning Hy. Sy. Dr. Moore is Pt., &amp; a <hi rend="italic">new </hi>hand in Cl. is <hi rend="underline italic">Miss</hi> Browning! a teacher at High School: <hi rend="italic">I don’t like this</hi>, &amp; so I told Stanislaus last Tuesday in town—<hi rend="italic">to me </hi>it is a horrid <hi rend="italic">innovation</hi>: of course <hi rend="italic">he </hi>battles for it, &amp; I believe <hi rend="italic">he </hi>has made <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the appointments! being wire-puller general: he told me one <hi rend="italic">again</hi>, in a nasty kind of way, (like him!) that they “would have been quite free from debt now, were it not for <hi rend="italic">that </hi>£10. <hi rend="italic">obliged</hi> to be given for Buller’s Books!” (of course a covert poke at <hi rend="italic">me</hi>!)</p>
         <p>A few days ago I recd. an <hi rend="italic">open </hi>envelope, bearg. Wgn. pt.mk., a closely printed 4pp. 8vo. pamphlet—“The Maori-Polyn. Comp. Dicty.—opinions of the press, celebrities &amp; experts,” contg. about 50 quotations,—I suppose <hi rend="italic">you have seen it</hi>; no imprim., &amp; I think ptd. in Engd.—(I will <hi rend="italic">lend </hi>you my copy, should you <hi rend="italic">not </hi>have seen it.) I shall send you the <hi rend="italic">envelope</hi>, as it is addressed to me by a fem., &amp; <hi rend="italic">you </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">may</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> know the hand</hi>: I have my <hi rend="italic">thoughts </hi>about it.</p>
         <p>I shall also send you a post-card lately to hand from London! from Dr. Cooke in <hi rend="italic">reply </hi>(!!) to a rather long letter I had sent him, (of <hi rend="italic">this </hi>I had made a copy &amp; I enclose it—return <hi rend="italic">at leisure</hi>,) I confess, I do not like such a mode of noticing (<hi rend="italic">not ansg.</hi>) letters.—I shall also enclose Beilley’s note, that came with the Sparrow Circular, that you may see it—&amp; burn it.—</p>
         <p>You will also see, in “Herald” an account of Rees’ meeting: his sp. &amp; W.C’s. ditto. R. sent me a special invitation but I did not go:—<hi rend="italic">partly</hi>, however, owing to my being <hi rend="italic">unwell</hi>. Having said <hi rend="italic">this</hi>, I may go on; we had heavy rain here <hi rend="italic">last wk</hi>; thermr. <hi rend="italic">went down</hi> 20°–25° in 48 hours, &amp; I <hi rend="italic">felt it</hi>: old Rheum. came back, <hi rend="italic">again</hi>, and I have lost many days, not being able to do much—nor anything well—and to add to it, the <hi rend="italic">Dean </hi>saw me on Thursday 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. to beg me to help! as <hi rend="italic">O. Dean</hi> had <hi rend="italic">gone</hi> off to Kuripapg. <hi rend="italic">sans </hi>leave or saying anything about it!—the Bp. was to be at Woodville &amp; Dvk. (Confirmations)—Well, I agreed to take Augustine’s in <hi rend="italic">the mg. </hi>and Meeanee at night—and I did so, retg. at ix.30:—but it was rather too much for me in my weak (physical) state: <hi rend="italic">i.e. </hi>the <hi rend="italic">walk </hi>to Augustines &amp; back in the hot sun, carrying my “swag”—and the climbing this hill! the Ch. S. (even <hi rend="italic">2 </hi>in the <hi rend="italic">one </hi>day) I can still manage—but <hi rend="italic">not</hi> the outside work: I have to go to Taradale tomorrow mg., &amp; this I hope to perform.—I wish to help Tuke, who has <hi rend="italic">4 </hi>Services tomorrow, &amp; all apart!—The Bp. is gone to Py. Bay. Knipe is about leaving for Engd. there to stay: Sherman is coming-back! Conroy is gone to Engd. Lyndon to Australia for 2 mths. and—it is gravely announced in “D.T.” that Rev W. Marshall is about to leave Australia for Holy Land”.!!!</p>
         <p>Yesty. Rev. E. Robertshawe paid me a visit, spent ½ day w. me—he is <hi rend="italic">now </hi>nearly quite well; he is staying at Hastings, exchg. with Rev. J. Hobbs for 3 Sundays: his wife is still ailing: Eccles, I hear from R., is quite well. My eldest son, must go out too soon, &amp; so has had 2 relapses (like myself!) &amp; now is <hi rend="italic">obliged </hi>to keep indoors &amp; that in their severe winter!—<hi rend="italic">He </hi>should have taken warning by <hi rend="italic">me</hi>.</p>
         <p rend="end">Monday 6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., iv. p.m.</p>
         <p>I have had a wretched time of it since I began this letter! &amp; even now am only half alive. Yesty. mg. I felt very well; day fine though chilly from S. wind: at ix.50 I descended to M. Road to meet trap, &amp; was there till x.20—<hi rend="italic">no </hi>trap came! so I had to climb the hill w. a sorrowful heart, and a fresh cold (&amp; great chill) I had taken.—I cannot describe my state of mind, &amp; of body: I had reasons for knowing there would be an extra large Congn. at T. awaiting me—it being too Queensland Colln. day: I became worse, went to bed at 1 p.m., &amp; was soon taken w. <hi rend="italic">severe </hi>diarrhea; this lasted till 7 this mg. a terrible time, words fail to describe, what I have endured. At viii this mg. I sent to Dr. H. fearing results, but <hi rend="italic">not </hi>to come up this terrible hill, to him, but stating case, I soon got med. from Welsman, &amp; am better: hope I may sleep tonight.—</p>
         <p>Tuke came in by Rymer to see me, all hands fearing the worst: Congn. was a large one &amp; kept seats till xi.15: unforty. <hi rend="italic">no wire </hi>to T. on Sundays: we find now, that Cunningham, my regular driver, to whom Robert had given the <hi rend="italic">usual notice </hi>on Friday mg., had aftds. heard I was <hi rend="italic">unwell</hi> &amp; so looked for <hi rend="italic">another</hi> notice!!! much sorrow expressed on all sides, but “’tis no use greeting over spd. milk”. I wrote my short note to “Herald”—I send you a copy of this day’s paper contg. it.<note xml:id="ftn3-634" place="foot" n="634"> Jackatye. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> 6 March 1893.</note> You will also see a <hi rend="italic">long </hi>narration re <hi rend="italic">Wm.M.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A <hi rend="italic">decent </hi>yg. m. named Peter Schwabe called on me this mg—perhaps <hi rend="italic">you</hi> knew him in “D.T.” office—he is w. Peacock, and is now his <hi rend="italic">overseer</hi>, &amp; having 6 wks. holiday revisits Napier. Had a long chat w. him. Good bye</p>
         <p>w. kind regards, Yrs truly, </p>
         <p>W. Colenso</p>
         <p>[I hope our letters may <hi rend="italic">not </hi>again cross in transit: if they do!! then I shall <hi rend="italic">wait</hi> ere I again write.]</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
