<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0928">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1895 March 6: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1895-03-06">1895 March 6</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1895 March 6: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-727" place="foot" n="727"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, March 6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. 1895.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I verily believe the whole mo. of Feby. has come &amp; gone! without a line from me! &amp; <hi rend="italic">worse </hi>still—my last, of Jany. 25 (kindly ansd. by you)—&amp; now the 6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. <hi rend="italic">March</hi>—makes the <hi rend="italic">hiatus </hi>still more awful. However, I have had <hi rend="italic">you </hi>very often <hi rend="italic">in mind</hi>:—and had I your last letter of 9<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. Feby. with me, inland at Dvk., I should have replied—I went thither on 22<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi> (a day later than I had fixed, Hamilton &amp; Dr. Hocking<note xml:id="ftn3-728" place="foot" n="728"> He meant Dr Hocken.</note> travelling so far w. me,) and I returned last night to Napier—&amp; shall have to go again to Dvk., <hi rend="italic">for 24</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>., inst., to enable Robertshawe to visit the Weber District.—–</p>
         <p>I suppose I told you, in my last, of Ch. work <hi rend="italic">then </hi>ahead! and so it turned out, for nearly 3 weeks I was the <hi rend="italic">only</hi> Ch. of Ed. Minister <hi rend="italic">here</hi>! Bp. Dean, &amp; Archd. S. at Genl. Synod, &amp; Welsh “bar-bound at Wairoa” so my hands were <hi rend="italic">full</hi>, but I was <hi rend="italic">enabled </hi>to perform <hi rend="italic">all</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Laus Deo</hi>.) My <hi rend="italic">last </hi>Sunday however (17<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> Feb.) nearly did for me—2 Services in Cathedral, to <hi rend="italic">large </hi>Congns., especially the Evg.S., the Fijians &amp; other visitors being present,—the heat excessive, &amp; Congn. most attentive, insomuch that I <hi rend="italic">over</hi>-exerted my physical strength, &amp; got back to Hermitage at ix p.m. with difficulty. I was right glad to get a holiday—though I had to take the Ch.S. at Dvk. (as agreed) on 24<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. Feby.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Here</hi>, this day, I found 3–4 Wgn. P. you had kindly sent: also, ditto (some) from <hi rend="italic">Buller</hi>, &amp; from Florance, Solr. Woodville. <hi rend="italic">One </hi>of Buller’s was sent to me at Dvk., very likely he had heard from Ham. of my being <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, as H. had told me he should <hi rend="italic">seek </hi>to see Buller. I have also recd. from B. (<hi rend="italic">here</hi>) a copy (“Author’s C.”) of his forthcoming papers in vol. XXVII—but have merely <hi rend="italic">peeped </hi>at them. It is <hi rend="italic">sad</hi> (to say the least of it) to find <hi rend="italic">those 2 </hi>“pillars” assailing each other!—and from what I can <hi rend="italic">at present</hi> see of their squabble—there are faults on <hi rend="italic">both </hi>sides. Another cause of regret (w. me), is, your not having a <hi rend="italic">better </hi>President for this year, particularly after <hi rend="italic">Schaw</hi>. While at Dvk. I recd. a proof (<hi rend="italic">one </hi>slip) of part of my Waikare-moana paper, for revision: in retg. it, I said, I would <hi rend="italic">greatly prefer </hi>having the <hi rend="italic">entire </hi>proofs of <hi rend="italic">one </hi>p. at a tiime, (<hi rend="italic">as before,</hi>) &amp; not piece-meal.—</p>
         <p>I suppose you will have fully heard of our <hi rend="italic">town </hi>fires: (1) Wilson, Dentists, <hi rend="italic">old </hi>house, wholly gone, &amp; remains removed. I thought much on Mr. J. Anderson, living so <hi rend="italic">near</hi>, but he was not greatly alarmed, his Housekeeper keeping good watch: (2) Rev. J.H. Paterson’s stable, &amp;c,—a narrow escape for Manse, &amp; other houses there, owing to <hi rend="italic">still </hi>night: (3) Higgins’ in Hastings-Street, extingd. <hi rend="italic">in time</hi>: (4.) Davidson’s <hi rend="italic">old </hi>house, Shakesp. Rd. terrace (last Sunday viii. p.m., folks <hi rend="underline italic">in</hi> Chs!!!) a total burn. While I was at Dvk.—2 distressing casualties: (1.) Ella Friberg, had, some time back, fallen on the ground severely, &amp; a packet of needles was under her bare arm, &amp; some entered it! [How, I cannot say.] The Dr. extracted 2: well last Thursday her arm much swollen the Dr. operated—1½ hours! without chloroform, she bore <hi rend="italic">it well</hi>: 4 portions of needles (2 heads &amp; 2 points), were taken out, still more remaining,—on Saturday <hi rend="italic">tetanus</hi>, Sunday prayed for in Ch., death supposed to be near; I wired to Makotuku, &amp; found on Monday she was a little better—tho “<hi rend="italic">not </hi>out of d.” The Dr. remd. there <hi rend="italic">all the time</hi>, and on Monday evg., an <hi rend="italic">old </hi>Settler, <hi rend="underline italic">much respected</hi>, Anton Berntsen, a German, lost his life, was severely bruised &amp; mangled by his horse, and died in 2 hours:—a grown up family.</p>
         <p>The School children now go out on Saturdays—taking turns—to the Bush or vice versa to the sea-side (Napier) Last Saty. Dvk., Makotuku, &amp; Ormondv., were invaded! several hundreds,—<hi rend="italic">I don’t approve of it</hi>: I greatly fear, in spite of the greatest care, accidents <hi rend="italic">must </hi>follow.—</p>
         <p>Since my last to you I recd. a long L. from John Poole formerly Sch. Master at Waipukurau, written after his return to his home nr. Blenheim: he had been spending a wk. at ’Pukurau (at Manse) &amp; was much pleased. Also, I have had to write <hi rend="italic">largely</hi> to Commissr. Taxes,—2–3 times. Do you recollect Singleton Rochfort? Last week I had a long letter from him in N.S.W.—very well: <hi rend="italic">good </hi>eyesight, &amp;c—employing his time in study—&amp; in translating some very old standard French works, and now going to take up “Rolls of Parliament of Edward I, A.D. 1278–1307”—but laments the Booksellers <hi rend="italic">won’t publish</hi>!!—–</p>
         <p>Mentioning “eyesight”:—my own is, at last! becoming defective for small print (minion downwards): and I cannot (yet) find specs. to suit: but Dr Hocking,<note xml:id="ftn3-729" place="foot" n="729"> He meant Dr Hocken.</note> who is an Oculist, kindly &amp; of his <hi rend="italic">own </hi>will exd. my eyes at some length &amp; says—I don’t need specs. at all! &amp; dissuades me from using them, <hi rend="italic">i.e. </hi>use only <hi rend="italic">smoke </hi>or grey glasses: my sight is certainly <hi rend="italic">good</hi>, ordinarily—but I <hi rend="italic">cannot use </hi>my pocket-Bible in pulpit as I used to do.—–</p>
         <p>I find, that our <hi rend="italic">new </hi>Bp. is gone to Wairoa, &amp; <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, next Sy. at Fraser-town, he will “consecrate Ch., &amp; ordain <hi rend="italic">2 Maori </hi>Deacons. Welch is now settled in St. Augustine’s: Bradbury at Tauranga for 3 months, that Jordan may have a holiday—<hi rend="italic">long looked for</hi>! our former Bp’s. family, here on the hill, inform me—they have (again) recently heard from <hi rend="italic">him</hi>, in Persia: both were <hi rend="italic">well</hi>, &amp; going to enter on their new house.</p>
         <p>Did you know Karl Mortensen?—<hi rend="italic">At last </hi>he (too) has got a portion of his <hi rend="italic">justly-deserved </hi>deserts—he should have been caught &amp; punished, years ago. The Chief J. spoke (in sentencing) very truly concerning him, &amp; his precious wife!—–</p>
         <p>I shall send you ½ doz. copies of my last Mao. tract against Ch. of Rome; &amp; could send a doz. more—if <hi rend="italic">required</hi>.—There is a <hi rend="italic">History </hi>concerning them (the reason <hi rend="italic">why </hi>left on hand), one day I may <hi rend="italic">tell </hi>you:—also, some other stray things.</p>
         <p>Thanks for <hi rend="italic">all </hi>you last sent me: Archdn Farrar’s. &amp; others: hope you are pretty busy—<hi rend="italic">not too much so</hi>!—<hi rend="italic">I have </hi>Max M’s. “Anthropological Religion”—(Alas! for an <hi rend="italic">old </hi>man’s memory!! I have the Work <hi rend="italic">here </hi>in this room; read by me at Dvk. 2 yrs. ago; and <hi rend="underline italic">noted</hi> some <hi rend="italic">strange </hi>statements in it <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Maoris!!). Thanks for kind informn. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Baillie Brors., Booksellers, shall follow-up anon. “<hi rend="italic">T.C. Williams</hi>” of advg. notoriety,—is a son of <hi rend="italic">H.</hi>W. of Paihia, ygr. bror. of Archdn. <hi rend="italic">Sam</hi>. Be sure you give my <hi rend="italic">best </hi>thanks to yr. Father when you write, for <hi rend="italic">his opinion </hi>on my Letters v. Romanism: I <hi rend="italic">value it</hi>. Poole, <hi rend="italic">ditto</hi>: Jordan <hi rend="italic">do</hi>: Welch <hi rend="italic">do.</hi> but (as <hi rend="italic">you </hi>pretty well <hi rend="italic">know</hi>) most of <hi rend="italic">our </hi>ygr. Ministers are “High” Ch.—ergo, I obtained from “Herald” office all copies remg. of “<hi rend="italic">Courier</hi>” contg. them, but lacking my <hi rend="italic">first </hi>letter, wh. are <hi rend="italic">better</hi> printed, &amp;, in some places <hi rend="italic">corrected</hi>. Bk. N.Z. matter, a sad, and heavy one for <hi rend="italic">me—</hi>yet <hi rend="underline italic">worse</hi> for <hi rend="italic">many others</hi>; and yet those arch-marauders allowed to escape!!</p>
         <p>And now, my dear friend, I am come to the <hi rend="italic">grand </hi>point in your <hi rend="italic">last </hi>viz. your naming your dear son <hi rend="italic">W.C.</hi>—another proof of your stable friendship—which I have ever esteemed.—(This makes 7 (<hi rend="italic">known</hi>) to me, in N.Z. &amp; in Victoria.<note xml:id="ftn3-730" place="foot" n="730"> William Colenso Harding. William Colenso Drummond, son of John Drummond, blacksmith at Ongaonga. Walter Colenso Winkelmann, son of Charles Winkelmann, Te Aute teacher and later Northland teacher and vaccinator. Walter Colenso Johansen, Norsewood. Bernard Colenso Blacklock, Mt Roskill. William Colenso Reader, son of Felix Reader, chemist of Melbourne. John Colenso Heath Simcox, Colenso’s grandson.</note>) May your son grow up &amp; be a <hi rend="italic">better</hi>, &amp; more <hi rend="italic">useful </hi>man than his old namesake: more <hi rend="italic">anon.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I hope Victor is doing well: &amp; <hi rend="italic">all </hi>yr. family. And w. kindest regards and <hi rend="italic">best wishes</hi>, Believe me, Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>                                                                                   W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. The Roll for <hi rend="italic">Victor</hi>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
