<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0899">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1894 May 30: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1894-05-30">1894 May 30</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1894 May 30: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-685" place="foot" n="685"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke 30<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. May, 1894.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding,—</p>
         <p>Your kind friendly &amp; truly welcome letter of 27<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst. reached me <hi rend="italic">here </hi>yesty. and as (at <hi rend="italic">present</hi>) I can do nothing, &amp; have you much in mind, I have concluded to scribble to you—<hi rend="italic">to pass away time</hi>! [I have many letters to write—to ansr., even letters, also, <hi rend="italic">unopened</hi>! from Engd. last wk—which I cannot take up, <hi rend="italic">now</hi>.]</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">First</hi>, however, of myself: in my last to you of 20<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">replied </hi>to) I said, how <hi rend="underline italic">very well</hi> in health I <hi rend="italic">then </hi>was!—well on 22<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. I returned to this place from Wdv. purposing to proceed to N. on 26<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. On 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>., 24<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., &amp; 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., (weather <hi rend="italic">fine</hi>) I spent 2–3 hours <hi rend="italic">ea. day</hi> in the woods—enjoying myself! only on this <hi rend="italic">last </hi>(Friday) aftn., I had gone thither without my <hi rend="italic">usual </hi>cloak, &amp; wearing only my <hi rend="italic">very thin </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">old</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> bush </hi>coat, &amp; so found it <hi rend="italic">cold </hi>in the wood—much rain, too, having fallen during the past night, &amp; so making it wet there: that night I was hot dry, feverish, (with 2 cases <hi rend="italic">here </hi>of typhoid fever—one, <hi rend="italic">in </hi>this hotel, &amp; one over the way, <hi rend="italic">within speaking distance</hi>, &amp; both brought hither from Napier!) Saty. mg. I determined <hi rend="italic">not </hi>to proceed to N. &amp; that night was a terrible one to me! of colic &amp; diarrhoea! &amp; all <hi rend="italic">in darkness</hi>, too! how I longed for mg.—for some one to speak to. Mg. came—at last! could not get up to bkfst., Dr. soon came—med., &amp; all that day only a cup of (poor) tea! The weather too had changed on Saty. aftn. now pouring rain, &amp; cold withal: well, that Sunday was a sad one: (even the wretched “Harmy” cod. not perform:) Monday—still unwell, in bed, &amp; very <hi rend="italic">weak</hi>, but that nt. I got a little sleep. Tuesday mg., by daylight, informed, that out of <hi rend="italic">us </hi>“4”—2 had been taken, &amp; 2 left!! (Here I may mention, the man who died <hi rend="italic">in </hi>this hotel, was the owner of the “Strasburg Clock” show; &amp; the man who died across the street—French, the master of Robjohns’ Store, whose <hi rend="italic">sister</hi> Charl. R. married—<hi rend="italic">both</hi>, it was known, had brought t.f. w. them from N.—Indeed, F. had most imprudently slept in <hi rend="italic">same bed </hi>w. his brother from Xt.Ch. whom he had gone thither to meet, who was then under the influence of t.f., &amp; is <hi rend="italic">now </hi>laid up w. it!) Well, the body from this hotel was buried yesty. (rain still pouring!) &amp; the body of F. taken by early train this mg. to N. for interment: Cy. Robjohns having come hither yesty. for that purpose. Yesty. was rather a sad day w. me—not well able either to write or to read! still <hi rend="italic">very weak </hi>(shall I say to you<lb/>—<hi rend="italic">both </hi>body &amp; mind?) I wanted something <hi rend="italic">nourishing</hi>: Dr. presd., Brandy in <hi rend="italic">milk</hi> this <hi rend="italic">latter </hi>I dislike raw—however I used it—wishing for my <hi rend="italic">old sustaining </hi>regimen— “Guiness Extra stout”, which Dr. disappd. of, fearing return of diarrhoea, [at my house in N., in <hi rend="italic">this respect</hi>, I could have fared better:] finding myself so <hi rend="italic">low </hi>&amp; cold, yesty. evg., I (having abjured By. &amp; Mk.) got a bottle of port wine, &amp; 2 glasses, w. hot water &amp; nutmeg &amp; sugar, I took last nt. at x. &amp; to bed, &amp; feel better to day—able to sit up &amp; write this:—dark gloomy &amp; cold weather still continuing—w. showers at intervals: outside, plenty of rain, so, I hear, at Wdv., w. “slips”, again! in that wretched piece of engineering—the Gorge! &amp; also, w. you at Wgn. As far as <hi rend="italic">I can see</hi>, at <hi rend="underline italic">present</hi>, I purpose leaving on Saturday next (2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. proxo.) for Napier: <hi rend="italic">shall I do so</hi>? I “<hi rend="italic">Halt</hi>”!</p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">March</hi>!] Now I turn to yr. letter—to wh. howr., I <hi rend="italic">cannot </hi>(at present) do justice: but I thank you heartily for it, as it served to <hi rend="italic">cheer </hi>yesty., while it drove sleep far from me last nt., thinking over the <hi rend="italic">strange </hi>views my friend held, re “Salvn. (?) Army”. Here you &amp; I, are at the very <hi rend="italic">antipodes</hi>! I consr. it as the greatest delusion of the “Devil”, that has ever yet appd. <hi rend="italic">v. </hi>Xn. Ch.—even <hi rend="italic">worse </hi>than Rome! It was only 2–3 days ago, in talking w. Robertshawe <hi rend="italic">re </hi>same—I sd. “It is a mysty. to me—how <hi rend="italic">any </hi>Xn.-Ch.-minister (who ought to know the N.T. (at least), and to be in some degree acqd. w. Eccl. Histy., anct. &amp; modn.) can allow this wretched outcome—this travestie (that I say not, “blasphemy”) of Xy. to be from <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>, &amp; therefore good &amp; true!” Just because, all such (1) <hi rend="italic">has been</hi>: (2) most clearly predicted by Jesus himself, &amp; this not merely <hi rend="italic">once</hi>, but usually, from beg. to end of his solemn teachings &amp; warnings, [Take a <hi rend="italic">few</hi>: Matt. VII.13–23, (and, w. 22, 23, take &amp; comp. XXV. 37–39; who had <hi rend="italic">never heard </hi>the n. of Jesus! Matt. XXIV. 4, 5, 11, 23–25, w. parall. p. in other Gosps. Rom. XVI. 17, 18. 1 Cor XIV. throughout. 1 Tim. I. 9–12, V. 13, 14. 2 Tim. III. 1–7. (<hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi> v.6) Titus II. 1–6.] <lb/>(3.) &amp;<hi rend="italic">so </hi>taken up by Paul (&amp; others): I have preached agt. them, &amp; written agt. them, &amp; spoken to their puffed-up “Captains” agt. them, with all my powers, &amp; hope to do so to the end. Your remarks on this being <hi rend="italic">better </hi>than other mod. “fads” (named), are little to the purpose, as, unlike them, these are <hi rend="italic">not decent</hi>, (showing <hi rend="italic">no </hi>“fruits of the spt.”<lb/>—Gal. V. 22, 23, &amp; parall. pass.) but repulsive, disagreeable, disturbing: let them (if they will) meet us those others—Adventists, Theosophists, P. Brethren, Christadelphians, Mormons, &amp;c., aye, as<hi rend="italic">Baptists</hi>,—a <hi rend="italic">little older</hi>—or even, as the “Worshippers of Satan” in <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>,—but let them do, as they <hi rend="italic">all</hi> do—<hi rend="italic">not offend </hi>(wilfully too!) others—peace abiding folk: let them meet in their houses, or “barracks”, or what not: you, my friend, or yr. children, may live to see the <hi rend="italic">grave error </hi>of conceding to these misguided semi-hysterical fanatics, the priv. of Sunday <hi rend="italic">public </hi>processions and performances in our <hi rend="italic">town streets</hi>, this continued—the day will come for the Rom. Cath. to do the same (as <hi rend="italic">now </hi>in sp., port., &amp;c) w. their idolatrous &amp; blasphemous “Host”: others, too, will follow; &amp; jostling, &amp; mockery &amp; fights, (<hi rend="italic">fierce </hi>ones) will ensue—just as have been, &amp; will be, in Madras, Bombay, &amp;c. Again: you seem to have been influenced in your views—by the <hi rend="italic">wonderful progress </hi>the Army has made (compared, of course, with other <hi rend="italic">modern</hi> fads,) but you omit (?) <hi rend="italic">their peculiar facilities</hi>—(1) <hi rend="italic">money </hi>from <hi rend="underline italic">others</hi>: (2) <hi rend="italic">steam </hi>comm., by Ld. &amp; by W. (3) their <hi rend="underline italic">low</hi>, <hi rend="italic">lying</hi>, talk (<hi rend="italic">suitable to the mob</hi>) &amp; to the better-informed, &amp; wealthy, <hi rend="italic">where the </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">nidus</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> exists</hi>—½ insanity or ½-hysterical, or ½-year of hell! or ½ desire-of-compounding for past sins, &amp;c, &amp;c., (this <hi rend="italic">last</hi>-mentd., <hi rend="italic">always existing</hi>, and of such service to Rome, &amp; <hi rend="italic">ruinous </hi>to Engld. until stopped by Hy.VIII’s law of “<hi rend="italic">Mortmain</hi>”) but, &amp; <hi rend="italic">again </hi>for the <hi rend="underline italic">Army</hi>! in part repealed in these mod. times: <hi rend="italic">e.g. </hi>an old Eng. lady <hi rend="italic">the other day</hi>, gave in her will on her d. bed ₤20,000 to that arch-imposter Booth! (4.) the new (and <hi rend="italic">erroneous</hi>) position of women! (<hi rend="underline italic">agt.</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">universal use</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">s.s</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi>) to rule the roost!!! (5.) Also: the enormous profusion of <hi rend="italic">false</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="italic">fanatical </hi>Hymns, of the last ½ centy. M. &amp; Sanky. Anct. &amp; mod. Ch. praise Methodist, &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c—and, (6) the <hi rend="italic">increased rage </hi>for play, &amp; for <hi rend="underline italic">Music</hi>! To this big array I cod. add <hi rend="italic">more</hi>—but you can supply them: <hi rend="underline italic">all unknown formerly</hi>. Would this “Army” (think you?) come out, go forth, as those of old did? as <hi rend="italic">all true </hi>missionaries have ever done, of <hi rend="italic">all </hi>churches (and here I, certainly, include myself &amp; a <hi rend="underline italic">few</hi> others I have <hi rend="italic">personally known</hi>:) <hi rend="italic">not </hi>for pay, nor “blare”, nor ease, nor to worry other &amp; older Xns.,—but to go where the name of Xt. was <hi rend="italic">not </hi>known! Methinks the words of Govr. Hobson to the Rom. C. Bp. Pompallier, in 1840, are quite applicable here—to this army— “How is it I always find yr. Ch. in these seas <hi rend="italic">only follg. </hi>where our Eng. Miss. have established Xy.?” and this brings me to another strange sentence or two of yours: viz. “We must at least place the movement on a level with Islamism. – – – The “Army” is on a vastly <hi rend="italic">higher</hi> plane than Islam”. I <hi rend="italic">deny </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">both</hi>: (1) perhaps you are not aware of the wretched debased religious state of Arabia when Mahomet arose? &amp; what he was <hi rend="italic">enabled </hi>to accomplish? (to <hi rend="italic">me </hi>most wonderful: equal to, if not comparing, Paul’s with the Grecian, &amp; Roman (barbarous) colonial countries. (2.) In the Koran (<hi rend="italic">their S.S.</hi>) are glorious holy <hi rend="italic">truths</hi>—in accordance, too, w. <hi rend="italic">reason</hi>. (3.) In the Mahometan <hi rend="italic">cities</hi>, far better, higher morality, exists (commonly) than in our belauded Xn. ones! Religion—there (&amp; <hi rend="italic">suitable for them</hi>) is more practical: true, they have <hi rend="italic">their </hi>fanatical sects (as the “army”) but not for opposition, show, &amp; gain.—But I must conclude <hi rend="italic">this subject</hi>: but before I do so, I would just add 2 remarks, (to anticipate objections, or questions,) “Why, then, the Army?” <hi rend="italic">Ansr. </hi>To chastise the idolatrous &amp; slumbering &amp; “unco guid” Xn. Chs. (so-called)—to prepare anew for <hi rend="italic">the time </hi>(<hi rend="italic">sure to come</hi>—<hi rend="underline italic">Blessed be </hi>
            <hi rend="underline smallcaps italic">God</hi>!) of <hi rend="italic">Reformation</hi>:—when <hi rend="italic">all</hi>—the Chs. of Greece &amp; of Rome, of Engd. &amp; of Scotland, of Luther &amp; of Calvin, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">all</hi> their branchlets—shall agree (severally, or at once) to cast aside for ever their <hi rend="italic">false creeds</hi>, doctrines, <hi rend="underline italic">catechisms</hi>, hymns, &amp;c &amp;c—and be content to teach, without adulteration or adding, <hi rend="smallcaps italic">truth</hi>—the word of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>—whether spoken in the O.T. or by J., or by his apostles, &amp;c., in the N.T., or by Confucius, or Buddha, or Mahomet, or any other—in any time, manner, or place: Truth, <hi rend="italic">first</hi> &amp; alone, <hi rend="italic">wherever </hi>found, (as Gold,)—<hi rend="underline italic">then</hi> by authority: <hi rend="italic">not as now</hi>—authority (or authoriti<hi rend="underline">es</hi>!!) <hi rend="italic">first</hi>!!! As I said, in a letter written hence to a Presbytn. Mr. since I came— “Adhere to Xt’s. teachings, and to those of his Apostles: beware of Man’s (of Church’s) additions &amp; comments: it is Churchianity the world is sick of, <hi rend="italic">not </hi>Xy.” But, my friend Harding, before all this can come to pass—the Bible itself must be <hi rend="italic">better understood</hi>—by <hi rend="underline italic">Ministers</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">generally</hi>: it must no longer be palmed off, as <hi rend="italic">the Wd. of </hi>
            <hi rend="smallcaps italic">God</hi>—but, as <hi rend="italic">containing</hi>, w. other books, the Wd. of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>: the gold must be (and <hi rend="underline italic">will be</hi>) extracted from the ore, &amp; stand purified: and towards this true Bibl. Exegesis &amp; Criticism together w. Science are gradually &amp; silently preparing the way—in spite of <hi rend="italic">all </hi>opposition.—</p>
         <p>I thank you for yr. remark—<hi rend="italic">re </hi>had <hi rend="italic">you </hi>been living in Judea, A.D. 30, etc,—I was not before aware that Carlyle had <hi rend="italic">so </hi>spoken: but I have often (or on several occasions) in preaching, espy. about Easter week, told my Congns.—that had they &amp; I been there—<hi rend="italic">we too </hi>should have cried out, “Crucify him: Serve him right”: (perhaps to the horrifying of some present.) I could say more, on <hi rend="italic">this head</hi>, but must stop.</p>
         <p>Before howr. that I quit yr. letter, I must say a wd. more, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>another subject therein: (although in my so doing, or <hi rend="italic">plain </hi>speaking, I may offend you, which I would not willingly do: I mean, your coming out for “<hi rend="italic">the Prim. M</hi>.”—I cannot say I like this. It reminds me of <hi rend="italic">old times</hi> in N., of Gd. Templars, of Rechabites, &amp;c—&amp; which I had hoped had become lost (as it were) in the <hi rend="italic">better &amp; higher </hi>forms of Scotch Presbyterianism.—to me, it smacks of a <hi rend="italic">decensus</hi>: or, of something else, I don’t know how to name—briefly &amp; <hi rend="italic">truly</hi>:—copy. when <hi rend="italic">considd. together w. </hi>your heavy &amp; constant professl. &amp; family duties,—<hi rend="italic">these are your </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">primary</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> ones before </hi>
            <hi rend="smallcaps italic">God</hi>, &amp; that not merely for the present, but the <hi rend="italic">future. Your family </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">need you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">—the P.M. </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">can do without</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> you</hi>. </p>
         <p>Thanks for your explicit inform. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the Williams’—there is <hi rend="italic">much</hi>, <hi rend="italic">very much, here </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">remaining</hi>, for <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi> to know.</p>
         <p>You may have seen some notice in the papers, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>meeting of our H.B. Inst., on 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>.,—<hi rend="italic">said</hi>, to have been well-attended: Dr. Innes on squinting, &amp;c—Owen w. Bk. Board diagrams (!!) &amp; Coffee, &amp;c., <hi rend="italic">ad lib</hi>.; &amp; all well-pleased. Humphries, “President” (!!!) w. an apology—for not having prepd. an “address” (sunbeams from Cucumbers!) Hill, is coming out <hi rend="underline italic">strong</hi>—under their <hi rend="italic">new </hi>head, the <hi rend="underline italic">Bapt</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>Mr. Cox, on that <hi rend="italic">same</hi> night in their room! (I have written a p., <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, on my “early &amp; adventurous crossing<hi rend="underline">s</hi> of Waikare-moana (A.D. 1841–3) &amp; travels in Urewera Cy.—then <hi rend="italic">unknown </hi>to Europeans”;—but whether <hi rend="italic">I shall </hi>ever read it, at N., is highly doubtful: I suppose, it would be pleasing—interesting—written in popular language, even <hi rend="italic">sans </hi>coffee &amp; Cakes!)</p>
         <p>Among the many local letters recd. of late are 3, that were you here you should see—<hi rend="italic">one</hi>, at least, I will send, w. my brief reply:—this is from Taylor White! the “cheek”, or the “egotism” of that man: one is from another (nearly as bad, but an educd. person) Howlett—which, has surprised me not a little: perhaps I told you, how, 4–5 wks. ago, he had sent me sundry <hi rend="italic">small </hi>spns. of alpine plants to be named (pretending to a <hi rend="italic">sup. kn. </hi>of Boty. &amp;c)—those were left at N., but I got them, &amp; <hi rend="italic">worked hard </hi>at them: all mere bits; no flrs., &amp; succeeded in naming them all—adding, 2 might be <hi rend="italic">new</hi>, &amp; if he wod. send me a spn. or two (or even a leaf or two) more, I should be certain, &amp; if new, would describe, w. some of Hill’s (from E. Cape), &amp; mine, from Dvk.—Recd. a <hi rend="italic">long</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">ramble</hi>, in reply, of what he is going to do next season,—<hi rend="underline italic">barely</hi> thankg. me for my note— “being unwell &amp; <hi rend="italic">in bed</hi> (?) could not write”—without replying to requests in my <hi rend="underline italic">letter</hi>, &amp; closing w., “Dont <hi rend="italic">reply to this</hi>.”—H. may rest assured—it will be long, ere he hears from me again: the 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. is from a Mr. Buchanan (“c/o Murray R. &amp; Co.”) <hi rend="italic">re </hi>“Introduction of Brit. flies, as <hi rend="italic">baits </hi>for trout.”!!! I think I must send you the copy of my reply (as I took one).</p>
         <p>I suppose this is the longest letter you have ever had from me? is it to be the <hi rend="italic">last</hi>? (I hope not.) I have left much unsaid (on <hi rend="italic">other matters</hi>) I should like to say.—In <hi rend="italic">one </hi>respect (at least) I am better off here than at N., I <hi rend="italic">see</hi> people passing, and I have a <hi rend="underline italic">few</hi> callers, &amp; my sitting-room &amp; bed-room <hi rend="italic">adjoin </hi>on the <hi rend="italic">ground </hi>floor—no going up &amp; down stairs. I have been shown a no. of “Wairoa Guardian” of May, contg. a <hi rend="underline italic">good</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> art. </hi>on the late Synod—I wish I could buy a copy for you: I am thinking of writing the Manager for a few copies, if I do, &amp; get them, I will send you one. In a late “Standard”, there is an excellent Paper from the Brit. Ambassador at Wellington, <hi rend="italic">official</hi>, to Brit. Govt., on “<hi rend="italic">Prohibition</hi>”, carefully compiled from offl. sources—supplied by the U. States: which, if <hi rend="italic">duly consid.</hi>, should stop the blatant braying of Isilt. &amp; Co.—But, (and may I not <hi rend="italic">ask you</hi>?) they <hi rend="italic">will </hi>not, (possibly, <hi rend="italic">now cannot</hi>,) listen <hi rend="italic">to reason</hi>: like all other faddists, their <hi rend="italic">own </hi>ignorant or intentionally-lying “Doctors” are believed! &amp; their nostrums swallowed. But see the Paper (&amp; <hi rend="italic">note </hi>the Edl. art. thereon) and judge for yourself;—and, stick to <hi rend="doubleunderline underline italic">the Truth</hi>! like a good soldier of J. Xt., leaving results to <hi rend="smallcaps italic">God</hi>. </p>
         <p>Did I tell you of my letter to Cheeseman, secretary &amp;c. to the Auckld. branch N.Z.I.? I wished (<hi rend="italic">again</hi>) to say a word, before too late, in favour of Suter, the Swiss scientist (vid. his papers &amp; dwgs. in <hi rend="italic">Malcology</hi>, in “Trans.”) who has long been nearly starving, w. his large family, so I wrote to Chn., <hi rend="italic">re </hi>above; also, “Index Kewensis” contg. a <hi rend="italic">few </hi>of his plants; &amp; also of Hill’s finding “<hi rend="italic">Dactylanthus Taylori</hi>,” at E. Cape, &amp; that I could send him a spn. if required; &amp; also, sent him a copy of our N. H.B. Inst. “Report”,—but have had <hi rend="italic">no reply</hi>! <hi rend="italic">I don’t understand this. </hi>From your friend Tregear, I have lately recd. a copy of “No. 15, Jl. Depart. of Labour”,—the whole of p.1, being an <hi rend="italic">apt </hi>quotation from one of my <hi rend="italic">old </hi>papers! If you have not yet seen it, <hi rend="italic">Look it up</hi>. It was kind of T.,—<hi rend="italic">will you </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">thank him</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> for me</hi>?</p>
         <p>I think I gave you a copy of our (wretched!) H.B. Ph. I. “<hi rend="italic">Report</hi>”:—but I did not tell you, that, among the acquired Books, the one in Italian (<hi rend="italic">i.e. </hi>title), was my gift, being the one sent to <hi rend="italic">me</hi> as a member of the Columbus Anny. at Genoa—it is a portly 8vo., valuable for its many engravings, as well as its Papers—only one, however, in English: several in French, &amp;c; Cheeseman, very properly, sets his “<hi rend="italic">Donations</hi>” down <hi rend="italic">as such</hi>, with ns. of Donors: possibly (?) some one, here after, <hi rend="italic">may </hi>look into my gift. Thanks for meaning of “<hi rend="italic">Encinal</hi>” (Sp.) I have <hi rend="italic">not </hi>a Sp. Dicty. May Dr. Caro’s &amp; his wife’s <hi rend="italic">loss</hi>—lead them to think of <hi rend="italic">their </hi>grievous errors in joining the <hi rend="italic">Adventists</hi>! “Dy.T.” <hi rend="italic">this evg.</hi> says— “Notice to our Readers—D.T. is today printed on a new two-feeder <hi rend="italic">Wharfdale </hi>machine—just imported from J. Kelly &amp; Co., Otley, Yorkshire, thro’ Mr. G. Mitchell, Xt.Ch.—one of the most recent improvements, for rapid ptg., &amp; prodn. of <hi rend="italic">best wk</hi>.” (Unhappily, <hi rend="italic">not </hi>shown in specimen to hand! <hi rend="italic">W.C</hi>.)</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">31</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">st</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>Noon cold, gloomy weather still continues: a <hi rend="italic">wire </hi>just to hand, from Waipawa, “<hi rend="italic">can have </hi>2 rooms <hi rend="italic">there Sunday</hi>, if reqd.”, so I hope to start <hi rend="italic">on Saty</hi>. Do not think of ansg., or <hi rend="italic">noticing</hi>, this “labour of love” in a hurry—if <hi rend="italic">at all</hi>. In “Wdv. Examr.”, 30<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., a <hi rend="italic">letter</hi>, onslaught on Hill, Inspr. (lately here &amp; <hi rend="italic">there</hi>) for <hi rend="underline italic">faulty</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> pron. </hi>to <hi rend="italic">Teachers</hi> &amp; to <hi rend="italic">scholars</hi>! <hi rend="italic">See </hi>it, if you can. I am still improving, but <hi rend="italic">weak</hi>. Was gladdened to know V. was improving. I suppose, vols. “Trans.” nearly ready. Lots of begging Circulars to hand—<hi rend="italic">Chs</hi>., town &amp; Cy., <hi rend="italic">Ep. &amp; Presbytn.</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sy. Schools, Com. ditto: Fire Brigade, Volunteers, Hort. Socy., </hi>&amp;c. &amp;c.—sad to <hi rend="italic">see </hi>so many out of employ! &amp; winter on <hi rend="italic">them</hi>!—</p>
         <p>   And now, my dear friend, goodbye. May the blessing of God, our Hy. F., be ever w. you &amp; yours.—</p>
         <p>                   Yours truly &amp; affy.,—W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>6/VI/94 noon: <hi rend="italic">Dvk. Still here</hi>!—</p>
         <p>Tom. Baddeley died on Monday evg.—I had remained to see <hi rend="italic">end</hi>: to be buried this aftn. and I was to bury (in <hi rend="italic">part</hi>)—but <hi rend="italic">again </hi>taken ill last nt., severely too &amp; as before so <hi rend="italic">cannot </hi>go out to stand in the wet &amp; cold.</p>
         <p>Hope to return to N. this wk. Am very weak, Just <hi rend="italic">now</hi>—This Paper only returned to me this mg.—W.C.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
