<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0844">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 September 11: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-09-11">1892 September 11</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 September 11: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-611" place="foot" n="611"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Sunday night,<lb/>Septr. 11<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. 1892</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I have been thinking on <hi rend="italic">you</hi> very much this day, &amp; so it has culminated in a determination to write to you this evening—although I shall not conclude same until <hi rend="italic">after </hi>my return from Sy’s. meeting tomorrow nt. and this said Meeting, &amp; my preparing for the same, w. wish that <hi rend="italic">you </hi>would be there, have had much to do w. my writing now. This day is my first <hi rend="italic">idle </hi>Sunday for many months! I have kept <hi rend="italic">quietly </hi>at home, though weather fair yet cold. As, I suppose, I said to you in my last,—I left Dvk. on Saturday 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi> for Waipawa, halting there to take duty for Eccles (gone to Woodville), &amp; arrived here on Monday night:—3 Letters had just come in, &amp; one was yours of 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., as <hi rend="italic">usual </hi>a capital letter, &amp; one in which I again go thoroughly w. you. It was not so long as often w. you, &amp; so, I suppose, you did not notice (overlooked) some parts of my last. I do hope you will come out (even if only v. Maskell—you will have, at least, Tregear w. you,) in your projected Maori literature paper: you will find somewhat to aid you in my p. on their <hi rend="italic">Poetry </hi>&amp;c., in vol. XIII, (so shamefully overlooked by Buller a few years ago when he said, there w. you! “<hi rend="italic">noone </hi>had written on that subject”!)—also, in my Papers on their <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Colour-sense</hi>, &amp;c, in vol. XII—but let me tell you, If you read this <hi rend="italic">latter</hi>, look for its <hi rend="italic">supplement </hi>further on towards the end, disjointed from it <hi rend="italic">purposely </hi>by the Editor: I suppose you can borrow those 2 vols. if you have not got them.</p>
         <p>I arrived here pretty well on Monday night, 5<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., next day remained at Home, writing for S.F. Mail: but, oh! the misery of Rheum. in rt. shoulder joint &amp; down arm, so that I <hi rend="italic">could not </hi>put forth my arm horizontally to take a dip of ink! obliged to pass pen to the surly clownish left hand for each dip! (temper <hi rend="italic">not </hi>improved thereby!!)—and it is still painful, <hi rend="italic">much worse in bed</hi>: I write this in pain. Well: I went to town on Wednesday, &amp; again on Friday on business. Craig seeming very well, w. a new addition to his shop, running out behind his Desk windows, &amp; already well-stored w. Children’s Books—a large, dry commodious room.—Saw Messrs. Paterson &amp; Sidey, both well. Mrs Lang has given up her Bakery, &amp;c—taken by a person named Phillips from Auckland (an old hand at that trade); Mrs.L. going to open a Boarding-house in late resid. of M.R. Miller, on hill.—Ellison is <hi rend="italic">out </hi>of “Waip. Mail,” &amp; Whittington of “Herald” off. <hi rend="italic">in </hi>as Ed., future price 1d. You will have heard of Haggen: I go w. Prendergast (<hi rend="italic">for once</hi>) in his remarks, &amp; so, I believe, the many here. Some good remarks in “D.T.” of last night (or, possibly, Friday.) In same, also a leading article containing long extract from a <hi rend="italic">good sound </hi>sermon lately preached in <hi rend="italic">R.C. </hi>Cathedl. at Auckland—on <hi rend="italic">Dishonesty. </hi>Yesty. Dr. Spencer kindly called and spent ½ hour, &amp; after him <hi rend="italic">Mr. Hill</hi>,!! the first time for more than 2 yrs.!! he remd. an hour—these 2 my <hi rend="italic">only </hi>visitors.</p>
         <p>I have <hi rend="italic">recently </hi>recd. a long &amp; good letter from “S.H. Decur, Whanganui”—on my “<hi rend="italic">Status Quo.</hi>” Evidently he knows the subject,—goes w. me (only seems to say, I could have done <hi rend="italic">more </hi>for myself, &amp; quotes from Owen’s, &amp;c.) but he does not seem to lay hold of the <hi rend="italic">chief </hi>thing in my paper—<hi rend="italic">fully to exculpate </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">Dr.M</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>I must write to D.—<hi rend="italic">who </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">what </hi>is he? and also another long letter from Suter, XtCh., <hi rend="italic">re </hi>same, giving me extracts from a paper of Owen’s in the Library <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, together with a copy of the drawing of <hi rend="italic">that early first </hi>Bone.</p>
         <p>(2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. part., 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> noon)</p>
         <p>By dint of perserverance fighting aginst pain<hi rend="underline">s</hi>! I have put up my promised packet to send w. this.—Last night a heavy one w. Rheum. in shoulder joint—<hi rend="underline italic">wearying</hi>!———and this day—<hi rend="italic">sciatica</hi>! <hi rend="underline italic">added</hi>—–I fear much, if these <hi rend="italic">united</hi> continue, my place will be w. Job on his dunghill.—but <hi rend="italic">without </hi>society! I hope, however, I shall have <hi rend="italic">no worse thoughts and utterances than he had.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I hope you may have time to <hi rend="italic">read </hi>my paper (vol X) on the <hi rend="italic">Kuri</hi>,<note xml:id="ftn3-612" place="foot" n="612"> Colenso W. 1877. Notes, chiefly historical, on the ancient dog of the New Zealanders. <hi rend="italic">Trans NZ Inst.</hi> 10: 135–155.</note> &amp; <hi rend="italic">note</hi>, that that mention of Dr. H. &amp; the skin in Cy. Museum was the <hi rend="italic">first </hi>rift in the lute! followed up by those on (<hi rend="underline italic">his</hi>) Maori names of places in Geogy. &amp; Maps of N.Z., as touched on in “3 Lity. papers,”<note xml:id="ftn3-613" place="foot" n="613"> Colenso W. 1883. <hi rend="italic">Three literary papers read before the Hawke’s Bay Philosophical Institute during the session of 1882:—I and II, On Nomenclature; III, On “Macaulay’s New Zealander.” </hi>Daily Telegraph Office, Napier. 41p</note> &amp; mentd. by me in <hi rend="italic">Inspg. Schools.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I did hope to write you more this time, but <hi rend="italic">cannot </hi>at <hi rend="underline italic">present</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">If </hi>my pains &amp;c continue—I would I were at Napier. I feared an increase of rheum. on Sunday evg. in Ch.—the Congn. (&amp; Chwdn.) would have upper windows open, &amp; the draught downwards on my head was <hi rend="italic">great</hi>!—Indeed the 2 candles by me shot out their flames horizontally, &amp; guttered, &amp;c. I looked <hi rend="italic">round </hi>&amp; <hi rend="underline italic">up</hi>, now &amp; then, in hopes the hint would be taken, but not so. I told them on My. mg. that if that is persisted in, I do as the Jews in their synagogues—<hi rend="italic">keep in my hat</hi>.</p>
         <p>I should return you 3 nos. Review only I note what you say respg. them.—Last wk. in going to P.O. for a p. note to pay Owen, I got 3/- worth <hi rend="italic">for you</hi> (in 2 1/6 ones, they not having any 3/- ones) which I now enclose. Do not be angry—give to Victor. Your cousin R. told me last wk. his Father <hi rend="italic">was in Auckland</hi>.</p>
         <p>Pardon this—<hi rend="italic">done </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">in pain</hi>—</p>
         <p>Yours always,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
