<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0346">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1877 October 10: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1877-10-10">1877 October 10</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1877 October 10: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-294" place="foot" n="294"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand,<lb/>Octr. 10, 1877.</p>
         <p>A. Juff, Esq.,</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir,</p>
         <p>Yesterday I recd, your welcome letter of Augt. 23, &amp; was glad to find you were all well—<hi rend="italic">in 7 Dog days</hi>! May this also find you in good health. It is too early to begin to write for our next <hi rend="underline italic">out</hi>going Mail (20<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. I think)—but I had better do so now—while disengaged, though suffering from Ear-ache. I should now <hi rend="italic">have </hi>been at <hi rend="italic">Wairoa</hi>, but have again been cruelly left behind! &amp; <hi rend="italic">no fault of mine</hi>. (Unless you say, I should go &amp; lodge for a while <hi rend="italic">at the Port</hi>.) My work was <hi rend="italic">over</hi> on Monday night of this season of H.B. Phil. Institute; &amp; <hi rend="italic">all last week</hi> I was <hi rend="italic">hard</hi> at work on School matters—after <hi rend="italic">end</hi> of Septr. Quarter.—</p>
         <p>Well, yesterday mgs. “<hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>” informed us, that the Wairoa bar was still bad, &amp; Capt. of Manaia did not know when he could go (that Bar has been <hi rend="italic">Bad</hi> for nearly a month: goods <hi rend="italic">once </hi>during the month landed on the <hi rend="italic">outer </hi>beach of H. Bay!)—I even went to Spit yesty. mg. to pass the entries for case of Books &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">Tea</hi> per H. Denny,—&amp; in talking w. them there only heard the above repeated—&amp; yet <hi rend="italic">2 steamers </hi>left last night, 8, for Wairoa—the river having opened &amp; entrance good!! (this, of course, only known by me <hi rend="underline italic">this mg.</hi>, enough to make one wild!) I telegraphed this aftn. to Wairoa— “Ready, waiting, yet again left behind, owing to information in H. of yesterday mg.—I am vexed.”—This day, too, has been nice, calm, quiet; of course, <hi rend="italic">I wait </hi>to go by first oppory.—one thing is good, I have <hi rend="underline italic">now</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">nothing to hinder me. </hi>I quite expect to be there within a few <hi rend="italic">days</hi>: so, as I said, I write to <hi rend="italic">you</hi> now.</p>
         <p>In your last letter to hand, you say nothing of <hi rend="italic">yourself</hi>: what on earth you are, or can, be doing!! As to <hi rend="italic">my </hi>buying land! or helping anyone to do so, (such blocks, or pieces, too, as you might like!)—ask me to catch a star, or bale out H. Bay. I will never never have any thing more to do with Land buying!—I wish I had <hi rend="italic">none</hi>—save just what my house stands on: it is our eternal source of worry &amp; anxiety: but I <hi rend="italic">will not</hi> be worried by it: I value my time, my poetry, my books &amp; my study,—far far beyond the land. I have tried to sell—let—anything: <hi rend="italic">no</hi>! Yet they want it. Well then I’ll <hi rend="italic">shut it up </hi>&amp; let it for a term merely as a grazing paddock, &amp; this I have just <hi rend="italic">completed</hi>, after much humming &amp; haaing—on part of N. &amp; Close,—4 years @ ₤40.—and <hi rend="italic">now others</hi> come to enquire!! I would have shut it up altogether but for the <hi rend="italic">Rates</hi>—which, <hi rend="italic">altogether</hi>, Country &amp; town, on <hi rend="italic">unoccupied </hi>Land, are <hi rend="italic">heavy</hi>. To finish this Land story: no arrangement yet w. Sladen: Mackay is done up, executions out against him: Robertson &amp; Drummond (Taradale) can do <hi rend="italic">nothing yet</hi>: Hague has now cheated altogether, scarcely any assets, &amp; <hi rend="italic">I </hi>shall have (I fear) to pay <hi rend="italic">his</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">last </hi>year’s rates as well as losing that rent! P. Dolbel (I got, <hi rend="italic">at last</hi>, to <hi rend="italic">see me</hi>—he can do nothing!! (₤140. per ann. &amp; all back unpaid <hi rend="italic">Interest </hi>(<hi rend="underline italic">fresh</hi>) of some years = ₤500.) he has spent his money recd. for Maungaharuru in land &amp; in sheep! at last he pays me ₤<hi rend="underline italic">25</hi>. !!! P.D. told me himself last week, that he could not have thought of acting as he has towards me, <hi rend="italic">only I was so easy</hi>!!—Besides all that,—<hi rend="italic">several </hi>P.N. dishonoured! Were it not for my small salary, &amp; a nest egg or two in reserve, I must have wanted.—Lascelles has 3 or 4 in hand! (of mine) w. poor prospects: <hi rend="italic">I </hi>never knew such a dishonest cheating time. I have had enough to disgust me for ever &amp; aye about land!! I leave the Land for <hi rend="italic">others</hi>.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="italic">Red </hi>Kowhai is now beautifully flowering (one shrub 10 feet high!)—and it is marked, for <hi rend="italic">its seed, for you</hi>. I sow the Surrey Hills <hi rend="italic">Foxglove</hi> in a day or two, and watch its growth for <hi rend="italic">L’s. sake.</hi> Miss Ross of Norsewood school has hastily &amp; quietly married a <hi rend="italic">young</hi> Dane up there called Thomson:—&amp; Mrs Wood <hi rend="underline italic">widow</hi>, of Roseneath, has ditto ditto another Prussian, rejoicing in the name of Hans Bygum!! Your friend Mr Sidey, performed this <hi rend="italic">latter </hi>job, at <hi rend="italic">Roseneath</hi>, &amp; they went off instanter to the N. Govt. being sadly beaten, resigned yesterday! what next? (see Papers.) H.B. Sheep show on today, Stafford, Sutton &amp; others come up to it. Giffard, Britten, Dyer, selling out. Presbytn. Ch. built at Kaikoura, to be opened next Sunday by Sidey. Mrs. Neil’s House <hi rend="italic">to be</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Working </hi>Men’s Club House, rent ₤120.!! (I <hi rend="italic">find</hi> this house belongs to Tiffen). “Helen Denny” anchored here 2 days ago. Do you know that Subn. Section beyond <hi rend="italic">old </hi>Lock-up, which was bought by a visitor: an “Indigo planter”? Well, Lee took possession of it!! &amp; has now sold (his <hi rend="italic">possession </hi>right) to Duncan Guy, for ₤50. who has made a road through it, winding from “Sebley’s Gulley,” &amp; now calls himself “<hi rend="italic">Owner</hi>”!! A most barefaced thing—yet <hi rend="italic">Weber</hi> defends him!! May I be delivered from <hi rend="italic">all such</hi> – – – !! Robjohns has built a good House for himself, up over old quarry at corner of Coote &amp; Shakespeare Roads. I see tenders are this day called for filling-in Browning’s 4 Sections 96–99 in Clive Sq. Dr. Gibbes’ new House is spoken of as being <hi rend="italic">the </hi>building for the new Union Club. How, or Why, I don’t exactly know,—but <hi rend="italic">I do </hi>know this, that the Dr. <hi rend="italic">wishes </hi>to <hi rend="italic">remove to Havelock</hi>. Dr. Hitchings is looking very well. G. Moore (Wellington) is just dead.</p>
         <p>You will see in “Weekly Mercury” much about the Colorado B. for which <hi rend="italic">we </hi>are indebted to you.—Stack’s Beetle is all <hi rend="italic">bosh</hi>! I have some sent to me, <hi rend="italic">a common N.Z. Camex</hi>, a nasty smelling thing if touched, often found <hi rend="italic">in </hi>lettuce, &amp; on strawberries, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
         <p>I was not a little vexed at the Institute Monthly Meeting on Monday 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—the last, too, for the season. (Dr. Hector had written earnestly requesting Members to meet, &amp; keep it going.) I had advertised, as in duty bound: &amp; lo! only 3 besides myself!!—J.A.S., Sturm, Holder—after waiting ¾ hour, Reasden came, &amp; I had to read an elaborately written paper of nearly 50 closely written pages to 4 Members!! the others, living <hi rend="italic">near</hi>, would not come. I don’t intend to work any longer for them—for nothing. Rearden was vexed, &amp; in moving a vote of thanks, gave vent to his feelings. Dr Spencer strolled in at near 10 o’clock. Christy Minstrels, Niggers, <hi rend="italic">Low fancy</hi> Balls, &amp; Comic Songs, are the rage at Napier,—aye, &amp; inland, too!—</p>
         <p>I must stop: if I don’t go to W. before M. leaves I may add something more. <hi rend="italic">Very few </hi>Papers <hi rend="italic">from you</hi> (6), &amp; <hi rend="italic">no Illustrated </hi>ones, which you have mentioned in your Letter.—</p>
         <p>Goodbye from yr. old friend,                 W. Colenso.</p>
         <p rend="end">Thursday afternoon, 11<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>Here I am! at it again!! This is a most glorious day, even here, where fine weather is so common. The blue above, the blue below, the sun shining (not too hot), the <hi rend="italic">gentler </hi>Sea breeze, the white rippling waves on the beach—the town shut up &amp; gone, by all carriages, &amp;c, &amp;c, to the Stock Show at Hastings—I am here suffering from tooth &amp; ear-ache, with intervals of relief.  Only this mg. (9) Fannin came over very kindly to have an hour’s chat. I had gone up stairs to my bed (after breakfast) feeling unwell &amp; moody, &amp; wishing to be out of the way. F’s. coming cheered me up a bit. I must try to give you<hi rend="underline">W</hi>idow <hi rend="underline">W</hi>ood’s <hi rend="underline">w</hi>ooing: Miller (gaoler) was one of S.W’s. trustees; having business to do with the widow, he sent his Prussian under-gaoler Hans to Roseneath: the <hi rend="italic">next </hi>day Hans went thither of his own account, &amp; the <hi rend="italic">next </hi>day Mr Sidey married them!! F. says, that he &amp; Miller were on the wharf when the trap drove down with the newly md. pair. Hans jumped out, &amp; shook hands with M. &amp; F. on leaving, and said to Miller that “<hi rend="italic">Mrs Wood</hi> was in the trap”: M. responded—“You should have said Mrs. Begums.” M. says, the children will have a <hi rend="italic">good </hi>stepf. in B.—they do not seem to be <hi rend="italic">greatly cared </hi>for by their mother!—</p>
         <p>Tylee sold just 12,000 ac. Land in Septr. &amp; nearly all to 2 or 3 buyers (see D.T.) It came about in this way,—Cable having sold his Wairoa run &amp; left that place, was here &amp; going out, looking about,—which so frightened Kinross &amp; his Overseer that a rush was made to secure themselves.—Bell has just sold his Land at Wainui (₤34,000); &amp; so has Bee (₤15,000) at Mohaka. (see Papers). I think <hi rend="italic">E</hi>. Fannin will soon seek to sell his run, as his health is bad. The S. folks are struck with the beauty of <hi rend="italic">our perennial climate. You &amp; I </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">ought</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>to have <hi rend="italic">secured</hi> a good thumping run: <hi rend="italic">one </hi>such block is better worth having than all my scattered fragments, &amp; gives far less trouble. F. tells me it is a fact, as to D.Guy <hi rend="italic">taking</hi> possession of subn. sn. 37—and in that open unblushing way—and it <hi rend="italic">is likely</hi> that he will <hi rend="italic">keep it</hi>! I found from the Rate Book which I examined last week, he had set himself down as “Owner”—as well as “Occupier”. I told F. that if I were an R.M. &amp; my clerk so acted—it would cost him his office: or (if such a thing could be supposed)—if I were Newton, &amp; Tos. so acted, I should give him warning to leave. A sad sad defeat of <hi rend="italic">moral principle</hi>. Guy has just done another <hi rend="italic">good </hi>thing! Corporation consent to fill in his Sn. (no. 352) for him, he giving a part <hi rend="italic">as a track</hi> from Craven Street to Railway. That street (by Newton’s <hi rend="italic">old </hi>store &amp; Mrs Craig’s) will be <hi rend="italic">the street </hi>to the Station—the only <hi rend="italic">one </hi>being from Carlyle St., but by the<hi rend="italic"> other</hi> way.!!—</p>
         <p>I suppose Bryson is going to build—on section <hi rend="italic">above </hi>that one you got planted for him, in his absence—(those trees have grown <hi rend="italic">well</hi>, far beyond N.Williams’,)—as there are lots of timber just carted there on top.—The Wms. have managed to carry <hi rend="italic">their</hi> man this time as Bp.—he is named Stuart (<hi rend="underline italic">refused</hi> by Synod last year) &amp; is sd. to be a <hi rend="italic">relative</hi>. <hi rend="italic">All have </hi>agreed—top, bottom, &amp; middle! See a curious bit in <hi rend="italic">D.T. </hi>of yesterday, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Sutton’s sleeping &amp; <hi rend="italic">snoring</hi> in the House! The Gas lamps are lit, &amp; make darkness <hi rend="italic">visible</hi>—being so far apart: one in centre of Cl. Sq. (i.e. Tennyson St. corner of M. Road,) next at Wilson, Dentist’s, corner: one in Milton Road in the angle, just below my little <hi rend="italic">higher </hi>gate, &amp; one (next) by Clayton’s Cottage:—so, on White Road, &amp; on Spit Road—stars twinkling in darkness!—A man named Elliott came in from Petane way, was taken ill, &amp; died in a few hours; on the inquest, another m. named Elliott attended, &amp; the deceased proved to be <hi rend="italic">his brother</hi>, had not <hi rend="italic">seen</hi> each other for 30 years: both wealthy: looking after runs: not much brotherly love! I ween.</p>
         <p>H.R.R. is going to cut up his Hampden land into small 20–30 acre farms. Ellison &amp; Turley are the <hi rend="italic">new </hi>Borough Valuators. Manoy <hi rend="italic">sen. </hi>has been elected to the Wairoa County Council. I see, in today’s H., that P. Dolbel got yesterday the 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. prize (of that Class) for his imported Lincoln Ram:—it was said he <hi rend="italic">ought</hi> to have had it <hi rend="italic">last </hi>year.—</p>
         <p rend="end">Sunday, 14<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I am giving you a Journal instead of a letter! new My.—Grey (Premier), Sheehan (Nat. Mr.), Whitmore (Col. Secy., Upper Ho.) Macandrew, Ballance, &amp; Larnach, are the others,—<hi rend="italic">it won’t stand long, as now constituted</hi>. Auckland &amp; Otago <hi rend="italic">can now agree</hi> as to <hi rend="italic">one general</hi> policy: we shall see.</p>
         <p>Case per “H.D.” Books &amp; <hi rend="italic">your Tea</hi>, in box in this house, looking as clean &amp; fresh as when it left Dixon’s Warehouse! Fear I shall not have time to open it till <hi rend="italic">after </hi>Xmas.</p>
         <p>Yesterday, I had an enquirer from Waipawa after a Sn. there: suppose it will again end in 0!</p>
         <p>I had a <hi rend="italic">painful</hi> job last week; Lear had been seen several times of late by my man, sleeping about our fences &amp; under trees, &amp;c.—at last he spoke with L., who sd. he had been 3 days &amp; nights wandering,—Gray having turned him out,—&amp; that he wished for death, &amp;c, &amp;c. (I had previously helped him.) So I saw Scully who sent 2 p.men, who hunted him up &amp; took him away. I then saw S. <hi rend="italic">again</hi>, <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to have L. brought up as a vagrant &amp; sent to Gaol, but to place him in the “Old Man’s House,” which S. had done. It is a sad sad story! L. was well off <hi rend="underline italic">here</hi>, a free-holder &amp; w. money.—another victim to P. Houses,—or, <hi rend="underline italic">rather</hi>, to <hi rend="italic">discontent</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">seeking</hi> to be <hi rend="underline italic">rich</hi>! (a lesson to <hi rend="italic">us</hi> all.)</p>
         <p>Curiously enough, the 2 steamers which left in such a hurry last Tuesday night for Wairoa, both came to grief! The “Result” (screw) went out &amp; gained no place! her crank pin broke, &amp; after 3 days in the H. Bay, winds contrary, endeavd. to sail back to Napier! “Manaia” (paddle) on leaving Wairoa, returning, in crossing the Bar, was struck by a sea, which caused the anchor (badly fastened) to fall over &amp; so <hi rend="italic">she dragged it through</hi> the shingle of the Bar! the rollers going over her! had the anchor <hi rend="italic">held</hi> she must have gone; passengers (Maney &amp; others) much frightened. Very likely had I <hi rend="italic">known</hi> of their going, I should have chosen the “Result,” from what Cable &amp; others had told me,—&amp; only fancy W.C. 3–4 days in that <hi rend="italic">wee </hi>craft rolling about in H.B.!! &amp;, after all, <hi rend="italic">not reaching </hi>Wairoa: <hi rend="italic">you might have heard of it from some one</hi>,—<hi rend="italic">and a bit more</hi>.— However, <hi rend="italic">I have yet to go</hi>, &amp;, possibly, tomorrow.</p>
         <p>Your friend Morrison has put up a <hi rend="italic">public </hi>clock, over his verandah which is greatly enlarged (the clock): this of more real service than Sir D’s. gift, which is “stowed away,” ostentatiously, up above the Royal Yards, &amp; is out of sight; save from Clarendon Hotel!—</p>
         <p>I was amused the other day in passing by Conroy’s (late Hague’s) Shop—to see 52 couples of Rabbits!! The weekly Coach brings them every week now, from Wairarapa. I note, from Returns, that on some Runs, 1000 <hi rend="italic">a day</hi> are killed, on a <hi rend="italic">single </hi>Run! &amp; in Dunedin 1000 per week are regularly sold.—I fear our foolish thickheaded knownothing &amp; thoughtless Acclimatisation Societie<hi rend="underline italic">s</hi> have done great mischief in N.Z.—<hi rend="italic">future </hi>times will show.</p>
         <p>Don’t send me (specially) papers contg. <hi rend="italic">War</hi> news: <hi rend="italic">I never read any</hi>: our short telegrams are quite enough. When G. Grey went to be sworn-in, he &amp; Normanby met for <hi rend="italic">first </hi>time! &amp; no doubt, were <hi rend="italic">Exceedingly polite.</hi>—</p>
         <p>(15<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) Just got a note from Black, Wairoa, enqg. after yr. 5 ac. Sn., have replied, <hi rend="italic">that I will see him </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">there</hi>: send me <hi rend="italic">your lowest </hi>fig. I heard, some time ago, it was not a very good one.</p>
         <p>And now I must close. Kind regards to all family, &amp; believe me, ever yours, <hi rend="italic">truly</hi>,        W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>