<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0901">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1894 July 12: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1894-07-12">1894 July 12</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1894 July 12: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-687" place="foot" n="687"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, July 12/94</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding—</p>
         <p>“Nolens volens”, I must write to you tonight, come what may! for your <hi rend="italic">2</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">nd</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>letter of the 10th. inst. I read this mg. I may perhaps say I have been having <hi rend="italic">you much</hi> in mind of late—having recd. your letter of 8<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. June, <hi rend="italic">shortly</hi> after my arrival here from Bush, and I will tell you—I was a little vexed when it came in—bec. I had party. requested you in my <hi rend="italic">long </hi>ep. from Dannevirke—<hi rend="italic">not to reply quickly</hi>, and so—when I saw yours w. <hi rend="italic">6</hi> stamps on it, immy. after my return to N., I guessed you did <hi rend="italic">the opposite</hi>, &amp; so I did not open it for 3–4 days—being <hi rend="italic">extra busy </hi>after my prolonged absence: and since then daily busy, &amp; much worried, and <hi rend="italic">not </hi>feeling strong—my attack at Dvk. tilted me over pretty considerably.</p>
         <p>And now that I am writing to you I know I shall not say ½ of what I should like to say” indeed, I don’t know where to begin! I will take up your <hi rend="italic">last</hi>. Thanks for all<hi rend="italic"> </hi>you have <hi rend="italic">so</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">well</hi> told me <hi rend="italic">re </hi>yr. Socy. Mtgs. and for the slips from Papers: I marvel much at what is sd. in one of them <hi rend="italic">re </hi>old <hi rend="underline italic">Field</hi>: I have his book &amp; there is <hi rend="italic">little</hi> in it <hi rend="italic">new</hi>. Am not sorry that W. B—r got a bit of a dressing, he <hi rend="italic">needs </hi>it: I notice in a late Roy. Sy. No. proceedings—that W.B. had sent them <hi rend="italic">all </hi>his papers, in vols. Trans., bound up <hi rend="italic">into 1 vol.</hi>! I recd. my “A. copies” last wk., &amp; w. them a note from our Hon. Sy. at wh. I warmed up, &amp; wrote—I enclose copy of mine. <hi rend="italic">This evg. </hi>he &amp; Hill came as a “Deputation”, to make up matters, &amp; so I have agreed to read my P. at Augt. Mtg. (D.V.) Hamilton sent me a copy of his p. on Moa Bibliography which has surprised me! but more so at his <hi rend="italic">choosing </hi>to bring forward every scrap!!! good, bad, indifferent. Hill goes w. me, in finding fault w. H. for so doing—&amp; so I shall tell H.—Hector, also, sent me, a copy of yr. proceedgs. &amp; I find, on that mem. night, some one yclept Tanner, said, “I was too <hi rend="italic">personal</hi>.” Who is he? &amp; what does he <hi rend="italic">know </hi>of the case? Atkinson has printed some more <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Tregear, &amp; sent me a copy—you may have seen it? Correspdce. &amp;c. w. N.Z.I.—with a private letter from T.!! I have been (&amp; still am) very busy putting-up a <hi rend="italic">big lot</hi> of Mosses Lichens, &amp;c. for Kew, my collecting, &amp; also, others,—from 1854! hitherto I had sent Hepaticæ &amp; Fungi, only: my front room (parlour!) is a work-shop. Since my return I have had <hi rend="italic">2 visitors</hi> (until this evg.) the Dean &amp; Hill, once Ed. Grubb (says) he is <hi rend="italic">coming</hi>—but the weather <hi rend="italic">of late </hi>against him. I have a short letter in Hd. this mg. which I will send w. this.<note xml:id="ftn3-688" place="foot" n="688"> Issues of the <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> for July 1894 are missing.</note> I also send you 2 old letters I lately found in overhauling my locker both will interest <hi rend="italic">you</hi>—but <hi rend="italic">contrarily.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There are also other matters for you to see—return all, except advts. I have no time to write on matters political—They are <hi rend="italic">mad</hi>! w. their <hi rend="italic">fads</hi>: and won’t I fear stop, until they had made us (the Colony) the laughing-stock of the world! I note what you kindly &amp; feelingly say <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Bk. N.Z. I would that I was <hi rend="italic">clear </hi>but so far from ever selling—I took more shares! I have been 2–3 times to see B. but, either “<hi rend="italic">Engd</hi>.” or “<hi rend="italic">out</hi>”: I do <hi rend="italic">not know the position</hi>. However I never was one who thought much (anxiously) over money matters. I have not yet heard from Cheeseman, <hi rend="underline italic">somehow</hi> he will not ansr. my L. I have all but concluded—<hi rend="italic">I have finished w. the Bush</hi>—cleared out! we were 4 down <hi rend="italic">together</hi>, &amp; adjg.; 3 died! I only recovered: I staid to see end &amp; funeral of my yg. friend–whom I kissed in his coffin. I was to have buried, but was again taken ill.—I staid also, to console his mother &amp; brother—but at <hi rend="italic">such times</hi> man can effect little.—I have no Ch. work now.</p>
         <p>The great theme here just now is the mis. Breakwater! how it will end I cannot say. <hi rend="italic">Heavier </hi>taxes we <hi rend="italic">know </hi>(<hi rend="italic">also indicated </hi>by Boro’ Council, in <hi rend="italic">Rates for town</hi>!) &amp; now the “<hi rend="italic">erosion</hi>” (or <hi rend="italic">worse</hi>) of Petane Beach, or that from W. Spit to P. is to the <hi rend="italic">fore</hi>. This day I notice <hi rend="italic">all low lands </hi>largely under water, a sad sight from this hill-top.—The Bp’s. Sister &amp; daughter (my neighbours) have heard from <hi rend="italic">him</hi>—he was well—but <hi rend="italic">no one else </hi>that I know of have heard. I see Mr. Paterson is <hi rend="italic">now </hi>at Wgn.—I suppose you will be sure to see him. On 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. June, Rev. Mr. Grant called on me at Dvk., &amp; <hi rend="italic">we spent a pleasant hour</hi>—he came for the Sy’s. duty, 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">new </hi>Pn. Ch. at Havelock is nearly finished, &amp; will be opened on 22<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. (so Mr Fraser kindly informs me) I should much like to be there. Perhaps you knew Hy. Williams’ 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. son who died last wk. at Taradale. Craig as usual is busy, and (I think) much older <hi rend="italic">in appearance</hi>—thin, worn, grey, and wears specs. always—so does Hill! The next shop to Craig’s, is now a <hi rend="italic">flash </hi>Barber’s Estabt.. Fannin, Tiffen, Lyndon &amp; other old hands are all well.—</p>
         <p>I was sorry to hear of your being <hi rend="italic">hors de combat</hi>—but pleased to know of yr. rallying—&amp;, I hope, <hi rend="italic">soon </hi>“<hi rend="underline italic">all</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> right</hi>” again: and the <hi rend="italic">good news </hi>of Victor being so much better!—I saw yr. Uncle J. in town on Monday last, he was very well, had only heard from his son at <hi rend="italic">Adelaide. </hi>Our winter is more than ½-thro’, hope w. spring <hi rend="italic">you </hi>may have a return of <hi rend="italic">good </hi>employ in your Office. I have <hi rend="underline italic">much</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">less</hi> Rheumatism this year &amp; winter, but I have <hi rend="italic">other </hi>maladies—getting weaker &amp; weaker &amp; <hi rend="italic">feeling </hi>it! among them, I would I could sleep better—or had <hi rend="italic">you </hi>to talk with. Good bye</p>
         <p>   Kind regards, yrs.                      W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
