<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0768">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 February 13: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0495.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-02-13">1891 February 13</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 February 13: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-512" place="foot" n="512"> ATL qMS-0495.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, 13 Feby., 1891.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Of course! &amp; <hi rend="italic">again</hi>!! Yours of 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">crossed mine in transit</hi>—which I had vainly hoped to avoid: although I commence this today—I shall <hi rend="italic">withhold</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">it</hi> until I hear from you: so as to become <hi rend="italic">regular</hi> in our correspce.</p>
         <p>And so you have an addition to yr. family: good, may such ever prove to be a <hi rend="italic">blessing</hi>—in every sense: I am much pleased in hearing of both M. &amp; daur. <hi rend="italic">doing well,</hi> &amp; that your wife has her Mother with her. I would, however, that your dear little son was further advanced in restoration, &amp; shall hope for <hi rend="italic">better</hi> news by by-&amp;-by.</p>
         <p>My last to you was on the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> closed &amp; posted on 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. &amp; I hoped it might reach you on the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>—<hi rend="italic">in time</hi>:—I am still here &amp; <hi rend="italic">still unsettled</hi> (as it were), but I think I shall leave next wk. for Dvk., where, however, I <hi rend="italic">may</hi> not stay long: <hi rend="italic">shall not</hi>, unless I should get some Ch. work to do—of which I know nothing at <hi rend="italic">present</hi>.</p>
         <p>I went to Clive last Sy., mg. fine: at Ch. congn. about 45—<hi rend="italic">mostly</hi> children, only 4 adult males! At close of Prayers. I <hi rend="italic">felt </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">suddenly impressed</hi>, &amp; so told them all, I should come again next Sy. Evg. S., &amp; for the Ch. to <hi rend="italic">tell their parents</hi>, whom I hoped to meet there! (<hi rend="italic">repeated</hi> at close of Sermon.) I am keeping pretty well,—the weather, (<hi rend="italic">to-day</hi> wet, foggy, very close, &amp; <hi rend="italic">yesty</hi>. &amp; night before steady downpour!) against me: I notice in Wdv. P.—that in <hi rend="italic">Jany.</hi> they had 7 days rain! &amp; on <hi rend="italic">one</hi> day <hi rend="italic">over</hi> 3 in!!—</p>
         <p>I sent you Tuesday’s Herald, containing <hi rend="italic">our meeting</hi>—but <hi rend="italic">not</hi> our long contention (closing at X.15!) this began w. <hi rend="italic">my</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">refusal</hi> to stand as Pt.—Dr Sp. also, would <hi rend="italic">not</hi> accept it: then Hill (acting Chn. At meeting) agreed to take it, but sought there &amp; then <hi rend="italic">repeatedly</hi> (backed by Large &amp; Craig) to have <hi rend="italic">2</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">nd</hi> My. in month altered to <hi rend="italic">3</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">rd</hi> to <hi rend="underline italic">suit him</hi>: which I contended could only be done at a “General Meeting”;—I warned them of <hi rend="italic">alterations</hi> to suit <hi rend="italic">special</hi> occasions—especially of sprung catch ones; as, possibly such a one (as precedent) might lead ere long to having their meeting on Sunday nights:—but I had no one <hi rend="italic">w. me</hi>. Mr. Oliver remarked that I might be induced to become Pt., on the nights for mtg. being held in the <hi rend="italic">summer</hi>: (I had adduced, as an addl. reason, the diffy. of getting out from <hi rend="italic">here</hi> of a dark (&amp; might be) stormy <hi rend="italic">winter’s</hi> night.) After a <hi rend="italic">heavy</hi> amount of palaver, &amp; uphill wk., it was agreed, that <hi rend="italic">at close</hi> of the first “<hi rend="italic">ordy</hi>” mtg. in May, this altn. should be proposed—I only voting against it.—The <hi rend="italic">Crinum</hi>, &amp; its history, were shown &amp;c <hi rend="italic">before</hi> mtg. began &amp; McD. <hi rend="italic">for once</hi>! coming <hi rend="italic">early</hi>, &amp; in good mood! He had lately been to Auckland—he told me.—I thought of <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, &amp; wished you <hi rend="italic">were there</hi>. [I have pretty good reasons for believing, that H. both wished &amp; <hi rend="italic">schemed</hi> for Chair.]</p>
         <p>I enclose some additional Extracts, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the Press, which will <hi rend="italic">show</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">further</hi>, how others wrote of it—e.g. Bp. Selwyn—a most <hi rend="italic">diligent</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">enquiring </hi>man in every minutiæ of the Mission, especially in all former matters; and in this he was aided, (1) by his <hi rend="italic">own</hi> sharp Chaplain, &amp; yg. men: and (2) by the <hi rend="italic">old Missionaries</hi>—at Kerikeri &amp; Waimate, &amp;c.—and (3) by he &amp; they having, subsequently, so <hi rend="italic">much</hi> to do with the <hi rend="italic">Press</hi>, translation, &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>I note what you say—<hi rend="italic">re</hi> stuffing <hi rend="italic">our</hi> Papers, &amp; again (<hi rend="italic">as</hi> in general) agree with you, &amp; deplore <hi rend="italic">it</hi>,—this habit or custom is great &amp; constant now, here, w. <hi rend="italic">D.T.</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">H.</hi> but those <hi rend="italic">addresses</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">speeches</hi> (I had referred you to) in XtCh. papers <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Mtg. of Sc. Assn were <hi rend="italic">different</hi>, &amp; such as you would agree with: if I get copies, sent for by Craig, of Jany. 16, 17, I will send you one. I have (<hi rend="italic">ventured</hi>!)—written to Sir J.H., thanking, &amp;c.—and I am thinking of again taking up my discarded paper &amp; subject of <hi rend="italic">Hawaiki</hi>:—also, “A Memoir of the Martyrs of Science in these Seas:”—for I fear, I must have <hi rend="italic">done</hi> with Botany.——</p>
         <p>Last wk. I recd., thro Govt.,—a big Ms. from Kew, contg. list of my <hi rend="italic">Hepaticæ </hi>(sent thither last year), named by the great expert—Stephani of Leipzig:—there are several sps. nov., but not so many as I had expected.——</p>
         <p>Did I tell you, that Kirk, senior, has got the billet of editing a 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. Ed. of the Hd.Bk. N.Z. Flora? How <hi rend="italic">he</hi> got it, I cannot understand: it should have been committed to a 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">class</hi> European (or Amern.) Botanist, <hi rend="italic">aided</hi> by all local helpers. Sir J.D.H., <hi rend="italic">I know</hi>, was applied to, some time ago, (and I strongly advised him to accept—at least, the <hi rend="italic">supervision</hi>, but he cld not, as his <hi rend="italic">whole time </hi>until his end! is devoted to his great work<hi rend="italic">—Fl. Indica. </hi>[And he told me, that even if he should accept, there were certain portions (as mosses, Hepaticæ, Fungi, &amp;c.) which would have to be done by <hi rend="underline italic">experts</hi>—at that partr. branch: no doubt, K. thinks <hi rend="underline italic">he</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> can do all</hi>!!! So it is:—some <hi rend="italic">rush </hi>in where <hi rend="italic">angels fear</hi> to tread”!] I have a very poor opinion of Kirk’s <hi rend="italic">compilation</hi>—“Forest Flora of N.Z.,”—especially the plates! <hi rend="italic">Far better</hi> ones, of the <hi rend="italic">same</hi> plants, were exd. 50–60 years ago! &amp; so I <hi rend="italic">told</hi> K.—He has written to me, to aid him, w. spns. &amp;c., &amp; I have promised to do so—as far as I well can: he is, far too synthetic for me.—</p>
         <p>I am pleased w. your observations on <hi rend="italic">age</hi> of world, &amp; <hi rend="italic">of human</hi> race:—this (once) great Polynesian people will have justice done them—in days to come. I noticed that Stack (!) had come out w. a paper on the Maoris—which (from the portions given in papers) he must have largely <hi rend="italic">culled</hi> from mine in Trans. N.Z. Inst.—just like Smith—in his on <hi rend="italic">M. Proverbs</hi>, (and Tregear, also, <hi rend="italic">in his on Maoris</hi>, published in London: have you seen <hi rend="italic">this</hi>?) T. sent me a copy.—</p>
         <p>And then, your remarks on M &amp; NG—these <hi rend="italic">discordant</hi> consonants, in Polyn. dialects,—as used in RIMA and RINGA:—but there is <hi rend="italic">more</hi> to be said, <hi rend="italic">here</hi>—which also <hi rend="italic">struck</hi> the early <hi rend="italic">sc</hi>. voyagers <hi rend="italic">after</hi> Cook:—they found that those high chiefs known to C., whose <hi rend="italic">names</hi> he had carefully written, were now bearing <hi rend="italic">other</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">names</hi>, &amp; those <hi rend="underline italic">must not</hi> be mentioned (extending to 40–50 of the most common words which occur in conversation, and bearing not the least affinity whatsoever to the former expressions!): just so it was in N.Z., only here, there being <hi rend="italic">no</hi> monarchy nor <hi rend="italic">paramount</hi> chief, when he died—or during his life in <hi rend="italic">other tribes—</hi>the <hi rend="italic">old</hi> term would again come into use: there are some <hi rend="italic">fine</hi> remarks on this common rule.</p>
         <p>You casually mention the <hi rend="italic">binding</hi> of Tregear’s Dicty. I hope it will be strongly bound: above all, discarding those <hi rend="italic">detestable</hi> wires!</p>
         <p>Your mention of a certain Ms. Dicty. of R.C. Misss., &amp; how it was pillaged &amp; used:—reminds me of one of our <hi rend="italic">early</hi> writers on Maori (or N.Z.) who, in the end of his wk., did something similar, and so Taylor, in his <hi rend="italic">Botanl. List, </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">&amp;c</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi>—ere long, I suppose, I shall see how (your friend) Tregear managed with my letter A.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">14</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi> Formerly a day of <hi rend="italic">interest</hi>! Valentine’s Day! (now <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> said about it, in our locals, a <hi rend="italic">good</hi> thing, too!) and, the day of <hi rend="italic">Cook’s death</hi>! Weather still, damp, <hi rend="italic">foggy</hi>! &amp; very close.</p>
         <p>What do you allude to, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> “Colliers’ Bibliography?” is it <hi rend="italic">the same</hi> as in “List Govt. Pubns.” @ 2/6. Do you <hi rend="italic">know</hi> anything of “Maps N.Z.,” N. &amp; S. Islds., Royal, 2/6 pair”? in Govt. List. I want a good <hi rend="italic">clear one</hi> of N. Island, to lay down my own wanderings &amp; figures of 8! Luff had one here in his off., on wall, contg. <hi rend="italic">my tracks</hi> of ’43: I drew the map &amp; laid them down for Bp Selwyn, &amp; he sent it Home—I believe that Map was pubd. by Arrowsmith. I wonder if L. has <hi rend="italic">that map</hi> now: &amp; do you know him suffy. to enq.? <hi rend="italic">&amp; if so, </hi>to give you the date, no., &amp;c. of that Map.</p>
         <p>(<hi rend="italic">25</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th.</hi>) I <hi rend="italic">now</hi> close: &amp; am</p>
         <p>My dear Sir, Yours ever</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
