<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0830">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 May 31: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-05-31">1892 May 31</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 May 31: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-588" place="foot" n="588"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Woodville, May 31<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. 1892</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I came hither (as usual) on Saturday, &amp; have remained till today, and as I brought yr. kind letter of 22<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. with me, and have an hour to spare, I will ansr. it, w. thanks, from this place, this day too being the <hi rend="italic">last </hi>day of May!—</p>
         <p>First,then, thanks, extra, for your paper contg. review of Hudson’s Entoml. Book—I should much like to <hi rend="italic">see </hi>it (by &amp; by at N. <hi rend="italic">perhaps</hi>), but I hesitate in buying a copy—as I <hi rend="italic">did</hi> in subsg. to it, on recg. a note w. prospectus—having been so shabbily served by Thompson with his Fern Book after aiding him too! (Once bit 2ce shy!) Did you write that Review? I also thank you for your clipping of Kipling’s—I <hi rend="italic">go w. </hi>you, as usual, in your just remark, on him &amp; his, and especially your own nice &amp; poetical line:—viz.—“He <hi rend="italic">can </hi>see the wonder the beauty and the romance of the scenes that have been before our eyes from childhood.”—In the clipping, however, you have <hi rend="italic">underlined</hi>— “What a splendid cry it is, the proclamation of the creed that brings men out of their bed by scores at midnight!” True: but I (?) go a step further, <hi rend="italic">now</hi>:—I have <hi rend="italic">often</hi> repeated (priv, &amp; pub.)—</p>
         <p>“Blind unbelief is sure to err,” &amp;c—</p>
         <p>But <hi rend="underline italic">now</hi> I add— “Blind belief is sure to err.” and my own observation, &amp;c—amounts to this, that the latter is the <hi rend="italic">more</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">prevalent</hi> and the more dangerous! from the Pope of Rome &amp; the Abp. of Cy.—John Knox &amp; Spurgeon, down to the lowest of the African fetich worshippers. Would but you &amp; I cod. talk fully on this subjt.</p>
         <p>I send you 2 clippings—one (Maori) to hand <hi rend="italic">here </hi>on a fragment of Npr. (some one emulating Tregear &amp; Co., appy.) the other I cut out for you at Dvk. Thanks for yr. kind offer to send me “Little Minister,” I have <hi rend="italic">recently </hi>got a copy from Craig: I had to send to him for paper, pens, &amp;c, and <hi rend="italic">so </hi>I said, If “L.M.” <hi rend="italic">in stock</hi>, send me a copy, which he did, but I have not yet looked at it. Had he not done so I shod. have thanked you. One thing C. cod. not ansr. I had enqd. re a new transln. w. comments of Ecclesiastes—by a Heb. Scholar (some such name as Dr. Ginsberg—who, I bel., transld. &amp; wrote fully on the Mashite Stone) but C. could not find it: perhaps you may aid, but no great matter as I <hi rend="italic">have </hi>it (advt.) <hi rend="italic">at N.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Ten days ago I sent my draft Mao. Lex. résumé, w. <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the offl. letters (22 I think) &amp; replies, to Capt. R. for his opinion, &amp;c,—it <hi rend="italic">may </hi>now be at Dvk.—when I get it, you shall know, &amp;c.—I note what you say re “Hawaiki” &amp; “Green Stone” Papers! Aue! <hi rend="underline italic">when</hi>?—I much fear, I <hi rend="italic">can not </hi>even <hi rend="italic">re</hi>-commence them while in Bush. My month of “May” (like Zachariah’s course in temple) is now fulfilled—&amp; June is at hand, shall I also fill this? <hi rend="italic">&amp; shall I then return</hi>?—<hi rend="italic">I cannot leave this Ch. unprovided for, &amp; so closed</hi>: there is no Lay R. here: at same time, I confess, (as I told Rev. R. Stewart yesterday,) there is but <hi rend="italic">small </hi>encouragement; But I have (I trust) long ago, learned—to look beyond man in these matters.—I was much struck (<hi rend="italic">again</hi>) yesterday, in reading in Ch. (1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi> less. mg. S.) Deut. XXX.—are <hi rend="italic">these </hi>words—warnings—<hi rend="italic">promises</hi>—respg. that unhappy—wondrous—race of Jews—about to be fulfilled?–</p>
         <p>I was much pleased to find you still writing in such a cheerful &amp; vigorous strain. Last wk. I recd. a wire from Fannin, that he wod. spend an evg. w. me at Dvk.!! He came too, by “Express” (aftn.) train, &amp; we <hi rend="italic">talked </hi>&amp; talked till XII! next mg. early he went on to Wgn. to meet his wife, <hi rend="italic">again </hi>retg. from Dunedin, &amp; once more! well: I saw them both <hi rend="italic">en r. </hi>on Saty. noon—she seemed very well.—Several letters to hand from <hi rend="italic">new </hi>sc. correspdts. (or would <hi rend="italic">become </hi>such!) must <hi rend="italic">give all up</hi>: from Indiana, Paris, &amp; an <hi rend="italic">invitation</hi> from Genoa! (<hi rend="italic">Great </hi>Italn. Botanl. Socy.) to keep w. them their quad cent. in hon. of Columbus.</p>
         <p>Farewell, my dr. friend: hope you &amp; yours are well: kindest regards from,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>Weather cold fog <hi rend="italic">mornings</hi>—fine from 1 p.m.</p>
         <p>In the great gale at Napier the tallest biggest Blue Gum so conspicuous on top of gulley behind the kitchen and closet was uprooted &amp; came down across back yard &amp; marking fences, &amp;c but just clearing the house. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
