<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0913">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1894 October 3: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1894-10-03">1894 October 3</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1894 October 3: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-701" place="foot" n="701"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Octr. 3/94</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I feel somewhat inclined to write to you to night,—to thank you for so very kindly sending me 3 papers; to do this, I fear, I caused you some trouble &amp; waste of time: I wish also to tell you a little <hi rend="italic">re </hi>events of last wk. here:—and (before it is too late) to call yr. attention to <hi rend="italic">2 </hi>of our last wk’s. papers (D.T., &amp; Evg.N., of <hi rend="italic">27</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>) as these contain <hi rend="italic">stirring </hi>arts. on the Bishop-elect. I have endeavoured <hi rend="italic">in vain</hi> to get copies! (like those you mention w. you) <hi rend="underline italic">sold out</hi>.</p>
         <p>1. Howlett’s letter, which you read on file, is an incisive one! &amp; contains much to the point; curiously enough, 2 days ago I recd. a letter from Howlett, containing <hi rend="italic">that letter</hi>, also “Neuropath’s”—both as clippings sent to him from Wgn. I believe that Hill, finding that I could not get to see a copy, wrote to Howlett, &amp; so H. to me; his letter that covered them was only a short note of introduction.—–</p>
         <p>The long abstract from (or, rather, abstract of) Tregear’s “<hi rend="italic">Myth</hi>.” paper, sent by you—is, a flighty farfetched one: no wonder that the Dons came down on him! I should think <hi rend="italic">T. himself </hi>(or some <hi rend="italic">good friend</hi>) <hi rend="italic">furnished the report</hi>—no ref. to either Maskell or Sir James. I also noticed, that your meetings are <hi rend="italic">fortnightly</hi>: good, w. workers, as it keeps alive interest in them.—</p>
         <p>I sent you copy of mine to Peacock: I have his reply—which I will send for your considn.—I do not exactly like it.</p>
         <p>Yesterday I despatched my lot to Engd., 5 tin boxes (3lbs. ea.) of Crypts. w. long letter memos. &amp;c., per <hi rend="italic">Direct </hi>M.; w. letters &amp; papers (as usual) per S.F., I have also been ansg. several local letters, so that I have—once more!— “cleared the decks”!</p>
         <p>Lascelles, Senr., is <hi rend="italic">leaving for India</hi>: his Library sold last wk. I visited <hi rend="italic">Monty’s </hi>sale-room<hi rend="italic"> </hi>first to see the books, several good ones among them, &amp; I thought on you<hi rend="italic">—I party. wanted “</hi>N.Z. Fl. Handbook<hi rend="italic">”, in </hi>
            <hi rend="underline">good</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>condn. &amp; indeed <hi rend="italic">uncut</hi>, but it went beyond my fig. (left w. auctr.)—&amp; brought 31/-—<hi rend="italic">good</hi> it was worth that—&amp; <hi rend="italic">more</hi> to any one requiring it; (I don’t know who bought it). I got “Lives Eng. Cardinals”, 2 vols. 8vo., also “Life of Margaret of Anjou”, 2 vols. 8vo., both in <hi rend="italic">very good </hi>condn. Library books: also, Tennyson’s, Shelley’s, Karr— “Tour round my Garden”, 2 copies, 3 vols. “Trans. N.Z. Inst.” (IX, X, XI,), “Pictorial Cabinet of Marvels”, 4to—intg, &amp; fully illd.—these latter ones I purchd. to give away to yg. correspdts. in Country: today I opened a big parcel, from London 2 months ago, contg. “Paxton’s Flower Garden”, 3 vols. 4to. w. smaller books:—so you may see I am a little again in your favourite line.</p>
         <p>I suppose you will have known the results of the Synod: Archdn. L.W. being Bp.-elect. During the past winter, Hill, having got hold of the vol. “Report <hi rend="italic">General </hi>Synod, w. Constitn. &amp; Rules of the Provinl. Ch.”, he found, that I, <hi rend="italic">as a licensed Cl.</hi>, was <hi rend="italic">entitled </hi>to a seat in Synod, but to make it sure, H. wrote (a case) to Bp. Cowie actg. Primate, &amp; Bp. C. in reply, said, [he told Eccles the same when in Auckld.] “<hi rend="italic">I had</hi>”, referring H. to the same Canon, containing it. So H. on Synod opening brought up the matter, but President (Archd. L.W.) would not allow it; much talk (pub. &amp; priv.) folld., &amp; in the evg. the 2 Archdns. came to Hill &amp; sd. “How much they should like to see me there w. them, <hi rend="italic">but </hi>under the <hi rend="italic">proviso </hi>cl.”, &amp; I had told H., <hi rend="italic">I would not </hi>accept it.—Howr. next day at meeting, Can. St. H. propd. &amp; Archd. <hi rend="italic">S.</hi>W. secd.—a Resolution invitg. me, &amp; Fielder was sent up w. it—I told F. I wod. not go thither, save <hi rend="italic">as my right</hi>.—but Robertshawe, Eccles, &amp; others, also came &amp; I gave way to them, &amp; went, and certainly was <hi rend="underline italic">very well recd</hi>. Bp. elect came down to entrance to receive me, with a hearty shake hand &amp; kind words (!!!) folld. by S.W. &amp; the Canons, &amp; the Dean, &amp; the Parsons, &amp; some of the older identity lay—Newton, Shirley, St. Hill, &amp;c. &amp; so I remd. till close—x.15 p.m.——I give <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi> this in full: I expect to go to Woodville after mid. of month. I am keeping well, but feeling <hi rend="italic">sudden change</hi>, <hi rend="underline italic">cold</hi> S., yesty. &amp; to-day. Hope you &amp; yours are well</p>
         <p>Believe me yours truly,    W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S., Who is this “George Allen” that comes out re Ngauruhoe? as an authority.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="underline italic">P.S</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. Supplimentary to mine of 3</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">rd</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. inst.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="end">Napier<lb/>Friday<hi rend="italic">night</hi>
            <lb/>Octr. 5/94</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I am going to surprise you,—I trust agreeably so.</p>
         <p>I think I told you how I was assisting Robertson, G.P.O., with <hi rend="underline italic">old</hi> P.O. memoranda—sorts: well, he wanted more of the <hi rend="italic">earliest</hi> times of <hi rend="italic">Colony, </hi>&amp; I promised to dig and delve in hopes: so, this day I went to work, and to my surprise found the enclosed curious-looking letter—opening it, reading, &amp; also my <hi rend="underline italic">rough</hi> draft<hi rend="italic"> </hi>of a reply! <hi rend="underline italic">I was astonished</hi>:<note xml:id="ftn3-702" place="foot" n="702"> Colenso here refers to a letter from the Colonial Secretary’s office and his reply (25 July 1891 above).</note> then I sought <hi rend="italic">first</hi> for my <hi rend="italic">old</hi> Pg. Off. waste book &amp; having found therein the entries, &amp;c—I made up my mind to copy <hi rend="italic">these</hi> for you: &amp; they altogether must tell their own tale.</p>
         <p>I <hi rend="italic">have scarcely any recollection of the whole transactions</hi>!! not even w. all these various entrys to aid me: but I have little doubt that the whole lot was <hi rend="italic">the lot which Yate brought to N.Z. from Sydney—</hi>as I wrote to you some time ago—&amp; was scarcely ever used. You may copy the 2 letters, if you wish to do so, &amp; of course keep the memos. extracted. I have a <hi rend="italic">faint</hi> remembrance of Edgar, none of Kitchen; Mr Kempthorne was the C.M.S. agent at Auckland; and in “Jany 1843,” I transferred everything of Pg. Office to Mr. Telford—a young printer from Scotland, sent out by C.M.S. to succeed me <hi rend="underline italic">as Printer</hi> (only) when I went to reside with the Bp. at Waimate. Yours ever</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>Have found a few old P.O. memoranda, which I am sending on to Wgn.—<hi rend="italic">Have lost a day</hi>!</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">          Memo—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I find these old entries in my Pg. Off. waste-book:—also, monies received duly entered in Pg. Off. Ledger, &amp; accounted for:—</p>
         <p>1841.      Sold to G.A. Edgar, Printer, Kororareka, 1 fount</p>
         <p>Augt. 11   of S. Pica type, weighing 297lbs., @ 2/6.—–</p>
         <p>Type, 297lbs., @ 2/6. . . . . . . . . . . . .  £37. 2. 6</p>
         <p>                   Ink, 13½lbs, @ 3/6. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  2. 7. 3</p>
         <p>                   2 cases for type . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<hi rend="underline">.  6. 0</hi>
         </p>
         <p>                                                                                             £39.15. 9</p>
         <p>   By Bill on Bank @ 3 months</p>
         <p>                   accepted by W. Wilson . . . . . .  . . . . .  37.10. 0</p>
         <p>                                                                           Balance  <hi rend="doubleunderline underline">£  2.  5. 9</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">            Mem.</hi>Offered Press for £25.—–</p>
         <p>“Octr. 28. Received of G.A. Edgar, on a/c. C.M.S.—</p>
         <p>                   for 103lbs. Type, @ 2/6 . . . . . . . . . . . £12.17. 6</p>
         <p>                    “        13½ Ink, @ 3/6 . . . . . . . . . . . . .<hi rend="underline">.  2.  7. 3</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="doubleunderline underline">£15.  4. 9</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Mem. </hi>Cancel Type sold to Edgar, Augt. 11<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., as <lb/>                     that was returned.”</p>
         <p>1842</p>
         <p>“Feby.26.<hi rend="italic">Mem. </hi>During absence at the Southward, Rev. H. Williams lent the Printer at Kororareka Canon Roman type to compose these words, “The Bay of Islands Observer” and also a brass double rule.”</p>
         <p>“1842</p>
         <p>March 2. Kororareka Printing Company:</p>
         <p>           1 parchment Tympan skin.”</p>
         <p>“July 16. Cash of G.A. Edgar for small <lb/>                       iron printing press . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<hi rend="doubleunderline underline">£25. 0. 0.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>“Nov.2      Sold to Mr. J. Kitchen—</p>
         <p>                   194 lbs. S. Pica type, @ 2/6 . . . . . . . .£24. 5. 0</p>
         <p>                     19 lbs. ditto  ditto . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2. 7. 6</p>
         <p>                     10 lbs. quads. @ 2/- . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .1. 0. 0</p>
         <p>                     2 lbs. s. pica 3-nick, f.s. . . . . . . . . . . .<hi rend="underline">. . 5. 0</hi>
         </p>
         <p>                                                                                                   £27.17.6</p>
         <p>                                                           By Cash . . . . . . . .  20. 0.0</p>
         <p>                                                                           Balance   <hi rend="doubleunderline underline">£7.17.6</hi>
         </p>
         <p>                           for which I have his note of hand:—</p>
         <p>                           “Old imperfect type returned by Edgar.”</p>
         <p>1842. <hi rend="italic">Mem.       </hi>Sent to Mr. Kempthorne—</p>
         <p>                                   Mr. Kitchen’s Note-of-hand for  <hi rend="doubleunderline underline">£7.17.6</hi>
         </p>
         <p>                                                           Correctly copied:—</p>
         <p>                                                                                   W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
