<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0335">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1877 January 8: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1877-01-08">1877 January 8</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1877 January 8: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-282" place="foot" n="282"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand,<lb/>January 8/77.</p>
         <p>A. Luff, Esq.</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir,</p>
         <p>On the 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst. I received yours of Novr. 14<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., &amp; was glad to find you were all well. My last to you was on Decr. 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., since which several things (events) have happened, marking peculiarly our <hi rend="italic">New </hi>Year! 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. Death of Sir Donald McLean, which took place on evening of 5<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—he was buried yesterday (Sunday) amid a <hi rend="italic">large </hi>concourse of people; the grave was dug <hi rend="italic">within</hi> Barclay’s fence, &amp; close to that of Mrs B.,—it was a dreadfully hot day, &amp; the <hi rend="italic">2 long </hi>services (first, Mr. Sidey’s, &amp;, second, Mr Irvine’s, Masonic Chaplain,) were almost unbearable. Sir D. has gradually sunk; they had 4 Doctors at last about him, but it was of no service. I had a very kind note from him, written by himself, on the 14<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. ulto. (the day he left for the Station) full of hope, but he soon became worse there, &amp; returned to his own house (lately occupied by Ormond, Mrs. O. &amp; family having left for Wallingford just before Xmas.) I saw the body yesterday—face thin &amp; worn &amp; expressive of <hi rend="italic">much suffering</hi>; the poor son, who was in the Chamber of death, seemed much careworn &amp; not very strong.—A useful man is <hi rend="italic">gone</hi>; his place will not easily be filled; I hope the Natives <hi rend="italic">will act reasonably in future</hi>. On Decr. 31<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. Gowing’s son, a nice little boy, was killed by lightning in Wood’s house at Waipawa, &amp; the others had a <hi rend="italic">narrow </hi>escape.—(This was our first New Year’s day <hi rend="italic">news</hi>!) Bp. Hadfield’s son, who was at National Bank here, &amp; <hi rend="italic">much liked</hi>, died also last week, rather suddenly; believed to have been caused by rupture of an intestine in rowing! Mr. P. Bourke’s daughter Dora also died last week after only a few days’ illness,—thus, 4 deaths in the first week of New Year (&amp; others, too, unknown to us). In this evening’s Paper is a telegram announcing the destruction of Purvis Russell’s house at Woburn, by fire. Towgood, too, is gone to England! having parted from his wife (somehow)—&amp; <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the Furniture, &amp;c. are advertised to be sold without reserve next week. Willy, having <hi rend="italic">lost </hi>his trial against the Bank, has advertised his house &amp;c &amp;c for <hi rend="italic">sale</hi>,—he removing to Wairoa. In a <hi rend="italic">subsequent</hi> trial (Sup. Court here), W’s. conduct in <hi rend="italic">another </hi>matter was commented on,—and, I see, he “<hi rend="italic">resigned</hi>” his office of Curator of Intest. Estates (which took place <hi rend="italic">soon after</hi> return of the Ch. Justice to Wgn.), Banner has it now. I could not see that W. had a leg to stand on in the case between him &amp; Bank,—&amp; <hi rend="italic">expenses heavy</hi>. Nairn’s furniture, &amp;c, are to be sold tomorrow. J.N. Wilson is still in Quarantine—on an islet near Auckland—smallpox in Mail Steamer!—only think of that—<hi rend="italic">J.N.W. </hi>in Quarantine!! <hi rend="italic">George</hi> Carter (Capt. C’s. 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. son) is married to Brooke Taylor’s <hi rend="italic">3</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">rd</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. daur.</hi>—and Alfred, his brother, is (I hear) to marry <hi rend="italic">another</hi>! <hi rend="italic">I</hi> don’t like it.</p>
         <p>The Municipal Corporation, voted the Mayor ₤<hi rend="italic">200</hi>. as <hi rend="italic">honorarium</hi> (he <hi rend="italic">present</hi>, who took it, as “all right!”) 16 poor souls were brought up today for <hi rend="italic">Rates</hi>! they all have to pay with 5/- ea. expenses.—Newton has been obliged to resign—as a Contractor (“Dy. Telegraph”—which has <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the printing now, for both Genl. Govt, &amp; Borough! so that Carlile &amp; Co, are ½ mad!!) C. &amp; Co. have so abused N. Ky &amp; Knowles, that writs for libel have been served on C. &amp; Co., damages ₤1000. each!! (some of <hi rend="italic">our </hi>New Year’s fun!) There was rather strong excitement in some places over the County Council elections (<hi rend="italic">viz</hi>. Waipukurau, Waipawa &amp; West Clive), Sy Johnston beat H.R.R. at Waipuk., Rathbone &amp; Laurence &amp; Herrick beat Buchanan, McLean (Gwavas) &amp; Dr. Stokes (B. was nowhere, &amp; <hi rend="italic">rightly served.</hi>) &amp; Whitmore beat Sutton at Clive: Sutton was next to mad! (H.R.R. but little better) &amp; both Sutton &amp; H.R.R. have commenced law proceedings!!! I much fear that some of our County Councils may act foolishly; if so, they will <hi rend="italic">retard </hi>our prosperity. Of course another new election for Napier will soon come off, &amp;, no doubt, His Worship the Mayor will be in the field,—also (I hear) F. Sutton! &amp; there may be others. If <hi rend="italic">this old man </hi>is <hi rend="underline italic">offered support</hi> he will try it, <hi rend="italic">not else</hi>. The Mayor was to have given a grand public Ball on night of 5<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., great preparations were making at Oddfellows Hall,—even putting up additional <hi rend="italic">rooms</hi> outside,—I may say (to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>) that we stopped it on <hi rend="italic">that </hi>day as Sir D. was dying; the M. told me, that some of the <hi rend="italic">Invitees</hi> had said, Who is he, that the Ball should be delayed? &amp;c. &amp;c.—(I <hi rend="italic">felt</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">grieved</hi>: what a world we live in!). Two or three things have tended to make me sorrowful <hi rend="italic">today</hi>,<lb/>1.<hi rend="italic">this day </hi>24 years ago, my house at Waitangi &amp; its contents were burnt;<lb/>2.<hi rend="italic">this day</hi> 24 years ago, McL. bought this spot (Scinde Island) of the Natives;<lb/>3. Gollan &amp; self talked<hi rend="italic">feelingly</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">re</hi> McLean yesterday: O—d. was dreadfully cut up, because (w. Dr. Grace) purposely in the “Stella” to <hi rend="italic">see McL.</hi>, but he was too far gone to talk—or to hear anything! O. is just gone to Wallingford, &amp; will remove w. wife &amp; family shortly to Wgn.</p>
         <p>I think I must have told you in my last, that I had written <hi rend="italic">plainly </hi>to O. about my office, &amp;c, &amp;c,—pressing for a definite ansr., <hi rend="italic">one way or t’other</hi>, by 31<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. Decr.; this I have <hi rend="italic">not</hi> yet got, I <hi rend="italic">wish I had</hi>; but “he will <hi rend="italic">see me before he </hi>goes S.,”—we shall see.—</p>
         <p>I have <hi rend="italic">not</hi> see P. Dolb. since my last, &amp; am sorry at this: the more so as McKay has been served w. a writ (debt), &amp; I can not get any thing from <hi rend="italic">him</hi>! (How shall I <hi rend="italic">act there</hi>?) Bibby is at me, for ½ dividing fence at Waipawa, which, of course, I must pay. I suppose, I shall have to go round money <hi rend="italic">seeking </hi>shortly: I hate it. The Ormonds testimonial is likely, I think, to succeed, R. Stokes (so M.S.T. says)—spoiled it by <hi rend="italic">his </hi>maxm. &amp; minm. ₤3.3.0 and 10/-. I note what you say about Witty &amp; the dividg. fence, &amp; sections, &amp; will see him shortly: he only returned today from Wairoa. I have been a bit <hi rend="italic">sad </hi>w. Jens Neilson’s affair: I told you in my last, I had written to him; well, in my absence (schools) the enclosed letter came from N., when Xmas. (<hi rend="italic">lawyer’s </hi>holidays) was over, I went to Lascelles to see the sd. Deed,—&amp; was told that “<hi rend="underline italic">2</hi> months ago <hi rend="italic">your agent </hi>Mr Cotterill, acting <hi rend="italic">under p. of attorney from you</hi>, got the Deed from L. to send to England”!!! Of course I was <hi rend="italic">obliged</hi> to tell N. this:—he did not like it, &amp; it <hi rend="italic">looks</hi> ugly. Dr Gibbes’ <hi rend="italic">new</hi> house is begun. F.Sutton has a <hi rend="italic">mansion</hi>! at Mangateretere W., where he now lives. I only saw it on Saturday. Tanner’s <hi rend="italic">grounds</hi> (trees, &amp;c.) are looking <hi rend="italic">well</hi>. I went to see Sturm on Saty. last—for the <hi rend="italic">first </hi>time; he <hi rend="italic">deserves </hi>more support than he gets. Our Ch-of-Engld. <hi rend="italic">dissentions</hi> are still going on—worse, I think, than ever! I saw Mr Sidey last week, &amp; we talked; he was looking remarkably well; I remembered <hi rend="italic">you</hi> to him. Fannin is elected Clerk to H. Bay County Council, ₤100. pr. an. to begin (<hi rend="italic">soon</hi> to be ₤200.) so he will <hi rend="italic">now </hi>do. The rainy weather in Decr. hindered me much, so that I only finished my last school on 22<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. returning <hi rend="italic">tired</hi> on evg. of 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>., but <hi rend="italic">to work</hi> on Xmas. day, boxing-day, Sundays &amp; New Year’s day<hi rend="italic">s</hi>—until all Teachers’ accounts were ready for Edn. Board.—But <hi rend="italic">I</hi> will <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be servant-of-all-work much longer. O—d. is now Mr. of Public Works. “Helen Denny” left yesterday w. several passengers,—hope she may arrive safely; but I have heard fears expressed (inland &amp; elsewhere) of <hi rend="italic">wet wool</hi>. </p>
         <p>I have not yet opened all your Papers, I send you some as usual. Had O. <hi rend="italic">decided</hi> (one way or t’other) I could have told you <hi rend="italic">more</hi>: <hi rend="italic">several </hi>immigrants still in Barracks, able-bodied men, too,—who are much discontented, &amp; here is the “Fern glen” coming with <hi rend="italic">more</hi>! Grubb is very well. I saw <hi rend="italic">J. </hi>Dinwiddie last week, he was well. So good bye, once more, &amp; </p>
         <p>Believe me, Yours truly, Wm. Colenso</p>
         <p>No.2                                 Jany. 9<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. 1877</p>
         <p>I thought I had helped <hi rend="italic">you </hi>to <hi rend="italic">your share</hi> of the pie—last night, but I am at it again!—</p>
         <p>I have been thinking of you (as I often am), and I find I have not replied to a portion of your letter:—with reference to your Wairoa Sections, I purpose going thither in Feby. (if I <hi rend="italic">continue </hi>to hold my off. of Inspector) and then, on the spot, I will make enquiries.—My 2 Sections (399 &amp; 400) near Harbour, are still <hi rend="italic">unbroken</hi>; I don’t greatly care about selling them <hi rend="italic">just now</hi>—what will you offer for them? I have lately had Ellis (Brewer), Miler (Railway) &amp; others enquiring after an allotment on the hill—I have told them pretty nearly what I sent you; Canning, Gollan, &amp; others, are coming after shearing. Robjohns has <hi rend="italic">hindered </hi>the opening of Tennyson St., (S. end); I had heard he would and w. election coming off the Mayor cannot afford to offend <hi rend="italic">R. &amp; his party</hi>.—I have also lately heard of a trial <hi rend="italic">impending</hi>, between G. Hunter &amp; Blair’s widow’s <hi rend="italic">husband</hi> relative to his property of Robjohns’ late Blair’s.</p>
         <p>The National Bank gave ₤1000. for the <hi rend="italic">little</hi> corner! where Lee’s office was!! there is to be a fine building there, which (with the new Masonic at the other corner) will cause Tuxford to build!—</p>
         <p>I note what you say about Barraud’s Book: the Govt. got it “<hi rend="italic">hot &amp; heavy</hi>” for subscribing so <hi rend="italic">much</hi> to it: it was Vogel’s wild doing. I thought the Govt. richly deserved it: it was a counterpart of their doing <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Buller’s compilation—N.Z. Birds,—which was not wanted. Barraud, again, is <hi rend="italic">truly himself </hi>in all that matter!</p>
         <p>Young Lascelles (the little wee fellow) has left his father’s house, &amp; Bray takes him up—as a husband for his daughter.—15!!</p>
         <p>I went <hi rend="italic">purposely </hi>last friday, to see Bray about it; had a long talk w. them (2) B. &amp; wife: I hope my visit will not be in vain—but I fear—<hi rend="italic">Tempus omnia revelat.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Carter’s 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. son is going w. the Heslops (Jr.) to learn the art &amp; mystery of Station life; may he do well.—</p>
         <p>This mg. appears Carlile’s <hi rend="italic">first </hi>article in favour of Mr Mayor—as our Member—if he will cut adrift from the malignant Repudiation party!—I have heard that Carlile is about to marry! It is time (if at all) for he is getting greyer &amp; thinner than ever!! Miss Harvey has resigned the U.M. Town School; &amp; Mrs Carr has done the same at Meeanee—going today to Tauranga (Bay Plenty) to her daughter Mrs Gascoigne: Miss Cooney is to have the Meeanee School.—</p>
         <p>The men are still at work on my corner section (108) having been <hi rend="italic">hindered </hi>by so much rain in Decr., they may finish this week; it will be a good site for a House. the old ragged mound is nearly gone!</p>
         <p>I have written a letter to W. Wesley Bookseller, 28 Essex St. Strand, contg. also a draft for ₤35, for some Books for our H.B. Phil. Institute, &amp; sent him a copy of Rules w. our Members’ names. Had O. decided, &amp;, <hi rend="italic">in so doing</hi>, decided me! <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to return to Engd. then I should have asked you to ex. a little commission for me w. my old Agents—Dixon &amp; Co., Fenchurch St.,—this must stand over.—(Grubb told me this day, he could <hi rend="italic">not </hi>write you this time).</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Evening</hi>: I now close. Our Eng. Mail is off tomorrow overland to Wgn. I have had several visitors today who have hindered me a little. Among them—Mr Grant, the School Mr., on a tour returning from Wgn. by Coach; he is looking <hi rend="italic">well</hi>, &amp; has a good school (130) at Onehunga &amp; Mrs Grant another, about same: it was very kind of him to call on me—this <hi rend="italic">very hot day </hi>too! He leaves this evening. In Telegraph of this evening—5 Candidates are named! Rhodes, Tiffen, Buchanan, Stuart, &amp; Sutton: Sutton’s address is to be out tomorrow! The Mayor gives his <hi rend="italic">great </hi>Ball <hi rend="italic">tonight.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>     Good bye, Yours ever,   W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>