<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0851">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 November 18: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-11-18">1892 November 18</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 November 18: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-623" place="foot" n="623"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke, Novr. 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>/ 92.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I did not intend to write to you <hi rend="italic">this week</hi>, but, on considn., I see, if I do not do so, I fear I shall <hi rend="italic">not </hi>have time next wk., <hi rend="italic">neither </hi>(perhaps) the wk. <hi rend="italic">after</hi>,—so here goes. Tomorrow I go for the <hi rend="italic">last time </hi>to Woodville, and I have long promised myself a day or two there—to see the Gorge, tunnell, &amp;c &amp;c, &amp; to make a few calls: I am not sure of retg. to N. next wk., I may do so, &amp; then comes Eng. Mail—also, our Sy. Meeting on 28<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—but I don’t care (<hi rend="italic">now</hi>) at being present. This aftn. I recd. a letter from Hill, who is back at Napier,—informing me he will be at Makotuku on Monday &amp; Tuesday, &amp; will come on here to spend evg. w. me, if I am disengaged, &amp;c. I have written saying, I will wire to him from Woodville, early next wk.—– Mrs. Eccles &amp; family are <hi rend="italic">there </hi>now; &amp; E. was there on Sunday last: I saw him on platform here on Monday (in his returning to Waipawa) and he gave me to understand, there is to be a social meeting <hi rend="italic">there </hi>on <hi rend="italic">Thursday</hi> next—to welcome him &amp; to say <hi rend="italic">Adieu</hi> to me! and the Dean, on his way back from Wgn, is expected to be present: however I told Eccles, I should <hi rend="italic">not </hi>wait there until Thursday doing <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi>! to return hither on Friday afternoon:—we shall see.—</p>
         <p>Yesterday (17<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) I made my <hi rend="italic">long </hi>journey! away to the Bush beyond Tahorati plain, E. My dear <hi rend="italic">old</hi> haunt! whither I had <hi rend="italic">not </hi>gone for ’92!! it is, at least, about 2½ miles, so, thither &amp; back including sinuous wanderings, must be 5–6m., occupying from I.30 to IV.30, p.m., I was however completely knocked up before I rejoined my lodgings, &amp; only did last mile w. <hi rend="italic">difficulty</hi>.—and as a consequence this day I have been <hi rend="italic">idle</hi>! or next door to it. I should not like to pass such another fortnight as this <hi rend="italic">last</hi>, such a horrid waste of valuable time—&amp; so <hi rend="italic">much to do</hi> at Napier: I am keeping pretty well—always excepting these <hi rend="italic">remains </hi>of Influenza w. Rheum, so that I scarcely know an hour without pain—still fixed in my rt. shoulder, sometimes arm &amp; wrist, &amp; <hi rend="italic">worse at nights.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I duly recd yours of 13<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. &amp; since then your <hi rend="italic">kit </hi>of clippings: but why <hi rend="italic">these</hi>—of Uganda (of which I have seen too much in “Standard”)—and of the Bordeaux Wine Mchb.? I send you some, enclosed. Your long <hi rend="italic">former </hi>clipping of Mr. D. Lewis, was overlooked by me through your putting it <hi rend="italic">into </hi>Shortland’s Bk. it is interesting &amp; pleasing—but there is an anachronism in it, where the writer (a Wesleyn. Minister, I fancy,) in speaking of D.L. being designed for the <hi rend="italic">Ch. of Engd</hi>.—calls it “the <hi rend="italic">Anglican</hi> Clergy”! this hateful term is a <hi rend="italic">modern </hi>one: then there is mention of Rev. <hi rend="italic">Walter</hi> Buller <hi rend="italic">for James</hi> B.—Have you seen a copy of Wright’s letter to Ballance <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Hautumu Island, as a kind of Ark for <hi rend="italic">all </hi>N.Z. Fauna &amp; Flora? Wright sent me a copy—but <hi rend="italic">no reply </hi>from me. Capt. Preece’s wind-up is a <hi rend="italic">sad </hi>one. W.C. Smith was here a few days ago w. Cadman—they passed me but w. <hi rend="italic">averted </hi>look. What you say of Sturm &amp; Mao. Rat is, in <hi rend="italic">great measure, new </hi>to me. I send you a part of a “Standard” I had set <hi rend="italic">aside for you </hi>3 wks. ago, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Whittier, &amp; only found it today—it will interest you. Will you allow me to take on Shortland’s little B.R. with me to Napier—&amp; return (say) by end of December? I had said, Have you a <hi rend="italic">copy </hi>of that paper of mine on Mao. Dog (vol. X Trans.)? If you <hi rend="italic">have</hi>, then return the one I sent you, but if you have <hi rend="italic">not</hi>, keep it. I sent you “Herald,” w. my letter <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Rothschild: in “Evg. News” of <hi rend="italic">that date</hi>—<hi rend="italic">I have got it </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">hot &amp; heavy</hi>!! &amp;, <hi rend="italic">again</hi>, last evg. Snazelle wrote a dreadful letter against Rev. Mr. Paterson &amp; another in “Herald” of 17<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.,<note xml:id="ftn3-624" place="foot" n="624"> Snazelle was an entertainer who held Sunday concerts with song, poetry, literature and displays of paintings. See <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> 1 November 1892.</note> “<hi rend="italic">E. News</hi>,” same date, has taken it up <hi rend="italic">well</hi>: &amp; so others in “Herald” of <hi rend="italic">this </hi>day.—Will seek to obtain copies for you.</p>
         <p>Hope your firm’s troubles are over.</p>
         <p>I am tired—arm painful—write slowly. Yours truly. <lb/>                              W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>23/XI/92 </p>
         <p>Retd, fm. Wdv.—<hi rend="underline italic">finished</hi> work <hi rend="italic">there. </hi>hasten to fulfil promise—send you 5p., recd. from Craig—but <hi rend="italic">none </hi>of E.N. 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>!! (hope you may have <hi rend="italic">seen it</hi>—if not will <hi rend="underline italic">lend</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>you my copy). Will write from N.—next wk. W.C.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
