<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0483">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1882 February 8: to Balfour</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73378/">Balfour</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1882-02-08">1882 February 8</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1882 February 8: to Balfour<note xml:id="ftn3-121" place="foot" n="121"> ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier Feb 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1882</p>
         <p>Mr D.P. Balfour</p>
         <p>Dear Sir</p>
         <p>Believe anything of me, rather than its being “out of sight, out of mind” with you. Such is not the case; indeed I could not have succee­ded had I tried that game—for your name (apart from your letters) has been often <hi rend="italic">read</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">written</hi> by me of late; only this day I addressed a “D.T.” to you, containing a brief account of our annual meeting. One thing you may learn from it, that our little (and one time despised) Society is now firm &amp; flourishing. Twelve new members this week, &amp; among them, our Mayor (Pro­vost or Head Baillie) Vautier, Hon J.N. Wilson, Mr Pat. Stirling McLean, Mr Tanners eldest son, Mr Moorhouse, &amp;c.</p>
         <p>The “Report” is in printers hands &amp; I hope to send you one <hi rend="italic">next</hi> week. I have been <hi rend="italic">very busy</hi> about this clan, or ship, almost too much so, for my health, but I hope now for a holiday, &amp; then, Awa to the woods, &amp; green braes. I duly received your two letters(&amp; chq.) of 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Jan, &amp; 23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Jan &amp; was glad to find you and yours were then well—may this find you all so. Your kindly remembered subscription came early (comparatively), and is now a long way ahead of <hi rend="italic">a lot</hi>.</p>
         <p>We have been trying it hard of late to have a room of our own, <hi rend="italic">wholly</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">entirely</hi> so; and we are prepared even to build, but then we must be <hi rend="underline italic">near</hi> to the Athenæum, so as to be under the <hi rend="italic">one</hi> caretaker. Up to the present we cannot get the Athn Committee to agree to <hi rend="italic">our terms</hi>, or even to approach them; and they stand out for <hi rend="italic">too much</hi>; but we <hi rend="italic">will accomplish</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">it</hi> somehow. I am glad that Mr Kinross is again elected to our Council;—I fought hard to be allowed to <hi rend="italic">retire</hi>, but it was “no go”; indeed, when appealed to, I was obliged to confess that I knew not of a <hi rend="italic">substitute</hi> among us.</p>
         <p>It is said, that old Elijah <hi rend="italic">found</hi> a young Elijah—on whom to throw his mantle—I am not so lucky. If I had only a little help on <hi rend="italic">days</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">of meeting</hi> it would not be quite so heavy as it now is.</p>
         <p>I have not seen my old friend P. Dolbel for the year (save once, passing in town). Here, at <hi rend="italic">present</hi>, dark &amp; gloomy, &amp; sultry, &amp; dry; should like to see rain. With kind regards</p>
         <p>             Believe me ever</p>
         <p>                             Yours sincerely</p>
         <p>                                             W. Colenso</p>
         <p>P.S. Don’t hurry or trouble yourself about your <hi rend="italic">Fuchsia</hi> blossoms; <hi rend="italic">all</hi> in­sects you meet with, pop into a bottle into a little whiskey.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>