<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0914">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1894 October 24: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1894-10-24">1894 October 24</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1894 October 24: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-703" place="foot" n="703"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke, Octr. 24/94</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>I am not sure that I <hi rend="italic">owe </hi>you a letter, but as I am <hi rend="italic">here</hi> (idle!) on my way back to N., and next week is S.F. Mail one, I have better write to you <hi rend="italic">now</hi>. </p>
         <p>I left N. for Woodville last Saturday, <hi rend="italic">mainly </hi>to give 2 sittings to Lindauer for his portrait—which Hony. Secy. D. had informed <hi rend="underline italic">him</hi>, “<hi rend="italic">must </hi>be ready &amp; w. him <hi rend="italic">4 days before </hi>next meeting of our Institute”—but I had heard <hi rend="italic">nothing </hi>from D. about it, it seems as if they would take me by surprise! I came hither, to spend 2 days on my way to Waipawa—there 1 day, &amp; on Saty. to N.—but Robertshawe is gone to Palmerston Show of Stock. Before I left N. I sent you a copy of Rayner’s Caricatures! I may say before I had gone through the booklet myself: it was pubd. on Wednesday 7<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. I was in town for 2 hours only on 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> purchd. 3 copies, &amp; came away by xii o’clock ’bus—to call on Bp. Stuart’s family on the hill. On <hi rend="italic">Friday</hi>—2 letters appeared in the Herald re Rayner’s work—1, that R. should be horsewhipped for his attack on ladies; &amp; 1, expressing regret, &amp;c, that Craig should have so lowered himself as to publish such a scurrilous work, &amp;c—and, on Saturday, a statement, that Craig would sell no more, &amp; was calling-in all copies from vendors.—I have <hi rend="italic">since </hi>found that I am not quite so badly used—in <hi rend="italic">words</hi>, though the caricature is vile! but <hi rend="italic">why </hi>I should have been pilloried w. Swan &amp; Carnell, &amp; Co. I cannot understand. I should add that R. saw <hi rend="italic">your </hi>article, &amp;c, in Chicago P., &amp; admired execution.<note xml:id="ftn3-704" place="foot" n="704">
               <hi rend="italic">Fred Rayner’s Sketch Book of 50 Caricatures “Things You see when Your out without Your Gun” in Napier, Hastings, &amp; Waipawa</hi>. Lithographed by Brown, Thomson &amp; Co, Wellington.</note>—</p>
         <p>On my arriving here last night, I found the Wgn. p. you had kindly sent me; contg. Atkinson’s, &amp; Archdn. L.W’s. letters; <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Tregear’s wk. I have no doubt that the Archdn. is correct <hi rend="italic">re </hi>T’s. knowledge of <hi rend="italic">Maori</hi>—such was always my opinion, apart from his book, of which I know nothing.—And I think that the Governors N.Z. Inst. should publish Atkinson’s paper—now that they published (<hi rend="italic">again</hi>) Quatrefages’ old <hi rend="italic">printed </hi>one. I have to get a paper ready for our next (&amp; last) meeting.—</p>
         <p>I enclose an advt., which <hi rend="italic">may </hi>make you wonder! I can no longer stand the paying of <hi rend="italic">heavy rates &amp; taxes </hi>on unoccupied T. Sns., better to sell <hi rend="italic">at a loss</hi> &amp; have done w. them: I ought to have disposed of them <hi rend="italic">years ago</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I see, in today’s paper, that McDougall of “Herald” is to be the future Ed. of “Dy.T.”!!! wonders will never cease. The <hi rend="italic">late </hi>Ed. was certainly a clever well-read man: I liked many of his articles. Mr. Sidey spoke well of him to me.—</p>
         <p>I had the mg. S. at Cathedl. on 14<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>—a very large congn.—almost appalled me—to walk up through such a dense mass: text Col. III. 17: evg. S. at Augustine’s, &amp; Bradbury at Cathedral.—</p>
         <p>Rather peculiar the 2 Editors dying nearly together, &amp; just so the 2 old Meeanee Settlers—Heslop &amp; Hallett: I went to Hallett’s funeral: of course you knew him: his sons were there &amp; they told me, their mother had borne the terrible shock as well as could be expected. There w. you at Wgn. you are soon to have high Ch. doings—it is <hi rend="italic">said</hi>, that L.W. may also be “consecrated” there at same time. I cannot say <hi rend="italic">I like </hi>the Governor taking-in the <hi rend="italic">English party</hi> to lodge &amp; board. I see by “<hi rend="italic">Examiner</hi>” of this day, that W.W.C. will <hi rend="italic">cease </hi>as Edr. of “Evg. Press” at end of this month: also, <hi rend="italic">anther </hi>Wgn. P. will be discontinued.</p>
         <p>The weather here, &amp; at Napier, &amp; at <hi rend="italic">Woodville</hi>!! for <hi rend="italic">3 weeks </hi>has been very fine: there is a prodigious <hi rend="italic">show</hi> of blossom everywhere on fruit trees, indicating plenty—may such be realized! I have been keeping well—<hi rend="italic">feeling </hi>old age, &amp; Rheumatism at times: today however symptoms of sore throat, which, with coughs, is common <hi rend="italic">here</hi>. Good bye kindest regards to all</p>
         <p>           Yours ever sincerely,</p>
         <p>                                                           W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. Have had <hi rend="italic">no </hi>papers sent inland to me.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">No. 2.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. I closed my letter to you late last night (having had 2 visitors), and in bed I recollected <hi rend="italic">another </hi>small item <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the old ptg. p., which I had, at N., determined to tell <hi rend="italic">you</hi>.</p>
         <p>In further rummaging for old Post.O. spoils for Robertson G.P.O. (who, by the way, seems a nice fellow, writes <hi rend="italic">good manly </hi>letters free from “fads”, &amp;c.) I came on a wee <hi rend="italic">home-</hi>made Memo. Book, &amp; one of the first items therein—date, “<hi rend="italic">Jany</hi>. <hi rend="italic">1835</hi>”—was, “recd. from Genl. Store at Kerikeri—a lot of loose type, 1 pair cases, &amp; a ptg. press”!!!—and to this hour I have <hi rend="italic">no recollection </hi>of the said “press”: it must have been a <hi rend="italic">small </hi>one as it was <hi rend="italic">together </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">in a case</hi>. Now at Paihia, my <hi rend="italic">first </hi>residence, for several months I had <hi rend="italic">no </hi>house or “whare” of my own—<hi rend="italic">my </hi>room (<hi rend="italic">pro tem</hi>) was the wee “vestry room” (so-called) of the Mission chapel—a small portion of a long <hi rend="italic">low </hi>“lean-to”, wh. ran the length of chapel, &amp; was only 5 feet high at entrance side, the major part being used as an Infants’ school-room, and outside my window the <hi rend="italic">cemetery</hi>!!</p>
         <p>Mr. Baker (Eb’s. pater) was the <hi rend="italic">store-keeper </hi>of Paihia station, &amp; in his big store the said big box of type, &amp;c., was deposited—where it stood undisturbed for years! <hi rend="italic">all </hi>I can recollect is, the mass of shining new type (<hi rend="italic">pie</hi>) in that case, w. 2 or 3 “pages” of letters in brown paper among it—&amp; even this is very shadowy.—</p>
         <p>And I have been thinking that <hi rend="italic">this press</hi> is the one that the Maoris now have in the Bay, (according to Winkelmann, &amp; <hi rend="italic">his </hi>informant,) this they could have <hi rend="italic">easily </hi>obtained (by plunder or purchase) from Kororareka, &amp; <hi rend="italic">not </hi>either of my 2 (Stanhope, &amp; Columbian— “Eagle”) from Bp. Selwyn’s Parnell, Auckland—whither these were taken a few <hi rend="italic">weeks</hi> after I had left the Bay. Moreover, in my ptg. off. Ledger (wh. I was allowed by the N. Missionaries to retain) I find <hi rend="italic">all </hi>sales only entered &amp; accounted for: I <hi rend="italic">should </hi>have looked therein <hi rend="italic">earlier</hi>, had I remembered the transactions, as this big book was always out—loose, &amp; handy in my back-room y’clepd “Library”. I hope this may <hi rend="italic">interest you</hi>.</p>
         <p>   I feel better this mg.; would I were at N.!</p>
         <p>           Good bye,<hi rend="italic">again</hi>, Yrs. sincerely,  W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
