<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0881">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1893 September 3: to Wiremu Colenso</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL Ms-papers-10535-1.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/74618/">Wiremu Colenso</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1893-09-03">1893 September 3</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1893 September 3: to Wiremu Colenso<note xml:id="ftn3-658" place="foot" n="658"> ATL Ms-papers-10535-1.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand,<lb/>September 3/93,</p>
         <p>My dear son Willie</p>
         <p>I think you &amp; Sarah will be surprised on receiving this letter,—at the size of the envelope! and no doubt the contents are most important to you both. I believe, that in my last I mentioned what I had in hand for you, but I did not <hi rend="italic">then </hi>know of these <hi rend="italic">forms</hi>—which came to hand last week, from London per Brindisi Mail. At first sight of them, I feared I should have some difficulty—as I must get some “disinterested Person” to make the required “declaration,” and such must have known you from “10 to 15 years of age”: I thought on Fannin, Newton, Tiffen, Dr. Hitchings,—but would one of them <hi rend="italic">willingly</hi> undertake the job? &amp; go with the Notary before our Chief Magistrate &amp; sign the form.—At last, I thought on our friend Knowles, and he very lovingly undertook to do it—I filling-in the Govt. form: all this extra trouble occurs in <hi rend="italic">your</hi> case, through the loss of the Ch. Register—which was burnt in Noa’s house on Ngaruroro <hi rend="italic">after</hi> it had been handed over by me to Rev. S. Williams, (who succeeded me here) and who had left it in Noa’s charge. Read it (the <hi rend="italic">form</hi> for you to sign) well: and when Sarah (or you) receives the Certificate from London (which she sent me last year and which I had sent in July to London, to our friend there,) then do you both go to some J.P. in Penzance, and sign the Declaration before him, writing yr. n. in full, <hi rend="italic">William Colenso Junior, </hi>and he will attach his official signature and you will have to send both forms to London. It is all a very simple matter for you and for Sarah: the J.P. has <hi rend="italic">no questions to ask</hi>, but <hi rend="italic">merely to witness </hi>your &amp; Sarah’s declarations, that you are the 2 persons therein mentioned. Keep them clean, especially the <hi rend="italic">first </hi>page, as this page our friend in London will fill in for us, &amp; also do all the rest. And take care of the seals, on yours, and when you make them up in the <hi rend="italic">Registered </hi>Envelope for London, see you <hi rend="italic">do not</hi> put the seal under the stamps-corner.—I have written to our London friend, Mr. Brock, to send to you those Certificates of Sarah’s, which must be appended to page 2 of her form <hi rend="italic">before </hi>that she can sign it, as it is referred to in page 3. I have long known Mr. Brock, and Mrs. Tucker<note xml:id="ftn3-659" place="foot" n="659"> Colenso’s sister Jane Emily.</note> too knows him <hi rend="italic">well</hi>: enquire of her. You will notice, on page 4, that the Annuities are paid <hi rend="italic">quarterly</hi> by the Government: I do not know whether we may be in time for the <hi rend="italic">first </hi>quarter mentioned, January, but that information you will get from Mr. Brock, when he has completed paying-in the money to the Government; and I think that Mrs. Tucker will be able to tell you much about how those payments are managed, because she receives her little annuity that way.—And now I think I have told you <hi rend="italic">all </hi>about it.—–</p>
         <p>My last to you was (closed) on 7<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. August,—since then yours of July 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>, is to hand. The time since my last has flown rapidly away; I have been <hi rend="italic">here</hi>—at pump or wheel—ever since working away, and have been on the whole <hi rend="italic">very well</hi>. Have been to town say ½ doz. times, weather of late fine: trees &amp; shrubs on all sides coming into leaf &amp; bloom. I have not had any Ch. duty to perform during the past month: and have been to St. Augustine’s on Sundays to hear Canon Fox,—I was there <hi rend="italic">this morning</hi>, it being such a fine day. Canon Fox will only hold service there <hi rend="italic">once </hi>more, as he is returning to Poverty Bay: I have been to see him 2–3 times, and like him much, he is such a dear humble retired man—and a first-rate Scholar; he is not so much at Home <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, for his people do not appreciate him. A Mr Bradbury, from Wellington, is coming in his stead in October. I am thinking of taking a run into the <hi rend="italic">Bush</hi> about the end of this month, but not to make any long stay, having no Ch. wk. there this year. I have only seen the Bp. once, &amp; then I met with him in town (at “Newton’s Corner”), we walked together and chatted for about 5 minutes, but he has been much away inland—1 Sunday at Dvk., &amp; 1 Sy. at Woodville, &amp; he only returned to Napier on Friday night (1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. inst.) Mr Robertshawe came to N. a fortnight ago, and staid to <hi rend="italic">dinner</hi> w. me (pot luck!)—a very rare occurrence! He wished to <hi rend="italic">sleep here</hi> but I could not well agree to that, as those 2 rooms are <hi rend="italic">lumber</hi> rooms, &amp; no one has slept in them since you left, &amp; I have no spare bedding, and it was not worth while, buying and routing for <hi rend="italic">one </hi>night; he was again very well. I felt <hi rend="italic">bothered </hi>(as I told Mr. K.) <hi rend="italic">what</hi> “profession or occupation” to set down for <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, I <hi rend="italic">would</hi> I knew of <hi rend="italic">something</hi> decent. I thought of, “old salt,” or “retired seaman,” or “disabled,” or “laid up in ordinary,” &amp; a doz. other things: an old sailor (man-o-war’s man) that I knew in Penz., used to make little nets (6d. each) “kips” for boiling potatoes in—but I fear you are not advanced as far as that; and so I was obliged to write— “gentleman,” (otherwise, Idler.) Of course when you send the forms to Mr. Brock write a nice short note with them, but I dare say he will write to you. I send some Papers, as usual. Mr. Hill, Inspr. Schools, is about to leave N., having been appointed <hi rend="italic">Head</hi> Inspector of the Auckland District. I shall not feel his leaving much, as he rarely ever comes now to see me; but then I don’t go to see him, he lives far away—<hi rend="italic">last</hi> house on Bluff hill, overlooking Breakwater, and to go there, &amp; return, by “Cab” costs me 5/-—<hi rend="italic">I cannot walk it</hi>. I sent (once more!) the <hi rend="italic">first </hi>part of Maori-Eng. Lexn. to Govt., but I have not yet heard from them: I could have cried over it, (in reviewing it,) for I found that my knowledge of Maori is <hi rend="italic">now </hi>very small! through <hi rend="italic">non</hi>-usage, and <hi rend="italic">age</hi>: my memory is failing me fast: my time for <hi rend="italic">all such work, </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">is gone forever</hi>. Here in garden flowg. nicely are 2 plants of Kowhai ngutukaakaa—the <hi rend="italic">N. </hi>species, which is a brighter purer red than the S. one: I wonder <hi rend="italic">which</hi> is yours, or do you possess <hi rend="italic">both</hi> sorts? Latty has them. If you do <hi rend="italic">not</hi>—then put up 1 flower of yours into the <hi rend="italic">Plymouth</hi> P. that I may know; there is a fine plant of the S. kind now in full bloom in Cl. Sq., 6 ft. high; it grew to a large size at old <hi rend="italic">Waitangi</hi>.</p>
         <p>I note what you say about <hi rend="italic">kumara</hi>, &amp;, if I live, will send you some roots next season—but, unfortunately, such are not ripe till March (late) or April, &amp; then might not reach you in time for planting, and so of <hi rend="italic">pumpkin</hi> seeds—<hi rend="italic">these</hi>, however, you shall have in time. If you still have my book, printed here—“<hi rend="italic">Fiat Justitia</hi>,”—you will find <hi rend="italic">in it</hi> about poor Te Kooti, also some of his <hi rend="italic">prayers</hi>, when in trouble, translated by me: if you have it not, let me know, I have spare copies. I am pleased at <hi rend="italic">your</hi> feeling for <hi rend="underline italic">him</hi>, and so does Latty.—–I note what you <hi rend="italic">now</hi> say concerning the rude behaviour of little May to <hi rend="italic">you</hi> when at “No.8”: I am sorry to hear of it, but you <hi rend="italic">should have told me of it at the time</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">more besides</hi>: at the same time, one must not forget, that she was then <hi rend="italic">very young</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">I</hi> should not like for her (<hi rend="italic">in England</hi>) to call you “<hi rend="italic">Willie</hi>”: such would be quite the thing <hi rend="italic">out here</hi>. What did Maud call you? or how address you? (But never mind, those are things long past.) L’s. <hi rend="italic">last</hi> letter I do not like at all: and he has got a <hi rend="italic">long</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">plain</hi> one from me.</p>
         <p>As to your “Indigestion”: I am pretty sure it is to be placed to 2–3 things:—1. want of <hi rend="italic">sufficient good </hi>exercise: 2. <hi rend="italic">too great use </hi>of tobacco: 3. and (perhaps) tea, or coffee, or bacon &amp; eggs, or some food—pastry, pancakes, ’taty-cake, “sweets,” disagreeing with you, <hi rend="italic">try to find it out </hi>yourself and <hi rend="italic">don’t</hi> go to Doctors, neither be taking medicine now &amp; then.</p>
         <p>I cannot help thinking (or <hi rend="italic">believing</hi>) that the serious attack of Influenza I had last year, has, in some way, fought the <hi rend="italic">older </hi>Rheumatism! I cannot account for it, but so it is: I have very little Rheum. now, &amp; <hi rend="italic">now &amp; then</hi> a “touch-up” of Infl. remainders in my feet; but I am marvelously better than I was this time last year, &amp; yet I was then inland <hi rend="italic">working</hi>! <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">has been</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">is</hi>! <hi rend="italic">good to me</hi>. Lat’s. Rheumatic “Electric Belt” (which I ordered &amp; pd. for) &amp; your Medicine so kindly sent,—are still <hi rend="underline italic">unopened</hi>! I suppose the owl was attracted by the light, no curtain ever down at the end garden window; very often in writing a bird comes on bang! but not such a broadside as that owl. Once at Waitangi, by daylight, those 2 windows in the dear old “study” being opposite, a Kingfisher came bang <hi rend="italic">through</hi> one, smashing the pane! &amp; flew over to the other; but then <hi rend="italic">he </hi>has such a <hi rend="italic">ram</hi> of a beak!!</p>
         <p>I should again tell you, that you have much to thank Mrs Tucker for, in my making <hi rend="italic">now </hi>this Government annuity for you and for Sarah; Mrs T.—<hi rend="italic">has always been your best friend in England. </hi>I should like for you to let her see your Certificate.</p>
         <p>Good bye my dear Willie.</p>
         <p>May God bless you is the constant prayer of your Father</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>—night: I have put up for you <hi rend="italic">12 Newspapers</hi>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>