<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0295">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1875 August 25: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1875-08-25">1875 August 25</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1875 August 25: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-227" place="foot" n="227"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand<lb/>August 25 1875.</p>
         <p>A. Luff Esq</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir</p>
         <p>Words won’t express how right glad I was to see your own hand writing again! You will have heard from me, that I have heard of the arrival of <hi rend="italic">your ship</hi>—after a long passage (which I was sure was wholly unexpected on your part,)—but I wanted to know more than that: viz. how you &amp; yours had sped &amp; were! Well on the 6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. Augt. I had the <hi rend="italic">pleasure</hi> of recg. your letter via Brindisi, also the nice interesting Diary kept by your son. I had no idea you would have seen so <hi rend="italic">many </hi>ships! so widely different to what it was when I was an ocean-voyager! Two days ago (on 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>.) I recd. yours of June 29, for which I also thank you (I must tell you that you have <hi rend="italic">not dated</hi> either of your letters,—I go by their <hi rend="italic">postmark</hi>.) I am so glad to find that you &amp; yours were well, &amp; that <hi rend="italic">you had </hi>the very great pleasure of seeing your Father (this strikes a chord in my bosom!)—also your Brothers.—You also gave me the news of the arrl. of “Cel. Queen” in the Thames—my nephew has written from Cornwall, on 27<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. saying Willie has teleg. to them when official on 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., &amp; my Brother had gone up to London (as he did before) purposely to receive W. but, strange to say (for there <hi rend="italic">was</hi> time enough) I got nothing <hi rend="italic">more</hi>.—</p>
         <p>One thing your last letter lacked, you never mentioned your family;—is George at school, or where; believe me I am interested in their welfare, &amp; be sure you let me know.—</p>
         <p>Mr Grubb is at P. Bay, acting R.M. for a month or so: he has written to me to tell you he recd. yr. letter (from Suez), &amp; will write by-&amp;-bye. not perhaps by <hi rend="italic">this</hi> Mail: he is <hi rend="italic">alone</hi> there &amp; has plenty to do. I am keeping <hi rend="italic">George’s Diary</hi> for him, until his return.—Henn here in our P.O. is also alone! he has G. Lindsay as a cadet—but he is too young &amp; too strange yet to do much). Henn is worn-out! &amp; young Miller, who was getting on nicely &amp; promises well, is, I regret to say, Laid up w. Rheumatic fever, &amp; is <hi rend="italic">very bad</hi> (so his father told me,)—Miller himself has been, also, confined to his bed for a week or more. Mrs Johnstone, Confectioner’s wife, died yesterday. Maori MacKenzie is also dead—from the fever, &amp; several others inland—both Europeans &amp; Natives. The “Friedburg” from Hamburg, w. 251 immigrants, arrived yesterday—<hi rend="italic">all well; no </hi>deaths on voyage (91 days from Start Point) but several births: these immigrants are nearly all foreigners—I hope they may do well: our winter is passed, weather tolerable but unsettled, peaches in blossom. I have been much more unsettled of late, than I could wish—1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. a little anxiety about you &amp; W.—2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>.—the matter of the great slip or chasm here in the hill side, which is daily increasing! &amp; no one can say (owing to the loose soil) where it will stop—all done by Dunbar, &amp; Weber, &amp; others digging for Railway works—instead of going a little farther off to the <hi rend="italic">small </hi>hill which is Govts.—well, to add to above folks right &amp; left, have had some surveyors who have come <hi rend="italic">into </hi>my old paddocks &amp; driven in pegs—&amp; only this mg. I was obliged to go down &amp; stop them fencing within my fence!—</p>
         <p>3. Then the Appeal against Rates on Monday last (23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>.) in R.M. Court, the precious M. Council not caring to <hi rend="italic">consider</hi> our complaints—Robjohns, Ferard, Self, &amp; others)—I got £<hi rend="italic">36</hi>.—on <hi rend="italic">the whole</hi>—struck off: but nothing on <hi rend="italic">these grounds</hi> (viz. Hague’s, Watt, &amp;c)—Duncan, J.A. Smith, John White &amp; Sealy—Kinross, too, on Bench:—I send you a paper.—The chief reductions were made by the Bench on 3 Sns. on the White Road (2 by Mao. Club, &amp; 1, the remg. unsold portions of 309 &amp; 316)—&amp;, as I take it, through my showing that J.A.S’s. sections,—same side, adjg., but <hi rend="italic">nearer </hi>this way—were rated less—viz. £30. (mine £35. &amp; £40.) Some one on the Bench said, it was owing to mine adjg. the M. Club!!—Renouf, when sworn, I asked why. Said, because I (and <hi rend="italic">you</hi>) had valued them at so much per ft. frontages, &amp;c, &amp;c. I questd. R., If that was the “<hi rend="italic">fair </hi>reasonable value,” wh. the Act mentioned: and, if there was no difference in selling in bits (trouble, time &amp; expense) than selling in a lot:—and if he considered my price so fair, why he did not value J.A.S at same?—&amp;c. &amp;c.—However Robjohns, Ford, Ferard, myself, we all gained something on our Appeals,—I (of course) <hi rend="italic">least</hi>. You could scarcely believe Sealy saying (&amp; arguing) that T.S. 108, where my gate &amp; brambles are, was <hi rend="italic">all flat</hi>!! I have now to pay £17.19.0 yearly! only <hi rend="underline italic">one</hi> rate!!</p>
         <p>Worse still, both the Papers have, of late, been pandering to the low common Chartist-like opinion—Why should certain folks have large fine properties, gardens, &amp;c, &amp;c,—and that they should be made to pay heavily in Rates, &amp;c, &amp;c,—all which is <hi rend="italic">applauded</hi> by the 1000! Stuart, Tuxford, &amp; Swan, are <hi rend="italic">obliged </hi>to retire in Rept., but are all asking to be re-elected. Renouf told me, that the ½ ac. opp. to the Brewery on White Road, was lately sold for £<hi rend="italic">300</hi>., &amp; that W.H. Russell sold <hi rend="italic">all</hi> his Onepoto Sns. remarkably well, all at once and at (about) £<hi rend="italic">80</hi>. each! I could not but think of <hi rend="italic">mine</hi>!— </p>
         <p>4. There is any amount of trouble about <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the Abbotsford Sns.,—party. those you bought: S.W. won’t (now) give in, &amp; Rochfort (!) turns round, &amp; says, “he don’t see how Mr.W. can”: &amp;, “it will take a long time to settle,” &amp;c &amp;c—for peace’ sake, I must make up my mind to lose pretty much ground there—if I wish to sell.</p>
         <p>5. Drower’s sm. P.N. for saddlery, fell due on 19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>, &amp; was dishonored!!—it came on me as a thunderclap, for I had gone to B.N.Z. to arrange the draft for Walsall: I wrote to D.—who has offered a <hi rend="italic">part</hi> (<hi rend="sup ">2</hi>/<hi rend="sub">5</hi>ths) at <hi rend="italic">end </hi>of mo. (<hi rend="italic">after</hi> this Mail leaves) and a Bill at 3 mos. for <hi rend="sup ">3</hi>/<hi rend="sub">5</hi>ths.—I have again written, but, as yet, no answer.</p>
         <p>6. Yesterday—after 2 days (or nights) talk, off &amp; on, w. Price, I sold him <hi rend="italic">the remg.</hi> land at Tarawera, 244 ac. @ £4.10., to be pd. for by instalments extendg. over 3 years, Int. at 6. Cotterill told me, W. Couper wishes to <hi rend="italic">pay</hi> for his B. Shop, &amp;c, at Havelock: conveyance is making out. Wilson is gone to Engd. Naden Brors. have dissolved Partnership. Colledge has left Jacobs, &amp; joined Craig, who has bought stock &amp;c from Dinwiddie (Herald), &amp; dissolved <hi rend="italic">from them</hi>. P. Dinwiddie is going out of Business. I have not seen Rev. Mr Sidey for a long while; he has been unwell, but is better. J. Woods <hi rend="italic">eldest</hi> son is dead from fever: they are, I hear, at New Caledonia!!—</p>
         <p>Garry is <hi rend="italic">still</hi> boring on 333 (Robjohn’s Brewery Sn, Wellesley Road) but no water—40ft. deeper than Railway well. Speaking of Grubb, forgot to say, he sent me your chq. to sum for £15.–.– which <hi rend="italic">squares</hi> what I had pd. him for you. If Regr. at Wgn. comes on me for fees on your acct. I will gladly pay them. (I see they are going to alter stamp duties to get more money)—&amp; make <hi rend="italic">mortgages</hi> pay. You must look to Papers for <hi rend="italic">political </hi>news—they are still fighting over Abolition of Provinces Bill, but the Opposition number but few.—You ask what ship Rhodes went by? He did not leave for England:—only America, and (I believe) India. Tiffen &amp; lady left last week <hi rend="italic">en route </hi>for America: she has been <hi rend="italic">long ill</hi>. I recd. 2 papers from you “Dy. Telegraph” &amp; “Graphic”:—the “Wananga” is now a bulky affair of a Paper—pubd. weekly at old Times Office—&amp; abuses McL. <hi rend="italic">roundly</hi>! Redstone (smith) has a store built next to Metht. chapel for Grocery: &amp; Carlile, solr. has a <hi rend="italic">concrete </hi>off. building next to Blythe’s. J. Hamlin pulled down most of yr. Ho., &amp; has greatly enlarged &amp; raised it <hi rend="italic">high</hi>. <hi rend="italic">M. </hi>Hamlin poor fellow! is just gone to Auckland to be <hi rend="italic">cut</hi> again for Cancer (in throat &amp; <hi rend="italic">neck now</hi>,) or <hi rend="underline italic">die</hi>!—During the first week of this month I suffered severely from <hi rend="italic">Neuralgia</hi>—day &amp; night—<hi rend="italic">no relief</hi>! &amp; I was nearly mad, &amp; nearly gone too. I enclose an advt.; could you get me a bottle, &amp; put it into a tin box in cotton, &amp; send it:—of course I will pay <hi rend="italic">all </hi>expenses.<note xml:id="ftn2-228" place="foot" n="228">
               <p rend="justify"> Colenso attached a clipped advertisement from a newspaper:NEURALINE gives instant relief in TIC DOULOUREUX, Neuralgia, Sciatica, Toothache, Rheumatism, Gout, and all Nerve and Local Pains.—LEATH and ROSS, Homœopathic Chemists, No. 5, St. Paul’s Churchyard, and 9, Vere-Street, W. All chemists, in bottles, 1s. 1½d. and 2s. 9d.; by post, 1s. 3d. and 3s.</p>
            </note> —My last letter to you was a <hi rend="italic">long </hi>one on 30<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> July—I find, from a late Gaz., that <hi rend="italic">Donald</hi>—<hi rend="italic">bought</hi> on H.W.P. Smith’s Run 271 a. rural Land: and I heard the Remark,—where was Duff? This day 4 ½ ac. Sns. on W. Spit were sold <hi rend="italic">at upset</hi> price only! by Govt., Lyndon, J.A.S. Scully, &amp; Miller, purchasers. They have been puffed largely in <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>: speaking of the Bridge,—of £<hi rend="italic">100</hi>. being a sure return ere long for the £10. note, &amp;c, &amp;c., &amp;—<hi rend="italic">no bid</hi>!!</p>
         <p>Sealy has been buying largely in Woodville—he took however the precaution to go there first. P. Dolbel is well, &amp; I believe will succeed in selling his lease or right on his old Mohaka Run. Your old acq. R. Brown of Clive has sold out,—and is now a wanderer! he thinks of migrating to Povy. Bay. So: <hi rend="italic">good night</hi>.</p>
         <p>26<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—Young Irvine is back again, looking <hi rend="italic">very</hi> weird-like! he is allowed to go about anywhere free: but I think his coming back <hi rend="italic">here</hi> is wrong: his father told me, 3 weeks ago, that his mother had gone to Wgn. to get him sent to his Brother in Melbourne,—that might have been <hi rend="italic">right</hi>. Irvine, is rated at £<hi rend="italic">300</hi>!!—</p>
         <p>Trestrail told me in town today, that he had lost <hi rend="italic">all</hi> his hill property here in town—that is it took it <hi rend="italic">all</hi> to clear him in the lawsuit, (<hi rend="italic">double</hi> one) in Sup Ct. w. Giffard. I was sorry to hear this. The Friedberg Immigt. Ship which only arrd. on 24<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—left this mg. early for Java!! <hi rend="italic">Dispatch</hi>.</p>
         <p>And now my dr. Sir good bye</p>
         <p>Bel. me ever &amp; always Yours W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>