<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0859">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1893 February 22: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1893-02-22">1893 February 22</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1893 February 22: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-632" place="foot" n="632"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Feby. 22/93<lb/>(night).</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>I have been having you very often in mind of late—many things provoking thereto, and should have written, lately, but for the S.F. Mail which closed here this mg. My last to you was on the 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., since then <hi rend="italic">two letters </hi>from you, one dated “5<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.” which must have crossed mine in transit, and one dated “19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.”, to hand yesterday, for both of which—and for “Evg. Press,”—<hi rend="italic">March </hi>Calendar, “Typos”, &amp; sundry clippings—<hi rend="italic">thanks</hi>.—</p>
         <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Of myself</hi>: on 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. to Taradale for evg. S. there, retg. in mg. by Rymer, &amp; again at T. on 19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. for mg. S.—also 2 visits to town—rest of time at Home, &amp; wkg. <hi rend="italic">hard</hi>;—at last! putting up <hi rend="italic">all </hi>my plants, of years collecting into bundles, &amp; marking them—but it is still “<hi rend="italic">pye</hi>”—unsorted!! I got Slater up to put up a lot of shelves for me in all 3 rooms &amp; have stowed away those bundles! and have my books, &amp;c, &amp;c, to put in order yet: I have been daily in my shirt sleeves, &amp; quite warm &amp; tired every evg. heat great! in this cool house 85° (in Bk. N.Z. below 92°) &amp; very little if any of sea breezes. I have been keeping well—scarcely any Rheum. but sometimes when in town Influenza <hi rend="italic">in feet</hi> very bad! Have not heard a sound from Woodville! which <hi rend="italic">seems</hi> strange.</p>
         <p>In town—a fortnight ago, Large fell foul of me (<hi rend="italic">in his way</hi>) to get me to become Hony. Secy. to our Inst.—NO. And again, last Friday, to tell me that the annl. mtg. is to be held on 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi> &amp; that Dr. Moore is to be Pt., Humphries Vice Pt., &amp; Dinwiddie (little Lawyer) Hony. S’y.—so, all cut &amp; dried between them: advt. in todays P. for 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>—I shall <hi rend="italic">not </hi>attend.</p>
         <p>Mrs Fannin having gone back to her Asylum, (she never ought to have been brought back to N.) F. is about to give up housekpg.—has let his house, also another <hi rend="italic">new </hi>one just finished, on ground <hi rend="italic">below </hi>Hill’s, &amp; facing Cape K. Sevl. Commees. have voted for E. Board, so far yr. Cousin is a long way ahead (&amp; <hi rend="italic">rightly</hi>, too), &amp; Williams, &amp; then Cohen; Sidey is <hi rend="italic">low </hi>down, &amp; Haggen, &amp; Bierre nowhere (&amp; <hi rend="underline italic">rightly, too</hi>!) I must get you a “<hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>” of last wk, which contains a tit-bit of Haggen, &amp;c. – – I am rather sorry for D.S.,—I would that Fred. S. were <hi rend="italic">out</hi>! Tanner is going to Engd. but as he is coming back in time for the election (<hi rend="italic">vain </hi>man!) the E. Bd. would <hi rend="italic">not take his resign</hi>., but gave 6 mths. leave of absence. <hi rend="italic">You know </hi>the yg. woman &amp; will be pleased to hear, that out of total no. of marks (1430, 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> yr.) “<hi rend="italic">Harriet Burdett, </hi>Waipawa, is at the <hi rend="italic">head</hi>, with 1232.—Have not seen Hill since date of my last, &amp; Craig only once (busy—doubly so now that Howe has left: <hi rend="italic">I don’t like his new </hi>hand from Auckland (<hi rend="underline italic">Private</hi>:)</p>
         <p>Have had a long L. from Hamilton, wife got safely back, &amp; all well there, &amp; H. in for more “<hi rend="italic">finds</hi>”!!—</p>
         <p>I send you a lot of sundries. One mention of a Paper read at a meeting in <hi rend="italic">Penzance</hi>, by President, on wingless Birds—&amp; (of course) <hi rend="italic">Moa</hi>: he gives <hi rend="italic">another fable</hi>,—&amp; though that Socy. possesses all our vols. of “Trans. N.Z. I.”, &amp; also <hi rend="italic">separate copies </hi>of my Papers, &amp; I, too, a Member,—nothing said of them!! (Buller over again!) <hi rend="italic">Another</hi>, is a <hi rend="italic">book</hi> printed in the Bush (? the first)—why, so many <hi rend="italic">blank </hi>pp. should be, and why <hi rend="italic">so many </hi>exhibits, I know not: there are a few errors in it.—I also add the List of <hi rend="italic">our </hi>N. Hortl. Society Exhn.—also, a sheet of P.D’s. Rubber stamps (<hi rend="italic">sent round </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">in</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> “D.T.”</hi>—not in “Herald”, as an inset!!!) also, a clipping posted to <hi rend="italic">me </hi>by Rees,—I shall <hi rend="italic">not attend</hi>—don’t believe <hi rend="italic">in R</hi>.: also, 2 clippings, from “Standard”. “<hi rend="italic">Biblical Misprints</hi>”: and “<hi rend="italic">Century Dicty.</hi>” &amp; one, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> a wk. “<hi rend="italic">Early Printing</hi>”, from a Cat. to hand <hi rend="italic">this day</hi>. Also a List from “Luzac &amp; Co.” that you may see the <hi rend="italic">cut</hi>: &amp; the mention of 2 wks. on <hi rend="italic">last page</hi>—these I should like to see—but the <hi rend="italic">price</hi>!!—I also return poor Bassett’s <hi rend="italic">Letter</hi>! <hi rend="italic">You must </hi>have <hi rend="italic">felt</hi> that blow!!</p>
         <p>I noticed an error in your “Typo”, P.84, re “Haggen”—l<hi rend="underline">o</hi>nd for land: most unusual w. you: I only detected it through twice readg. <hi rend="italic">re H.</hi> And another (&amp; a <hi rend="italic">greater</hi>, and a <hi rend="italic">repeated</hi> error of yours—in your over-weight letter (&amp; ’tis much over, owing to your <hi rend="italic">terribly thick</hi> paper &amp; envelope), I would not care for extra 2d.—but the <hi rend="underline italic">fine</hi>!!</p>
         <p>I felt the clatter &amp; rattle of the earthq. here in this house, &amp; was <hi rend="italic">nearly </hi>making a bolt! And strange to say neither Robert nor his wife, both in their house, <hi rend="italic">felt </hi>it! &amp; would scarcely believe me: it was much more severe down S.—</p>
         <p>I note what Dtr. B. told you <hi rend="italic">re </hi>my papers being “voluminous”: <hi rend="italic">it is true</hi>, and I am sorry for it, &amp; would (if I <hi rend="italic">well</hi> could) withdraw <hi rend="italic">some of them</hi>. When I wrote some in Bush, I did not expect to have any on Botany, &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>You tell me of present vol. being in hands of Govt. Printer: so, also, Gore has informed me. I hope <hi rend="italic">you </hi>&amp; your Council, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">new</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>President, will work well together: <hi rend="italic">I congratulate you on becoming a Member.</hi>—</p>
         <p>PRIVATE: I have received a circular from Xtchurch, (rather a long one), asking me to join in requestg. Govt. to republish H’s. “Handbook of N.Z. Fl.” with additions; <hi rend="italic">and</hi>, to give Kirk the job. This <hi rend="italic">latter </hi>I could never do: he is not fit for it: he could help w. spns. of <hi rend="italic">phenogams </hi>&amp; ferns. I am sorry to see K. dubbed “<hi rend="italic">Prof.</hi>”, in the report of your mtg. you sent me: only a few years ago he was “hackled” in S. papers for it, and styled a “Quack”.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Again</hi>! you are right “Effective <hi rend="italic">Advertiser</hi>” it should have been—but you don’t say <hi rend="italic">if you have a copy: </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">let me know</hi>.—</p>
         <p>It is <hi rend="italic">sad</hi>—aye, leaves a train of <hi rend="italic">saddening</hi> (yea, <hi rend="italic">ugly</hi>!) thoughts in my mind, what you say, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>a certain <hi rend="italic">person </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">not calling on yr. Father</hi>. I have jotted down in my tablet <hi rend="italic">to do so</hi>, when I next go to town.</p>
         <p>I am on the <hi rend="italic">qui vive re</hi> news from (or of) my eldest son: but I have gleaned a few grains of consolation—in seeing the “Standard” papers to <hi rend="italic">31 Decr.</hi> addressed by his wife (as was often done), while his sad pencilled scrap was dated on 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I am glad to know of Victor being all right again:—only wish <hi rend="italic">you were fully occupied in yr. professional work</hi>: I am sure you are <hi rend="italic">steadily</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">seeking</hi> it, &amp; equally <hi rend="italic">sure</hi> you <hi rend="italic">deserve</hi> it, &amp; so, I venture to hope—<hi rend="italic">the good time</hi> will yet come.—<hi rend="italic">Be brave: look up: </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">wait</hi>.</p>
         <p>Some days I can scarcely write legibly! fingers, unruly: but are nearly all right this evening.</p>
         <p>And now, good bye, w. kindest regards &amp; best wishes, yours truly, W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. But what of Williams’ Dicty.? I thought you had that in hand.—</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
