<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0536">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1883 May 21: to Balfour</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73378/">Balfour</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1883-05-21">1883 May 21</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1883 May 21: to Balfour<note xml:id="ftn3-185" place="foot" n="185"> ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier May 21st 1883</p>
         <p>Mr D.P. Balfour</p>
         <p>Dear Sir</p>
         <p>I have 2 of your letters before me—of the 6th &amp; 12th inst.—thanks for both. I was pleased to find you had received mine to you of 25th ulto from “Bush”. I left on 2nd May—<hi rend="italic">in rain</hi>! and so home!!! &amp; then plenty of it here!!. I have never known such a wet April &amp; May in N.Z. Formerly these 2 months were my prime &amp; favourite travelling months, &amp; delightful weather. Of course I was much disappointed—loss of time, too; still I kept in good health, for from <hi rend="italic">the first</hi> I had determined <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to fret, &amp; I had plenty of writing to keep me employed—I gained several new things notwithstanding.</p>
         <p>And now I am off again to the Bush; on Wed mg, early train.</p>
         <p>Don’t think me demented!. By last English mail (since my return) I had a letter from Sir J. Hooker, Director Roy Bot Gardens, Kew, &amp; among other matters he tells me of their great want of many N.Z. plants—. Now several of these I saw all around me there, in dells &amp; out of the way places, and so I have made up my mind to go &amp; get them at once—this being Autumn &amp; a good season.</p>
         <p>I told Sir J in my letter of Saturday, that I would rather than a £10 note I had got his letter while there. If I have fine weather I shall not be long away from Napier.</p>
         <p>I sent you a “D.T.” containing a brief report of our meeting. Hope you got it.</p>
         <p>Now to your 2 letters.—Your “find” of <hi rend="italic">Loma. filiformis</hi> must have been pleasing to you, especially to get it in fruit; at the N (and also S) it climbs to the top of the highest forest trees, and mostly “fruits” at the top—so that it is difficult to get fruiting spns.</p>
         <p>As you say, it is not very common about <hi rend="italic">here</hi> (though it is Petane way, &amp;c.) but plenty in forest S of Manawatu—ground there matted with its <hi rend="italic">smaller</hi> barren fronds.</p>
         <p>The others, in this first lot, I cannot at present say much about; I have twice run over them; perhaps by &amp; bye when I shall have a <hi rend="italic">Botanl. week</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Examn</hi>;—they may turn up something. Larger spns (&amp; whole, unbroken ones) are always preferable, even of <hi rend="italic">small</hi> things; &amp; don’t attempt to wash any of the <hi rend="italic">Hepaticæ</hi> &amp;c.,—except if muddy, just passing them untouched thro clear water, &amp; then leaving them to drain &amp; dry on a cloth.</p>
         <p>In yours of the 12th I note your drawing &amp; remarks of “a beautiful vegetable curio”—also the specimen. Your drawing coloured is the better of the two, but I should much like to have some more, particularly with the “swellings” you mention. Your drawing shows them, but there is but <hi rend="italic">one</hi> (&amp; that damaged) on the plant.</p>
         <p>This has interested me much, for about 32–33 years ago I had found it on the W side of the Ruahine range, but <hi rend="italic">without</hi> “swellings”. I was crawling on hands &amp; knees through a (then) dry watercourse, seeking my way, when the blackish hair-like stems arising from the leaves on the ground caught my eye!. I sent it to England, but (as far as I know) it is not described (with many other of our smaller things) in the Hand Book. I hope to examine this fully by-&amp;-bye, but I need better specimens. You will have seen in “D.T.” that much of our meetings work fell on me (as usual). Indeed, it was thus. Either a paper &amp;c from <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">no</hi> meeting; so I gave in. I worked very hard for that meeting; all Winkelmanns specimens had <hi rend="italic">followed</hi> me to N, &amp; it was a heavy job, the getting them out, &amp;c., &amp;c., in time.</p>
         <p>I found 35 letters on my table awaiting me; exclusive of my Eng ones, which I had sent for, &amp; <hi rend="italic">answered</hi> from the Bush—i.e. <hi rend="italic">in part</hi>.</p>
         <p>I am afraid to think of our next months meeting; I have <hi rend="italic">promised</hi> the Council a Botan paper—<hi rend="italic">if I can</hi> get it ready—&amp; to show some new plants. Hope your promised “case” will be here before I return.</p>
         <p>Keep your eye on your Divot plants. The Hepaticæ generally will soon be in fruit. Handle them <hi rend="italic">very carefully</hi>; eggs &amp; glass are as nothing to them, when in fruit.</p>
         <p>I have several letters yet unanswered;—I could not resist writing to you.</p>
         <p>Goodbye; Kind regards to Mrs Balfour, self, &amp; love to bairns—all. </p>
         <p>             Yours very truly</p>
         <p>                             W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. Packed today a box of roots for Sir J.D. Hooker, to go by “British Queen” and sent him last week a packet of seeds by Mr Enys of Christchurch who is on a visit to England. W.C.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>