<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0896">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1894 March 21: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1894-03-21">1894 March 21</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1894 March 21: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-682" place="foot" n="682"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, March 21/94</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>I have been thinking on you—pretty much of late, several things carrying me in that direction, and so I had made up my mind to write to you on <hi rend="italic">this day</hi>—having despatched my usual S.F. budget! When, lo! last night your long &amp; kind letter of 19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. came to hand. As usual—it is a kind of “bitter-sweet,” <hi rend="italic">better </hi>news of dear V., <hi rend="italic">good re </hi>work; <hi rend="italic">bad</hi>—your own health—I had almost feared <hi rend="italic">this</hi>, (and I believe I have touched on it—in letters to you)—you <hi rend="italic">do </hi>require change—for a while—<hi rend="italic">rest</hi>, absolute, from daily &amp; nightly worry: if the sea agrees with you I should prescribe a sea-voyage, but you will know best.—</p>
         <p>Now, the “several things” that caused me to have you in mind, are these:—1.) on my return to N. on 9<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst. I found a heavy lot of “Proofs” from Wellington, of <hi rend="italic">all </hi>(!) my remg. Papers—including the Tongariro &amp; Taupo one (<hi rend="italic">re </hi>Collie) and—<hi rend="italic">yours</hi>!—<hi rend="italic">i.e. </hi>von Haasts, so kindly <hi rend="italic">read </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">by you</hi>—such a lot of reading, and (as before) <hi rend="underline italic">without</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> copies</hi>: and these had been <hi rend="italic">here </hi>nearly a week, for I had <hi rend="italic">early </hi>written to Jago, not to send any more to Dannevirke: the proofs however were very clean ones—I lost no time in going (3 times) over them and returning to Wgn.—</p>
         <p>2. Another cause: I purchased at Craig’s a Londn. Almanac—for the sake of planetary movements, and I thought what a nice treat the coloured prints would be for V., so I have cut them out, &amp; shall send w. this.—</p>
         <p>3. Ditto: my receiving from you the parcel (heavy) of party. paper reptd.,—I suppose there is nothing else in it, I have <hi rend="italic">not </hi>opened it.—</p>
         <p>4. Some Catalogues &amp; papers from Home &amp; from America—which I thought <hi rend="italic">you </hi>might like to see.—</p>
         <p>5. Another vol. of “Index Kewensis”, bringing it down to end of I. This is an Herculean wk. (being done against time!) Hooker tells me <hi rend="italic">feelingly </hi>that his principal (no 2) collaborator—a yg. m., <hi rend="italic">devoted to such </hi>work—16 hours daily!—was <hi rend="italic">obliged </hi>to leave off—for a time—had 1 month’s holiday, hoping he may recruit. I find (casually—no regular search) several of my plants in the wk., but, <hi rend="italic">unforty.</hi> it does not contain any after ’85 (or ’<hi rend="underline italic">84—Papers</hi>) and my chief ones in “<hi rend="italic">Trans</hi>.” commence then—viz. “’85.”—</p>
         <p>I have been keeping well since my return: folks geny. say—how well I am looking! and I suppose it is true, but my <hi rend="italic">legs </hi>are not much stronger for climbing hills, or stairs! Soon after my return I called at Dr. Hitchings’ <hi rend="italic">late </hi>residence to see his 4 daughters, being my neighbours, &amp; found them <hi rend="italic">well </hi>&amp; apparently comfortable together, though lamenting loss of their <hi rend="underline italic">kind</hi> Father. I see Dr. Moore is made Gaol Surgeon in Dr. H’s. stead; I had to go thither in <hi rend="italic">trap </hi>&amp; visited other persons same morning.—Have been 2ce. since to town, &amp; last Sunday mg. to Augustine’s—&amp; heard Bradbury. Last wk. I recd. a letter from <hi rend="italic">Hill</hi>—“Gisborne, 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.”—saying, he had colld. some plants, wk. before, at E. Cape, had (this time!) pd. partr. attention—having taken pressing boards &amp; straps w. him—and had even “humped” the lot through the country, &amp; there were several <hi rend="italic">new </hi>things—and he had given them into hands of a “Commercial”, coming to N., to leave with Craig:—well, I was on <hi rend="italic">qui vive</hi>! &amp; teased (?) Craig: steamer from Gisborne came on <hi rend="italic">Sund. </hi>mg.,—&amp; <hi rend="italic">last evg. </hi>(Tuesday) I recd. them, Miss Hill kindly bringing them. My heart sank when I saw how tightly the said boards had been strapped up! lost no time in opening—&amp;—oh! the old, old, tale—all ruined—rotten, &amp; pressed to bits!!!—some being very succulent, &amp; some really <hi rend="italic">new</hi>: have been working at them today, soaking some flowers in hot water, &amp; using camel’s hair brush, &amp;c, &amp;c.—–Your tip of a leaf I also soaked, &amp; laid out flat: it <hi rend="italic">reminds </hi>me of the “Oak leaf Geranium”: <hi rend="italic">I doubt it being a N.Zr.</hi>—I had scoured Jackson’s Bay on my 2–3 visits, but shod. you go thither again, &amp; it in flower or fruit, secure a bit for me. I have also been wkg. on 3–4 of my <hi rend="italic">finds </hi>at Dvk.</p>
         <p>I think I told you in my last of my engaget. w. Robertshawe for 15<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. proxo., and I <hi rend="italic">may </hi>go inland <hi rend="italic">early </hi>in April, to help Eccles at Wdv.—day not yet fixed, and I expect Bradbury <hi rend="italic">here </hi>will want aid, shortly, as he is about <hi rend="italic">to be married</hi>, to some one down S.—your way? Sandy Grant’s 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. son was married, here, a day or two ago, to a “Miss Conroy of Takapau.”—And I see, your cousin R. &amp; wife, are off to the old Cy. Mr. Sidey has been unwell but is better, I called to see him; Mr. Paterson is <hi rend="italic">well</hi>: Rev. R. Fraser kindly called on me last wk. &amp; spent an hour w. me. To day is voting day <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Licence Commees. I found I had <hi rend="italic">no </hi>Vote! so have kept quiet here in House. Carnell told me Sir. G. Grey had enqd. after me, &amp; was coming hither to see me, but was told of my absence. I scarcely think he will return again. At Dvk. they are actually going-in for lighting by electy.! and for asphalte kerbs. Drummond, <hi rend="italic">J.P. </hi>was brought up, &amp; fined for firing a rifle <hi rend="italic">within </hi>town! &amp; Dr. Caro, J.P. brought up here, for trespassing across Ry. lines—to see a patient. The weather of late has been peculiar—Dull, clouded dark days, no wind, &amp; threatg. rain—but none falling, yet both N. &amp; S. getting it.</p>
         <p>Now to yr. letter: am <hi rend="italic">much pleased </hi>at your <hi rend="italic">superor </hi>wk. for Govt. Insurance. The Bp’s. married daughter here is a widow w. 3 childn., they &amp; his dear old sister, live in W. Marshall’s old house, &amp; have a <hi rend="italic">right</hi> to go to &amp; fro per this paddock. Your Uncle John has a <hi rend="italic">sharp</hi> letter in paper—pitching in to the “Herald’s” miserable penny<hi rend="italic">-</hi>a-liner! S.J., will, no doubt, when the oppy. comes, repay w. <hi rend="italic">Interest.</hi>—Yes: you are right,—Dr. H’s. son married one of Arrow’s daughters. You say,— “<hi rend="italic">You</hi> remember death of<hi rend="italic"> </hi>Dr’s. <hi rend="italic">first </hi>wife”:—how so? Did <hi rend="italic">he not come out as a widower to N.Z.</hi>? I hear from “good authy.” at Dvk. that Clayton was wild about his having sold out, &amp; offd. his successor <hi rend="italic">₤</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">200</hi>. over to give back!! <hi rend="italic">Re </hi>“New Flora”: at Auckld. Mrs Hetley &amp; her friends saw Premier &amp; strove hard for her illd. work to be taken up:—<hi rend="italic">coloured </hi>plates, forsooth! You are <hi rend="italic">right </hi>as to old Field!—but his book is an out-&amp;-out failure in a sc. view: may do for Boarding School girls: Kirk, in letter to me, noticed <hi rend="italic">that folly </hi>of his! which you also have detected. I have <hi rend="italic">never seen </hi>Taylor’s “Past, present &amp; future”; he is a terrible plagiarist, &amp; not to be trusted in <hi rend="italic">his own </hi>views &amp; translations (!!) of Maori matters, &amp; words. Thanks for your kindly looking-up Tregear: but I suppose <hi rend="italic">nothing could </hi>be done in Seddon’s absence. I believe Fannin’s daughter will soon be married to yg. Canning. Bob. Price seems to be quietly enjoying himself in his new Bush. Cannot learn anything of <hi rend="italic">our </hi>Society: no report yet: I sent Large my subsn. last wk., but no reply: in my note, I sd. I knew he was <hi rend="italic">not </hi>now Treasr., but I did not know who held that office; You surprise me, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>his daughter going to Engd. I shall send you a Californian Paper that you may <hi rend="italic">see </hi>&amp; note something in it. I suppose you know—it is now <hi rend="italic">fixed </hi>that Dicken’s Street is to be widened; and I suppose Emerson St. will follow ex. Frank Ormond called last Saturday bringing a pretty flg. sprig of a shrub, which he says (<hi rend="italic">from others</hi>) is a <hi rend="italic">Bush </hi>one, but growing in their gardn. at Wallingford—it is, however, wholly <hi rend="italic">unknown </hi>to me, &amp; I <hi rend="italic">doubt</hi> it being a Maori. Among other new books recently from Engld.—is the Life of “Muhammed the Apostle”—by an Arabian author, &amp; now translated: its title— “The Rauzat-us-affa, or Garden of Purity”: shall I find time to read it?—–</p>
         <p>And now I close: I send ₤3.5.0 to pay for ptg. Py. paper: I hope this may find <hi rend="italic">you </hi>much better: ditto Victor, and Mrs Harding quite well. And with thanks and affectionate regards,</p>
         <p>     Believe me, yrs. sincy., W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. I don’t sleep very well—disturbed by long &amp; strange repeating dreams.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
