<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0292">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1875 July 2: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1875-07-02">1875 July 2</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1875 July 2: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-224" place="foot" n="224"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand<lb/>July 2 1875</p>
         <p>My dear Sir</p>
         <p>Were I to attempt to tell you how very much <hi rend="italic">you</hi> have occupied my thoughts of late—you would scarcely credit me. My anxiety was great about you—not hearing any tidings of the Waikato (which moreover bore the name of being a clipper—&amp; was <hi rend="italic">selected</hi> by you)—three times in June did I telegraph to head quarters at Xt.Church, and at last on the 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. I got a meagre telegram saying she had arrived—but nothing more. We don’t, at present, know even the day of her arrival—but suppose it to have been about the middle of June—so you must have had a <hi rend="italic">long</hi> passage. I hope, in due time, to hear of your being quite well, also your wife &amp; family. No news yet of <hi rend="italic">our</hi> H. Bay Ships— “W. Cundell”, “Q. Bee”, and (Willie’s) “C. Queen”—but hope to hear of all of them shortly.</p>
         <p>Since my last to you (of June 4) the “County of Kintore” and the “John Norman” have arrived here—the 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. w. Immigrants &amp; a splendid passage of only 82 days, &amp; <hi rend="italic">all well</hi>! Young Newman is her Doctor: I have heard good things of him <hi rend="italic">at his profession in Engd.</hi>, but he <hi rend="italic">looks</hi> very young &amp; boyish): the “J.N.” had a very long passage—but arrived safe, &amp; no passengers; she is now landing her Gas pipes, &amp;c. &amp;c. I know that my last month’s letter has <hi rend="italic">not </hi>yet left N.Z., (I suppose you will get it w. this,)—it was a sad stormy time when the “Luna”—w. Sir D. on board—left for Wgn., but she was obliged to put back from Palliser Bay to Cape Kidrs. for weather, remaining under our Cape some 3, 4 days, so, was too late for the Mail! &amp;, strange enough too, it was the same a week before w. the Suez Mail hence, which was left here! much growling as usual. I fear that my <hi rend="italic">first long</hi> letter to you, &amp; Papers, by the <hi rend="italic">March </hi>Mail, were lost in the “Schiller”. The Storm which detained the “Luna” did much damage—especially among shipping, &amp; loss of Seamen, all along the Coast from E. Cape to Bluff—the beaches at Timaru, Oamaru, &amp;c, being strewn with wreck! The wind blew down the Wesleyan “Church” in Cl. Square,—altogether a perfect smash, not a stick of the main building left standing,—I always thought it was too slight, and too pretentious,—or, attemptedly imposing: floor 7 feet from ground, a great flight of steps, huge roof, &amp;c, &amp;c. 3 fine <hi rend="italic">red</hi> gums, which you have admired, were also blown down in this place—2 in avenue, &amp; 1 in garden—uprooted &amp; prostrated. I, however, slept well that night, being now so securely boxed in w. trees, so that this house did not feel it much. Since then we have had another gale,—less wind &amp; <hi rend="italic">more rain</hi>,—great floods, &amp; the usual loss (see Papers): I was at Waipukurau, <hi rend="underline italic">caught</hi>, &amp; shut up there, doing nothing! (losing time &amp; money) for 8–9 days! I went on to inspect Waipawa School before vacation (it having been omitted owing to the bothering Elections,) &amp;, there being no room in the rowdy houses there, I went across in the rain &amp; darkness to the Waipukurau; the next day it <hi rend="italic">poured</hi>: &amp; soon the rivers were very high (flocks of ducks in HRRs large paddock near Lloyd’s garden!!) &amp; no crossing for Coach until end of the next week. I came by the <hi rend="italic">early</hi> mg. C., although I had <hi rend="italic">promised </hi>Rev. J. White, &amp; others to meet them at Waipawa in the mg. &amp; return to N. by <hi rend="italic">afternn. </hi>C.,—however, I felt impelled <hi rend="italic">to go on</hi>! &amp; then the aftn. Coach broke down, this side of Te Aute, a sad overturn &amp; passengers <hi rend="italic">hurt</hi>: thanks be to <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>, for his deliverance!—P. Gow keeps the Hotel there now, &amp; seems a <hi rend="italic">nice quiet</hi> kind of man, &amp; has a <hi rend="italic">large amount</hi> of Custom. The day I went in, Miss Kelly of Pakipaki (no.2) was married to Bishop,—S.W’s. overseer. I cannot get Mr S.W. to come to any arrangement about my Waipawa Sections: he writes, &amp; talks, <hi rend="italic">very fair</hi>—but <hi rend="italic">does </hi>nothing, &amp;, consequently, I cannot (well) sell a Sn. there: a Ch. Commee. has now been formed at Waipawa, &amp; the <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Minister Mr. Eccles, who also took my part in the matter, brought the subject before them: but no! the Comee. being formed of Arrow, Collins, Rathbone, Philips, &amp;c.,—have the majority, &amp; say that Rochfort, Abbott, &amp; all <hi rend="italic">are wrong</hi>! Shall I go to law? or shall I give all up?</p>
         <p>Here, too, in town:—the Municipality <hi rend="italic">are </hi>carrying on! Their 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. Common Rate is now out; I give a sample; Hague’s paddock, Rent ₤30., they assess at ₤60. Steed’s, Rent ₤35., they assess at ₤50., my House &amp; paddock ₤95 (I don’t object to <hi rend="italic">this</hi>), but my little <hi rend="italic">gateway</hi> and, Wilkinson’s Cliff, is, ₤18. more!—then the unoccupied Beach Sns., those by Mao. Club, ₤45. <hi rend="italic">each</hi>, annual, value to let—all the others (scraps, &amp; all, from Scandinavian takings) in proportion:—I have been to see the Mayor: he says, They cannot alter it now, my only remedy is to Appeal before R.M., which I must do. Then they are seeking to carry a Water Rate,—hills to pay for flats! and have sent in to <hi rend="italic">me</hi> an Order to erect an earth closet within a month, failing which they will do it, &amp; make me pay: this, I suppose, they will do—but they cannot make me <hi rend="italic">use</hi> it! The P. Council is now sitting, and I see (last night) Lee managed to get Hills exempted from this Water rate,—if Gen Assy. will assent to it. J.A.S. tried to get my ₤100. struck off! it ended (I see) in ₤50. being added thereto; but this won’t keep me in the work,—it is far <hi rend="italic">too heavy</hi> for me,—I mean the <hi rend="italic">clerical </hi>portion: still I thank the P.C. for their <hi rend="italic">expression</hi>, &amp;c.</p>
         <p>Another very nasty thing (to me,) has happened here:—you may recollect 2 Sns. in Carlile Street not very far from Grindell’s, belonging to Te Hapuku, &amp; to “the Queen” (or Te Hei); well they had a nice ascent, for building, towards my hill: somehow the Railway (<hi rend="italic">Weber</hi>) got their assent to level, &amp;c. (for, I hear, a ₤5.)—of course, in so doing, ruining that property:—well, the quarry men went on, leaving no batta, &amp; <hi rend="italic">undermining mine</hi>, when down it came! Hague’s fence—4 posts &amp; rails,—a perfect ugly charm: I knew <hi rend="italic">not</hi> of it, (you know I don’t go out <hi rend="italic">there</hi> much, &amp; my man was ill w. fever,) Robjohns came to tell me of it—&amp; the very puriri posts &amp; V.D.L. rails were now being carried off for firing!—I went &amp; saw it—called on Weber,—<hi rend="italic">not his </hi>now, he left it secure, go to Peppercorne: I sought him, 2–3 weeks (rainy time). Hague now threatening about his horses, as I have to keep fences up, and at last P. says, <hi rend="italic">he left it</hi>, because the Railway sub-contractors would undermine, &amp; give him “jaw”,—he saw then what was coming; &amp; now I have been on those fellows track; &amp; Scully has taken it up: <hi rend="italic">all talk</hi> about it, as a great shame (you can see it from MacMurray’s)—but I fear that I, in this case also, “must grin &amp; bear it”!—The property <hi rend="italic">there</hi> is now spoiled—a ₤100. would not compensate, &amp; no one can say where the said charm will stop. My man is still weak,—<hi rend="italic">not yet</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">able to do any thing</hi>! Two nights ago P.D. came to see me,—it was 8, and I, of course, <hi rend="italic">alone</hi>: <hi rend="italic">no one had called of an evg. since you left</hi>! &amp; I almost wept at seeing any one. I do not think I can stand this excessive loneliness: I hope I may not, foolishly, <hi rend="italic">try it on too long</hi>,— — —</p>
         <p>The P.C. has gone on very well, an exceeding “happy family”: A Deane Speaker: J.A.S. seems the <hi rend="italic">leader </hi>of the Opposition! but cannot <hi rend="italic">do</hi> any thing. All the estimates were passed in no time. H.R. Russell’s petition for compensation (in Motuokaia Land Case) is now employing the <hi rend="italic">Select </hi>Comee. If he gets any—what should not some others also have? But see the Papers I send you.–</p>
         <p>The sickness is at last stayed in Town—but is still heavy in the Country—about Te Aute, &amp;c.—Nicholson’s wife, Kaikoura Hotel, is laid up—and Johnson at Poukawa, &amp; many others. The young folks of the Town (Newton’s, Moggridge’s, Smith’s, Yates’ &amp;c) are recovering—but very very slowly.—</p>
         <p>Barry tried to sell sections at Taradale, by auctn., but failed; cut them up too small (they say). Lyndon is going next week to sell a new Township at Pukahu, called Wolseley (!)—near Close’s land &amp; Collins’ House. H.R.R. is also going to <hi rend="italic">try </hi>his Hampden Land: but see the papers.</p>
         <p>Young Irvine is worse, in the Asylum! his Brother passed his second (or senior) examination <hi rend="italic">creditably</hi>. Ross has left the Grammar School. Knight (<hi rend="italic">again</hi>) lost his case against Miller! he is now in town as a clerk—somewhere—perhaps with Lascelles.</p>
         <p>Plenty more of law coming-on between Natives &amp; Europeans, holders of Land!—Lucky, you &amp; I, to escape that trouble, cost, &amp; anxiety. Dolbel took a gentleman to see his Mohaka Run—out in all the gale! lost his horse! forded rivers on foot, breast-high,—little to eat—no house at night, &amp; returned nearly dead! P.D. has got Rheumatism!! &amp; I fear, through foolishly <hi rend="italic">persevering</hi>, has lost a <hi rend="underline italic">good</hi> customer: but then he (P.D.) tried hard to get through, owing to <hi rend="italic">approaching </hi>Council. Wilson’s terrace not yet finished: another large Building (“Orange Lodge”?) between it &amp; Trestrail’s.</p>
         <p>And now I must conclude. I hope you &amp; yours are all quite well, &amp; enjoying with a zest the Eng. summer. I am pretty well. And heartily wishing you every good.</p>
         <p>I am, My Dear Sir,</p>
         <p>Yours truly</p>
         <p>W. Colenso</p>
         <p>P.S. I had forgotten to say, that yesterday Grubb spoke to me about your Premium—I told him <hi rend="italic">I will pay it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Maclinder is to keep Parkin’s house, &amp; Mrs P. is to be married to Topping: <hi rend="italic">on dit.</hi>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>