<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0958">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1896 February 4: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-1</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1896-02-04">1896 February 4</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1896 February 4: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-774" place="foot" n="774"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-1</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier Feby. 4th, 96;<lb/> 10 p.m.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Your kind welcome letter of 2nd inst. is <hi rend="italic">just now</hi> to hand and though I was about shutting up for the night—I will <hi rend="italic">commence</hi> a return one to you. My last to you was on Jany. 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. (&amp; <hi rend="italic">my first letter </hi>this year!) and lo! a month is already gone!!—(Ugh! how stupid! my last written on 16<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. January).</p>
         <p>Well: I am right glad that you have accomplished your <hi rend="italic">flitting</hi>, always troublesome, but in your case particularly so: and I am doubly glad (so to speak) that you have secured a <hi rend="italic">better</hi> situation and that you are satisfied with it, and also, that you have plenty of employment in office,—surely N. Year is beg. <hi rend="italic">well</hi> w. you?</p>
         <p>I note that you are <hi rend="italic">extra busy</hi> on the Sunday, and that you say (in defence),— “I write the same to you: but you <hi rend="italic">do</hi>, and after all I am the younger” True, my good friend—with this <hi rend="italic">vast difference</hi>—I have <hi rend="italic">no </hi>wife &amp; family <hi rend="underline italic">dependent</hi> on me: and while you <hi rend="italic">are </hi>mentally strong, you are <hi rend="italic">not </hi>possessed of an iron frame, and you are hard at work 6 days (&amp; sometimes nights) in each week, and you <hi rend="italic">know </hi>that our bodily frames <hi rend="italic">require </hi>that weekly <hi rend="italic">rest</hi>: had you <hi rend="italic">no </hi>work on the 6 days, or <hi rend="italic">no one dependent on you, </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">I would encourage you to the utmost in preaching the Truth</hi>.</p>
         <p>Our Dean <hi rend="italic">preaches</hi> some excellent sermons: I very much like to hear him. On Sy. last (mg.) he began with, “One reason why Ministers of various Xn. Denoms. do not succeed better is, <hi rend="italic">they do not live up to what they preach in the pulpit</hi>’: (evg.) he “walked” in to those well-to-do folks with every thing smiling around them—and <hi rend="italic">no</hi> thought of <hi rend="smallcaps">God. </hi>But it would require <hi rend="italic">your graphic pen</hi> to do him justice. I read Lessons for him last Sunday both mg. &amp; evg.—Heat <hi rend="italic">very great</hi>. Congn. overflowing at night. Heat <hi rend="italic">here</hi> in my shaded house 92º, 94º <hi rend="italic">yesterday</hi>, &amp; very close, but rain fell, &amp; cooled air.</p>
         <p>Last Thursday night (30<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. Jany.) I was much gratified in receiving a letter from dear Bp. Stuart (his <hi rend="italic">first to </hi>me) from Isfahan: I did not read it until <hi rend="italic">next morning</hi>, 31<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. and <hi rend="italic">then</hi> it suddenly flashed on my mind—that on <hi rend="italic">that day</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">that hour</hi>, we had parted at Ry. Station 2 <hi rend="italic">years</hi> before! when I lost my best &amp; truest friend in N.Z. (not excepting R.C.H.)—it was indeed a <hi rend="italic">sad time</hi> to me: his letter is a <hi rend="italic">long </hi>&amp; a <hi rend="italic">good</hi> one, and I have this day finished my long reply of 18pp., sending also, papers, &amp; copies of my p. in “Trans.” vols. XXVI, &amp; XXVII. Both the Bp. &amp; his good dear <hi rend="underline italic">filial</hi> daughter seem to be doing well there—but mostly among Armenians: great no. of Jews, also, residing there.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="underline italic">Feby. 5</hi>
            <hi rend="sup underline italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">.</hi> (noon). “Pity the sorrows of a poor old man.” I had, last night, discovd. my error <hi rend="italic">re </hi>my <hi rend="italic">latest letter</hi> to you: &amp; now, this mg, <hi rend="italic">yours to me </hi>of the “<hi rend="italic">18</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>”, on yr. “leaving for Tawa flat, written in one of those new flashy envelope cards, &amp; contg. the <hi rend="italic">good news </hi>of your having, at last, surmounted your difficulties—<hi rend="italic">re</hi> removal, &amp; so wrote cheerfully, &amp; thoughtfully for me, that <hi rend="italic">I might share your cake.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Well: now I am inclined to go on w. my letter—<hi rend="italic">feeling</hi>—out of sorts, not fit for anything—save sleep? &amp; then to be scared by ugly Dante like dreams &amp; demons!—I wish to send you few <hi rend="italic">excerpts</hi> that I have been culling for you—same may interest &amp; some make even <hi rend="italic">you </hi>laugh—i.e. <hi rend="underline italic">quietly</hi>.</p>
         <p>I am glad to know of your dear daughter having returned to you safe, but I had no thought of her going <hi rend="italic">by sea</hi>!! had made sure, it was to be by Rail. In town last week I saw Hon. Secy. (first for nearly 3 weeks) told him of letter from Gore <hi rend="italic">re</hi> supposed missing Paper—<hi rend="italic">all right</hi>, <hi rend="italic">now</hi>: &amp; reminded him of <hi rend="italic">day </hi>for Annl. Mtg. H.B. Ph. I.—took him by surprise— “no report ready”, &amp;c. however that would not matter, as it was understood, while Mtg. <hi rend="italic">called</hi>, no quorum (11) and so, <hi rend="italic">ppd. till March</hi>, when Hill would be here: he duly advd. it, but I see <hi rend="italic">nothing </hi>respecting it, in “D.T.” and “H.”—</p>
         <p>Pinkney is opening an oppsn. Girls’ High School. Dr. Sidey has <hi rend="italic">sold</hi> his house to Dr. Moore: S. told me it was too large for him, <hi rend="italic">now</hi>: but I have not learned the place of his future sojourn: Craig does <hi rend="italic">not </hi>know.</p>
         <p>A curious statement in p. this morng. Methodists at Waipawa, headed by Pendray, have met with “S. Army” leaders there, held high festival in M. Chapel, sworn to be brothers in wk., &amp; duly “<hi rend="italic">consecrated</hi>” themselves.—–</p>
         <p>A fortnight ago Bp. Williams issued Circulars—to meet in H.B. Farmers’ Assn. Room (Fielder’s Chambers) on 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. ulto. (<hi rend="italic">re </hi>petitioning Parlt. &amp;c.—for introdn. “Irish National Script. Lessons” into pub. schls.) (—<hi rend="italic">great holiday</hi> here, Caledonian Annual, Sports,)—well, I went; doors all locked—off to Deanery &amp; Cathl., fell in w. Bp. &amp; Dean,—Bp. went to <hi rend="italic">see</hi> for himself (doubting me?)—&amp; at last, after our <hi rend="italic">long standing in Tennyson Street</hi>,—strengthened by Cornford. Sen., &amp; Worboys—we held the said mtg. in St. John’s Sch. room—present (besides) St. Hill, Hobbs, &amp; the yg. Curate assistant from Taradale: (Clarke having to attend funeral there &amp; Welsh <hi rend="italic">absent</hi> w. Sy. Sch. picnic). I had thought over the matter (being well acqd. w. it &amp; “Irish Schl. Books”)—and after Bp. had <hi rend="italic">fully opened</hi>, I rose &amp; said my say—what I believed to be <hi rend="italic">better</hi>—&amp; <hi rend="underline italic">more likely</hi> to <hi rend="italic">please Voters</hi>—&amp; <hi rend="italic">pass in Parlt. </hi>viz. why “<hi rend="italic">Irish Natl</hi>.”—unpleasant to many: Books themselves contained verses from <hi rend="italic">Douay</hi>—to catch <hi rend="italic">R.</hi>C’s. 50 years ago in I., would not do so here—If Script. at all, our newest &amp; best Trans. (I should prefer N.T. only, or w. Job some Psalms, &amp; the <hi rend="italic">later</hi> Isaiah), our Teachers geny. would <hi rend="italic">not like</hi> it, (½ hour evy. mg., w. recital L.P.,) &amp; then, some other one to be appd. to that duty, a schism in sch. directly: better for ea. Mr. to use the <hi rend="italic">Saty</hi>. mg. with his own flock: I did not like even our Dean every Friday 3.30 p.m. with scholars—worn &amp; tired, fagged &amp; careless, &amp;c.—giving instances—<hi rend="italic">I had known</hi>.</p>
         <p>And then the sd. specimens Less. Bks. from Craig’s,—a. <hi rend="italic">wretchedly printed</hi> lot—, thin, very <hi rend="italic">small</hi> type, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">very dirty</hi> (I believe done in Scotland, &amp; I suppose a <hi rend="italic">contract</hi> job); what were in use when I was Inspr., were ptd. in Ireland, large type (L.P.) <hi rend="italic">&amp; well &amp; clearly done</hi>, &amp; thick volumes. W.C. finished; dead silence; Bp. spoke again (in a <hi rend="italic">low </hi>tone) but in favour of his scheme, which the Dean &amp; St. Hill supported: and so—it ended; Commee. to wk. <hi rend="italic">energetically</hi> w. a pd. Secy. &amp;c.—<hi rend="italic">first mtg</hi>. this aftn. III—but I don’t go. On leaving w. Cornford he told me, “I was right in what I said”. The Dean made a good sp.—only <hi rend="italic">gently </hi>replying to my obsns. re <hi rend="italic">his</hi> Friday aftns. The Bp. is gone inland to visit Bush District, &amp; will be some time away. I shall send you this mg’s. “<hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>”, as it contains 2 good arts., one, on wine, I wish <hi rend="italic">you to consider. </hi>On Saty. last, high noon, I was visited by m. &amp; wife, tourists, just landed to see me, &amp; back off to Aukld.—Card “<hi rend="italic">Alfred Webb</hi>.” They wished to know <hi rend="italic">much </hi>re Maoris—present state &amp; prospects: religion, &amp;c. I believe them to be Quakers—<hi rend="italic">very pleasant </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">time</hi>: Mrs. W. “a descendent from Fox”: they knew of my having known the 2 Wheelers, here (Bay of Islands) 1837, &amp; were <hi rend="italic">well</hi> acqd. w. Miss Colenso Natal’s daughter, &amp; <hi rend="italic">adv</hi>. for Zulus: they much wished to see <hi rend="italic">Te Aute Coll</hi>!!!—had been in Mr. Pope’s Compy. at Wgn. I parted w. regret: directed them to <hi rend="italic">Crerar</hi>, for <hi rend="italic">my pubs.</hi> wh. they took down: they are Irish, &amp; I <hi rend="italic">think</hi> he sd., he was in Ho. of Com.</p>
         <p>Looking into your letter again—I read (w. sorrow)— “We are all well—except that Mrs H. is sometimes <hi rend="italic">overwrought</hi>, for <hi rend="italic">her wk. is heavy</hi>”. Could not <hi rend="italic">you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">lighten it</hi>, (as formerly,) by being <hi rend="italic">more</hi> w. your family<hi rend="italic"> on Sundays</hi>?—pardon me this. A long kind note from Buller who is gone <hi rend="italic">far S.</hi> Has Sir Jas. Hector returned to Wellington?</p>
         <p>I suppose I must <hi rend="italic">halt</hi>, here: Heartily wishing you &amp; yours every needful Blessing, Bel. me Yours very truly</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>The Bp. says—I should learn prudence in my old years!!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
