<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0775">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 April 5: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-04-05">1891 April 5</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 April 5: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-520" place="foot" n="520"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier,<lb/>Sundy. Apl. 5/91: 3 p.m.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Already am I beg. a L. to you—to have it ready to send off (say) tomorrow.</p>
         <p>I left Dvk. on Thy. aftn.,—was at Waipawa until 4 p.m. Friday: while there saw Mr Eccles (who had kindly come to Ry. Sn. to meet me)—spent Friday mg. w. him: &amp; the <hi rend="italic">upshot</hi> is,—I am to preach the Thksg. S. there on Sy. evg. 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. inst. &amp; give the Lecture for Sy. Sch. on some evg. in that same week: &amp; so, I <hi rend="italic">think</hi>, I shall go back to Dvk. from W.—being ½-way there &amp; <hi rend="italic">May</hi> my <hi rend="italic">favourite</hi> month for being abroad. I had fine w. back, but it was very <hi rend="italic">hot</hi>, &amp; I saw signs of rain &amp; foretold it, &amp; it began on Fy. night,—all day yesterday (most refreshing to the parched earth!—so difft. outside!!), &amp; today showery cloudy &amp; cold,—few, I ween, at Ch. I hope to go to town tomorrow.</p>
         <p>On my arrival here (7 p.m.) I was not long in looking over the heterogenous lot of parcels, &amp;c, &amp;c, from all parts—&amp;, to my horror, found the <hi rend="italic">Dy</hi>. was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> among them! My man, who is very careful in all P.O. matters, says, he never saw such a parcel:—so I must enq. of Jago, &amp; <hi rend="italic">report</hi>. Among the lot of parcels was one large flat thin, (add. by you?)—this contained your Father’s scrap-book having the “Greenstone-mako,” story,—for which I am indebted to you:—I must run through it &amp; return it before I leave on next Saty.</p>
         <p>Among my “odds &amp; ends” from Dvk I find Large’s rect., wh. I <hi rend="italic">ought</hi> to have sent on to you—I now enclose it. By the way,—Large, Craig, Lyndon, Dinwiddie, Holt, Cooper, &amp; others were also in train w. me: returning from <hi rend="italic">their</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">holidays.—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I find, I have the celebrated <hi rend="italic">Asses</hi>-song! wh. I shall copy &amp; enclose.</p>
         <p>I also found (N.Z. Directy.) our correspdt. Dawson at Akaroa is <hi rend="italic">the P.M.</hi> there.</p>
         <p>I have just looked out a copy of my paper on the <hi rend="italic">Moa</hi>, and (in the same) <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi>, &amp;c, of Maoris:—<hi rend="italic">now</hi> you will be able to discern <hi rend="italic">how</hi> Smith used my p. on Proverbs!—I cannot understand Collier’s <hi rend="italic">quotn.</hi> on my Moa Paper:—As I sd. before to you, I <hi rend="italic">never heard</hi> of Owen’s <hi rend="italic">early</hi> paper:<lb/>1. <hi rend="italic">Sd.</hi> to have been sent out to N.Z.?<lb/>2. <hi rend="italic">when?</hi> 3. <hi rend="italic">to whom</hi>? 4. <hi rend="italic">who recd. </hi>it? <lb/>5. <hi rend="italic">By what means</hi>, &amp;c——</p>
         <p>Prof. Owen, himself, repubd. my paper in “Annuals” &amp;c (dated May 1/42), without any such note or remark:—and, <hi rend="italic">subsequently</hi>, kindly sent me copies of his large elab. papers (of <hi rend="italic">later dates</hi>) on Apteryx, &amp; on Dinornis. Dr Mantell was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> deceived, <hi rend="italic">neither</hi> was Sir W.J. Hooker, nor Prof. Owen, himself.—</p>
         <p>[Monday 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 3 p.m., <hi rend="italic">in town this</hi> mg.] Having (I fear) Owen &amp; Moa (one or both) “on my brain”! I will <hi rend="italic">first</hi> go on w. this.</p>
         <p>At <hi rend="italic">our</hi> Phil. Inst. Liby.—I took up <hi rend="italic">Owen,—</hi>“Extinct Wingless Birds of N.Z.” and I copy from it the following:—<lb/>“first piece of a bone brought to Coll. of S., to Owen, for sale in 1839:—on publication of his paper respg. it, in 183<hi rend="underline">8</hi>”(?)—“100 extra copies were struck off &amp; distributed <hi rend="italic">in</hi> N.Z.”(?) “In this distribn. I was effy. aided by Col. W. Wakefield—by J.R. Gowen, Esq., a Dir. of the then newly estabd. N.Z. Co.; by my friend Sir W. Martin, and by the Bp. of N.Z.”— “Answers, anxiously expected through years 1840, 1841, &amp; 1842,—at length arrived in letters from Rev.W. Cotton, &amp; Col.Wd..”</p>
         <p rend="end">
            <hi rend="italic">Vol</hi>.I. preface, p.V.</p>
         <p>At p.109, an extract is given from Col. Wd’s. letter to J.R. Gowen, Esq.—</p>
         <p rend="end">“Wgn. 19 Sept. 1843. </p>
         <p>“I recd<hi rend="italic">. lately</hi> your letter respg. the Moa, <hi rend="italic">with</hi> Profr. Owen’s <hi rend="italic">notice</hi>. I have taken steps to procure some of the bones,”&amp;c.—</p>
         <p>[This is all that I can find bearing on the subject.]</p>
         <p>There is, however, a long letter from Rev. W. Williams to Dr Buckland, Oxford, sent from Poverty Bay w. some Moa bones, &amp; written in Feby/42,—in which <hi rend="italic">no allusion whatever is made to any paper of Prof. Owen’s, (nor, I </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">regret to have to say</hi>, to my visit there in Decr./41, nor to the bones I then gave to W.W. to be sent Home:—unless such has been subsy. eliminated!—<hi rend="italic">I have my good reasons for thinking thus:) altogether</hi> it seems to me quite of a piece (though not so valid) as the story of J. Smith the <hi rend="italic">first</hi> N.Z. <hi rend="underline italic">printer</hi>!—</p>
         <p>I suppose, you pretty well know, there was <hi rend="italic">no</hi> friendship between the N.Z. Coy.,&amp; the <hi rend="italic">old Missionaries</hi>:—besides, they (Wakefield &amp; Co.)—kept far away to the S., in Cook’s Straits; &amp; had, I expect, far more important matters to look after: but the date and <hi rend="italic">tenour</hi> of Col. Wakefield’s letter to Mr Gowen is sufft. for <hi rend="italic">me</hi>.</p>
         <p>I called early at P.O. to see Jago <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the missing parcel (T’s. Dy.)—he &amp; all his people know nothing of it, &amp; affirm such a parcel <hi rend="italic">never came there</hi>.—So I shall post this letter to you at once, without waiting for yours, hoping you there at Lyon &amp; Blairs’ may be able to satisfactorily ascertain all about it, &amp; send me on my book. Being a Library (&amp; dearer) copy, it may be more easily put to rights: <hi rend="italic">I hope so</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I called in at Craig’s, and he showed me a copy of the work, but I had <hi rend="italic">too much to do </hi>to stay or even to open it:—it was a 21/- one<hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Rev.—Tuke, got hold of me in street, to accompy. the Dean to their thksg. Serv. at Meeanee on Wedy. evg. (he had sent me a Card,)—<hi rend="italic">I may go</hi>.</p>
         <p>Robert brought me a card on Saty. evg. from p. box—a letter for me at counter by paying fee: well this mg. I got it—and it was a note from Hon. Secy.White: wishing to know, how <hi rend="italic">many</hi> p., &amp; <hi rend="italic">when</hi>,—from me, this season, as Cl. are desirous of drawing up a “syllabus” &amp;c.—note, <hi rend="italic">dated 28 March</hi>, <hi rend="italic">posted at N. 2</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">nd</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> April</hi>, &amp; at Dvk. On <hi rend="italic">3</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">rd</hi>.</p>
         <p>“The “Ass song”—must <hi rend="italic">stand over</hi>.</p>
         <p>Here I must close:—</p>
         <p>I propose leaving N. on <hi rend="italic">Saturday</hi> next: but I will write again shortly.</p>
         <p>With kind regards</p>
         <p>Yours truly</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
