<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0832">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 June 18: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-06-18">1892 June 18</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 June 18: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-591" place="foot" n="591"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Woodville<lb/>Saty. aftn., June 18/92</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I only recd. yours of the 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—and as I am here on <hi rend="italic">this</hi> occasion earlier than usual and have an idle hour I <hi rend="italic">commence </hi>a letter to you which I may finish on Monday. I expect the Bp. here this afternoon, which is also the cause of my being here now. Last Sunday (&amp; indeed the Saturday also), the weather was really dreadful! Worse I think than on the Saturday before. Yesterday the long-wished-for change took place—it was fine—today glorious! May we have such weather tomorrow. I hope you have read Capt. Russell’s speech to his Hastings constituents on Saty, 11<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. (as given in “Herald.” If not let me know—I have a spare copy.) I have at last! written my offl. L. to the Native Minister &amp; sent it in; how pleased I should have been if <hi rend="italic">you</hi> could have seen my draft (&amp; probably aided me) before I copied it! but time was pressing &amp; I wished him to get it <hi rend="italic">before </hi>the opening. Mentioning that reminds me of what I have long wished to get from you—(1) <hi rend="italic">re </hi>my <hi rend="underline italic">first</hi> paper to MacLean, N. M., 1873, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Lex.—of which I sent you a copy, &amp; asking, If you had before seen it? and so, (2) <hi rend="italic">re </hi>a paper that went to you w. it—i.e. my <hi rend="underline italic">Petition</hi> to Parlt. presented by Captn. Russell—did you ever before see <hi rend="italic">that</hi>?—of course (!!!) I gained <hi rend="italic">nothing </hi>by it, but it has a <hi rend="italic">long </hi>story.—In my <hi rend="italic">last </hi>notes to Capt. R. (writing on Lex.) I mentioned my letter to McLean of ’73, asking him (Capt. R.) to look it up, in Appx Journals, &amp; read it, as I had not a copy with me to send to him. Capt. R. leaves about <hi rend="italic">end </hi>of next week. Re Hudson’s book &amp; your “Review”: you did not (I think) tell me at the time that you <hi rend="italic">had </hi>written a Review, but, that you had been applied to &amp; had not made up yr. mind: I have just looked into it, &amp; <hi rend="italic">purpose </hi>doing so more fully <hi rend="italic">next week </hi>&amp; then writing to you about it. [I cannot write well <hi rend="italic">here</hi>—table shaking unsteady, &amp; seat too low.] Condie, Taradale, is dead, long ailing: and a mighty fuss made over a Jockey (Clifford alias “Wally”) who died at Gisborne, body brought to Hastings, a grand funeral! and his <hi rend="italic">race </hi>friends wanted Hobbs to preach a <hi rend="italic">funeral sermon</hi>!!! Report in “Herald,” of mtg. H.B.Ph.Inst. on Monday 13<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>, was astonishing, subject [<hi rend="strikethrough">Network</hi> fell asleep here for 5 winks! &amp; can not reading own last word!!!] Waitomo Caves, nr. Auckland, &amp; Bold aiding with Limelight; but I was staggered with “200 present” <hi rend="italic">N.B. </hi>our <hi rend="italic">big</hi> room will scarcely hold 80, &amp; so I wrote to Hill, Prest. &amp; Chn.—–Rees (noisy &amp; slap-dash, &amp;c &amp;c) had been having a duel w. Ed. Herald (Pirani?) over Ed’s. Review of Rees’ Life Sir G. Grey: I wish R. had <hi rend="italic">not </hi>come to Napier to reside, but you will soon have him w. you at Wgn. In mentg. (again) to you re Appx. 1861, &amp; the Petition <hi rend="italic">v. </hi>Renata, I had supposed it was an exceptionally <hi rend="italic">easy </hi>matter for <hi rend="italic">you</hi>—seeing you &amp; Didsbury were so friendly, &amp;c &amp;c. I am sure it was my copy Appx. and I think the very last page in the big book. <hi rend="italic">I had long sought my copy</hi>,—early lent to McLean or to Fannin,—or to – – – but in vain. Many of the Papers, &amp;c. of that date were lost in the “White Swan.”<note xml:id="ftn3-592" place="foot" n="592"> On 29 June 1862 the S.S. <hi rend="italic">White Swan</hi> was holed by a rock while carrying politicians, civil servants and state documents to the first meeting of the Government in the new Capital, Wellington. The Captain ran her ashore at Uriti Point with no loss of life, but great loss of official papers. The 1861 <hi rend="italic">Appendices</hi> does not contain any document that could be described as a petition against Renata Kawepo (who was then opposing land sales while swearing his allegiance to the Queen), so it may well have been lost in the wreck.</note> Possibly, your “cockabulli” is the S. <hi rend="italic">pakeha </hi>pronunciation (or writing) for <hi rend="italic">Kokopu. </hi>I had a nasty fall, over <hi rend="italic">abrupt &amp; steep </hi>end of a newly cut kerb in going to Ch. last Sunday night in darkness &amp; tempest &amp; rain!! at first I feared I was done for! it gave me an awful <hi rend="italic">internal twisting</hi>, &amp; brought back Rheumatism in back &amp; loins, which lasted 2–3 days, but I felt, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">am</hi>, thankful ’twas no worse. Night pitch dark, with <hi rend="italic">strong </hi>wind &amp; rain.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="underline italic">Sunday aftn., 19</hi>
            <hi rend="sup underline italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">. 2p.m.</hi>—</p>
         <p>Shut up here I now proceed with my letter. Yesty. 3 p.m. I walked to Ry. Station to meet the Bishop: he came, well, (I had not seen him since he was last in town,) &amp; we walked together to hotel.—On our way, <hi rend="italic">Sowry </hi>came up to us, riding hard &amp; going on towards Manawatu, saying, Mr. Penney’s <hi rend="italic">eldest </hi>son was just now drowned in that river! His <hi rend="italic">youngest </hi>was buried about 3 wks. ago in that stormy weather,) It appears the young fellow (?17 or so) had been about a week or more, on some newly-acquired land on E. side, &amp; was returning in company, but missing the ford horse rolled over &amp; both were carried down the river! (body not yet found, &amp; may not be!) As the Bp. <hi rend="italic">knew </hi>Mr. P. well he went to his house to see him that evg. I don’t know him—not even by sight.—–Weather this day fair <hi rend="italic">for winter</hi>, showery <hi rend="italic">after </hi>XI., Bp. preached from 1 John IV 8–9 (Epistle for the Day) Congn. about 50–55. He is gone this aftn. to Victoria,—as Mr. Burnett, Chwdn. had <hi rend="italic">so </hi>advertised.—–</p>
         <p>The Bp. told me—the last mtg. of our Society was held in the <hi rend="italic">big </hi>room—to show Bold’s Limelight display of the Cave photo’s.—and, that there were <hi rend="italic">not </hi>200 people present; he merely went to see the <hi rend="italic">pictures</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I was very pleased to hear such a favourable account of all your children—<hi rend="italic">may such continue &amp; increase</hi>! I was very busy last week <hi rend="italic">re </hi>outgoing Eng. Mail; in writing from Dvk. one has a <hi rend="italic">few hours later</hi>. You kindly enq. after the little grandr. in England, she is still improving, still taking med.—still in Londn. physician’s hands: her parents <hi rend="italic">now </hi>have good hopes. Last week I had 2 sad notes from John Anderson (my man’s son) both f. and m. laid up w. La Grippe, f. <hi rend="italic">severely</hi>, John went to seek Dr. H.—who sd. he was not able to <hi rend="italic">climb my hill</hi>! but (as John says) “he manfully endeavoured &amp; <hi rend="italic">did </hi>so”—but w. this mournful addition—that he, the Dr., did not expect to live thro’ another week!! Poor dear <hi rend="italic">old soul</hi>! I trust he will yet be long spared to N., <hi rend="italic">we cannot afford to lose him.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There is (I am <hi rend="italic">told</hi>) a very large attendance of Maoris at H. Tomoana’s place; the “best of it is”—that (the Papers say, from their “own Correspdts.” on the ground) that they “have the <hi rend="underline italic">origl.</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>Treaty of Waitangi”!! Possibly it <hi rend="italic">may </hi>be one of the 100 copies I printed <hi rend="italic">at the time</hi> on blue flp. folio; (I see <hi rend="italic">it </hi>now in my mind’s eye!) It seems a curious coincidence, that they should hold <hi rend="italic">such </hi>a Meeting <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, &amp; that I (perhaps the <hi rend="italic">only </hi>Europn. living who was <hi rend="italic">present</hi>) should be <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, almost within hail! &amp; wholly ignored! I wonder if any of those Maoris there who can read English, has seen my little book of “the Sg. the Ty. of W.”?—I think it would interest them—<hi rend="italic">all</hi>—to read of the <hi rend="italic">speeches </hi>of their Chiefs.—–</p>
         <p>I have not looked into “Morris” since my last (no time), but have often thought of one of his simple &amp; pathetic tales at the end!! as an “Albatross”: is it in yours? I not unfrequently think on his words:—</p>
         <p>“Ah! sometimes too much knowledge blights;<lb/>And ignorance indeed is blest.”—–</p>
         <p>I was much pleased to find the Jury in the <hi rend="italic">Eketahuna</hi> (?) Murder Case had found a v. of “Not gy.” <hi rend="italic">To me</hi>—it was simply shameful on the part of Govt. (&amp; that <hi rend="italic">old C.J.</hi>,<note xml:id="ftn3-593" place="foot" n="593"> Sir James Prendergast was Chief Justice 1875–1899.</note> whom I much dislike cannot account for “antipathies”)—to put those 2 men <hi rend="italic">repeatedly </hi>on their trial! The time may yet come, when a man—committed to gaol on little or no evidence—whether for an alleged civ. or crim. offence—<hi rend="italic">may turn round and obtain damages </hi>for such imprisonment, for such false &amp; slanderous charges,—and that too (&amp; especially) from <hi rend="italic">ignorant </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">careless </hi>country J.P’s.,—&amp; <hi rend="italic">lying Police</hi>!—–</p>
         <p>I suppose you saw, in papers, the pars. respg. Canon D’Arcy Irvine, &amp; his resignation of his benefice? What a pity, our vol. of “Trans.” not yet out! Should you see Gore—ask, If Authors’ copies can not be issued <hi rend="italic">before </hi>the vol. those at all events wh. have not plates.</p>
         <p>And now w. kindest regards &amp; best wishes, believe me yours truly, W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
