<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0992">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1897 March 26: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1897-03-26">1897 March 26</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1897 March 26: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-823" place="foot" n="823"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Woodville, March 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.,<lb/>1897.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Yours of 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. to hand this afternoon (with several others, &amp; 2 packets of <hi rend="italic">work</hi>!) I thank you for it, and I clearly see—If I am to ansr. it early—I must <hi rend="italic">now </hi>do so.</p>
         <p>I left N. on 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>—stayed a night at Waipu. &amp; came straight on <hi rend="italic">here</hi>—for the <hi rend="italic">first time</hi>—Baddeley <hi rend="italic">not replying</hi> in time to my note: here I found Eccles unwell, &amp; in Dr’s. hands, so I have been &amp; am helping: I took both Services last Sunday (besides 4 long walkings to &amp; fro) and the day was a most trying one—the wind a hurricane, &amp; dead against me; I could scarcely totter along the roads: E. having gone off to N. for a change &amp; is still absent, so I have to take Ch. duty again here on 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>—and, it <hi rend="italic">may</hi> be, afterward: weather today and of late very wet &amp; cold.</p>
         <p>Had good &amp; attent. Congns. last Sy.—especially at night: <hi rend="italic">three</hi> Services were <hi rend="italic">advertised </hi>for that day: 1. the “Wesleyan Ch.”, annual Harvest thksg. 2. the Presbytn. Ch., <hi rend="italic">spl.</hi> Sermon <hi rend="italic">re </hi>a late great professor. 3. “Army—spl. Services, 3, mg., aftn., night, by Mr. John Younghusband.”<lb/>—Have only been out twice all this week, owing to wet &amp; wind: one day I called at the Manse, &amp; spent an hour with Rev. H. Lewis,—who had early &amp; kindly called <hi rend="italic">here</hi> to see me—I absent: leaving him I visited G. Heslop, who is recovering from his broken scalp—in jumping from his buggy to save himself. I have had letters from N., <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Mr. Hill (&amp; others of <hi rend="italic">that ilk</hi>) and am sorry to find, that H. now says, “<hi rend="italic">I never intended to give that £1,500</hi>” &amp;c. and more of a similar kind—aye <hi rend="italic">worse</hi>. I mention this to <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">only</hi>. Robertshawe has also been interviewed at Dvk. by a <hi rend="italic">Napier man</hi>, re <hi rend="italic">W.C.</hi>, and R. has come out strong—that I was always against H. Ch., and would not preach as he wished,—getting old—inclined to lecture his Cgn. &amp;c, &amp;c. (and so it goes! <hi rend="italic">those two</hi>, whom I had so greatly trusted—<hi rend="italic">&amp; loved</hi>!!—late in Feby. I recd. a strong, affect., begging note from Bamford (R’s. Churchwdn. &amp; friend) begging <hi rend="italic">aid </hi>towards enlargement of Eng. Ch. at Dvk.—“<hi rend="italic">NO</hi>”, reply, owing to their doctrine &amp; tactics:—The Dean is to be there on 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. proxo. to open enlarged Ch. &amp; R. to be at Cathedral, long desired! Our friend, Rev. R. Fraser is about to leave N.Z. for Home, his goods to be sold on 31<hi rend="sup">st</hi>; he visits Taupo then ’Pukurau, and If he preaches a S. (his last) in Sc. Ch. <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, I will (D.V.) be there to hear him. He is one of the dearest <hi rend="italic">Sc. Ministers</hi> to me: I have known him for many years: heard him preach in the old school-room <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, when I was Inspr. Schools. I have been trying hard to induce <hi rend="italic">his</hi> countrymen &amp; brother Ministers to make up a purse—for F. is poor, thro’ having been so shamefully robbed by a fellow at Havelock—who was an elder in Sc. Ch.!—but Dr.S., &amp; Mr. J.G.P. don’t look favourably on the plan: we must try—I give £5.5.0. (first don.) and I shall try others. You will have <hi rend="italic">heard </hi>of Licencing Election at N. yesty. I am <hi rend="italic">glad</hi>—those 2 women are <hi rend="italic">out</hi>, &amp; at <hi rend="italic">bottom</hi>! ditto <hi rend="italic">Large</hi>!!! L., now-a-days, will <hi rend="italic">seek </hi>everything. Have just concluded a contract with Holt, to re-roof House w. Iron, &amp; felt and re-line, upstairs, &amp;c—making a big hole in £100, <hi rend="italic">necessary work</hi>, yet, <hi rend="italic">If I knew </hi>of my time being <hi rend="italic">short</hi>, I would not have concluded it. <hi rend="italic">Money </hi>scarce, yet applications from all quarters! Even England, since I came hither.—–</p>
         <p>A letter to hand the evg. from Rev. W. Welsh, bemoaning death of a young m. named Compton (one of his choir) leaving wife (sick) &amp; 2 children: you may have known him. In passing thro’ Waipukurau I heard your cousin was much better: I did <hi rend="italic">not </hi>see Mr. Grant. Yesty. <hi rend="italic">2 packets </hi>from Hector! one, my “Pt. Address”: I am pleased at <hi rend="italic">this</hi>—being <hi rend="underline italic">my last</hi>; one, my short Botl. paper. And <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, this evg., 2 from Govt. printer, 2 packets, one—<hi rend="italic">revise</hi> in pp. of last proofs: &amp; one proofs (bulky) of a <hi rend="italic">fresh </hi>sheet in slips: but I cannot look at them till after Sy., and I have had a large no. of letters to ansr., so that, though shut up here, my hands are full, and <hi rend="underline italic">I am keeping very well</hi>. My chief want being, <hi rend="italic">a sofa to recline on</hi>, &amp; the bed (in bed-room) being away from light; However I have <hi rend="underline italic">much</hi> to be thankful for, &amp; hope I may be able to hold out a little longer.—–For 2 hours this night I have been in a <hi rend="italic">strange </hi>position (may <hi rend="italic">you</hi> never know it!). The noise of the big drops heavy rain on iron roof (my priv. parlour being upstairs) and the <hi rend="italic">worse</hi> noise of folks on piano in “Commercial” room immy. beneath me!—</p>
         <p>I am glad to know your foot has recovered its wonted vigour—may I add? let not that lesson be in vain. Thank you for what you have said <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Bosher—but still, it is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> clear to me! I fear it is <hi rend="italic">another</hi> of Wgn. Jury muddles. What shameful disclosures <hi rend="italic">re</hi> that fellow Ward! yclept “<hi rend="underline italic">Hon</hi>”! I <hi rend="italic">cannot go</hi> with all this <hi rend="italic">fuss</hi> &amp;c <hi rend="italic">re</hi> show of male stock for <hi rend="italic">Home</hi>, Maoris, and all! more <hi rend="italic">waste </hi>of public money. Pleased to know you <hi rend="italic">saw</hi> Rev. J.G.P. at Wgn., a reminiscence, &amp;c, &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>And now Good Bye. May every blessing be yours—family, leash, and store. </p>
         <p>With kindest regards, ever affy. yours</p>
         <p> W. Colenso</p>
         <p>I agree w. writer of that letter in Wgn. P. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Cathedral, and have the <hi rend="italic">lowest </hi>opinion of that miscreant Pusey! at <hi rend="italic">Home</hi>, I denounced him &amp; his teachings as the curse of Ch. of Engld. P. was suspended 3 yrs. by Bp. Oxford for his vile Sermons.</p>
         <p>PS have been reading “Banks’ Journal”. Very interesting; but <hi rend="italic">defective</hi> in <hi rend="underline italic">N.Z.</hi> matters; still something to be gained from it.—</p>
         <p>Letters &amp; papers Delivd. here curiously!<lb/>“Herald”—day <hi rend="italic">after </hi>pubn. xi.30 a.m.<lb/>“D.T.”—<hi rend="italic">second </hi>day <hi rend="italic">after pubn</hi>.—(ditto)</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
