<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1064">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1898 November 13: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1898-11-13">1898 November 13</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1898 November 13: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-922" place="foot" n="922"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">
            <hi rend="italic">Napier, Sunday night, late<lb/>November 13</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">
               <lb/>1898</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I must try &amp; write you a few lines tonight. <hi rend="italic">Imprimis</hi>: I hope you (&amp; yours) are quite well, and that w. Parlt. rising <hi rend="italic">your heavy &amp; continuous </hi>labours have ceased. I have often, <hi rend="italic">very often</hi>, had you in mind——and something more. I duly recd. your kind post-card &amp; thank you for it. I have been (&amp; <hi rend="italic">am</hi>) very busy—partly owing to the carelessness, or shortsightedness of others! I was going inland early last month, (legal business, &amp;c, at Waipawa) <hi rend="italic">obliged</hi> to defer it on account of Synod, &amp; then, when about leaving, all packed, a wire from Eccles at <hi rend="italic">Newmkt. Auckland</hi>! asking me to go to Wdv. on Sunday 30<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. ult., &amp; take 2 Services!—At <hi rend="italic">first </hi>sight—I roared, <hi rend="italic">Kahore</hi>: for E. was to have seen me <hi rend="italic">re </hi>such matters after Synod, &amp; left N. without doing so! However, better thoughts prevailed, &amp; I agreed to go: left N. on 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. for Wpu., &amp; thence to Wdv. on 29<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. staid 2 days at Vicarage, weather <hi rend="underline italic">dreadful</hi> both wind &amp; rain! however was enabled to do the duty—&amp; returned to N. (from Dvk. &amp; Wpku. on Saty. 5<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.)—In some fluster from S.F. Mail <hi rend="italic">closing</hi> on the <hi rend="italic">Tuesday </hi>nt. <hi rend="italic">That </hi>aftn. your Mr. Robertson called, &amp; I spent an <hi rend="italic">agreeable </hi>hour w. him, he only got from me a copy ea. of 2 old proclamations, or circulars, ½ sht. fcp. ea: one Maori, one Eng. He <hi rend="italic">much </hi>wishes for <hi rend="italic">copy N.T.</hi>—8vo. I showed him <hi rend="italic">my 2</hi>—remaining copies, (of which more anon).—–</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Last week, </hi>Hill sent me a <hi rend="italic">big </hi>case of shrubs, &amp;c, from the Ruahine <hi rend="italic">woods</hi> (gathd. by him &amp; Olsen <hi rend="italic">on the Sunday</hi>—6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) Mostly Clematis, the large fld. sp. &amp; 2 immense mats of kidney fern, and some com. <hi rend="italic">big</hi> Ferns, &amp;c, &amp;c, all ruthlessly chopped down, &amp; up by roots—as <hi rend="italic">a loving souvenir </hi>to me from the woods!!! (I wished them 20 fathoms deep!) The <hi rend="italic">big case </hi>gave me &amp; Robert some trouble, and at last I sent it, w. ½ contents—as was marked—to Mr. Hill, by Barry, express costing me 2/6: besides 2–3 days of heavy &amp; extra <hi rend="italic">fag</hi>!—–</p>
         <p>To cut short,—last Saty., 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. a letter offl. from “Dept. Justice”,—from Seddon—that, “If I would supply E. H. “Mao. Lex.” Govt. would print it” (short &amp; sweet). I have replied, “Yes, <hi rend="italic">endeavour </hi>to do so, though <hi rend="italic">time lost </hi>thro’ delay I fear may op. agt. me,” (also short)—and tomorrow I intend wtg. to Mackay, to ask him If he will rec press copy, written on <hi rend="italic">both </hi>sides—but <hi rend="italic">thus</hi>: on <hi rend="italic">rt. hd. </hi>page the <hi rend="italic">main </hi>body of wk., on <hi rend="italic">left </hi>hd. p. the additions (words) to be inserted, and, fearing my long description may not be clear, I shall say, that <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, who have seen the Ms., could perhaps explain, &amp;c.—My old rough Ms. is compiled <hi rend="italic">Maori fashion</hi>—the 2 vowels used instead of the <hi rend="italic">long</hi> marked one. And, of course, there will be a <hi rend="italic">deal </hi>of extra wk. in copying—in bringing words into their proper sequence: if M. <hi rend="italic">can grant it, that will save an extra copy</hi>. However, <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, I could wish S. had <hi rend="italic">not </hi>agreed,—as I fear my part will be too heavy for me: age tells! <hi rend="italic">six </hi>months thus <hi rend="underline italic">lost</hi>!!——</p>
         <p>I send you a “<hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>” w. this—to show the <hi rend="italic">utter rubbish</hi> of some folks. And I am thinking of asking Sir J.H. for <hi rend="italic">sheets</hi> of Kirk’s Flora, as far as it has been printed—<hi rend="italic">giving reasons</hi>, &amp;c. It seems (<hi rend="italic">to me</hi>) rather strange that not a word has <hi rend="italic">come forth re </hi>all those copies “A” Mao. Lex. given out by S.—–And I am not yet told—<hi rend="italic">my cost</hi> (though repeatedly asked for). I gave a copy to yr. friend R. Good bye</p>
         <p>I am keeping well. Kind regards.</p>
         <p>Yours truly,             W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="sub">*</hi>
            <hi rend="sup">*</hi>
            <hi rend="sub">*</hi>
            <hi rend="sup "> </hi>Good art. in “Herald” of Thursday 10th—paper by Miss Bisland in N. Am. Review. Would that our noisy women wod. read &amp; learn.</p>
         <p>Just recd. from your son, who requested— “when <hi rend="italic">read </hi>by me to forward to you”—have no time to read it, &amp; forward at once: hope you &amp; yours, there w. you, are all <hi rend="underline italic">well</hi>.</p>
         <p rend="end">W.C.<lb/>24/xi/98</p>
         <p>H.H. Bridge, called this aft., &amp; spent 2 hours</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
