<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0341">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1877 June 25: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1877-06-25">1877 June 25</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1877 June 25: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-289" place="foot" n="289"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand<lb/>June 25  1877.</p>
         <p>A. Luff, Esq.</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir</p>
         <p>Out outg. Mail does not close until 30<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., but I fear if I do not write to you <hi rend="italic">now</hi> I may not at all, for I am desperately busy! (end of Finanl. Year! &amp; Edu. Board sitting on 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. proxo. &amp; both Bd. &amp; Govt. wanting <hi rend="italic">every </hi>thing in by XII p.m. of 30<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. including my Annual Reports. I have just worked up <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the Qly. Returns which have come in (through sticking to it all day <hi rend="italic">yesterday</hi>—Sunday!)—Teachers, as usual, being behind: and now I turn to you. I wrote to you on the 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. of this mo.,—still I have much to say if I had time. Yours of May 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. came to hand 3 days ago, glad to find you were all then well, &amp; that the Photos. of Manawatu reached you safely. Did you get the Illustd. Austn. paper containing likeness of Sir Donald?—You make me smile when you speak of “owing me for outlay”!! Do you forget the money you <hi rend="italic">sent </hi>me? &amp;c &amp;c—but more anon.</p>
         <p>Since my last Sup. Court has sat;—Libel Case (Ky. Knowles Newton, v. Carlile &amp; Co.,) dreadful sounding of bugles &amp; trumpets, &amp;c. Jury gave Ky. ¼d. damages!!—Judge spoke <hi rend="italic">against </hi>it, &amp; would <hi rend="italic">not </hi>grant costs! Mrs Blair (Keith, now,) v. Neal &amp; Close (or rather N. &amp; C. v. Keith) about the Bakery &amp;c in Carlyle St., N. &amp; C. <hi rend="italic">won</hi>: but Robjohns tells me he understands, she is going on with <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the others! Neagle, Taradale affair, fined ₤100. Canning v. H. Matua,—C. won, but H.M. made over by <hi rend="italic">mortgage </hi>every thing he had, including his buggy, to H.R.R.!! But see the Papers I have already managed to put up for you. I send you also a Waka Maori that you may see the <hi rend="italic">nice </hi>Map of the seat of War got out for the Maoris &amp;c in it. I send you also some larger N.Z. papers, in which you may see matters of interest,—poor Singleton Rochfort!——</p>
         <p>Dr. H’s. son, Claud, has had a narrow escape, fell between the trucks, &amp; got much mangled, but can be mended—they say Louis Pelichet, also broke his leg—in autumn, but is well again.</p>
         <p>Jeffares has <hi rend="italic">both</hi> Toll-gates &amp; Gleadow has to “cut &amp; run”! Neale has been to me about Tn. Sn. 108, for a Wesleyn. parsonage (Smalley began it)—but, as I have no time, have put it off until <hi rend="italic">next week</hi> Pocock is offering his Sns. (see advt.)—I wrote to ask price of the corner one in Cl. Sq. (<hi rend="italic">under water</hi>), answer just in,—₤<hi rend="underline italic">400</hi>. Bosh!! Miller has lately sold a Run away in the Pohue direction (see Papers), and Maney’s <hi rend="italic">Moteo</hi> block is to be sold by auction next mo. “by order of Registrar of Sup. Court.”</p>
         <p>Whitmore, J.N. Wilson, Capt. McLean, &amp; Blythe, are gone to the hot springs—all for Rheumatism. A culvert has just been made in M. Road, <hi rend="italic">above </hi>my gate, and down in Cl. Sq, W. side—but, I fear, much too narrow, as they <hi rend="italic">always</hi> are. Many thanks (till I pay) for the seeds—come in good time, &amp; apparently capital condition. The tenant (Gillice) who took Martin’s place, has bolted, &amp; cheated me of 5 quarters, &amp; now I have let it to Troy,—who will soon <hi rend="italic">purchase </hi>it at just what it cost: <hi rend="italic">I am tired</hi>.</p>
         <p>I send you Papers contg. all about the <hi rend="italic">trials</hi>. Have to go to 2 more schools this week, weather permitting: <hi rend="underline italic">still</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">fine</hi>. Was at 6 last week, am pretty well done. To Wairoa (D.V.) in July.</p>
         <p>     Goodbye, Very truly yours,      W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>Meeting of H.B.P. Inst. went off <hi rend="italic">very well</hi>. Sending a <hi rend="italic">Paper</hi>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>