<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1036">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1898 March 11: to William Colenso</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL Ms-papers-10535-1.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1898-03-11">1898 March 11</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1898 March 11: to William Colenso<note xml:id="ftn3-884" place="foot" n="884"> ATL Ms-papers-10535-1.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, New Zealand,<lb/>March 11<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., 1898.</p>
         <p>My dear nephew William</p>
         <p>I thinking last to you was on the 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. Jany., since then yours of 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. Decr. is to hand, and I thank you for it, &amp; for all your kind Xmas. &amp; N. Year wishes.—Very pleased to hear of you &amp; your family being well―&amp; also of your son Rd. <hi rend="italic">doing well</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Yesterday </hi>I was gratified in reading in Penz. paper of Jany. 6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., of your Mayor, Mr. Julyan, kindly distributing <hi rend="italic">our</hi> little fund to the poor—as far as it would go! and of your and Rd. being (<hi rend="italic">rightly</hi>) present: the paper with others (monthly lot) had been here a fortnight, but as I always send them to Mr. Knowles on the day of arrival (for his wife to see) and he only returned them yesterday. I am right glad you have Mr. Julyan again for Mayor—by far the best man fitted for that office, among you: I am thinking of writing to him again shortly.—You have given me <hi rend="italic">sad </hi>news of poor dear Willie! with still <hi rend="italic">more sad </hi>forebodings on your part, which I trust may never be realised. I have just finished a letter to him &amp; to Sarah: ’97 has been a sad year of great affliction to our family! Mrs. Tucker, &amp; Edwin, Latimer’s <hi rend="italic">only</hi> child, <hi rend="italic">daughter 18</hi> (which <hi rend="italic">kind </hi>of <hi rend="italic">loss</hi> you too know something of:) myself, Willie, &amp; then Mrs Symons.—May <hi rend="italic">good </hi>result therefrom to <hi rend="italic">us all</hi>. I am keeping pretty (or <hi rend="italic">very</hi>) well, a wonder to <hi rend="italic">many</hi>! can walk <hi rend="italic">better &amp; do many things </hi>in the small way—including, however, <hi rend="italic">very much writing</hi>. I <hi rend="underline italic">love</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> work</hi>—was <hi rend="italic">brought early </hi>to do so, &amp; have been a hard (or, steady &amp; close) working-man all my days. On the last Sunday in Jany. I (again) preached &amp; helped in Service at St. Augustine’s, &amp; have promised to do so again on 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. as the Minister, Rev. Walter Welsh with his wife, leaves for England next week per “Ruahine”—on sick leave for 12 months: he is, &amp; has long been, my best clerical friend here in Hawke’s Bay—loving faithful &amp; true, &amp; I shall miss him <hi rend="italic">greatly</hi>: I have given him your private address, also that of Rd., of Willie, &amp; of Latimer, but he may not go so far W. as Cornwall:—he hopes to<hi rend="italic"> return</hi> to his charge here,—but I am very doubtful. By this Mail I send you a copy of my little book, just published, <hi rend="italic">against</hi> some of the Errors of <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi>, and also, of the miserable mongrel crew of <hi rend="italic">Ritualists</hi>! in our Mother Church. Of course, <hi rend="italic">some </hi>of my Clerical brethren out here <hi rend="italic">don’t </hi>like it—but <hi rend="smallcaps">God’s</hi> Truth shall be told, &amp; will prevail.—</p>
         <p>The failure of the “Penzance Bank” has affected folks around you: and <hi rend="italic">so here</hi>, the “Bk. of N.Z.” &amp; “Colonial Bank,” but this, respecting the old original shareholders in Bk.N.Z., is mainly the doings of the <hi rend="italic">present </hi>unprincipled Government, and <hi rend="italic">I am a sufferer</hi>: yesterday the Govt. got a very severe rebuff at Wellington in the Premier’s <hi rend="italic">nominee</hi> losing the election (Member of Parliament) though the Premier, with other Government Ministers, worked hard—as a common unscrupulous agent—<hi rend="italic">over</hi> 1000 votes (majority) against him. It is to be hoped that great good may be the result. I don’t dabble now in political matters—having plenty to do, &amp; <hi rend="italic">not loving </hi>turmoil &amp; worry. You mention your having lately seen Ellen, &amp; she seemed well. Can she manage to <hi rend="italic">live fairly</hi> on her annuity? If <hi rend="italic">not</hi>—I would add £10. yearly. Let me know. Too much warlike preparation &amp; rumour! I hope, however, the so-called Xn. nations may be kept (restrained by a higher Power) nfrom war. ‘’Tis sad to see how all hands seem to walk into peaceful hardworking China. Our rain <hi rend="italic">commenced </hi>on the 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>—(after a <hi rend="italic">very long</hi> drought—causing sufferings to cattle). And it still continues: the thirsty land trees &amp; shrubs &amp; plants (<hi rend="italic">remnants</hi>) rejoicing. Good Bye my dear nephew love to your good wife &amp; family, Mother, Sister &amp; Brother Rd. &amp; yourself—and believe me</p>
         <p>Ever your affectionate Uncle</p>
         <p>Wm. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. 14<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. night. Yesterday I was driven twice to St. Augustine’s—at my services I read lessons, preached &amp; assisted at H.C. Evg. S. I read prayers &amp; Lessons, Welsh preaching: he &amp; wife left this afternoon.—–</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>