<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0340">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1877 May 29: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1877-05-29">1877 May 29</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1877 May 29: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-288" place="foot" n="288"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier New Zealand<lb/>May 29 1877 (night)</p>
         <p>A. Luff, Esq.</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir</p>
         <p>My last to you was on 1–4 of this month, contg. 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. of a Dft. for £20. both which I hope you may duly receive.</p>
         <p>On the Queen’s Birthday (24<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. <hi rend="italic">here</hi>), I received your welcome letter of April 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>., also several papers;—&amp; was pleased to find you were all then well.—May this find you the same!</p>
         <p>Our only Eng. M. closes here on Monday next (June 4) at 8 a.m., but I commence now my letter to you, fearing if I put it off, I may not find time to write at all! even now I have more to do, in a short time! than I <hi rend="italic">can</hi> do, and this is my trouble. I was to have gone to Hastings today (school) but the rain set in &amp; hindered: I have been working hard (since my last) but I make slow progress—having suffered so much lee-way in all all March in vainly waiting on the Wairoa Bar!</p>
         <p>At this time I have 3 jobs in hand, schools: Eng. Mail: H.B. Phil. Instit. the Annual Meetg. <hi rend="italic">must </hi>be held on the 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. June, &amp; I have <hi rend="italic">all </hi>to do!—I greatly fear I shall not be able to see all the schools before Vacation, but I will try hard. I am sure <hi rend="italic">not </hi>to go to Wairoa until <hi rend="italic">July</hi> (as early <hi rend="italic">then</hi> as possible)—because I fear if I were to go thither about (say) 15<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.–18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., I should not get back in time to go through Teachers’ Quarterly accounts, &amp;c. for Edn. Board Meeting (July 2), &amp; so they would have to wait a whole month for their <hi rend="italic">Quarter’s </hi>pay, &amp; <hi rend="italic">year’s </hi>bonus!—which they could not afford to do. Your land matter there stands over (as agreed between us) until I see it: but it is <hi rend="italic">not losing </hi>in value.—</p>
         <p>I have lots of news to give you, rather more serious than usual—<hi rend="italic">Fires</hi>: we had a severe &amp; short one in town on Sunday night (19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.)—Mrs MacGregor’s large new House in Emerson Street was burnt down—inmates escaping with difficulty. The fire was exceedingly fierce: I could read well by it in my Bedroom; fortunately there was but little wind. <hi rend="italic">And</hi>, on Wednesday night following, the fine extensive Stables &amp; Coach House at Hotel Waipukurau was completely burnt up—with <hi rend="italic">all </hi>its contents, <hi rend="italic">11 </hi>horses!! several buggies &amp; coaches, stores, &amp;c. &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Great loss</hi>.—<lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Deaths</hi>: several; among them, Vaughan of M. Hotel,—at sea, on his way to Australia for health, only 3 days out! a man a Carpenter (whose eldest son was with Powdrell) named Goddard,—killed by the wheel of his own cart going over him on White Road:—young Carrington the Surveyor—at Taranaki,—of whom I have written before: a young man named Davies—formerly a Clerk here, a nephew of Rev. S.W. (Tannian who formerly worked for me)—a man named Talty who died rather suddenly in Dickens St, &amp; some others. <hi rend="italic">Weddings</hi>: Cotterill (Lawyer) to eldest daughter of Mayor.—<hi rend="italic">Births</hi>: Mrs Bennett, Mrs Locke, &amp; some others (in Papers). Accidents &amp;c., several, notably the total <hi rend="italic">loss</hi> of the “Ocean Mail” on Chatham Islands with a very val. cargo from Wellington to London; lives saved: a sad affair. I have for more than 30 years had a dread of the group—lying as it is in the very line of a vessel from Wgn. or from Lyttleton. You will see a very full account of the casualty in the <hi rend="italic">Wgn. </hi>Papers I send you (with some more interesting matter—including Bankrupt <hi rend="underline italic">rascality</hi>!). At a Races in P. Bay, J. Bourke’s son met some other horse in <hi rend="italic">full </hi>career, &amp; was thrown losing front teeth, &amp;c, &amp;c.,—lots of accidents from (careless) shooting,—including the waste of powder on 24<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>Gisborne is proclaimed a Municipality!! (may they like it!) Taradale is brought under Rivers Act (may it prove of real service!) Fannin (of Mohaka) is returned for that place in Wairoa Council! H.R.R. <hi rend="italic">is </hi>returned for Waipukurau. Webb, has started his paper, “Free Press,” at <hi rend="italic">Wairoa</hi>! May it prove useful &amp; serviceable and not become too supercilious &amp; “cheeky.” Sir D.—has been abused in the “<hi rend="italic">Wananga</hi>”—in a letter by a Maori. The poor (young) Native has been hung (<hi rend="italic">brutally</hi>) at Auckland and the great Native Meeting here at Omahu has been saying <hi rend="italic">big </hi>things. What they (Karaitiana &amp; Co.) <hi rend="italic">have </hi>done, &amp; what they <hi rend="italic">will</hi> do; that S. only cared to get in to defend his iniquity; &amp; that all <hi rend="italic">those </hi>Europeans are trembling for the consequences which they know are coming!——The Maori who wrote against Sir D., plainly, says,—the Maories know <hi rend="italic">all </hi>about <hi rend="italic">his death</hi>, that it was through <hi rend="italic">his</hi> perceiving he was done, &amp; could no longer oppress, &amp;c., &amp; that he foresaw the consequences, &amp;c, &amp;c, &amp;c. (I dare say, several Maoris think so.) The new R.M. has 6 months leave of absence already! R. Stuart is acting, &amp; Locke, is to act as Judge of Assessment Court, &amp; of F. Lands (Maori Land).</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="italic">various </hi>Ministers are still alive! each one after his own peculiar view, &amp; all, save one (the Jew), for money!! Macfarlane (U.M. Suprdt.) has been here a week &amp; more preaching &amp;c &amp;c. A Jew Minister came—&amp; performed certain rites, &amp; “consecrated” <hi rend="italic">their part </hi>of Napier Cemetery. Bp. Cowie, from Auckland, is now here, doing that kind of work for Taradale, also for the <hi rend="italic">buildings</hi> there, &amp; at Waipawa &amp; Waipukuu., &amp; confirming children, &amp; ordaining (2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. time) Mr. Eccles.—And your friend Mr Sidey is now away Lecturing, &amp;c, &amp;c,—for the good Presbytn. cause—at Waipawa &amp; at Waipukuu., &amp;c.—It is a pity they cannot agree (in such a sparsely populated Cy. as this) to build plain useful &amp; snug Buildings for D. worship, in which <hi rend="italic">all</hi> might agree to meet, turn &amp; turn about. For my part I don’t believe in their Churches lasting long—any of them—they must <hi rend="italic">all </hi>alter greatly before that. <hi rend="italic">All of man’s garnish </hi>to the plain &amp; simple Gospel Dish must be thrown aside, &amp; <hi rend="italic">then – – – </hi>There are several cases requiring <hi rend="italic">charity </hi>just now: see Papers. George Fan. has been unwell, <hi rend="italic">again</hi>! I wish he would <hi rend="italic">drink less</hi>. I have told him so. Tylee tells me, that for <hi rend="underline italic">every</hi> viewing of a Map, &amp;c &amp;c there is now a fee! which he calls a <hi rend="italic">good thing</hi>, I, the <hi rend="italic">contrary.</hi>—</p>
         <p>There has been a terrible row at Taradale. Neagle had both mortgaged &amp; given a Bill of Sale to an Auckland firm, &amp; on their <hi rend="italic">suddenly </hi>taking possession, N. endeavoured to shew fight: took away Ledger, &amp;c. by force!—it is to be a Sup. Ct. case.—<hi rend="italic">Too many insolvents</hi> of late. The big hole W. of Edwards’ is now being reclaimed; &amp; the Swamp is quietly jogging on with.—</p>
         <p>I have had my bother (with <hi rend="italic">more at hand</hi>) with some of my tenants, <hi rend="underline italic">&amp;c</hi>. Sladen, I told you of. Mackay, you will see in paper (<hi rend="italic">greatly deploring </hi>it did I appear in Court!) to stay execution. Rathbone offered a Bill—long date—which I have taken; but how by-&amp;-bye? Some others (3 of) I have agreed to defer for <hi rend="italic">a while</hi>; but I fear with <hi rend="italic">poor </hi>termination. <hi rend="italic">P.D.</hi>, I regret to say, I have not seen since my last; &amp; have written to him, (for he had forgotten me), &amp; no reply yet. Last week I saw Lyndon (as Abbott’s attorney) <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Waipawa Lands; I lose nearly 0.3.0, the difference between Rochfort’s survey &amp; <hi rend="italic">my</hi> conveyce. from A.,—and Turley’s survey according to Waipawa “<hi rend="italic">lights</hi>”—&amp; the Road Board there <hi rend="italic">have acted </hi>on Turley’s! &amp; the “Church” will <hi rend="italic">not </hi>give in! I have since written to Lyn. &amp; given him till June 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>.—but I fear a Lawsuit may be the end: <hi rend="italic">I hope not</hi>.</p>
         <p>You ask— “which? Invest in Land, or in mortgage?” I could <hi rend="italic">feelingly </hi>say, <hi rend="italic">Neither. </hi>I <hi rend="italic">won’t</hi>, if I can get any money in: I should prefer <hi rend="italic">Bank</hi> @ 5%—I have had more trouble during this last 6 months than I ever had before. And there is more coming! I should tell you, that Sainsbury asked me for the Cr. Gt. of Hy. Mackenzie’s (Lease) at Havelock, which now of <hi rend="italic">course</hi>, M. will have.</p>
         <p>I must not forget to tell you of the <hi rend="italic">funny </hi>mistake of Joe. Rhodes:—he, through Lyndon, advertised sections in Old Clive to be sold, when in came the owners bringing their <hi rend="underline italic">old</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>(<hi rend="italic">non</hi>-registered) Deeds from J.Rh. with them! they had <hi rend="italic">long ago </hi>built on them, &amp; Joe. had clean forgotten it!! &amp; had <hi rend="italic">no </hi>memo. of it whatever. Hardy was telling me, that <hi rend="italic">old </hi>Clive is picking up a bit now (quite time!) 2–3 <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Houses built there.—</p>
         <p>My own health has been fair, I have <hi rend="italic">endured</hi> (in travelling, by night too, &amp; <hi rend="italic">in </hi>mud, &amp; on foot, in <hi rend="italic">the dark</hi>—pitchy dark &amp; wet, &amp; <hi rend="italic">cold</hi>, seeking a shelter, &amp;c &amp;c) in wet &amp; <hi rend="italic">very windy </hi>weather, since my last; but our real winter has scarcely begun! It was <hi rend="italic">much </hi>more so, early in April! I was, however, laid aside 3 days last week, which I thought was fever. I cannot well do a <hi rend="italic">long</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">hard</hi>, day’s work now. I can get on with half a one very well. I stayed at Betine’s Waipawa, it was nice, quiet, &amp; clean.</p>
         <p>I see Wright (Cy.) is gone to Engd.—having “made his fortune.”—Abrahams is going next steamer, he wants <hi rend="italic">your address</hi>.—“Schichallion,” hence, I find has arrived safely. Renouf has removed to Kaikoura; he has the Contract for building Presbytn. Ch. there.</p>
         <p>I enclose a letter, which came to me,—it <hi rend="italic">may</hi> not be worth sending. How did you come off with our Stationery sent hence to Rhodes?</p>
         <p>Boylan has removed his door from corner, to centre of shop fronting Masonic. A huge culvert across from Manoy’s Corner to Newton’s Corner.—</p>
         <p>I put up for you yesterday the latest news, 2 papers. I hope the Russians will be <hi rend="italic">beaten</hi>— “to rags.”</p>
         <p>I wish you &amp; yours every Blessing, and am my Dear Sir</p>
         <p>Yours very sincerely</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. Just a word from P.D. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>business, Lyndon wrote on 31<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. May, offering me £35. as Compensation; but I want £50. as the least I can take. I have however promised to <hi rend="italic">see </hi>him again—first. </p>
         <p>W.C.</p>
         <p rend="end">Sunday night June 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>.</p>
         <p>And now I must close. Grubb came here early this aftn. &amp; remained till dusk, the <hi rend="italic">first </hi>visitor for many a long day. He has written to you. Since I commenced <hi rend="italic">my </hi>letter there have been 2 or 3 Railway accidents but no lives lost. (see Papers). I note in your last your asking for a little Commission in London: Hope you will <hi rend="italic">like</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">accomplish</hi>, the one I gave you with Dixon. I would say a word about <hi rend="italic">Papers</hi>,—send me those containing good Law <hi rend="italic">Judgments</hi>—whether Ecclestc. or Civil; something really worth your sending so far,—what I send you from this little wee hamlet, must be, in every respect, more or less interesting to you as you <hi rend="italic">know</hi> place &amp; people.—But those you send of the <hi rend="italic">Weekly </hi>Times,—D.Telegraph,—&amp; Times, are good. I saw P.D. <hi rend="italic">in town</hi> yesterday, <hi rend="italic">another </hi>wedding coming off <hi rend="italic">there</hi>! another niece, Jersey <hi rend="italic">couple</hi>. I am invited but <hi rend="italic">cannot </hi>find time to go.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>