<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1005">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1897 September 9: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1897-09-09">1897 September 9</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1897 September 9: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-841" place="foot" n="841"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, September 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1897.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>It is more than a month since I last wrote a letter to you—but you will (I trust) have recd. copies of “Herald” from me (24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. ulto.,<note xml:id="ftn3-842" place="foot" n="842"> Mr. Colenso explains. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi>, 1 March 1897.</note> &amp; 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. inst.<note xml:id="ftn3-843" place="foot" n="843"> Mr. Colenso in reply. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi>. 8 September 1897.</note>) which will show how I have been writing, and <hi rend="italic">not forgotten you</hi>. Yours of 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. Augt. is now before me—I thank you for it—a portion of it has interested me more than usual—that <hi rend="italic">re </hi>eccl. absurdities at Nelson: &amp; why? because Bp. Wms before he left N., told us of <hi rend="italic">him</hi>, &amp; that he the Bp. had written to him, &amp;c., and wished <hi rend="italic">all </hi>to help him, &amp; to get him to preach, &amp;c., in their churches.—I would hope that Bp. Wms. may return to N. before this noisy pulpiteer makes his advent among us.—In confirmation of which you wrote respecting him, I have also heard <hi rend="italic">re</hi> his doings at Nelson, &amp; have told the Dean of them: but the <hi rend="italic">fiat</hi> has gone forth.</p>
         <p>I hope your forebodings re Ch. of E. at <hi rend="italic">Home</hi> (or elsewhere) may <hi rend="italic">not </hi>be verified, though I fear they <hi rend="italic">may</hi>! I could wish that <hi rend="italic">you </hi>had written a few lines to me on receipt of “Herald” of 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. ult. I have recd. plenty of thanks from various quarters (some <hi rend="italic">unexpected</hi>!) with, of course, <hi rend="italic">cold water. </hi>I am a wee bit vexed at so <hi rend="italic">many </hi>Printer’s errors in this 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. L., I am sure my “copy” was good &amp; <hi rend="italic">clear</hi>. I suppose you may remember what I said in my letter, Xmas/94, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>any quotations <hi rend="italic">from S.S.</hi>, that in <hi rend="italic">such cases</hi> I <hi rend="italic">always </hi>quote from Douay, &amp; Vulgate,—it is necessary to bear this in mind.</p>
         <p>I have lately recd. from you—spn. of your new Dicty., many words are identical w. <hi rend="italic">Maori ones</hi>: but I do not admire—neither think much of—the writer or Compiler. Mentg. Dicty., reminds me to say that from a late note from Mackay, Govt. Ptr., there is no hope of any <hi rend="italic">more </hi>of letter “A” being done till <hi rend="underline italic">after</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>Parliament is <hi rend="italic">over</hi>: I expected <hi rend="italic">this</hi>, at same time intimated 3 weeks ago, to him, that as there was but a <hi rend="italic">little</hi> more (96 pp. having been printed) I thought it might be done <hi rend="italic">before </hi>Pt. should sit. However, “patience is a virtue,” &amp; I must once more exercise it.</p>
         <p>I have been reading with some interest your paper on “Kerns &amp; Serifs”, but cannot go w. you in your wish for the preservation of slang! &amp; wonder greatly at <hi rend="italic">your doing </hi>so—as I had supposed you would be sure to take the <hi rend="italic">opposite</hi>.—I enclose a clipping from a late paper, which is more in my way of thinking. The “S. Army” folks are out again!—<hi rend="italic">their </hi>yearly Feast (“Self-<hi rend="italic">Denial</hi>”) and <hi rend="italic">gift</hi>, which is a <hi rend="italic">lie</hi>—as they go round begging of everyone, even hiring agents paying them <hi rend="italic">commssion</hi>! Two of their <hi rend="italic">Grandees</hi> (clothed rather sumptuously!) called on <hi rend="italic">me </hi>last wk.,—they had previously impertinently sent me their long-winded circular, which I had answd. the night before but better still <hi rend="italic">here</hi>—it being <hi rend="italic">early</hi>:—I gave them my letter, telling them I would have nothing to do w. them—as I did not reckon them as Xns., but in same category as Adventists, Mormons, P. Brethren—&amp; a host of other Sects—I would help them—pretty largely?—as I would a Jewish, or Mahomn. party, If they would <hi rend="italic">abandon </hi>their <hi rend="italic">false </hi>religion &amp; stick to the moral &amp; physical helping. I would send <hi rend="italic">you </hi>the copy of my short letter, only it is <hi rend="italic">absent</hi>—sent to a Ch. inland.</p>
         <p>I am pretty well in genl. health—eat drink &amp; sleep, but my legs <hi rend="italic">do not </hi>get any stronger! so I am a prisoner <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, not going down town having no business,—nor <hi rend="italic">even once </hi>through the <hi rend="italic">little </hi>gate under trees close by! I walk <hi rend="italic">outside</hi>, when fine, but <hi rend="italic">soon tire</hi>. My arm &amp; hand, <hi rend="underline italic">slowly</hi> improving. Have <hi rend="underline italic">few</hi> visitors; and <hi rend="underline italic">little</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> desire to read</hi>!!! Buller kindly called last wk., gone to Fiji. Have recd. handsome Invitation to Norsewood “Banquet,” &amp;c., but <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi> possibly go: I regret this. Hope you are <hi rend="italic">well</hi>, &amp; doing much better in P.O., &amp; family all well. I hoped to have <hi rend="italic">finished</hi> w. my one sheet small writing &amp; close—but must continue.</p>
         <p>You (all) <hi rend="italic">there</hi> have had your big days—of late: Governor’s advent, &amp; Premier’s, &amp; Contingents’, return to Wgn. <hi rend="italic">Dont </hi>write too much about it!—I suppose “H. Arrow’s” L. in “Hd.” will have caught your eye! The <hi rend="italic">vain </hi>old man is surely looking out for a billet! He lives here <hi rend="italic">in town</hi> now, at the <hi rend="italic">Buffet </hi>Emerson St., he pd. me a visit 2 wks. ago. Hill’s letter is <hi rend="italic">peculiar</hi> (like him!) answered, in part, in “Herald” of this mg. I know <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> of com. pub. talk in town—I only see the Dean weekly, &amp; Welsh, who don’t bring me any “<hi rend="italic">news</hi>”. I went bang against <hi rend="italic">Choir</hi> movement, in my voting p., “<hi rend="italic">NO: twice over</hi>”; &amp; no doubt that displeased some folks: I heard the result was <hi rend="italic">astonishing</hi>! <hi rend="italic">for </hi>the innovation, “<hi rend="italic">very few</hi>”: against it, “<hi rend="italic">very many</hi>”. That affair of the “Tasmania” is a bad one, strange tales afloat: <hi rend="italic">no rock </hi>there in deep water but <hi rend="italic">close to shore</hi>.—–</p>
         <p>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. mg. I now go on with my letter: I feel ashamed when looking over it written <hi rend="italic">by night</hi> to see such scrawl! It seemed better then!! I noticed in paper your remark <hi rend="italic">re</hi> what I had seen on Ruahine, <hi rend="underline italic">twice</hi>: the extended remark in “Appendix” In memorium (<hi rend="italic">not</hi> in Trans.) is worthy your again reading it. Is there a copy of <hi rend="italic">this</hi> in Wgn. Library? It is nearly <hi rend="italic">out of print</hi>. If not, I would send one. Did I tell you I had a lg. L. from <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>, who had been laid up <hi rend="italic">6 wks</hi>.,—he wishes me to republish all my Botl. papers in “Trans” so all to be accessible to future botanists:—I replied No, not at my expense though I might subscribe well towards it. Last night a <hi rend="italic">note</hi> from Hamilton, <hi rend="italic">indignant</hi>,—wanting to know if my <hi rend="italic">papers</hi> mentd. in H.B. proceedings ’96, had been <hi rend="italic">sent</hi> to Wgn. They were <hi rend="italic">not</hi>. I had previously received a terribly lg. L. from him 3 4to. pp. <hi rend="italic">minute</hi> writing. <hi rend="italic">Many </hi>questions (Maori): I ansd. it last week. I have had my vol. “Trans” from Gore: did <hi rend="italic">you</hi> notice (readg. <hi rend="italic">or hearing</hi>) what Buller said, in quoting Sir J.D. Hooker’s L. to him <hi rend="italic">re</hi> “<hi rend="italic">Colenso</hi>”? Old Field—a curious fellow! Did you ever see him, &amp;c? I was <hi rend="italic">obliged</hi> to give up corresponding w. him.—</p>
         <p>Do you know if Luff takes in “Herald”? He formally did. I fear the Queen’s <hi rend="italic">reply</hi> to the Petition Maori Contingent, will not please them. Great fuss, &amp;c, &amp;c, here lately <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Railway <hi rend="italic">instanter</hi> to Wairoa; the long-bow <hi rend="italic">used re good lands</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">no</hi> engineering difficulties! The Ry can be made but where is the money to come from? I am sure it would never repay—no, not interest on loan. A <hi rend="italic">new </hi>loan $12,000 is now to be obtained to repair roads &amp; bridges, <hi rend="italic">H. Bay County</hi> damaged by late floods: which, in a year or two, may have to be repeated. I have recd. <hi rend="italic">pictorial</hi> issues (enlarged) “Graphic”, “Illd. L. News” &amp; “Black &amp; White”, Jubilee doings,—&amp; would send you a copy for Victor but suppose you have also recd. such from Home: I marvel <hi rend="italic">how</hi> such are executed in so short a time. This Linotype affair, Auckland, has an ugly aspect, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> “duties”! I have had 2 letters from <hi rend="italic">our dear old</hi> blind Xn. lady Mrs. Trestrail, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>subscribing towards Presbytn. Sy. School-house, about to be erected <hi rend="italic">near</hi> Ch., contract taken, £250: Gaisford having <hi rend="italic">given </hi>the piece land: of course, her <hi rend="italic">attached </hi>amanuensis writes for her. I would that I, <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, had some <hi rend="italic">such attached one.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Grindell is writing <hi rend="italic">largely</hi> to both H. &amp; D.T. “Supplements”: to “H.” <hi rend="italic">re</hi> his going w. D. McLean to purchase <hi rend="italic">N</hi>. H.B. (I think, mostly, from “H.” of early times): to “D.T.” <hi rend="italic">re</hi> his <hi rend="italic">still earlier</hi> adventures on W. Coast &amp; Wairarapa: <hi rend="italic">voluminous.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>xi. a. m. I am just come in from ½ hour’s walk outside in sun, day fine: in looking over lagoon from fence I am surprised to see how it is silting up! Perhaps, however, owing to <hi rend="underline italic">less</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> water</hi>. Very sad doings <hi rend="italic">here</hi> of late by “larrikins”! (school-boys?) breaking lamps, panes glass, ill-using china-men, &amp;c, &amp;c) hitherto <hi rend="italic">quietly</hi> dealt w. by S.M., also bicyclists on kerb pavements. <hi rend="italic">Know nothing</hi> of what “Institute” may have for next Monday nt. I have heard, that the Doctor’s late paper on <hi rend="italic">Bacilli </hi>has been found in a publd. work! Sch. Comee. Waipawa refused Gardiner leave to have B. Class in Sch.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">No. 2, addendum</hi>.</p>
         <p>A few days ago in searching for a missing pamphlet I opened an <hi rend="underline italic">old</hi> parcel addd. to me at Auckland!—books from Sandwich Islands—a <hi rend="italic">rare lot</hi>! &amp; some, I fancy of value—now: among them “<hi rend="italic">P. Progress</hi>” in that language, more than 50 yrs. old.—–But oh! how vexed I was—to find the devastation by some insects—not only paper but leather eaten &amp; torn. And <hi rend="italic">since then</hi>—in looking accidentally into some books <hi rend="italic">bound</hi> for me by a yg. man (relative of Mrs Caulton) <hi rend="italic">after </hi>he left Herald Co., I found them also eaten sadly—especially leather corners. I fear there is <hi rend="italic">great</hi> destruction going on among my books—major part <hi rend="italic">unused—</hi>&amp; I <hi rend="underline italic">cannot</hi>, though having spare time <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, <hi rend="italic">use my </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">rt.</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> arm sufficiently </hi>to go over them. Indeed, as I think I told you before,—my Library is the <hi rend="italic">only big</hi> matter on my mind just now, causing me anxiety—<hi rend="italic">not knowing </hi>what to do with it! for there are <hi rend="italic">several valuable works </hi>in it. Buller complains (&amp; rightly) of John White’s works—viz. Maori colln. &amp; <hi rend="italic">translation</hi>: just so, in my estimation. Others by Gudgeon, McDonnell, &amp; Co.</p>
         <p>I not unfrequently think on an impassioned speech by Sir W. Fox, in Ho. Reps. subject voting money for <hi rend="underline italic">C.O. Davis</hi>, as Ed. of <hi rend="italic">Mao Messg.</hi>; F. against it, saying those people wanted first to know English much less Maori—and he, then, classed such as (1.) Ignoramuses, &amp; (2) Brain-suckers: in which I fully agree. In Hamilton’s <hi rend="italic">big </hi>4to.—fully illustrated, he too takes from <hi rend="underline italic">all</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> alike</hi>! stories, recent, got up round camp-fires, &amp;c., improvised for the occasion, cooked to suit the ever-credulous pakeha, togr. with, tales &amp; legends from ancient times; some of <hi rend="italic">these last </hi>are enqd. after by H.—<hi rend="italic">jam satis</hi>. Of course, this arises from his “Bibliography”—which, also, runs <hi rend="italic">pari passu</hi> w. <hi rend="italic">Harding</hi> on <hi rend="italic">slang</hi>. You justly remark, my Pl. Address has some <hi rend="italic">old </hi>matter in it. Yes from former one ptd. by you,—as I have also in it stated: the <hi rend="italic">main reason</hi> with me for getting H. to publish it in “Trans.” was, my having mentioned Mantell, Huxley, Tiffen, &amp; Meinitzhagen deceased, &amp; Hooker, <hi rend="italic">in it</hi>, so I am Satisfied.</p>
         <p>Well, again,             Good Bye Yrs ever       W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. Don’t forget to return Dr. Adams’ letter.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
