<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0758">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1890 December 20: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0495.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1890-12-20">1890 December 20</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1890 December 20: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-500" place="foot" n="500"> ATL qMS-0495.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier,<lb/>Sunday night,<lb/>Decr. 21, 1890.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Again</hi> have our letters crossed in transit! (my last of 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., &amp; yours to me of <hi rend="italic">same date</hi>!)—and <hi rend="italic">again</hi> am I writing to you from the <hi rend="italic">old Corner</hi> of my table in sittg. room, where <hi rend="italic">you</hi> have so often <hi rend="italic">found</hi> me so engaged!</p>
         <p>My last to you was <hi rend="italic">closed </hi>on 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.—little did I then think of what was so near for me: I suppose I said to you (as to others), that on 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I was <hi rend="italic">wholly free from Rheumatism</hi>—a pleasing &amp; rare incident. Well, that Sy. was a <hi rend="italic">despy. drafty</hi> one in the Ch. insomuch that I had to quit my old seat, and find refuge by side of organ, (all owing to every door &amp; window open!) to keep the Curate’s announcement, I strove hard &amp; managed to preach at Evg. S.—he leading me to my hotel. The next day I was <hi rend="italic">very</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">bad</hi>—<hi rend="italic">severe</hi> attack of Rhm.—jaw, teeth, ear &amp; one side, no rest; ditto Tuesday! <hi rend="italic">Could not eat</hi>: took opium for pains &amp;c—on Tuedy. <hi rend="italic">aftn.,</hi> little better,—all were against my leaving on Thy., but I had arrgd. w. Rev. A. Grant, &amp; so was detd. if poss. to keep my word: I feared however the journey—party. <hi rend="italic">by night</hi> to N. Thy. evg. I left Dvk., got well to Waipukurau: to bed early: next mg. spent 1 hour w. Mrs Trestrail on way to the Manse: G. called for me—&amp; went w. him. Finished naming ferns by XII. (a <hi rend="italic">poor</hi> lot! &amp; mounted on thick white <hi rend="italic">blotting</hi> p., for me to <hi rend="italic">write on</hi>!!) We walked together to Town H., ladies engd. in Bazaar decoration, &amp;c. Aftn. at IV. to Rev. Knipe’s:—at V. back to Gow’s—left at VI.—here by IX.—&amp;, as usual, <hi rend="italic">took cold</hi> on way, owing to <hi rend="italic">women</hi> having 5–7 windows open!! This has brought back jaw &amp; tooth &amp; ear-ache, &amp;c—and has, mainly, kept me at the house all day—but I find <hi rend="italic">plenty to do</hi>! To my dismay I discovd. last evg., I had <hi rend="italic">left</hi> my thick vol. “Handbk. N.Z. Flora”, <hi rend="italic">in the Bazaar</hi>, so I wrote to Mr Grant—&amp; hope it is <hi rend="italic">safe</hi>—I shall not be myself until I get it—it <hi rend="italic">had</hi>, also, sm. spns. &amp; small loose notes, in it!—If Mr G. saw it soon after, no doubt he would secure it for me—as he had seen me using it at the Manse: he spoke very kindly &amp; nicely of <hi rend="italic">you</hi>—which <hi rend="italic">pleased me</hi>.</p>
         <p>While at Dvk. I recd. a note from McGlashan—re copies of Brett’s “Early Histy. N.Z.”—&amp; <hi rend="italic">here</hi> I found them arrived, w. a request for the chq.—as a fort. nearly had elapsed, I have written a note, w. chq., &amp; as it was an opportunity of saying something <hi rend="italic">anent</hi> the Book, I opened one, &amp; rushed thro’ it. I send you the copy of my note, as I believe it will interest you.—Have you a copy? or, <hi rend="italic">access</hi> to one?—One <hi rend="underline italic">strange</hi> passage I must call your attention to—at page 377:—“Sept. 1830. <hi rend="italic">First ptg, press in N.Z. Jas.</hi> Smith the printer (æt. 15) with W. Yate, ptd hymns &amp;c in Nat. lang. &amp;c; again p.379. “Jas. Smith<hi rend="italic">, printer</hi>”, &amp;c<hi rend="italic">.—</hi>strange, that I should<hi rend="italic">never have heard </hi>of this: &amp; more strange, that Yate, in <hi rend="italic">his</hi> Book on N.Z. &amp; the Ch. M. <hi rend="italic">never alludes to it</hi>; though he does, fully, his 2 visits to Sydney (1 bef. that date, &amp; 1 <hi rend="italic">after</hi>) to get Mao. Books printed; &amp; he is so <hi rend="italic">diffuse</hi> in <hi rend="italic">all his doings</hi>, &amp;c—. I see, <hi rend="italic">Sherrin</hi>, is the author; &amp; he, a few years ago, bothered me with several letters of enqy.—at <hi rend="italic">first</hi> I answered, but afterwards <hi rend="italic">declined</hi>—not having time: &amp;, I <hi rend="italic">suppose</hi>, he <hi rend="italic">remembers that</hi>: a few isolated passages &amp;c—indicate it. I hope you may see the said Book: I can (if you wish) quote <hi rend="italic">verbatim </hi>from Yate.<hi rend="italic"> </hi>
         </p>
         <p>This letter is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> intended as an ansr. to your last, &amp; enquiry <hi rend="italic">re</hi> “Te”—that must stand over—my hands &amp; head are <hi rend="italic">full.</hi> I have had to write lately to the Bp., &amp; to Canon Webb, &amp; to others unexpectedly, &amp; on serious matters, with more, <hi rend="italic">perhaps</hi> to follow.—I took a <hi rend="italic">return</hi> ticket &amp; <hi rend="italic">hope</hi> to get back to Dvk. by 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> proxo,—.</p>
         <p>You will have heard of Col. Herrick’s sudden death—<hi rend="italic">killed</hi> by a fall.—I was at Dvk. when he &amp; his large party arrd. &amp; we were togr. at the hotel, &amp; when he &amp; they went off on the Tuesday w. a number of horses—it was commented on by Clayton in his “B. Ad.”—as a sight in Dvk.—I wonder if the folks there will think, <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, on portions of my (3–4) sermons espy. on <hi rend="italic">such</hi> cases! so <hi rend="italic">frequently</hi> occurring there?—</p>
         <p>Among letters awaiting me one from Hamilton—dated 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. They were all well, &amp; intended leaving on 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> (yesty.) for Long Beach for 1 or 2 wks, as there <hi rend="italic">he</hi> would carry out his researches—after Maori <hi rend="italic">relics</hi>—wh. seem to be, prodigious! espy. in works of Greenstone!—all showing the correctness of my view as to <hi rend="italic">their</hi> extreme age in N.Z.—He, too, puts <hi rend="italic">many</hi> questions to me, which I cannot ansr. early.—</p>
         <p>Tomorrow, in town, (did not move out yesty.) I purpose <hi rend="underline italic">seeing</hi> to <hi rend="italic">your</hi> vol. Trans. Fannin I <hi rend="italic">see, </hi>is gone to Dunedin. I saw your Cousin Rechab at Waipu. &amp; I <hi rend="italic">thanked</hi> him <hi rend="italic">heartily</hi> for his <hi rend="italic">manly</hi> stand (<hi rend="italic">v. </hi>Sidey &amp; Sutton)<hi rend="italic"> </hi>at Ed. Board<hi rend="italic">. </hi>I hope you will see <hi rend="italic">the</hi> letter, from Chambers in “Evg. News,” of Thursday, 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—do look it up.—Here, everythg. is <hi rend="italic">very</hi> dry; no grass. Mrs. Margoliouth &amp; 3 sons were passgrs. from Hastings in train: we chatted: I had not seen her for—years! Must refer you to locals for Tanner’s <hi rend="italic">finale!</hi> What a lesson! (<hi rend="italic">to M.</hi>) from him, &amp; Sutton, &amp; Maney,—&amp; Co., Ever <hi rend="italic">hold to this</hi>—“the <hi rend="italic">honest </hi>wears well.”—</p>
         <p>Also:—in “Herald” (Thy. <hi rend="italic">or</hi> Friday) a smart Art. on <hi rend="italic">Inspr. Hill</hi>!—</p>
         <p>Of late, there have been several good—sound, Arts. in “Herald”.</p>
         <p>My <hi rend="italic">big</hi>, parcels from Engd. per Mail have at last turned up!—all appy. safe. One contains all the unsold <hi rend="italic">Ruahine</hi> books,—these I had requested, being nearly out. When shall I open them all? I have already 2–4 from London—recd. 1, 2, years ago, <hi rend="italic">unopened</hi>.</p>
         <p>I have often thought of an <hi rend="italic">omission</hi> of mine (in <hi rend="italic">our</hi> “Jub.”, pamphlet. i.e.—ptg. N.P.)—viz. The <hi rend="italic">many other books</hi> that were then—<hi rend="italic">during that period</hi>—also, ptd: some tens of thousands: Sherrin <hi rend="italic">brings them</hi> forward—in some years.</p>
         <p>In one of his old letters he told me how much he was then writing <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the old Wesley. Mission, in which C.O. Davis was to have aided!—and he has <hi rend="italic">plenty</hi> in this Book w. some <hi rend="italic">horrid carte’s</hi>. Not a word of Woon: but S. says, their press was set up in ’37; &amp; I note the <hi rend="italic">truth</hi> is told of “Rev” J. Buller, (<hi rend="italic">as I once told you</hi>)—he merely came to N.Z. as a young tutor from Sydney to N. Turner’s Misy. Children.—</p>
         <p>I am tired, &amp; must stop. Would I had <hi rend="italic">better</hi> tidings from you <hi rend="italic">re</hi> your little son. Hope this may find you &amp; yours well.</p>
         <p>And w. kindest regards, &amp; best old Eng. wishes for the <hi rend="italic">2</hi> appg. Seasons, I am,</p>
         <p>My dear Mr Harding,</p>
         <p>Yours very sincerely,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>—XI. a.m. Got XXII! &amp; taken in triumph to P.O. Left XXI w. Brother—He &amp; his all well—<hi rend="underline italic">Adieu</hi>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
