<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0852">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 November 29: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-11-29">1892 November 29</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 November 29: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-625" place="foot" n="625"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Novr. 29/92<lb/>VIII p.m.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>I think I will <hi rend="italic">begin </hi>a letter to you tonight—if only to tell you of <hi rend="italic">our </hi>Society meeting last nt. (though I sadly want <hi rend="italic">your </hi>graphic powers of description, <hi rend="italic">and </hi>quickness of hand in writing.)—</p>
         <p>I had recd. a note from White asking for Papers—if I could not attend (addd. to me at Dvk.)—replied, from <hi rend="italic">N.</hi>, “would be present.”—</p>
         <p>Last nt, at VII.30 I went to Museum: found Hill there <hi rend="italic">busy </hi>on his blackbd. w. artesian well. Company came in—soon after 8 I opened w. my Mao. Dog paper, during reading, several came in one by one, making great disturbance! White too hustling about opening windows, &amp; gas <hi rend="italic">low</hi>, so that I could not <hi rend="italic">well </hi>see to read. (it never occurred to me to increase the gas!—Holder <hi rend="italic">did </hi>this <hi rend="italic">aftds. </hi>for Dr. Moore.) Rheumatism (from which I had been tolerably free for several days) coming rapidly over me from the draughts from open windows!—my patience gave way! and I stopped reading, addressing those who had been lately coming in, remarking how they disturbed both me &amp; the meeting, marvelling at their not coming at the fixed hour, &amp; ending by hoping such would not be the case next year, or, if so, then doors <hi rend="italic">shut</hi> at VIII.15.—at close of my reading, there was a clapping (and so when I rose to begin): Lessong put a qu. or two, &amp; so did Heath, all proper; then Hill began—he did not know T. Wh. but approved of his interestg. paper: doubted the Mao. dog not being wild, &amp; of it having died out; &amp; <hi rend="italic">why </hi>so? &amp;c &amp;c It surprised me to hear him: &amp; again, <hi rend="italic">afterwards</hi> he again took T. Wh’s. part, on <hi rend="italic">putting </hi>vote of thanks to me: this caused me to take him up—on the ground of my paper in vol. X, <hi rend="italic">which I had pointed out to Wh. </hi>&amp; which, evidently, he did not care to see!—and I spoke rather strongly. Dr. Moore followed with his Paper, or rather <hi rend="italic">notes</hi>! and made a sad mess of it, al hands <hi rend="italic">tired. </hi>Some went out, lad. &amp; gent.! Hill twisted in his chair—for it was all about Tongariro, where Dr. M. had been lately—the old old story! but without a single bit of botanical or geological story to enliven. I think we were all glad when it was ended: but then, no one caring to speak, Hill got up, to explain the “very interesting paper,” &amp; being on his own hobby kept on—on—on ! and as all things have an end—so w. Hill: then others went out nearly X o’clock: then Ishowed some Botanl. specimens, not many but <hi rend="italic">interesting </hi>ones—some of Hill’s collecting. These White took round, &amp; such perhaps served to please—a <hi rend="underline italic">little</hi>! I giving short popular descriptions. Then a <hi rend="italic">youth</hi>, a member, a McLeod of Taradale, read his <hi rend="italic">long </hi>p. on electricity on plants—with some experiments, of his own (I believe),—but read it in such a <hi rend="italic">low</hi> monotone that it was dreadful! I never heard a worse reader, yet quite calm! It was indeed a time of trial to me, sitting <hi rend="italic">in pain </hi>on my chair. That over, about X.20, Hill, who had been bursting over his blackboard &amp; trophies from Mt. Vernon &amp; from Whanganui, began—remarking “it was too late”—only “a <hi rend="italic">few </hi>words”! But he <hi rend="italic">did </hi>try our patience: some went out, but he kept on, on, on,—&amp; <hi rend="italic">at last</hi>, closed: then remarks by H., general at end, &amp; <hi rend="italic">exit omnes</hi>. I climbed this hill in darkness after XI.—<hi rend="italic">quite tired</hi> &amp; in pain.</p>
         <p>Hill was evidently (<hi rend="italic">to me</hi>) displeased w. <hi rend="italic">me</hi>! why? hear. On Friday nt., 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., I recd a kind natal letterfrom him at Napier, saying, he should be at Makotuku School on Monday &amp; Tuesday follg., &amp; would come on to Dvk. to see me &amp; spend night w. me, if I would be there: I replied, saying, I could not exactly promise as I was leaving for town on 19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> for my <hi rend="italic">last </hi>Sy. duty there, &amp; did intend to remain there a day or two, but would wire to him on Monday from Wdv. I did so, on My. aftn. appointing Tuesday aftn. <hi rend="italic">purposely </hi>to meet H.—giving up some of my intended visits, calls, &amp;c.—as I much wished to see him—about his own plants, &amp;c.—<hi rend="italic">H. never came to Dvk. neither wrote nor wired</hi>!! and I <hi rend="underline italic">waiting</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="italic">others </hi>wondering, &amp;c &amp;c. We heard he was at M. those 2 days: and so, when I entered the room that night, &amp; saw him at his Blk. Bd., &amp; asked him, why he did not come on? he said, he was busy—&amp; then worked away! I replied, in <hi rend="italic">few </hi>words, that I had felt it, &amp; lost much by it.—But he is completely overwhelmed in his Artesian well matters: he could <hi rend="italic">not</hi>, however, read his p. on that subject. And—there were others, again from T. White! &amp; verily <hi rend="italic">another </hi>on the <hi rend="italic">Maori Dog</hi>!!!—all, with 2–3, <hi rend="italic">small </hi>Bot. ones of my own (at my request) “taken as read,”—Heath, &amp; Holder made some pertinent remarks on the Comee. of Directors at Wgn. Here I halt—it is late—I’m tired.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="underline italic">30</hi>
            <hi rend="sup underline italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">. (IV p.m.</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">)</hi> I should have added—I came away leaving H. &amp; a knot of his friends (all strangers to me) discussing the artesn. well: I saw <hi rend="italic">Mrs. </hi>Hill, &amp; conversed briefly w. her, on my leaving: she <hi rend="italic">seemed </hi>unwell!—among my <hi rend="italic">curious </hi>exhibits, was a large spn. of the “Codlin-moth plant”—&amp; in 3 of its flowers 2 big moths &amp; 1 blue butterfly, caught dead. It was sent to me from a garden in country. I have found out its Botl. name &amp; <hi rend="italic">may </hi>write a paper on it &amp; its <hi rend="italic">prey</hi>, after dissection, &amp;c. Do you know it?—But there was <hi rend="italic">little </hi>attention shown to any of the objects: folk, perhaps, were <hi rend="italic">tired</hi>! I did not know ½ doz. of them.—</p>
         <p>I went to Wdv. on 19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. (Rev. D. Sidey also, going thither in same carriage, from N., &amp; for a similar purpose—we also returned together on Tuesday to Dvk. where he remained until next day)—Morrison is to be placed at Woodville. Had very fine w.—&amp; good Congns. on Sunday, mg. I preached from last 2v. of Eccles.—evg. from Acts xx.32. I partfrom <hi rend="italic">them</hi>—the <hi rend="italic">work there </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">that </hi>Ch.—with <hi rend="italic">much regret</hi> I hope &amp; pray that E. may be of full service to them. On My. mg. I was driven in buggy thro’ the Gorge, nearly to Ashurst: scenery romantic, but a very <hi rend="italic">sad waste</hi> to place Raily. <hi rend="italic">there, it must be abandoned, &amp; sooner the better.</hi> Day very hot; don’t admire <hi rend="italic">Coach road</hi>! Aftn. returned to hotel, &amp; rested. Tuesday mg. called on Mrs. Eccles at Parsonage—found her unwell, from “Hayfever”—attacked regularly every year, &amp; getting worse, will leave for Melbourne <hi rend="italic">this Saturday</hi>: sad beginning, &amp;, I fear, <hi rend="italic">against </hi>Eccles.—next day, I saw E. at Dvk. in his way to Woodv., driving in his buggy: he stopped at Knight’s. I had returned unexpectedly to meet Hill! much talk there at his non-appce.—I <hi rend="italic">doing nothing</hi>! One gentleman remarked— “It is like H.” On coming to N. on Friday, Cornford was passgr.—he from Wgn that mg., &amp; so Howell to Woodv. Tomorrow (Dec.1) I go to town on business long-delayed. Have lately recd. Crombie’s Land Tax demand! &amp; to pay <hi rend="italic">whole year </hi>at once!! It is <hi rend="italic">heavy </hi>on me <hi rend="italic">just now</hi>—so many things coming together—on the <hi rend="italic">debtor </hi>side, and <hi rend="italic">I have to </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">wait</hi>. I cannot well put Hill out of my mind: and I am thinking whether, during his stay at Makotuku, his friend Wills may have told him something new &amp; <hi rend="italic">unpleasant</hi>—for we two have lately (in Sept.) had our duel, &amp; I wrote W. a <hi rend="italic">very strong </hi>reply. W. was staying at Hill’s house during Synod. Bide a wee: I shall know ere long—Rev. C.L. Tuke kindly called to see me on Monday; he, too, is <hi rend="italic">still suffg. </hi>at times, from Influenza of Jany. last!! I fancy, he wants help at T., seeing advt. in “Herald” <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Almc. “<hi rend="italic">w. Hg’s. Incorporated</hi>”—I wrote them a note, calling on them <hi rend="italic">to do so in reality</hi>: pointing out, that your Father cod. supply Planetary &amp; astral lore, &amp;c—–</p>
         <p>Your kind letter of 28<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. is to hand, <hi rend="italic">thanks</hi>: but you ought not to have written until <hi rend="italic">after </hi>E. Mail. I post with this Evg. N. (of 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.)—this please <hi rend="italic">return</hi>, could not get a copy any where, I do <hi rend="italic">not </hi>know who sent it to me, &amp; so <hi rend="italic">Marked </hi>it! I also send H.B. Herald of yesty.—report (!!!) of <hi rend="italic">meeting </hi>and a “Standard”—<hi rend="italic">death &amp;c of Renan. </hi>I go w. you in your praise &amp; esteem of Whittier—I always liked his poetry &amp; I think I have a vol. of it. Having <hi rend="italic">known &amp; </hi>valued the “Quakers” from my youth—I used when a youth to attend their meetings<hi rend="italic">. Thanks</hi> for inform. re those “<hi rend="italic">dials</hi>” in “Standard,” I was always puzzled by them!—</p>
         <p>Mrs Hamilton is here. Mrs Weber leaves at end of y. Shall I say!! I am glad? Your fship. is dissolved—that is, <hi rend="italic">I am if you are. </hi>I think much of you, &amp; sometimes I would you were nearer—but, I fear, my advice would not be worth much. Keep up good heart—health of <hi rend="italic">body </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">&amp;</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> mind</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I must soon begin Botany—for my deficient paper—promised. Yesterday your brother left 2 <hi rend="underline italic">old Maori letters</hi>—1 from the dean (writtenby J. Wh.), &amp; one from me. I shall send them to you—anon.—</p>
         <p>Good night: Kindest regards, yours truly, W.C.</p>
         <p>I knew that “Kennedy” well at the N. what stuff!!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
