<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0987">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1897 January 27: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1897-01-27">1897 January 27</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1897 January 27: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-816" place="foot" n="816"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Jany. 27, 1897</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I think it is a full month since I last wrote to you, since then <hi rend="italic">2 letters</hi>, &amp;, yesty, an “Evg. Post” from you. I shall commence to you tonight—finish tomorrow with looking into your letters &amp; replying, &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>I returned to N. on last day of ’96. I may say I hurried back, to help Mr. Welsh on Sunday’s, which I have done on the 4 Sundays since: he is now a little better but not well, &amp; would before this have been in Wgn. to see Dr. Mackenzie had his wife not been taken ill, about a fortnight ago, (pleurisy, &amp;c) and is still very weak. As I wished to <hi rend="italic">know </hi>how matters were <hi rend="italic">re </hi>my Museum Offer in May last, I waited (rather impatiently) for Dinwiddie to return from his holiday at Xt.Ch.—&amp;, at last! got him to call a Council Meeting on 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. at iv. p.m. All hands present, less <hi rend="italic">Humphries </hi>(the only good one!) (though had to wait for Hill, engd. w. his legion in our Museum room! now a <hi rend="italic">common place of meeting</hi>:) W.D. produced List of those who had replied to Circulars, on a ½ sheet notepaper—15 or so:—I hastily ran up ₤ col. found a little over ₤150.!!! (exclusive of McLean) So I soon told them what I had made up my mind to, viz. <hi rend="italic">to withdraw wholly my former offer</hi>; but, that as I had reason to believe Mr. McLean would contribute (<hi rend="italic">altogether</hi>) say, ₤<hi rend="italic">1000</hi>: &amp; he young, able, educated, travelled, rich, settled here in H.B., w. growing family, &amp; a <hi rend="italic">hearty desire</hi> towards a M. &amp; Ly. I would <hi rend="italic">support him </hi>w. ₤<hi rend="italic">500</hi>:—they wished me to hold on for another yr., or 6 months: “<hi rend="italic">NO</hi>”. Then I called their attention to present <hi rend="italic">state </hi>of museum Room! dirty &amp; things still unarranged, &amp;, worst of all! <hi rend="underline italic">their</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> compact </hi>with Athenm. Comee., allowing Athenm. to let out the present big Museum Room for any &amp; every purpose, &amp; as often as they pleased! reminding them how nicely we were fitted up in the <hi rend="italic">old</hi> Musm. room—now a “Kiosk”—or Tea-shop; and on looking into minutes of Council of last year, found (of <hi rend="italic">course</hi>!) <hi rend="underline italic">Large</hi> the <hi rend="italic">principal</hi> mover—I did not spare him &amp; them: I said, I would subscribe ₤25. (if other members of Institute would add thereto) to prosecute <hi rend="italic">that little </hi>Council for <hi rend="italic">so acting</hi>—upsetting our Lease, &amp;c.—provided, 2 Lawyers of N. agree we had a case: that the Athenm. Comee. were <hi rend="italic">always antagonistic </hi>to the museum—that one great evil arose from members of Inst. Council being also M. of Athenm. Commee.—that Large especially acted in that way—witness his gaining the ground for timber yd. sevl. yrs. ago, &amp;c—&amp;c—now the fat was in the fire! L. said a deal got up, w. stick, paced about, &amp; left the Room. I had also found fault w. Hill, who could come <hi rend="italic">here </hi>(to my house) &amp; speak plainly, &amp; <hi rend="italic">uphold me</hi> in all I said, while <hi rend="italic">there </hi>he sided w. L.,—<hi rend="italic">now</hi> saying, “What is the use of complaining,” &amp;c. All hands were on me, I was obliged to tell them—that <hi rend="underline italic">I knew all</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> from the beginning</hi>, &amp; they <hi rend="italic">did not</hi>—3 of the 5 present (W.D., Dr. Moore, &amp; Dr. Milne Thomson) in particular were all <hi rend="italic">new </hi>hands. Craig (I regret to say) made a bitter speech: (he &amp; L., have always been yoke-fellows:)—but Hill’s <hi rend="italic">last </hi>one beat all! H. said, that I, by my conduct last year had lost his party ₤<hi rend="italic">1000</hi>: for he had 100 fine yg. fellows who would give ₤5. each from their scant earnings, &amp; he could easily raise ₤<hi rend="italic">500</hi> more: and, that it was well known I hated the yg. men of Napier! At last Craig asked—If any other business? W.D. &amp; self said, “NO,” so I left the Chair. I staid a short time talking w. Dr. Moore about a new book on Egypt I had lent him—and finding others still remaining &amp; not doing anything, I enqd. “whether any thing in hand”: “NO, going to arrange for a pic-nic”; so I came away: that was Thursday evg: on Friday night I recd. a note from W.D. enclosing copy of a letter <hi rend="italic">written by them then &amp; there </hi>to Large, praising him for all he had ever done for Inst., &amp; protesting (“<hi rend="italic">dissent</hi>,” is the word used) against the “unwarrantable language used by the President,” &amp;c. &amp; signed by all. On Saty. I merely acknd. receipt: and I have heard of nothing since, but I <hi rend="italic">have not been </hi>to town, &amp; Hill, I hear, is at Gisborne.—<hi rend="italic">One thing</hi>, however, is <hi rend="italic">certain</hi>, that unless Craig, &amp; Hill, (<hi rend="italic">H. expecially</hi>) apologise—<hi rend="underline italic">we part</hi>. Of course they must back up <hi rend="italic">L.,</hi> they being in the same boat w. him.</p>
         <p>I omitted <hi rend="italic">one </hi>main thing: they (2 or 3) said, that McLean had told them <hi rend="italic">after </hi>his seeing me here on the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Decr., that I would agree to extension of time. It was useless my denying it, &amp; showing the impossibility of my having <hi rend="italic">so </hi>spoken. Well, that same night I wrote to McL., and on the following Tuesday he very kindly called &amp; staid nearly an hour—<hi rend="italic">denying </hi>his having so spoken, moreover I had <hi rend="italic">not </hi>said so; &amp; agreeing generally w. me, in all I related. One remark of his was <hi rend="italic">good</hi>: “Why, the very proceeds of <hi rend="italic">one day’s </hi>work at Totalisator would give funds enough for Museum!”—and then against Racing, &amp; Betting, &amp;c, to<hi rend="italic"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">your</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">heart’s content</hi>! our annual meeting is drawing <hi rend="italic">nigh</hi>: I have early in Decr. warned W.D. <hi rend="italic">re same</hi>, also, “Report” (not to be such a wretched bald affair as the <hi rend="italic">last</hi>!) and told him I would not receive a <hi rend="italic">rough draft</hi> report full of erasures, &amp;c. (as the last was—&amp; <hi rend="italic">so passed by them</hi>). I am not sure that I shall go, but I suppose—<hi rend="italic">I must</hi>: and such may be my <hi rend="italic">last</hi> appearance there. I gave W.D. my prests. “address” to transmit to Dr. H., w. my <hi rend="italic">only </hi>small Botl. p. early in Decr.,—and have <hi rend="italic">again</hi> (!) written to Dr.H., (lowering myself) but, as before, <hi rend="italic">no reply</hi>: however I have merely said—at pressing request of many members who <hi rend="italic">heard </hi>it (<hi rend="italic">my last words</hi>) I send it,—If <hi rend="italic">not </hi>pubd. <hi rend="italic">whole</hi>—<hi rend="italic">to be returned to me</hi>; also, my former paper on “Cornish Tin Mines,” &amp;c.—Unfortunately for me (<hi rend="italic">now</hi>), <hi rend="italic">not one friendly </hi>member by my side—or, rather, <hi rend="italic">not one </hi>I can take counsel with! I found, also, that <hi rend="italic">their </hi>agreement w. the Kiosk mob, is only for <hi rend="underline italic">1 yr</hi>!! and there is a <hi rend="italic">better</hi> Tea Rooms (higher, &amp;c.) on opposite side of street (this from McLean).</p>
         <p>Hamilton, in a <hi rend="italic">late </hi>letter, had said, If offer falls through, (and he would give £10. per ann. for 2 years to support it) he should take away his Deposits—I told the Council this, &amp; that I should take away mine.—Large, ever since he was made J.P., has become “too big for his boots”: he is member of Chr. of Commerce and (in this day’s paper) is seeking to be elected Member of Harbour Board; only 3 are wanted, &amp; there are 5 applicants. You will (no doubt) have heard of the death of Mrs Ferguson (Fannin’s clerk’s mother),—Miss Renouf also died last week, she w. her sister, both in St. Paul’s choir, &amp; <hi rend="italic">there </hi>singing 2 Sundays before decease. Our old friend Rev. R. Fraser, has <hi rend="italic">resigned</hi>! leaves for Scotland end of March. I have spoken w. Dr. Sidey &amp; Rev. Paterson &amp; Grant, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>retaining him—but <hi rend="italic">no use</hi>: they say, “he <hi rend="italic">may </hi>come out again”: but I don’t believe it. I told them <hi rend="italic">we </hi>must make up a purse for him.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="underline italic">28</hi>
            <hi rend="sup underline italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi> To proceed: your last, <hi rend="italic">first</hi>: thanks for <hi rend="italic">Manuka </hi>spns, all in good order &amp; condition: I think you may find them all in H.Bk. N.Z. Fl., as <hi rend="italic">vars</hi>. of <hi rend="italic">Scoparium </hi>(so Hook. but?) Years ago I had a good deal to say, &amp; write too (Home) <hi rend="italic">re</hi> same. J.N. Williams once sent me spns. of a still larger fld. kind w. blood red flowers: I had also seen that sort before. In Australia there are <hi rend="italic">several </hi>described sps., 20, or more. Thanks for news <hi rend="italic">re </hi>“<hi rend="italic">that Book Sale</hi>”.—–</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">To yours of 8</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi> I notice your tone of depression (spirits, mostly,) <hi rend="italic">re heavy daily toil</hi>, and forecasts! Would hope you <hi rend="italic">already </hi>have a brighter &amp; more genial time; also, that you had <hi rend="italic">less </hi>to do in the common daily work &amp; struggle of life &amp; your occupation, &amp; <hi rend="italic">more </hi>in that of a higher &amp; more suitable plane. Not unfreqy. have I heard some of your old acquaintances say—you did wrong in leaving N. &amp; <hi rend="italic">opening as Printer</hi> at Wgn.——Could you dispose <hi rend="underline italic">well</hi> (say ere long) of yr. Ptg. Off. and at <hi rend="italic">same time</hi> obtain sufficient wtg. and mental employ?</p>
         <p>At last! have had 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Revise of 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Sheet, letter A, Lex., pp. 48 (I <hi rend="italic">suppose</hi> about ½ through: no use urging).—A memo came w. it:— “marked broken letters would come well-up in wkg. off.” Replying, I sd. “I hope so: but <hi rend="underline">i</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">without</hi> dot, and <hi rend="underline">t</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">without</hi> cross (proofs, too, <hi rend="italic">good,</hi> clean,) seemed to me to be doubtful: and then I told them a bit of my expce. in Watts’, a <hi rend="italic">fine</hi> (6d.) for every damaged and mkd. out letter <hi rend="italic">distributed</hi> and of the “old shoe” attached to every imposing-stone frame to receive such letters—for foundry.</p>
         <p>Thanks, for all your kind remarks on portions of my former letters: <hi rend="underline">Kapai</hi>.</p>
         <p>Sir W. Buller had called here in my absence inland: &amp; to my surprise again! A fortnight ago—landing purposely to see me, on his way to Auckland, only on shore 2–3 hours:—I was much pleased to see him: <hi rend="italic">re</hi> my Prests’. “Address” he strongly urged me to forward it to Dr. H., &amp; that <hi rend="italic">he</hi> (B) would see him, &amp;c. I have since written to B.</p>
         <p>And now for another bit of <hi rend="underline italic">News</hi>! Two days ago (Tuesday aftn.) I here in my little room writing, my man came in to tell me— “Bp. W. &amp; Archdn. S.W were outside at the door”. (!!!) So I jumped up to receive them <hi rend="italic">gladly</hi>: they staid over an hour, after some time <hi rend="underline italic">pleasingly</hi> chatting in front room, we went to back v., Bp. overhauled ½ dz. or more books, &amp; then into my <hi rend="italic">little</hi> sanctum room—but throughout <hi rend="italic">alike</hi>—open, free, without reserve or coldness, &amp; partly on “<hi rend="italic">Trans.</hi>”<hi rend="italic">Inst. </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">vols</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi> the Bp made some dry telling remarks on “Taylor White and his Maori”: I <hi rend="italic">thought</hi> I would have given 5/- for <hi rend="italic">you</hi> to hear them, &amp; 10/- for Hector, Tregear &amp; Co.! They drove up in a buggy by Robert’s <hi rend="italic">new </hi>road. The Bp leaves end of February by “Ormuz”:—we parted lovingly.</p>
         <p>We had a <hi rend="italic">terrible</hi> scare of fire noon on 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Grass on brow above school: soon more than 100 assd., did all they could, fire raged! Everythg. so <hi rend="underline italic">dry</hi>! Providentially wind N. <hi rend="italic">down</hi> M. Road and strong, water scarce, &amp; only in buckets from taps and tank: Fire Brig. w. hose &amp;c, at last came—and ended it, <hi rend="italic">but</hi> had the wind been the <hi rend="italic">usual</hi> sea-b. strong from sea (as on day before) this h. &amp; its contents must have gone! for a time it sickened me: I was <hi rend="italic">physically</hi> helpless. It has cost me about £10. in the rewards for aid. This is the 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> within a wk. on my land: first was in “Hitchings gully”, early discovd. by laudable Harvey, now residing <hi rend="italic">there</hi>,who, w. women &amp; boys of the place, put it out, after “½ <hi rend="italic">ac. grass burnt up</hi>”. <hi rend="italic">Waterworth saw</hi> from Cl. Sq the beginning of No. 2, and says, “<hi rend="italic">a man did it purposely, and then cut and run</hi>”:<hi rend="italic"> </hi>the Detective has been to me about it. So you may see—my time (1897) has been a cheqd. one—<hi rend="underline italic">black</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> predominating</hi>.</p>
         <p>A “Mrs Hetley” (N.Z flower painter of some notoriety at Home—in past years) has had her colln. on view at Crerar’s—upstairs, agt. wall, some scores! I went 2ce to see them: she, hearing of this, wrote me a <hi rend="italic">fulsome</hi> puffing letter, begging my <hi rend="italic">favourable</hi> criticism: saying, how greatly they have been patronised by Royalty and praised at Paris, &amp;c. Unforty. I could <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be charmed and (having <hi rend="italic">no</hi> gallantry, neither chivalric politeness in my constitution) replied briefly—saying— “I could wish you had not written to me—because I cannot do as you desire, &amp; this for many reasons. Perhaps I am too well acqd. with our N.Z. Flora—both living, and as being faithfully represented in English and French botanical works more than 50 years ago: and this being the case I am somewhat amused in your saying, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>your work— “I published it to <hi rend="italic">make known</hi> the flora of N.Z.”, &amp;c, &amp;c.—I am obliged to reply rather briefly to your letters (my time being more than fully occupied) and permit me to add, I shall not be able to say any thing more on this subject.”</p>
         <p>While at Waip<hi rend="underline">u</hi>. on my way back , Gow informed me, that <hi rend="italic">no one would be permitted to see your cousin R</hi>., then very low—so I did not go, but recently a letter from Tuke that he had been to see him, &amp;c. &amp; found him <hi rend="italic">better</hi>. I have not seen your Uncle for a <hi rend="italic">long</hi> time.</p>
         <p>I have lately recd. from Archdn. S.W. a pamphlet neatly ptd. at Xt.Ch. by T.E. Fraser,— “The True Doctrine of the Eucharist”, extracted from a charge by the Bp. of Worcester, 1895, (and, I am told, reprinted at Archdn’s. expense,) it contains a few <hi rend="italic">Greek </hi>phrases.—And from Home, a small recent work by Jesse Page, “Among the Maoris or Daybreak in N.Z.”, containing many cuts, some new &amp; very good, some <hi rend="italic">old</hi>: much, of course, from Marsden to Selwyn, with some scraps of Maori—all full of mistakes! and no mention of the N.T.! save on <hi rend="italic">last </hi>p. (160)— “The whole of the Bible &amp; P.Bk. is <hi rend="italic">now widely </hi>circulated in the Maori language”.—pubd. by Partridge &amp; Co. I do not admire the work—though it may take well &amp; be believed:—price 1/6.</p>
         <p>Just before I left Dvk. I received a note from Dr. de Lisle, informing me of his Xmas.-Box—in a fine son born on Xmas. eve, &amp; wishing me to find out for him a pretty <hi rend="italic">Maori </hi>name. On my return, (memory <hi rend="italic">now</hi> being treacherous) I took up Wms’. Dy. to help me, and have been surprised and <hi rend="italic">amused</hi>, at the work of <hi rend="underline italic">you two</hi>! <hi rend="italic">Botanical </hi>papers, &amp; <hi rend="italic">Maori </hi>ones, in “Trans.” have been made to yield their stores. I jotted down 20 nouns, or so, but they (2) have <hi rend="italic">not yet decided.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Among <hi rend="italic">old </hi>letters lately turned down, I find a long one, <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d</hi>. 1866, written from “Govt. Ptg. Off.” by some ptr. named “<hi rend="italic">W. Kellway</hi>” (or something similar), <hi rend="italic">re </hi>ptg. Mao. Lexicon,—then in embryo—or <hi rend="italic">nubibus</hi>!<note xml:id="ftn3-817" place="foot" n="817"> Did he mean “incubus”?</note> did you ever hear of him? the 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>. no. of the “<hi rend="italic">Scindian</hi>” (High School, Gazette!) ptd. by Leigh &amp; B., is just out: I have a copy—<hi rend="italic">little</hi> of note in it. That is a rare discovery—that <hi rend="italic">precious </hi>metal at Collingwood: (“Gold is brass compared with it.”) Have lately had 3 or 4 visits from Andrews, Whanganui College: he returns today—but last night, I think, at Mount Vernon—by Invitation.—</p>
         <p>Yesty. our great annual Caledonian Sports Day: a genl. Holiday! Kilts, bagpipes, &amp; Gaelic in the ascendant: at Farndon—2 Cricket matches played,—Waipawa &amp; Patangata v. County Club,—&amp; 2 of <hi rend="underline italic">our parsons</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">prominent</hi> in them—Tuke &amp; Clarke: <hi rend="italic">I don’t like this</hi>.</p>
         <p>I have had a few small apricots, and 10 (all told!) peaches from my old garden,—the boys stole the gooseberries, before I returned, &amp; the minahs go for the figs!—</p>
         <p>III, p.m. So much this mg: when Hamilton <hi rend="italic">suddenly</hi> appd., just landed, &amp; looking <hi rend="underline italic">very well</hi>: only grey haired! we chatted for 2 hours, here again tomorrow at ix, &amp; on Saty. to Dvk. <hi rend="italic">en route </hi>to Wgn. The Bp. of Wgn. was at Te Aute, early in this month, w. Bp. Wms. &amp; nearly all our Clergy—<hi rend="italic">save we 4 here in N. </hi>I sent him (Wgn.) thro’ Eccles, copies of all my papers pubd. <hi rend="italic">here</hi>: <hi rend="italic">will he like them</hi>? “Jesse Page’s” book commences w. Macaulay’s N.Zr.! And now I must stop! several hours over this <hi rend="italic">for </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>. Kind regards to <hi rend="italic">you </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">all</hi>. Believe me Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Monday. It rained heavily all night glass too high “Fair” &amp; steady.</p>
         <p>In bed, revolving yr. letter—I found I had omitted to <hi rend="italic">thank </hi>you heartily for your good stand <hi rend="italic">re </hi>yr. Imposter Eugene, also, for your remark re “Flagellants”—good: I would <hi rend="italic">you </hi>saw &amp; sd. same re this mis-termed “Salvn. (!) army: but I dare believe you will yet see them in Þr. right colours—taking S’s. for your guide. I write in haste for post.</p>
         <p>Mem. sample of quick <hi rend="underline italic">compositing</hi> for an <hi rend="italic">old</hi> man—I copied Peacock’s letter <hi rend="italic">within</hi> one hour! &amp; mainly <hi rend="italic">for you</hi>. There.——–W.C.</p>
         <p>P<hi rend="italic">.S. </hi>I suppose you have seen <hi rend="italic">Report</hi> on Breakwtr?</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
