<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0492">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1882 March 25: to Balfour</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73378/">Balfour</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1882-03-25">1882 March 25</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1882 March 25: to Balfour<note xml:id="ftn3-132" place="foot" n="132"> ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier Saturday Mar 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1882</p>
         <p>Mr D.P. Balfour</p>
         <p>Dear Sir</p>
         <p>I have to thank you for your kind &amp; interesting note, or rather, letter of the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, &amp; also to apologize for not replying before, which, no dou­bt I should have done by last Thursdays mail to Puketapu, but for the out­going English mail of this day.</p>
         <p>I have been very busy indeed all this week, &amp; a good part of last in pre­paring for &amp; writing to E by this mail. We held our Council meeting last Friday week (17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>) to decide on what books should be ordered, and as (of course) <hi rend="italic">all the writing</hi> falls on me, I have despatched the order with a draft of £70, on account of Institute, also another order with the draft for £25 for books for self &amp; others—and all those books have had to be copied no less than 5 times; 1, for <hi rend="italic">our</hi>selves roughly, as sub committee chosen from 2–3 score of Catalogues. 2, those <hi rend="italic">put into order</hi> for the Council. 3, those <hi rend="italic">selected</hi> by Council; 4, ordered for Engd, &amp;, 5, Duplicate order for ditto,­ but, there, the job is <hi rend="italic">done</hi>; so I may throw hat &amp; wig into the corner!!. Now for your letter.—I had heard from P.D. who kindly called, that you had been in town, I hope Mrs Balfour &amp; yourself &amp; <hi rend="italic">family</hi>, too, are well. As to those water insects,—my man, who lived several years in the Petane Valley, says they are very common there in the “creeks”, he has seen 100s of them, &amp;c, which I am inclined to believe, because the <hi rend="italic">perfect</hi> insects are so numerous everywhere in the summer. My pair have long been dead, they eat nothing while with me, and by-and-bye one died, &amp; <hi rend="italic">split open</hi> in dying, so seeing the other was likely to follow suit, I put it into spirits. I should like to know to <hi rend="italic">which species</hi> these belong, but this can only be done by noticing their change, which takes place leisurely in, or on, the weedy banks of their stream, &amp; capturing one or two. I did see <hi rend="italic">one</hi> open its mouth, or mask, when, like you, I was cleaning it first in water, when I teased him a bit; &amp; I <hi rend="italic">intended</hi> to do so again, some day when changing the water, little thinking they would die so soon. I still do not think they used their masks to form those pellets—rather their feet—. Since my last to you, I have put up &amp; sent S (to Mr Fereday) 2 boxes of Moths &amp; Butterflies—a very troublesome job; and have written to Capt Broun in reply to his letter on our <hi rend="italic">Coleoptera</hi>, as well as several letters to our local collectors, in reply to queries, &amp; re specimens sent in. I daresay your newly found bush was (as you say) <hi rend="italic">Discaria</hi>; I have seen it, sparingly (years ago) between Pakowhai &amp; Hastings <hi rend="italic">site</hi>—also, inland beyond Pakipaki, &amp; more plentiful down the coast S of Castle Point, but <hi rend="italic">most</hi> of all at Poverty Bay—whence my original specimens.</p>
         <p>I suppose you knew poor <hi rend="italic">Ferguson</hi>; a sad blow to that family, F &amp; daughter taken together,—&amp; now others of the family including the mother are <hi rend="italic">very</hi> ill with the same disorder; there seems to be much sickness everywhere, both in town &amp; country. May you &amp; yours be preserved.</p>
         <p>I fully purposed leaving for the Bush on Monday next, but <hi rend="italic">now</hi> I am in doubt whether to go yet; “Herald” of this morning gives a sad account of state of health in the Bush Districts.—However I may go early next week so I write this today.</p>
         <p>I have had a long letter from a good Cry. Botanist at home, who had received the package of Liverworts I had sent him hence in Nov last, which I had managed to collect in the woods in that month in my very wet visit, &amp; he was highly delighted with his “Genus”. He has sent me a few spns in a letter of our British <hi rend="italic">Sphagna</hi>, (a peculiar looking kind of whitish Moss found in bogs, &amp; supposed to be the basis of peat,) &amp; will send more for our Institute. This Genus,’though common all over the world, is but scantily represented in N.Z., either in number of species or in bulk; indeed I have only met with it in the N. You may have, in wet holes or bogs, some of it, if so send in specimens. See your Hd Book under <hi rend="italic">Sphagnum.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>If I go—I expect to be <hi rend="italic">fairly</hi> home for the winter by the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> at furthest. And with kind regards and best wishes,</p>
         <p>Believe me</p>
         <p>Yours very truly</p>
         <p>Wm Colenso.</p>
         <p>No 2 Wednesday 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Being still here I add a few lines before posting my letter.</p>
         <p>I put off (unwillingly) my visit to the Bush—but I think I shall leave on Monday next, returning about the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>—all being well.</p>
         <p>The weather here is delightfully fine, and the “sickness” I hope is generally lessening. Using the word “sickness” causes me to remark I am pretty well sick—with seeing so <hi rend="italic">much</hi> of trash in the “Herald” re those Irish folks; between them, the Everlasting “Races”, &amp; <hi rend="italic">Cricket</hi>, I am often tempted to <hi rend="italic">stop my papers.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I have had a note from Nairn, Wairoa, containing spns of three ferns (which he wishes the names of), but nothing <hi rend="italic">new.</hi> I have not seen P.D. lately. Hope you are all well</p>
         <p>Yours truly</p>
         <p>W. Colenso</p>
         <p>Since writing my letter it has occurred to me to enlist your kind &amp; hearty energies in another way. When in 70 mile Bush in Dec, I discovered a <hi rend="italic">new</hi> plant of the Genus <hi rend="italic">Astelia</hi>; no doubt I had often seen it before in leaf, but this was in <hi rend="italic">flower</hi>, &amp; a prize; I dissected it, &amp; wrote its description, while up there; &amp; though I afterwards saw a few more plants, yet none in flower; unfortunately the plant (like all the genus) is diœcious, &amp; mine was the female. I want more, of both sexes, but particularly the male. It is much eaten by the cattle whenever it grows low down, on trees or fallen <hi rend="italic">logs </hi>(indeed, mine in flower had been so eaten), however I brought away a small clump, &amp; have it here doing well in my garden, in the fork of a tree. I enclose a leaf I have just cut. The leaves run a <hi rend="italic">few</hi> inches longer, &amp; a little wider, &amp; the plant looks like a bushy common coarse sedge. On my way home by train, between Ormondville &amp; Takapau, I was surprised to see <hi rend="italic">scores</hi> of these plants on both sides of the railway,—on the <hi rend="italic">smaller</hi> trees (not in forks) about 8–10–14 feet from the ground!. I spoke to John Stewart (at Takapau) &amp; have since written to him 3–4 times about them, &amp; he has been out, travelling some miles along the way: pulled down lots, but no flowers. Just see if you have the said plant in your bush. <hi rend="italic">Lar­ger</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">well known</hi> sorts grow high up &amp; in the forks of trees. It is <hi rend="italic">one</hi> of my jobs to hunt up this fellow—either in flower or in fruit.</p>
         <p>W.Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>