<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0797">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 August 12: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-08-12">1891 August 12</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 August 12: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-547" place="foot" n="547"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, August 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
            <lb/>1891.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I will begin mine to you today although I shall not post until I go to Bank on Friday (my day <hi rend="italic">out</hi>—as I found, accidentally, that Hill will be in his <hi rend="italic">office</hi> on that day—&amp; I wish to see him, as <hi rend="italic">Prest</hi>. of H.B. Ph. Inst.)</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Imprimis</hi>: I sincerely hope you may not have that unwelcome visitor Hoopg. C. invading you—for dear little Victor’s sake.</p>
         <p>I <hi rend="italic">regret</hi> your having had such paing. loss of time—that you <hi rend="italic">cannot spare</hi>, &amp; expense, in wtg. to Hamilton re Moa’s egg. I was aware of all <hi rend="italic">that</hi> (in Owen) &amp; much more, from <hi rend="underline italic">Travers</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>(!) and J.Wh., which I am sorry to see—lies on lies! All about Moas as a thing <hi rend="italic">recent</hi> &amp; very well known: Travers has always been a great sinner in this respect—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> buying up all manner of stories &amp; then <hi rend="italic">reproducing as his own</hi>!! J.Wh. however is terribly out in his meaning of a N. phrase, he gives it “Tautau a <hi rend="italic">Moa</hi>” (separating, &amp; w. cap. M.)—a fight between two after the manner of the Moas, which they had seen thus fighting, &amp;c.—“Mark, how plain a tale shall put him down”.</p>
         <p>Tautauamoa means, a squabble between 2 of same clan or village over a bed in plantation (<hi rend="italic">moa</hi>), a private quarrel, &amp; therefore of no conseq., soon over. (See p.95—vol.xii.) my Paper on Moa.</p>
         <p>There is great plenty of <hi rend="italic">such</hi>, that I have both seen &amp; heard of. (? Is Tregear free?) All owing to shallow men of mind, and a <hi rend="italic">determn. to find </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">there</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> the matter in Questn. </hi>(Plenty of <hi rend="italic">this</hi> in Commentaries on Scripture!)</p>
         <p>I send you an ext. re the <hi rend="italic">Australian</hi> “<hi rend="italic">Dinornis</hi>”<hi rend="italic">—</hi>unless yours is more recent.</p>
         <p>Hamilton is right—i.e. partly: He did write to me last, but in (<hi rend="underline italic">part</hi>) <hi rend="italic">reply</hi>. And he <hi rend="italic">did</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">offend</hi> me (vex me, really) and I told him of it: he had <hi rend="italic">better</hi> spns. of Taupo plants, when out w. Hill, these <hi rend="italic">were to be for me</hi> freely offered—given—but left at A., (to aid, in going over Hills wh. were damaged) well, last autumn, 1890 while in the Bush, H. allowed <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>, who was here &amp; with him, to have them:—I told H. of it, in my last, &amp; how I <hi rend="italic">felt it</hi>—<hi rend="italic">keenly</hi>: &amp; in writing to Kirk I let him know of it: <hi rend="italic">both avoided</hi> the subject in their replies!!!——For many reasons I did <hi rend="italic">not</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">expect</hi> such treatment from <hi rend="italic">H</hi>.: of K. I <hi rend="italic">say</hi> nothing!!!<hi rend="italic"> </hi>
         </p>
         <p>Having written to you so recently I have little to say, save our last Meeting (18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.) wh. was an extraordy. good one! I went there <hi rend="italic">before</hi> 8, &amp; found a big Musm. room <hi rend="italic">full</hi>!—row on row of ladies, mostly, looking this way towards door, I tried to get behind. No!—Hill gave me Secy’s. Chr.—the <hi rend="italic">small</hi> table was at <hi rend="italic">this</hi> end, for Secy. &amp; Hill, &amp; a big sheet was hung across behind it for Mag. Lantn show. VIII. arrd—folks kept pouring in!—Spencer &amp; daughter, the Bp, Craig, Pinckney, Lessong, Duncan, Hardy, Hill worked hard, w. Secy. bringing in chairs for 5 min. &amp; gave it up (in despair)! His paper was <hi rend="italic">very long, </hi>his prelimy. remarks <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Map, &amp;c. were <hi rend="italic">long</hi>, &amp; much time taken up in showing photos, on screen—he closed (to our ? intense satisfaction) at X. during wh. period no one moved—quæ. <hi rend="italic">could</hi> move!—so wedged in. I moved vote of thanks briefly, Bp. secd. in <hi rend="italic">1</hi> sentence, &amp; the show was over.—Unfy. (again!) H. said—“Next month 3 papers, Westall’s, Pinckney’s, &amp; Dr. Sp. (on Tuberculine) wants be read, &amp; be very interesting,” &amp;c., &amp;c. The <hi rend="italic">vols</hi>. “Trans” were there, (the case had gone on to Auckland!)—a thick book: I brought away 1 for Dr Yates, as Mail was <hi rend="italic">leaving</hi>, cost 3/11, <hi rend="italic">includg</hi>. Regn. fee 3d. I enqd. re Reports:— “printed long ago.” <hi rend="italic">Surprised</hi>: brought 1 for Yates, &amp; I find it is ptd. at “D.T.” office!! Why? I shall enq. To return to what Hill said, I remarked, “What of my Papers? I was early, in March, written to, <hi rend="italic">offy.,</hi> by Wh., <hi rend="italic">from Council</hi>—to enq.”—&amp; I replied”, <hi rend="italic">Yes</hi>.</p>
         <p>Two <hi rend="italic">aye 3</hi> things, in particular in yr. last. I <hi rend="italic">regret</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">much </hi>to see. 1, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> your son<hi rend="italic">,</hi> would you had better tidings to send me of him: <hi rend="italic">patience</hi>, must be your sheet-anchor: hope on. 2. Your having to work at Home by nt. on “Typo”—<hi rend="italic">I don’t like this</hi>: I fear you are burning the 2 ends of the Candle! You may carry on this throughout <hi rend="italic">1891</hi>—but, if no better prospect then, <hi rend="italic">stop it</hi>: your own health, &amp; family cares require it. 3. Your differences w. Blair—this is, <hi rend="italic">to me</hi>, still worse. I feel much for you, &amp; will <hi rend="italic">gladly</hi> send you £10. don. by next mail (<hi rend="italic">letter</hi>), if you will accept it.—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">This month</hi> (’90) I was steadily engd. at Wdv. in Ch. wk—5 <hi rend="italic">Sundays</hi>; and I was happy in it: at <hi rend="italic">present</hi> I am idle—in that line, &amp; I regret it.—</p>
         <p>Hill told me, in his note, that the Athenm. Comee. had behaved shamefully <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the Moa bones—threw them all out into the yard!! (Oh! Hamilton!) Large, at last, had them gathered , &amp; took charge at his place.—</p>
         <p>I don’t like this non-ptg. of Report. Neither do I like this turning of the Tutaekuri R. in this direction. To me, it is <hi rend="italic">very wrong</hi>, &amp; Napier may rue it. I borrd. Owen’s 4to; “Extinct Wingless Birds of N.Z.” and am sorry to find such <hi rend="italic">stuff</hi> about the Moa therein, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> last one killed at Waipukurau <hi rend="italic">apud</hi> Travers &amp; his henchman J.White. Also, in Rev. W. Williams’ letter to D.P. Buckland (Feby. /42) given <hi rend="italic">in</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">extenso</hi> not a line, nor intimation of the pair of <hi rend="italic">femora</hi> I had recently left w. W.W. to send home; indeed the whole written—<hi rend="italic">as if, no one but himself had ever moved in the matter</hi>. I was greatly surprised at this: and I think I shall publish, in this paper, a copy of one of W.W’s letters to me, re Moa, <hi rend="italic">about this time</hi>—I am ½-inclined to think a <hi rend="italic">portion has been expunged</hi>!!—</p>
         <p>Well now goodbye: kindest regards and best wishes. I forgot to say, in returning from Waipawa on 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ulto. I had Rev R Fraser, all the way! <hi rend="italic">we</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> sat togr. &amp; enjoyed ourselves</hi>—Yours affy. W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
