<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1046">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1898 May 9: to Wiremu Colenso</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL Ms-papers-10535-1.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/74618/">Wiremu Colenso</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1898-05-09">1898 May 9</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1898 May 9: to Wiremu Colenso<note xml:id="ftn3-895" place="foot" n="895"> ATL Ms-papers-10535-1.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Woodville, N. Zealand.<lb/>May 9<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., 1898.</p>
         <p>My dear Son Willie, and Sarah</p>
         <p>My last to you was on 8<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> (&amp; 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>) April, since then, &amp; only <hi rend="italic">recently</hi> here by <hi rend="italic">Vancouver</hi> Mail, yours of 16 March came to hand, you posted <hi rend="italic">too late </hi>for S.F. Mail: I was, &amp; am, much grieved to find dear W’s. eye no better—I trust it is <hi rend="italic">well</hi> now.—–</p>
         <p>I left N. on Tuesday, Apl. 26<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. for Waipukurau: next day back to Waipawa on business, there all day! &amp; missed train at 5 p.m. by 3 minutes, (no cab, &amp; <hi rend="italic">long</hi> walking!) so remained waiting till 7.30—got to Wai—–u, by 8.15, knocked up—to bed—no sleep, so feverish; <hi rend="italic">all next day on sofa</hi>,—but better by night, &amp; on Saturday came on here, for <hi rend="italic">Sunday’s </hi>“Harvest thanksg. Service” Mg. read Lessons &amp; preached: evg. read Lessons walking to &amp; fro (some distance) <hi rend="italic">both</hi> services.—Weather very fine, and folks kind, glad to see me; I consented to remain over <hi rend="italic">another Sunday</hi>.–Mr. Eccles kindly drove me about in his easy low-step buggy—4 days—2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>–5<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. On 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. (Tuesday) we went up that <hi rend="italic">high </hi>mountain, peak of Ruahine again: came back “all right”—<hi rend="italic">this time</hi>, thank <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>!—though some few <hi rend="italic">feared</hi>, ⅓ thought me fool-hardy—or worse, Yesterday we had (again) good attendance at Church—I<hi rend="italic"> </hi>preached, &amp; read Lessons both mg. &amp; evg. The <hi rend="italic">first</hi> time since March 1897 (&amp; in this Ch. too) that I have been enabled to preach <hi rend="italic">twice </hi>in one Sunday. How different with me <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, <hi rend="italic">this May</hi> to what it was <hi rend="italic">last </hi>May! In my evg’s. S. I told them of my thoughts &amp; experience on those two occasions: how truly that Hymn (chosen &amp; sung by them last evening) “<hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> moves in a mysterious way,” was realized <hi rend="italic">by me</hi>.— “Behind a frowning Providence, He hides a smiling face.” I am <hi rend="italic">very much better </hi>in health stronger too in legs, &amp; in lungs—it is really wonderful! as all say.—</p>
         <p>By “cable” this past week I heard of safe arrival of Mr. Welsh’s ship “Ruahine” at Plymouth, on 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. May 1 day after time: hope “<hi rend="italic">all well</hi>.”—</p>
         <p>I send you, <hi rend="italic">enclosed</hi>, specimens of our new (<hi rend="italic">small</hi>) postage stamps, the large 2½ d. one is now <hi rend="italic">extinct </hi>(sold out) and therefore of some value to the <hi rend="italic">collector</hi>—owing to an error in the spelling name of Lake—Wakat<hi rend="underline">i</hi>pu for Wakat<hi rend="underline">u</hi>pu<note xml:id="ftn3-896" place="foot" n="896"> Actually Wakitipu for Wakatipu.</note>—this has been altered.</p>
         <p>I leave here tomorrow for Dannevirke, shall only stay there <hi rend="italic">a few days</hi>, &amp; then go to Waipukurau—<hi rend="italic">few</hi> days—and then to the <hi rend="italic">Old Rest</hi>—or Hermitage. I hope <hi rend="italic">soon</hi> to be able to walk down to Napier: I left the Old Couple there well: so, son &amp; wife, in town.</p>
         <p>Mr. James Anderson of Napier died lately: a white-haired old man, who always lived close to Presbyterian Church, perhaps W. may remember him: he was the only European living in Napier who had been in my old &amp; big Mission House shortly before it was burnt down: and (as <hi rend="italic">he has said</hi>) I saved his life on that occasion by giving him a glass of port wine, &amp;c. he had been lost in the big swamps between Taradale (that <hi rend="italic">now</hi> is) &amp; Awapuni.</p>
         <p>My old <hi rend="italic">Nurse</hi> has been here, again this evening—with Mr. Eccles, hindering me, so that I fear I shall not be able to get away tomorrow: all are well, also Morgan’s wife &amp; family whom I went to see.</p>
         <p>Goodbye, dear Willie, &amp; Sarah, keep up your heart &amp; spirits, with a good look-out ahead. May <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> bless you both, ever prays yr. loving Father.</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>Am right glad the wretched Spaniards got a good licking, hope they may get a big lot more yet.—–</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>