<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0944">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1895 October 12: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1895-10-12">1895 October 12</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1895 October 12: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-756" place="foot" n="756"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier Saty. aftn.<lb/>October 12/95</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I must no longer put off writing to you—which I have been <hi rend="italic">going </hi>to do <hi rend="italic">several times</hi> of late: your 2 letters of 23 &amp; 29 August I have now before me (and have again read them) these, as you remark, crossed mine to you in transit—awkwardly for some correspce., and to tell you the truth—I have been, in <hi rend="italic">part</hi>, writing a reply to mine: <hi rend="italic">i.e. </hi>to some questions I had made.</p>
         <p>The recent death of Mr. Crerar, (another of your Napier friends,) whose body is just at this hour (3 p.m.) to be buried—forcibly reminds me of you: I had a great mind to attend the funeral, the wind on that hill (and I not having been out for this week), and my <hi rend="italic">not unbonnetting </hi>when there in the open (which, I know, cause unpleasant remarks) have served to keep me away: I respected him, also his son.—</p>
         <p>Looking over your letters (both shorter than usual, yet very interesting), I see but little to notice, save your kind readiness to receive from N.Z.I. my 2 <hi rend="italic">rejected papers </hi>in order to your printing them: thanks for that: but I have not <hi rend="italic">yet </hi>determined respecting them, whether to be printed or not: certainly not <hi rend="italic">by me alone</hi>. Some time ago I wrote my letter of complaint (a pretty full &amp; strong one) to our Hon. Secy., a Council meeting followed, and I am told a long &amp; pertinent resolution was drawn up &amp; sent (with copy of my L.) to Sir J.H. I have been promised copy of their Resolution (which I was also expecting and waited for to send to you) but have not yet recd. it: Hon. Secy. has been very busy of late: Sup. Ct., &amp;c, &amp;c—Hill, too, away N., and <hi rend="italic">I not in </hi>town, &amp;c. One thing I have fully decided on, &amp; <hi rend="italic">told them </hi>so, that I write <hi rend="italic">no more </hi>Reminiscences! &amp; Miscellaneous Papers: I <hi rend="italic">may </hi>give a kind of running short lecture, <hi rend="italic">viva voce</hi>, re such, that’s all. The remarks—complaints, by letter &amp; in person from several quarters <hi rend="italic">re </hi>these so-called Judges of papers, including Maskell, Travers, and Tregear!!!—are astonishing: <hi rend="italic">their own </hi>lucubrations, with those of their dear friends (Taylor Wh. &amp; Co.) will be very sure to find a place in the annual vol. I suppose one reason why no answer yet, is owing to absence of Sir J. Hector at Xt.Ch., <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the Exhibition there. And my mentioning this, reminds me to ask you to say to Gore—to send me <hi rend="italic">my</hi> copy of vol. XXVII.—</p>
         <p>You rightly condole w. me, as one of the unfort. shareholders in the Bank N.Z.; last week I paid over their 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. demand <hi rend="italic">this year</hi>! Yet, while it is heavy on me, alas! I know it must be <hi rend="italic">10-fold heavier on many others</hi>! I managed to pay it early so as to have done with it—banish it from mind (?) as well as from Agenda paper—easier said than done.</p>
         <p>Here we have been full of “stirs”. which still exist, and are in full force. In end of September the Synod (Ch. of Engd.) I only attended formal aftn. sittings, iv–vi; the <hi rend="italic">night </hi>sittings were those of work or, rather, <hi rend="italic">talk</hi>! However that is over, &amp; I may never go again.</p>
         <p>Our Instit. <hi rend="italic">last</hi> mtg. for ’95, should be held on Monday next, but I agreed w. Hon. Secy. (Hill, Carlile, &amp; others being absent) to put it off until 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. I have promised 2–3 small Botanl. papers, w. specimens, and (<hi rend="underline italic">if needed</hi>) a kind of address—which, If Hon. Secy. <hi rend="italic">is ready with his promised paper, may not </hi>be required.—Little or <hi rend="italic">no </hi>notice now taken of those meetings in our papers.—–</p>
         <p>I have been very busy—<hi rend="italic">in head &amp; mind</hi>—on a matter of importance (at least, to me,) viz. my <hi rend="italic">new </hi>Will. Of course, it has long been a matter of deep thought and of prayer; and I have striven hard to do justice, &amp; to do my best: I finished it (the Engrossing) last week &amp; signed it at Carlile’s office: so that, in a measure, is off my mind,—to be followed, however, with a Codicil—mentioned in it.</p>
         <p>Re Tom S___y: 3 things at <hi rend="italic">one </hi>time in our “Herald” this week: (1) that the whole of the Ins. money has been pd. to Mr<hi rend="underline">s</hi>. S., through the <hi rend="italic">agent</hi>—<hi rend="italic">young </hi>
            <hi rend="doubleunderline underline italic">Hy</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>Lascelles! (Insd. in <hi rend="italic">German </hi>Firm) (2.) that <hi rend="italic">T.S.</hi> will shortly leave N.Z. for Australia. And (3) that his fine &amp; large property—near Makotuku (leashold) is now advd. for <hi rend="italic">sale</hi> under Regr. Sup. Ct., <hi rend="italic">at order of the Mortgagee</hi>! <hi rend="underline italic">I feel for the poor Father</hi>.</p>
         <p>The Governor, with suite, are here—he is my neighbour (!) at McLean’s House: and goes with his Lady &amp; them—to Races—to Balls &amp; Concerts, &amp; to Theatres!! with them, offrs. &amp; men, of the 2 Men-o-war! and the G. will stay here over Tuesday 22<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Great opening </hi>day of Breakwater. Weather still keeping very fine. I have been steadily <hi rend="italic">at Home </hi>all this wk., and no visitors.————</p>
         <p>I suppoose you heard of the sudden illness of the <hi rend="italic">Dean</hi>? In going to the Cathdl. on mg. 15<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> ult., passing Leask’s, &amp; he inside fence, L. asked me— “What of the Dean?” I, surprised, asked, “What?” “Oh! a fit this mg. at early communion in Cathl., &amp; carried to house”! (as I had seen in the papers, the Bp. was to be at <hi rend="italic">Petane</hi>) met Dr. de L. coming away— “Yes: very ill &amp; put to bed: serious attack of Influenza”. I made haste to Cathl.—Vestry—no one <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, &amp; C. filling, now just xi.—after 4–5 minutes Welsh came, with Miss Hovell, in a terrible state of perspn. (the Dean had sent for <hi rend="italic">him</hi>—not knowing if I were well, &amp;c.) &amp; so I agreed <hi rend="italic">to assist</hi>: and took evg. S. at St. Augustine’s while W. took Cathedral: at <hi rend="italic">his particular </hi>wish, I again helped him there (St. Aug’s) last Sunday morning.—</p>
         <p>I sent you the “Herald” contg. Bp’s. address to Synod—hope you recd. it: 3 things in it, in particular, I liked: (1) no peace w. Rome: (2.) <hi rend="italic">against </hi>Bazaars: (3) Relegating prayer for Unity, (an <hi rend="italic">Innovation </hi>by some of our Clerics) to the <hi rend="italic">close </hi>of Evg.S., <hi rend="italic">before Blessing</hi>. I heard <hi rend="italic">nothing </hi>that the Bp. and others <hi rend="italic">said</hi>: he speaks low &amp; fast, &amp; I at a distance from him, &amp;c.—Bp. Stuart, (his sister tells me,) has been laid up in Persia with bad eyes, but was better.—</p>
         <p>Have not yet fixed for Bush visit: <hi rend="italic">may not </hi>go thither this season, there not being <hi rend="italic">any work </hi>for me. Mr. Tuke wants me to take Waipukurau 3–4 wks., that he &amp; Mrs. T. may have a holiday: have <hi rend="italic">not yet </hi>consented.</p>
         <p>Now, Good Bye: look into my last letters (if not destroyed!) &amp; see if there are not some questions to be ansd.</p>
         <p>And with kind regards &amp; best wishes</p>
         <p>Believe me, yrs. sincerely, W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
