<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1022">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1897 December 5: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1897-12-05">1897 December 5</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1897 December 5: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-865" place="foot" n="865"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Sunday mg.<lb/>December 5/97.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>Entered on another month, &amp; thinking often <hi rend="italic">on you</hi>, I will begin my letter early this day. Yours of 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. I duly recd. &amp; thank you for, containing as it did many bright gleams of hope. I think I have lately sent you several papers—(my <hi rend="italic">last </hi>of yesterday posted last night)—which will yield you some more of my public scribbling,<note xml:id="ftn3-866" place="foot" n="866"> Australia of the past. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> 4 December 1897.</note> and (in the main) I believe <hi rend="italic">you </hi>will <hi rend="italic">agree </hi>w. me. My 2 <hi rend="italic">Motions</hi> in Synod on Wedy. aftn. (17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.) day <hi rend="italic">after </hi>my last letter to you—were <hi rend="italic">well received </hi>by those present, though, of course, <hi rend="italic">not affirmed, The Bp. early speaking </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">against</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> them</hi>, (non possumus), which settled the matter: so, on 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. motion, after some small speechifying, mainly by Archdn. Sam., the Bp. asked “If I had any reply:” this old man did <hi rend="italic">say something </hi>which was much applauded—no doubt many went w. me, but it was <hi rend="italic">unpremeditated</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">very strong </hi>language, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">long</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> too. </hi>I must have spoken this time, the <hi rend="doubleunderline underline italic">last</hi>! as I told them, nearly 20m. at least: I have scarcely a <hi rend="italic">faint </hi>recallection of what I did say (owing to my <hi rend="italic">shattered </hi>memory from Wdv. disaster): I remember quoting from our <hi rend="underline italic">old</hi> Ch. Ed. Com. Hymn, (verse <hi rend="italic">left out</hi> in Anct. &amp; Mod.!) “Revive thy dying churches, <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord</hi>”; &amp; telling them to beware of trusting in <hi rend="italic">externals</hi>—even in <hi rend="underline italic">no</hi>. of <hi rend="italic">Commts</hi>., &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">no</hi>. <hi rend="italic">confirmed</hi>. I am the <hi rend="italic">only one</hi> who do not use “My Lord” to Bp. Always “My Bp.” (as <hi rend="italic">we used </hi>to do to Selwyn, &amp; I <hi rend="italic">know </hi>“My Lord” is <hi rend="italic">not </hi>strictly in order.) The Bp’s. son, Rev. Herbert W. is, or <hi rend="italic">was, </hi>“Reporter for <hi rend="italic">Press</hi>”(!!!) besides, &amp; also, Walker had <hi rend="italic">no room </hi>for much of Eccl. <hi rend="italic">dry wk. </hi>I have <hi rend="italic">since</hi> had good reasons for believing I displeased the “powers”, more perhaps by my 2 letters than by my <hi rend="italic">bold speaking</hi>: I have seen none of the clergy since—or of the Synod, <hi rend="italic">save Welsh </hi>who goes w. me—in <hi rend="italic">all </hi>I said, &amp; wrote. I was so exhausted as to walk, or <hi rend="italic">crawl</hi>, w. difficulty to trap outside by Dean’s gate—and was <hi rend="italic">laid up </hi>all next day—<hi rend="underline italic">very weak</hi>: &amp; did not go again to Synod. On those 3 days I went thither (15–17,) only <hi rend="italic">aftn.</hi> sitting, iv to vi whereas the <hi rend="italic">nt. </hi>sitting was the long &amp; “talkee-talkee” one. I may say, to you, I have had thanks from several <hi rend="italic">outsiders</hi>—members of Ch. of E.—both by letter, &amp; by word when in town.</p>
         <p>Welsh, poor dear fellow! is <hi rend="italic">very unwell </hi>w. diffy. he performed S. on Sunday 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. Nov. (he could <hi rend="italic">not </hi>attend <hi rend="underline italic">Evg.</hi> Synod) &amp; last week went to Wairoa by steamer, hoping (against hope) that a sea trip &amp; fortnight’s <hi rend="italic">rest</hi> may prove serviceable: if <hi rend="italic">not</hi> he will resign at once, &amp; what then? he hasn’t a <hi rend="italic">son</hi>!—Gardiner, too, is <hi rend="italic">resting</hi> on leave, &amp; Eccles is shaky, and this <hi rend="italic">poor </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">old</hi> supernumerary is <hi rend="italic">now </hi>“a broken vessel”. Wood, High School, offd. St. Augustines <hi rend="italic">both </hi>mg. &amp; evg. on 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Nov. Robertshawe only came to S. on 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>—&amp; <hi rend="italic">left </hi>on 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>—called back by “<hi rend="italic">wire</hi>”,—a <hi rend="italic">similar </hi>case to that of Balfour &amp; Tuke, the baby died at 3 days! child of banker’s wife at Dvk., so I saw <hi rend="italic">little </hi>of him.—</p>
         <p>During Synod week I received 2 good letters from abroad, <hi rend="italic">one </hi>from Bp. St. in Persia—Dear old man! says— “just passed <hi rend="italic">his</hi> Birth day, “3 sc. &amp; 10,” &amp; <hi rend="italic">feeling old </hi>age (I wish, still, he had never <hi rend="italic">left us</hi>:): and <hi rend="italic">one </hi>from Sir J. Hooker, long &amp; full of love—as usual: curiously, Stafford formerly Premier N.Z. was spending a wk. w. H., when my letter arrd. in it I had reported ptg. of letter <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> Lex., and so Stafford &amp; H. had their talk over it, &amp; <hi rend="italic">me</hi>. St. gave me the <hi rend="italic">Govt. order</hi>, as Col. Secy. &amp; P.—&amp; always, while in off., supported. Letters also from my 2 sons, at Home, more <hi rend="italic">cheering</hi>: we <hi rend="italic">all </hi>have our trials &amp; troubles—may they <hi rend="italic">prove</hi> blessings in disguise (Heb. xi, 11). I <hi rend="italic">often</hi> repeat my <hi rend="underline italic">old</hi> favourite phrase— “<hi rend="italic">Thy loving correction </hi>shall make me great,” Ps.18. I went to town last week (by trap as usual) to call on Mrs Florance &amp; daughter Ethel at Criterion (Ethel, here examn. Scholarship); and also to visit Mrs. Welsh, who had written me a sad note, she, too, being unwell. I also called on Peter Dinwiddie, in his den! re ptg. my half-promised pamphlet letters <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Roman Errors, (I had been with him before): we had long &amp; strong talk, P. being a regular screw: I told him he knew <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> of printing—not having served his time at it! Heigho! P. bristled, asserting his “20 yrs. management”, &amp;c—Freeman, present, having been <hi rend="italic">called down</hi>—I told P., “<hi rend="italic">No </hi>chapel would <hi rend="italic">allow</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">his claim</hi>”. F. had a good laugh, &amp; it ended—for the time: a memo. from P. (all <hi rend="italic">now</hi> done by <hi rend="italic">typewriter</hi>!)— “8/6 <hi rend="italic">page </hi>for 500, 10/6 1000 copies” have again communicated w. him—after going thoroughly into calculations myself, &amp; offg. “7/6 page for 600 copies” to contain about 45 p., 3 proofs, no <hi rend="italic">blank </hi>pp. save “4” (<hi rend="italic">insisted on</hi>! by P.) being <hi rend="italic">3 with printed </hi>cover, &amp; to be <hi rend="italic">stitched</hi>—no abom. rusty wire! a <hi rend="italic">cash </hi>job: I wish to sell at <hi rend="italic">1/- each</hi>—a dead loss (financially) <hi rend="italic">certain</hi>—adding, in my memo.—If declined I should <hi rend="italic">not </hi>seek to get pubd. <hi rend="italic">here</hi> (as Ed. of H. had kindly pubd. those letters), but <hi rend="italic">likely </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">may</hi> down S., where printing was more reasonable. Last nt. reply came—accepting my offer—but to put off job till beg. of new year, being extra busy w. Almanac &amp; other Xmas. matters. And so I have to buckle on armour afresh. Of course, my letters will be pubd. <hi rend="italic">as printed</hi> in Hd., <hi rend="italic">sans </hi>errors, your “50 yrs in N.Z.” being the <hi rend="italic">pattern</hi>—produced by me in our squabble: I shall give an <hi rend="italic">appendix</hi>: I suppose <hi rend="italic">my </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">last</hi> p. &amp; thank <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> in a <hi rend="italic">good cause. </hi>(I would <hi rend="italic">you </hi>were <hi rend="italic">nearer</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">at leisure</hi>.) Crerar will sell, &amp; <hi rend="italic">will help</hi>. This will finally keep me <hi rend="italic">here</hi> till <hi rend="italic">finished</hi>—<hi rend="italic">Autumn</hi>.</p>
         <p>I thank you for sending me Papers: you already know my thoughts &amp; opinions <hi rend="italic">re </hi>those old often-hashed-up views &amp; notions respg. Maori beginnings—now (afresh I suppose) to be again vamped by Smith &amp; Buller! I have the lowest opinion of Smith—better of Tregear! Buller has again been sending me tracts <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Horowhenua: a visitor (<hi rend="italic">friend </hi>of B.) told me he had <hi rend="italic">lately </hi>seen the <hi rend="italic">Govt. </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">new</hi> p. on H., laid on table at Athenæum, &amp; he <hi rend="italic">feared </hi>(<hi rend="underline italic">now</hi>) for B.—Could you get me a copy of this Govt. paper? and also <hi rend="italic">buy me 3 copies of T.C.W’s. pamphlet—</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">I will remit outlay</hi>.—</p>
         <p>2–3 things I have <hi rend="italic">omitted</hi>: In Synod on 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. Motion—I had dared to say the B. was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> in its entirety the w. of G.—that <hi rend="italic">our Ch. </hi>in formularies had <hi rend="italic">never </hi>said so, &amp; brought forth proofs (as I thought): <hi rend="italic">some </hi>got up &amp; accd. me of saying—Wd. of G. <hi rend="italic">not </hi>in B.! (the old, old, story!) I was obliged—in <hi rend="underline italic">reply</hi>—to set <hi rend="italic">them</hi> right—to profess <hi rend="italic">my faith</hi> standing on verge of eternity, &amp; warning <hi rend="italic">yg. clerics</hi>—that I <hi rend="italic">knew more </hi>than they did: so beware! (Hill was vastly pleased, so he told me.) Again—on recollection, <hi rend="italic">next day</hi>, <hi rend="underline italic">all that took place on 17</hi>
            <hi rend="sup underline italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic"> my Birthday</hi>!!! Another item: H.W. “reporter”, said, “Vote of thanks to me for £500. gift to Ch.” this has brought me <hi rend="italic">many applications</hi> for money, town &amp; Cy.—so that I have been <hi rend="italic">obliged </hi>to inform some—fully—<hi rend="italic">that</hi> was given in <hi rend="italic">Jany</hi>. last; had it not been <hi rend="italic">then </hi>given it would not—<hi rend="italic">could not</hi>—be, as I <hi rend="italic">needed it</hi>. I gave also some <hi rend="italic">reminiscences</hi> of the long past in my L. &amp; expce. wh. might <hi rend="italic">interest you</hi>—but I cannot write any more at this time. You will read my <hi rend="italic">last L.</hi> (with this) re Cook; it is a good thing I am <hi rend="italic">thus </hi>employed, &amp; in wtg. Home—such a <hi rend="italic">pile </hi>of letters!<lb/>—my principal grief is—not being able to go to Ch.,—only that <hi rend="italic">once </hi>one day at Cathedl. since March. The trap hire (<hi rend="italic">Sundays</hi>) is 7/6 to &amp; fro (on <hi rend="italic">that</hi> occasion, 15/-) &amp; I cannot stand it—besides trouble &amp; pains—to get into &amp; out from trap &amp; hobbling in Ch., &amp; <hi rend="italic">cannot, </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">yet</hi>, well kneel. My dear friend, that <hi rend="italic">shock </hi>physl. &amp; mental, was a terrible one: my fingernails all curiously marked (as if stayed growing for a short time) but now <hi rend="italic">nearly </hi>grown out. Memory still curiously affected,—e.g. Wel<hi rend="underline">c</hi>h <hi rend="italic">or </hi>Wel<hi rend="underline">s</hi>h: <hi rend="underline">P.C.</hi> Winkelmann, <hi rend="italic">or </hi>
            <hi rend="underline">C.P.</hi>W., Hubert <hi rend="italic">or </hi>Hector Burnett, sometimes cannot remember “Boulcott” &amp; then, non-pluss’d—<hi rend="underline">Road</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">, or</hi> Street, and so w. similar <hi rend="italic">old</hi> addresses at Home, &amp; scores of other cases: but, am “Daily improving” I think, in this <hi rend="italic">respect </hi>also. Have not yet passed the wicket-gate! I don’t walk <hi rend="italic">enough </hi>outside door—for I don’t like it. <hi rend="italic">Hand </hi>is getting better, &amp; so arm, <hi rend="italic">elbow</hi>, can hold knife to cut meat, now, w. <hi rend="underline italic">care</hi>: but a <hi rend="italic">fresh </hi>symptom—feet &amp; legs, ancles, <hi rend="italic">swelling</hi>, so that I cannot get on my boots, &amp; go to town in slippers: but <hi rend="italic">no pain</hi>—puffed up &amp; watery: I do not like <hi rend="italic">this </hi>symptom. Shall not, <hi rend="italic">yet</hi>, call in Doctor: Mrs Anderson is <hi rend="italic">against </hi>my conviction! of course. Now you will have enough <hi rend="italic">re </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">self</hi>. Began at ix—left off at xi (<hi rend="italic">I always read 2 Lessons &amp; Psalms </hi>&amp;c. <hi rend="underline italic">w. Ch. over the globe</hi>, part of <hi rend="italic">my belief</hi> in “Commn. of Saints”, as I have freqly. sd. in Sermons) recommenced at xii, &amp; now just struck i, (1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Less. this morng. Isaiah V: a fine one: I could have preached a Sermon right away.)—(so to dinner.)</p>
         <p>Among many other disagreeables—<hi rend="italic">worries</hi>, have lost a mg. last week with 2 Government valuators—Wundrum and a <hi rend="italic">yg. </hi>red-haired cheeky fellow who had <hi rend="italic">too much </hi>to say: had valued my propy. <hi rend="italic">here </hi>&amp; wished for my agreeing! this, however, could <hi rend="italic">not </hi>be, from the <hi rend="italic">fact</hi>, their valuation (<hi rend="italic">i.e. </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">said</hi> to be theirs) is exactly the same for “<hi rend="italic">Unimproved</hi>” land, as it is, &amp; has been, for “<hi rend="italic">Improved</hi>, or, including <hi rend="italic">all </hi>Improvements! on the ground that Land has advanced in Napier. (How I wish I had <hi rend="italic">done </hi>w. <hi rend="italic">this</hi>! &amp; <hi rend="italic">such like</hi>!!)</p>
         <p>I see, Pautawhero is dead! I regret him: I had <hi rend="italic">heard </hi>of him before. I wholly agree with the <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, re the Maori <hi rend="italic">Land</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Court</hi>, the <hi rend="underline italic">greatest</hi> piece of injustice the Maoris have ever known, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">by it</hi> they are nearly (&amp; soon will wholly be) ruined. Those wretched pă-Maoris, Agents! and Lawyers, are battening on spoil, &amp; encouraging them—to go at it again, when they know it is <hi rend="italic">not </hi>of use! I should like to see some of them <hi rend="italic">punished </hi>severely, &amp; would assist to do so. A <hi rend="italic">flagrant </hi>case lately to my notice—<hi rend="underline italic">clear too</hi>! very <hi rend="italic">sad</hi>, but too long to write: the <hi rend="italic">Government</hi> should <hi rend="italic">act</hi>, in time.—</p>
         <p>I hope you are now about being <hi rend="italic">settled</hi>—(1) In your new office: (2) In your <hi rend="italic">old </hi>matters, so as to have your mind clear of <hi rend="italic">that weight</hi>. I trust, too, you are in good health, also, wife &amp; family. I return clippings, as wished: have you <hi rend="italic">seen </hi>“Waikare-moana” <hi rend="italic">book</hi> pubd. by Govt.? who is the editor?— “Elsdon Best.”<hi rend="italic"> </hi>who (so-called) translator of M.? Weather <hi rend="italic">here </hi>very dry: <hi rend="italic">hills burnt </hi>up, Rain <hi rend="italic">needed</hi>, only 1 day rain in all Novr., according to Lyndsy, &amp; none since, no signs. Frost <hi rend="italic">last wk. </hi>cut down potatoes &amp;c at Hastings, &amp; inland.—</p>
         <p>I heard from Hill, that Robertshawe <hi rend="italic">got </hi>it <hi rend="italic">hot</hi>—from Canon St. Hill, Archdn. Sam. &amp; also from Bp. himself! R. had a motion—in fut. Bp. <hi rend="italic">not </hi>to summon to Synod, so as Cl. to be <hi rend="italic">absent Sunday</hi>. (Robertshawe, would <hi rend="italic">not</hi> come, as summoned: in <hi rend="italic">his case</hi> almost <hi rend="italic">worse</hi> than in any other, as he alone has a fair <hi rend="italic">Licensed </hi>Lay-Reader.) I, &amp; others perhaps, go w. R., but <hi rend="italic">motion</hi>! altogether out of place: at <hi rend="italic">first</hi>, I thought, the snubbing R. got—drove him back early.—–</p>
         <p>Hill has been writing <hi rend="italic">heavily several</hi> letters <hi rend="italic">re </hi>“Old man;s pension”, <hi rend="italic">for it </hi>wholly: opposing Walker and Adams, who seem by far to have the best of it, to say nothing of <hi rend="italic">McDougal</hi>. McD is a curious fellow—aiming, one would think, at being a second “Admirable Crichton”! such displays of learned &amp; foreign languages. <hi rend="italic">Kindest </hi>regards &amp; best wishes—</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso</p>
         <p>(arm &amp; hand tired) ii.30, p.m.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
