<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0303">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1875 December 12: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1875-12-12">1875 December 12</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1875 December 12: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-237" place="foot" n="237"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N.Z.<lb/>Decr 12 1875.</p>
         <p>My dear Sir</p>
         <p>Your kind, full &amp; most welcome letter of October 30<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> came to hand on the 8<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst. Right glad was I to find that at the time of your writing you were <hi rend="italic">all </hi>well, for you &amp; yours are <hi rend="italic">often</hi> in my thoughts,—whether I am at home or abroad.—My last to you was on Novr. 16<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>, since which much have taken place, of wh. I must endeavour to give you an outline.—To begin with the first, (in times, I mean)—the very day after (17<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. Novr.) I got out <hi rend="italic">my</hi> address to the Electors for the <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Napier seat in our Parliament, and, two days ago brought out <hi rend="italic">Maney</hi>! we are now 6 or 7 entered in the race, 2 of whom only can win, so a rare a lot of us <hi rend="italic">will </hi>come to grief!—of whom I may be one. Sir D.— <hi rend="italic">should</hi> be sure of one seat. (I hope he may get in without difficulty, but there is much against him, secretly). Then there are, Stuart (Mayor), Capt. W. Russell, Tuke, Maney, myself, &amp; J. Rhodes is <hi rend="italic">publicly stated</hi> to be brought forward (I believe, by Lyndon)—and Fannin told me 2 days ago that Sutton is also to be trotted out! It hung on for a long while, as to Sutton,—who was only waiting the decision of the Judges on the Mangateretere case; if that should be in his favour then he wd. come out, &amp; Hitchings told me that he (H.) felt <hi rend="italic">sure that S. </hi>would be at the head of the poll!! The Judges, however, gave it <hi rend="italic">against </hi>Sutton—and so he is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> coming out. I hear that he <hi rend="italic">feels </hi>it, &amp; so does Nielson &amp; others. Mr Hutchison who lent S. £5100. on that security !) Lee, too, was long talked of. The writs arrived last week &amp; Sealy (confound it!) has fixed on the 20<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. for nom. day, &amp; 30<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> for poll day:—instead of allowing the holidays to pass,—which he could have done as he is allowed a max. of 30 days by stat. This daily interferes with me.</p>
         <p>I don’t however think that S. knew of this, or knowing of it, acted on it—rather as I view it to suit Sir D.—who is now at the Criterion. It is said, the chances are between Stuart &amp; W. Russell. Maney’s coming out will take away <hi rend="italic">Catholic </hi>vs.,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>and several country ones from R.,—If Newton &amp; J. Rhodes come out, such will weaken Stuart and of course myself of whom I say nothing.) Tuke (the old goose!) has <hi rend="italic">no shame</hi>! But he is come out to vex the Govt.—he tried <hi rend="italic">hard </hi>for a billet &amp; so he will work this way as against G.R. who is the Govt. man. Stuart &amp; his Commee. <hi rend="italic">are working</hi>, so you know how the canny Scotch can &amp; <hi rend="italic">do</hi> work secretly. Alexr. S. <hi rend="underline italic">is</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>whisking about! He is a Good Templ. now, &amp; an officer too &amp;<hi rend="italic"> us</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">ing </hi>it, and Stuart has recently been re-installed Mayor, on the <hi rend="italic">nomn. </hi>of 2 or 3 of his <hi rend="italic">Council</hi>! no other having been proposed. Of course, I <hi rend="italic">not</hi> being a F. Mason, or a G. Templ., or Forester, or Oddfellow, or Methodist, or R. Cathc., or Teetotaller, or Orangemen, or H.B. Clubbite, being too much of a <hi rend="italic">Catholic </hi>in the real &amp; true sense of the word) to belong to any sect or party, have but a so-so chance; still, I do believe I would beat them if they would (or could) fight fairly.—I published a Maori advt. in the Maori Paper (Te Wananga), which took w. the Natives, and some of them wrote in reply, agreeing &amp;c., but I find their letters have not been published (the Natives told me this: I shall try to see them openly at Pakowhai shortly. Stuart &amp; Tuke have also addressed them in a Maori advt. Tuke hopes to gain them through his having said Heretaunga was worth ₤30. per acre. I have sent circulars <hi rend="italic">asking</hi> for a vote to <hi rend="italic">every</hi> voter on the Roll (including Stuart, Tuke, Sir D. &amp;c.) Two have returned by Post my Circ. one being Hooper the Barber (he puts his name inside) (I have employed the other Barber ever since the lawsuit) one being unknown to me. Although I <hi rend="italic">fancy</hi> the writing is that of Knowles. The Govt. wish (I <hi rend="italic">hear</hi>) to get in W.R. to aid them in the Heretaunga matter. </p>
         <p>A few good friends in town have (of their own accord) promised me their votes (as you know). I ask no one:—among them Turton &amp; Lascelles, Grubb &amp; Robjohns, 2 (N. &amp; Close’s), Higgins (2), several working men &amp; carters and a number in the Council. Still, you may (rightly enough) ask, Why bother myself about it? and I will endeavour to ansr. your Question. First, <hi rend="italic">I see</hi> I am daily getting less able for my present duty (schools): I can sit &amp; read &amp; write &amp; think (thank <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>, my faculties are clear,) but I cannot knock about the country &amp; sit on hard forms in draughty school rooms, (I have twice seen O. about resigning, but he will not hear of it &amp; begs me to hold on:)—but come it <hi rend="italic">must</hi>, &amp; that <hi rend="italic">soon</hi>. Second, the Govt. have, in their way, closed the Mao. Lexn. work. Third, my sons are in England, &amp; are willing to remain there; but I wish to know, (before I take the inevitable step) whether there is any work or duty I <hi rend="italic">may, can &amp; ought</hi> to do with L. before I should leave it (ever believing &amp; holding <hi rend="italic">that part </hi>of the Ch. of Engd. <hi rend="italic">Catechism</hi>— “to learn to do my duty in that state of life into which it shall please God to call me”—hence, too, it is that I can take &amp; <hi rend="italic">bear </hi>defeats perhaps better than many—especially when I have <hi rend="italic">sought</hi> direction—as I always do—in <hi rend="italic">all</hi> matters, &amp; abstained from every species of <hi rend="italic">bribery</hi> &amp; undue influence, so—. If again defeated—why then another indication England-wards: for I dreadfully <hi rend="italic">need</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">some</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">Society</hi>—now I have <hi rend="underline italic">none</hi>.—But I must stop this.</p>
         <p>Now for <hi rend="italic">sad </hi>news: poor Ernest Weber has been killed instantaneously while sitting at his writing! A muff of a fellow cadet, named Webber, in acquiring a gun wh. Mr. Weber had lent in the winter to Mr Miller, Railway Manager, &amp; wh. he had left <hi rend="italic">loaded </hi>in the room, fired it, &amp; the charge entered at base of E.W’s. skull, died immy. not even a cry! A card had been put up for the muff to aim at, up above, near the ceiling, &amp; it is believed, though the lad denies it, that he aimed at Ernest, thinking by the close report to frighten him: he says—the gun slipped!! There was an immense sensation about it. Poor W. feels it:—and so do I. I have thought, how could I have borne it—if it had been Willie: and then of <hi rend="italic">you</hi>—how you would have suffered if it had been one of your dear sons. Yesterday we had <hi rend="italic">two </hi>fires!—one at 1 a.m. near Carley’s house (&amp; everything up near Tylee’s &amp; Fannins): &amp; one Massey’s Wood &amp; Coal Depot just below nr. Cl. Sq. this at 4 p.m. Day remarkably fine, little wind &amp; that from N.W. or Wesleyn. Church would have <hi rend="italic">gone</hi>! Boylan’s <hi rend="italic">isolated</hi> store was in danger; but it was wholly saved. Massey (a hard working man) I am told by my man James feels it <hi rend="italic">bitterly</hi>. Renouf’s wife is dead; also Mrs Stewart, who lived in Poole Road; and <hi rend="italic">poor dear old </hi>Mrs Wilson. Lear is in a <hi rend="italic">sad </hi>way: nearly blind, only knows one by voice; has lost <hi rend="italic">every thing</hi>; not having A1. At present he sits all day in the verandah of the Royal when fine, in the sun: I only <hi rend="italic">first </hi>heard of it 3 or 4 days ago.—I fear he he took to drinking heavily, after his wife’s death; placed immoral unprincipled persons in charge—they receiving all the monies, &amp; trusting whom they pleased, &amp; it ended (as Mrs Ford told me) in L. giving up everything, Ho. &amp;c., Milton Road, to Swan, &amp; to Neal &amp; Co. who got <hi rend="italic">all</hi>!! I was led to give the poor creature money to buy <hi rend="italic">shirts</hi>. Aldridge, too, has come rapidly to grief, has given <hi rend="italic">up</hi> Butchering,—&amp; is out on the spree! Bishop, baker, is Bankrupt. Hack, of Brewster St, is selling off to go home in “H. Denny.” A man named W. Lyon hung himself at Puketapu—a hardworking sober young man —he had had a falling-out w. one of his companions. <hi rend="italic">Several</hi> have <hi rend="italic">suffered</hi> from Rheumatism—I have lots of <hi rend="italic">sympathizers</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">now</hi>! Houses are springing up—in your old street opp. your gate—2–3. Dinwiddie making a rookery! so over end of Wh. Road between the 3 Roads old &amp; new: &amp; on the hill near Lee’s old residence, W. of me: &amp; next to Dr. Spencer’s (on Rymer’s)—a shop for Martin, tailor: while the Herald office is enclosing the whole of J. Wood’s little garden, the Gums having been chopped down.</p>
         <p>Miss Carter is married to L. Margoliouth: and a short shopman at Boylan’s, married. Rev G. Morice, now stationed at Xt.Ch. has got a little one. Rev D. Sidey is now <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, at their Assembly. I have not spoken to Mr S. for 3–4 months!! I have been but little in town: I should go oftener there but I have no place I can <hi rend="italic">sit down</hi> in: Dr H. thought of my engaging a spare room for that purpose at the Masonic, and I agreed to it,—but have since given it up.) I have sold a sm. bit of Land, 33 ft. frontage, next to the corner of Sale Street, to a man named Goddard for £100. <hi rend="italic">at end </hi>of 9 yrs. or <hi rend="italic">all </hi>to be left for me, he paying £10. pr. ann.; he has already put up a house on it. Have let the 2 Paddocks (wh. Seed had) to Johnson, baker, the <hi rend="italic">inner </hi>one, &amp; to Scorgie butcher, the outer one, at £20. pr. ann. <hi rend="italic">each</hi>. Hague also paying £5. addl. Scally, had not yet put up the fence wh. he undermined, &amp; <hi rend="italic">refused</hi>, at last, to do it: so, he is in Lascelles’ hands.—Capt. Birch of “Chili” died at sea. The “Inverness” had a good passage, &amp; brought a goodly lot of Immigrants <hi rend="italic">all well</hi>: &amp; they <hi rend="italic">soon</hi> got berths. W. Morrice has been here again about the black mare. I told him of her hurt, which, no doubt, unfits her for <hi rend="italic">hard </hi>riding &amp; <hi rend="italic">long </hi>journies: He offered ₤7. &amp; then ₤9. for her. I have since written to him offering her for ₤12.—would rather he should have her (for his Bror’s. sake) than another. She is rolling in fat, &amp; no wonder,—I never saw the fields (&amp; Cl. Sq. too) so <hi rend="underline italic">green</hi> before in <hi rend="italic">Decr.</hi>—<hi rend="italic">green everywhere </hi>owing to our showery Summer.—Gary has an excellent flow of water from the new artn. well near the old one of Watts’,— it looks <hi rend="italic">well </hi>from the hill, <hi rend="italic">spouting</hi> away;—great waste of precious water, though.—Robjohns Brewery is advancing— looking somewhat strange there, below. The Gas-meter &amp; all its many buildings are looking well. The Australian parrots build &amp; breed here in Napier,—they are here, 5–8 in a flock, &amp; have <hi rend="italic">stolen</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">all </hi>my early cherries; they are <hi rend="italic">beautiful</hi> birds, but, I do think I must shoot them. The big <hi rend="italic">black</hi> slugs, which are by 100d’s, have also devoured all my <hi rend="italic">strawberries.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>And now a word of myself,—<hi rend="italic">health</hi>. I was getting round slowly but steadily, &amp;, 3 wks. ago, I made my first easy move out to Taradale in trap, taking my man w. me, for I was still weak; since then I have managed to visit Meeanee, Taradale, Puketapu, Hastings, Havelock &amp; Reignier’s, schools, and was holding out well, indeed getting stronger, but on Thursday (9<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>) I went to Rearden’s (the wind was desperately high, N.Wy., making several willows come down,) &amp; though I kept my hat on, the building being very draughty<hi rend="italic">,</hi> I caught a <hi rend="italic">severe</hi> cold which has again confined me, &amp; brought on a return of that nasty Bronchitis Cough so that I <hi rend="italic">could not </hi>go to Campbell’s school, on the <hi rend="italic">next </hi>day, as had been arranged.—I am to try to do so tomorrow; &amp; then the day after inland, all this week, retg. on Saturday for Nomn. on the Monday: I have very grave doubts, at times, as to how this <hi rend="underline italic">Bronchitis</hi> will end—thinking it may result in something like A. Kennedy’s, or Wm. Marshall’s,—(W.M. is now very ill w. it.)</p>
         <p>Dr H. told me, a fortnight ago when settling w. him that though he had known me 20 yrs. he never knew me so bad before—this I had known from my <hi rend="italic">own </hi>feelings, as well as from his coming up the glen so <hi rend="italic">frequently</hi>. But, <hi rend="italic">if returned</hi>, I may be able to do <hi rend="italic">that </hi>work, &amp; shall, if it be <hi rend="smallcaps">God’s</hi> will.—</p>
         <p>Tell your sons, that I gave out a tolerably hard <hi rend="italic">compound </hi>fellowship Sum to be done by the schools, as a special prize Sum,—and from Mr Campbell’s school I have 9 returns—<hi rend="italic">in extenso</hi>—the best one, as to execution, &amp;c (<hi rend="italic">all</hi> being correct) is <hi rend="italic">James Brandon’s</hi>:—then comes Miller, Polack, Bowden, H.C. Robjohns, G.F.Williams, W. Walker, G. Walker, &amp; Claudius Cato,—and I have lots from the other Schools, particularly the Country ones, <hi rend="italic">whence </hi>2 from <hi rend="underline italic">Girls</hi>. I will enclose a copy of the Sum for the Boys’ sake. I have also lots of essays sent in,—not yet examined. Over 300 <hi rend="italic">good </hi>prizes have I sent out just now. Never was such a time here with the Scholars, they are overjoyed &amp; rejoicing—and the Masters are drawn out into the vortex! The Scholars <hi rend="italic">leave </hi>their play &amp; <hi rend="italic">hie at 5</hi> to <hi rend="italic">work</hi> at Sums &amp; “Essays””—if the boys were but Voters,—<hi rend="underline italic">then</hi>!!!—</p>
         <p>I think it is time for me to stop! Still I have more to say. Fannin has purchased T.P. Russell’s at Puketapu, &amp;c, so making that property <hi rend="italic">one</hi>.—The “feed” is glorious this year! the Cows, &amp;c., are up to their knees everywhere in grass &amp; Clover! Archdn. Williams is getting a residence (at last!) built for <hi rend="italic">him</hi>, at Povy. Bay: he <hi rend="italic">ought</hi> never to have left it. Tuke asked <hi rend="italic">old </hi>W. Morris, the whaler, to give him his vote; he replied, If he had ₤500. he wod give them all to me, &amp; turned to, &amp; wrote me the story. At Meeanee Tuke asked a gardener there (named Gillice, a Tasmanian) for his vote: “What for?” said G.— “To go to the Ho. of Assy.” said Tuke. “That,” replied G. “is <hi rend="italic">your </hi>house of Asy., there at Peddie’s.” G. (a <hi rend="italic">perfect </hi>stranger) came afterwards to town, &amp; proffered me his v. Arihi has issued a warning advertist. relative to Locke’s <hi rend="italic">late</hi> purchases at Wairoa, saying <hi rend="italic">she </hi>will <hi rend="italic">not </hi>agree to it. (And she has a very great claim, I know, as her <hi rend="italic">Mother</hi>, a great lady, came thence,)</p>
         <p>I called on Sir D. 3 days ago—he was busy, very civil &amp; <hi rend="italic">more </hi>to me; he began talking about the Lexicon, &amp; how that <hi rend="italic">that</hi> was now <hi rend="italic">settled </hi>(?) I said, I did not come to talk about <hi rend="italic">that</hi>, &amp; would see him again.—He wears specs. now for writing. Sheehan has but just retd. to Town; he came overland, &amp; spent some time at Mt. Herbert. Burton &amp; wife are again enqg. after the 2 sections at Hampden for their <hi rend="italic">son</hi>—who “has saved a little money”: I have not yet replied; have had no time.</p>
         <p>And now, what shall I say? I shall look out anxiously to hear how you pass the Eng. winter; <hi rend="underline italic">don’t hide anything from me</hi>, for, if I am <hi rend="italic">again</hi> beaten, (which I <hi rend="italic">may </hi>be; &amp;, if so,—as I have written to Willie—I shall <hi rend="italic">not quite </hi>cry my eyes out,)—then I may, next year, be preparing to <hi rend="underline italic">follow you</hi> and W. And if I am <hi rend="italic">returned,</hi> I shall trouble you in my next w. a Commission or two. Drower has <hi rend="italic">not</hi> yet paid for the saddlery; <hi rend="underline italic">has paid</hi> another wee portion.</p>
         <p>And now I must say Good bye.</p>
         <p>May every blessing my dear Sir be yours and your dear family’s.—C. Dolbel should be now near N.Z. His brother P. desires to be kindly remembered. Grubb is well but busy, not yet in <hi rend="italic">new </hi>P. POffice.</p>
         <p>With every good wish for your welfare, Believe me</p>
         <p>ever yours sincerely</p>
         <p>Wm. Colenso</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>