<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0971">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1896 August 25: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1896-08-25">1896 August 25</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1896 August 25: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-791" place="foot" n="791"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke<lb/>August 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1896</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>I don’t know (<hi rend="underline italic">here</hi>) <hi rend="italic">when </hi>I last wrote to you, and I also believe that you have since written to me—but <hi rend="italic">now </hi>that I have a spare hour, I must no longer delay writing.</p>
         <p>I came hither yesty. from Waipukurau. I got here on Saty. (22) for Sunday Ch. duty. Mr. Tuke being absent—on his Ch. rounds. I heard, that yr. Cousin Rechab was <hi rend="italic">very ill</hi> (“no hope of recovery”—but qu.)—I purpose, on my retg., to go to Mt. Vernon to see him. Mr. Grant was <hi rend="italic">well</hi>: spent ¾ hour w. him in his little cosy study: Mrs Trestrail was, as <hi rend="italic">usual</hi>, cheerful: staying at Mrs. Smith’s house <hi rend="underline italic">to help Mrs. S</hi>., who had been <hi rend="italic">very unwell</hi>: Mrs. Trestrail’s <hi rend="italic">brother</hi> died at Napier, a short time ago, &amp; she is pleased at his going Home before her: dear soul! <hi rend="italic">God bless her</hi>.</p>
         <p>I am come on to this place—&amp; hence to Woodville on Friday next (a flying vt.) and suppose I shall be absent from N. say, a fortnight: retg. for Instit. meeting, &amp; Synod on 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. prox. <hi rend="italic">Our Inst. </hi>meetings are sadly falling off! Hill <hi rend="italic">promised </hi>papers for both July &amp; Augt. meetings (wh. were also postponed a week for <hi rend="underline italic">him</hi>!) &amp; <hi rend="italic">failed—both</hi>. Our last meeting—that interminable inveterate fellow, Taylor Wh.! out <hi rend="italic">again</hi>, in a dreadfully <hi rend="italic">long </hi>paper—<hi rend="italic">wholly extract verbatim</hi>, of J. Rutherford—from Liby. Enty. K.—altho’ Archdn. Wms. had <hi rend="italic">exposed </hi>it in ’90 vol.XXIII, “Trans.”, wh. of course, <hi rend="italic">White has</hi>. And <hi rend="italic">I </hi>had done <hi rend="italic">more</hi>—having been there on E. Coast, <hi rend="italic">several </hi>times (1838–1843), &amp; made every enqy., &amp; the Miss. were fully acqd. w. coming out at all—at such a dist. in time. However, I <hi rend="italic">did not spare</hi> White: only <hi rend="italic">wished</hi> he were present, <hi rend="italic">but </hi>as I told them— “10 to 1, White’s <hi rend="italic">bosh</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>will again be pubd. in Trans; while my papers, rejected”—so <hi rend="italic">I write no more</hi>.</p>
         <p>I should tell you the cause of my not writing to you—my long &amp; heavy job of putting up dried plants for Kew—overhauling my numerous (scores!) of lots from old times, referring to books, naming <hi rend="italic">pubd. </hi>ones, all done in parlour as workshop, having to clear <hi rend="italic">table </hi>every noon for dinner (to <hi rend="italic">please </hi>housekeeper), getting tired at iii. p.m. short days, often dark among trees, &amp;c &amp;c—I only finished my job last week, &amp; nailed down big case, &amp; wrote to Ellison &amp; D. to ship same: contg. also, mats, dress &amp; floor, ketes—&amp; other Mao. manufactures for Museum, Kew—my <hi rend="underline italic">last</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> donation</hi>!<note xml:id="ftn3-792" place="foot" n="792"> Listed in a letter to Thiselton-Dyer dated 19 August 1896. The kete is now in the British Museum collection.</note> During that job, I had reqd. visitors (friends if I have any in N.), &amp; acqs. <hi rend="underline italic">not</hi> to call, so have been very much <hi rend="underline italic">alone</hi>: w. lots of letters <hi rend="underline">un</hi>ansd. During same period, (and at last!!) proofs sent of first 8 pp., &amp; slips, of A Lexicon—by Costall—continued by Burn—then by Mackay—and dropped! for Parlt. not at all pleased w. proofs: comps. seem to have altered plan &amp; punct. , to please <hi rend="underline italic">themselves</hi>. I doubt if it will ever be pubd. &amp; I don’t greatly (if at all) care about it—<hi rend="underline italic">now</hi>.</p>
         <p>I have received from you copies of your letters in Wgn. p., and I thank you for them, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">go</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">w. you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">in them</hi>: 2–3 yrs. ago, in reply to Hutton, I went full tilt against the metrl. system, H. wishing <hi rend="italic">support </hi>to make it general at least, in <hi rend="italic">Inst. </hi>papers, which he <hi rend="italic">pursues</hi>: and I (<hi rend="underline italic">we</hi>) thank you for your letter <hi rend="italic">re </hi>J. Hosking’s <hi rend="italic">fad</hi>: Rev. Mr. Paterson, &amp; the Dean praises your p., &amp; rightly: Mr. P. told me, he had ceased subsg. to “<hi rend="italic">Prohibitionist</hi>”, owing to high intemp. language. I noticed in Evg. p. yesty.—I brought on w. me—that the Chief Govt. Analyst, London, had reported to Commissr. Somerset House, the <hi rend="italic">alcohol in Teetotal drinks</hi>—as Hp, &amp; herb, beer (<hi rend="italic">more </hi>than in pub. house Beer!) in sweet drinks: <hi rend="italic">vinifs. </hi>sherry &amp;c &amp;c—and <hi rend="italic">so</hi>—look-out, taxes, &amp;c, &amp;c. In your last p. sent, I was sorry to find a slip, reportg. <hi rend="italic">your own illness</hi>! I trust that is wholly gone by. I have been keeping pretty well—more or less daily Rheumatism, but in the early winter I had a <hi rend="italic">very severe </hi>attack of <hi rend="italic">diarrhoea</hi>, &amp;c—(<hi rend="italic">obliged</hi>, at last, to call in Dr. Spencer, as against possible results) that left me <hi rend="italic">very weak</hi>, for some time. (<hi rend="underline italic">2 p.m.</hi>) I see, in this day’s “Herald” death of Mrs Heath: soon after her husband. Doney (also) Hastings—I suppose you knew him, &amp; last week, Putnam, for many years Master Waipu. Hospital. I fear it’s a long time since my last: I have had <hi rend="italic">many things </hi>in<hi rend="italic">mind</hi>, to write to you about: “Herald” has had first <hi rend="italic">2 parts </hi>of a long story <hi rend="italic">re </hi>“<hi rend="underline italic">Tregear</hi>”, pubd. in wkly. suppt., I set them aside for you, expg. remr.—not yet pubd. but there are 2 audacious ones of late—one, on, (or <hi rend="italic">the</hi>) true meaning of the word, <hi rend="italic">pakeha</hi>! and one (yesty.) from <hi rend="italic">that</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Baker</hi> family <hi rend="underline italic">again</hi>! (I should like to know more of it: I wonder what <hi rend="italic">Archdn. Sam</hi>. says— “Baker” (only a Catechist)” in <hi rend="italic">charge </hi>of the Mission Station at Paihia—and the one person arranging ’tween <hi rend="italic">me </hi>and Capt. Hobson—Governor!—What lots of errors for the future! Our friend Hamilton (who should have known better) has done his best <hi rend="italic">that way</hi>, in bringing together <hi rend="underline italic">everything</hi>! chaff &amp; dust—lies &amp; truths—in his so-called “Bibliography of Maoris”, &amp;c—<hi rend="italic">He </hi>has bored me of late with <hi rend="italic">long</hi> letters full of enquiry re old Mao. matters &amp; things, &amp; needing <hi rend="italic">immediate </hi>replies: I did my best, &amp; hope he has <hi rend="italic">done</hi>.</p>
         <p>I think I must have told you, how I had written to Hector, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>publg. my Presl. address in next yr. vol.—well, no <hi rend="italic">reply</hi>: (that makes my <hi rend="italic">3</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">rd</hi>. L. to him, unnoticed, and so I say <hi rend="italic">Heoi ano</hi>!) But last mo. I recd. from Gore, a copy of <hi rend="italic">Wgn. Phil. Proceedings </hi>contg. Kirk’s long compilation,—i.e. his “<hi rend="italic">Address</hi>”, pubd. (as I thought) separately but <hi rend="italic">now </hi>I find part of vol. XXVII!. I have offy. infd. Dinwiddie I withhold mine: it shall not go to Wgn. to be criticised, &amp; called (purloined), &amp; returned: as some of my <hi rend="italic">former</hi> papers have been both there, and at Dunedin: and I have also request D. to apply for my paper on “the Tin Mines of Cornwall”, (<hi rend="underline italic">not</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">merely</hi> “<hi rend="italic">Reminiscences</hi>” as stated in the bald notices of <hi rend="italic">our </hi>Meetings).—I have been thinking of publishing it, and, if so, should like for <hi rend="italic">you</hi> to do so, that is, should you not be too busy.—May I ask,—Could you <hi rend="underline italic">easily</hi> get the said Ms. from Sir James, or from Gore, on my giving you a note to get it?—</p>
         <p>A curious coincidence happened last week: I had been engaged in clearing the wreck! <hi rend="italic">such a lot</hi>!! papers, bundles, plants, books, mss., &amp;c, &amp;c, from parlour, &amp; my eye lit on an <hi rend="italic">old</hi> “Order p.”, <hi rend="italic">1862</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">that very same day date</hi>, 20<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> Augt., &amp; on looking into it, I found notice of an important Motion of mine (and just as much needed <hi rend="italic">now</hi>!)—<hi rend="italic">all </hi>my compeers (save Stafford) therein mentioned are dead! (I have <hi rend="italic">no </hi>recollection of that matter.) I send it, as a fossil, for <hi rend="italic">you </hi>to see, think over, and, please, <hi rend="italic">return, early. </hi>See <hi rend="italic">P.S.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Of course you saw the letter from Bp. Stuart, in Papers, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>their imprisonment. I have not heard anything since, but as Mrs Clarke’s residence is wholly out of my track (&amp; time has been so precious with me) I have not called on her as I ought to have done. I have had but <hi rend="italic">very few </hi>visitors all the winter: save <hi rend="italic">poor</hi>, very poor, folks, sadly in want; even 5 a day, sometimes, rarely a day without any: I have sought help <hi rend="italic">in vain </hi>from Mayor, &amp;c.<note xml:id="ftn3-793" place="foot" n="793"> A plea for the starving. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> 10 August 1896. </note>
         </p>
         <p>During winter I have held Services in Cathedral, &amp; at St. Augustine’s—Dean being absent: I see, he is to lecture on Eng. Cathedrals, tonight at Taradale, &amp; tomorrow at St. Augustine’s. I believe Bp. Wms. is keeping well: I am told so. Breakwater is in <hi rend="italic">sad state</hi>, as the Papers will have informed you—a veritable “<hi rend="italic">White Elephant</hi>”;—that, and the <hi rend="italic">low-lying rivers</hi>, and Petane Beach—are 3 perennial troubles!</p>
         <p>Again: hope this may find you &amp; yours all right well. Kind regards and best wishes. Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely, W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. <hi rend="italic">Re </hi>“Order Paper”—I find I have <hi rend="italic">not </hi>brought it on. I send ch. 3 of paper on Tregear—wh. I have accidentally found in last Saty’s. “Supplt.”</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">No.2.</hi>)                                                                                 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. night</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Your kind letter reached me this evg., re-addressed from N., &amp; fortunately mine to you of this mg. was not yet posted—or (as before) our letters would have crossed in transit.—</p>
         <p>I was very glad to receive a letter from you, after so <hi rend="italic">long </hi>a silence (fault, if any, of my own). I am pleased to know you were a little better, &amp; hope your family may soon be “A.1.” again, and so <hi rend="italic">cheer </hi>the hearts of Mrs Harding &amp; yourself. Colds are very prevalent, especially <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, they say it is a species of Influenza. I thank you for your account, tho’ short, of your three meetings. I believe I sent you the “Herald” of 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. containing the <hi rend="italic">wretched </hi>mention of our last meeting, &amp; <hi rend="italic">that was written, </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">there</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">, by our Hon. Secy</hi>!! as he walked w. me to the Hd. office to do so, but the mention of it in “Dy.T.” was <hi rend="italic">worse still</hi>! so much for McD., &amp; H., &amp; their pretended friendship. Hon. Sy. took over 1 hour to read the account (I had the Book, my own, on table): Hill absolutely supported the <hi rend="italic">truthfulness</hi> of the story: H. had seen &amp; conversed w. <hi rend="italic">J.R’s. son, there, at Tokomaru</hi>, &amp; then I (last, of course) came out—or down like a Nasmyth hammer—producing also Archdn. Wm’s. <hi rend="italic">late</hi> paper: of course, Hill defended his position—but badly! No one present had ever read, or heard of, the Archdn’s. paper! I had nearly all the say!!of any consequence. However there was <hi rend="italic">one </hi>handsome thing there (and this too comprised <hi rend="italic">hundreds</hi>!) 8, 9, large drawers, w. glazed tops, containing <hi rend="underline italic">hundreds</hi> of our N.Z. Butterflies &amp; large moths, <hi rend="italic">all perfect &amp; beautifully set up</hi>, wings expanded, &amp;c &amp; their colours as fresh as ever! I never in all my life saw such a beautiful display of Lepidoptera! all the wk. of a <hi rend="underline italic">young</hi> shoemaker, Albert Norris, whose small shop is in Church Lane: he was present, (as, also, at all former meetings <hi rend="italic">this year</hi>) and is become a Member. I had heard of him—&amp; of these, before last autumn, and had often determined to ask him if he had caught them himself at Waikawa with nets? such a statement of love!! I heartily complimented him and so did we all. I felt <hi rend="underline italic">little</hi> by his side.</p>
         <p>Once more good bye &amp; thanks.</p>
         <p>Yours ever, W.Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. Norris’ Insects nearly all <hi rend="underline italic">named</hi>. I could not help thinking Hill &amp; wife examg. them, &amp; expressing delight on all. How <hi rend="italic">little</hi>, how <hi rend="underline italic">low</hi> Hill’s noisy socials were!!!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
