<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0314">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1876 February 23: to HBPI members</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MTGHB 18581.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="organisation" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73562/">HBPI members</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1876-02-23">1876 February 23</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1876 February 23: to HBPI members<note xml:id="ftn2-256" place="foot" n="256"> MTGHB 18581.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, February 23, 1876.</p>
         <p>Sir</p>
         <p>At a meeting of the Council of the H.B. Philosophical Institute, called by the President and held on the 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. instant,—the President, his Honor J.D. Ormond, Esq., in the Chair,—it was resolved; on a motion made by the Vice-President, the Right. Rev. the Bishop of Waiapu,—</p>
         <p>“The the Honorary Secretary draw up a Circular forthwith, and forward the same to the Members of the Institute,—to shew them our position with reference to our not receiving any copies of the volumes of ‘the Transactions of the Institute’ for 1874.”—</p>
         <p>In November, 1875,—on receiving a copy of the last volume of “the Transactions” for 1874, then just issued, (which I had got as an old member of the Wellington Branch of the N.Z. Institute,)—I wrote to the Manager, the Hon. Mr. Mantell, to ask, “When the Members of the H.B. (branch) Philosophical Institute were to expect their copies?” And his reply was, “That we were not entitled to any of the volumes for 1874, through our not having become affiliated in time.”</p>
         <p>I am really sorry for this most unexpected decision. But you will see, that it is no fault of mine (as your Secretary), and that I cannot help it. Our General Meeting to adopt Rules, &amp;c., took place on the 11<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. March, 1875; on the same day I wrote an official letter to the Governors of the New Zealand Institute at Wellington, requesting affiliation. On the 24<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. of the same month an answer was received, stating, that our application should be brought before the Board of Governors at their next meeting; and on the 15<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. April the official letter was also received, informing us of our incorporation;—which has also been subsequently announced, and our respective names given in full, in the last volume of the Transactions.</p>
         <p>It is true that this last volume (though issued late in 1875,) is really of work which mainly took place in 1874; hence, I suppose, our not getting any copies. It is an interesting and large book, containing over 600 pages and several plates; and I would that all our members had received a copy! Such a disappointment, however, cannot occur again.</p>
         <p>In conclusion, I may add, (to inform those members residing in the country,)—that notwithstanding the above drawback (which, after all, is only for the time, and merely affecting us individually,) much good has been done our Philosophical Institute generally:—which, it must not be forgotten, is a slip planted to bring forth good fruit for the <hi rend="italic">future</hi>. Several valuable specimens in Natural History have been obtained, and are in the hands of the members of the Council; ₤20. has been just granted to purchase Scientific Books for the new Library; ₤100. has been received as a donation from the Provincial Government, and carried (with other monies) to our Credit at the Bank; and Papers on various subjects have been promised and are in preparation by some of the members, to be read at our future meetings.</p>
         <p>     I have the honour to be,</p>
         <p>                             Sir,</p>
         <p>             Your mo. ob. servt.</p>
         <p>                     W. Colenso</p>
         <p>                             Hony. Secretary.</p>
         <p>P.S. I have further the honour to remind you, that (according to Rule 3 of our Constitution) “the Annual Subscription of ₤1.1.0. is payable in advance on the 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. day of January in every year”:—and, therefore, I will thank you to forward the same to me at your early convenience.</p>
         <p rend="end">W.C.              </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>