<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0344">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1877 September 21: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1877-09-21">1877 September 21</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1877 September 21: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-292" place="foot" n="292"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand,<lb/>Septr. 21/77.</p>
         <p>A. Luff, Esq.</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir,</p>
         <p>Yours of July 26, I recd. last week, &amp; was right glad to find you were all well. It seems but a very short time since I last wrote to you on 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. (&amp; 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) of August! time flies indeed, with <hi rend="italic">me</hi> now! I suppose it is mostly so, the older we grow; or is it (poetically speaking) that <hi rend="italic">his wings </hi>are grown longer &amp; he flies faster?—However, there are <hi rend="italic">lots </hi>of <hi rend="italic">news</hi> at this time, (&amp; here, during the past month,) such as it is; but I would rather <hi rend="italic">talk </hi>w. <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi> about it than write. I send you a rather larger lot of papers than usual, (nearly 30 I do believe), &amp; to them I must refer you for much which will interest you—and while on the subject of Papers, let me add, that I received but a <hi rend="italic">few </hi>from you in this last Mail (6 I believe), &amp; <hi rend="italic">not</hi> the “P. World” of which you wrote, saying such contained views of the <hi rend="italic">Wst</hi>.—I own I felt disappointed: I think I did wrong in some former letter to you in which I remarked on the quality of some of those you kindly sent; as, I fear, such a remark may have caused you to withhold: but your new <hi rend="italic">Weekly Times</hi>, &amp; Dy. Teleg., are always valuable: I don’t care so much for your <hi rend="italic">dearer</hi> (useless!) Papers—as “London,” &amp; “World,” &amp; “Live Stock Journal.” I had hoped to have recd. the full trial of Bradlaugh &amp; Mrs Besant; I find (by scrap!) that the lady made a <hi rend="italic">noble defence</hi>; she is a near relative of Lord Hatherley, the great Lawyer, &amp; should do so. I was disappointed in not getting a <hi rend="italic">full report of that trial</hi>.</p>
         <p>A few days ago we were startled &amp; grieved in hearing of the loss of the “Avalanche,” (news reached us within 36 hours!) several old Colonists with all their families gone! That was the Ship I had selected to go to Engd. in—if I went. And the Capt., I find, was Willie’s old Captn. (of Q. Bee &amp; Merope), so that had W. returned to him (as the Capt. both wished &amp; sought), in all probability he would have gone too! There are other curious matters, too,—<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the loss of <hi rend="italic">Capt. Wm’s. old ship</hi> (Q. Bee) here just 3–4 weeks before,—&amp; the loss of the other fine new ship “Ocean Mail” (which was to race w. the “Avalanche”)—just 3 days after leaving Wgn.—I think your <hi rend="italic">channel </hi>is about the <hi rend="italic">most dangerous</hi> piece of water a ship has to pass through. We have not yet got the <hi rend="italic">full</hi> account of our N.Z. folks lost in her, but it is sent for.</p>
         <p>There have been several deaths,—Plante (Draper), G.Sinclair (the old <hi rend="italic">thirsty</hi> painter!)—a yg. man called Graham (formerly a carpenter in Napier,) killed at Woodville in felling a tree, H.P. Smith’s <hi rend="italic">wife</hi>, of Aorangi, Johnson, Land Agent who was formerly in “Herald” shop; Mr T.G. Smith’s daughter, &amp; some others. (Plante’s death is a <hi rend="italic">sad </hi>story: his wife seduced by Britten left P., &amp; B. took her to Wgn. &amp;c. &amp;c.)—</p>
         <p>Fannin has been to Woodville, &amp; invested all his compensation money there. (foolish, I think). Holder is just back from Woodville, told me, today, that he has over 1100 ac. there! which he is getting cleared, &amp;c. A large portion of <hi rend="italic">my</hi> land is in the market (see advt. in <hi rend="italic">D.T. </hi>(<hi rend="italic">none in “Herald”</hi>!)—a few enquirers, but they want it for nothing—which they won’t get. (I am selfish enough to wish <hi rend="italic">you were here</hi>.) Mrs Tuke told me, she had been offered ₤400. for that bit of land near U.M. Chapel, but she won’t sell it for that!!—</p>
         <p>You may wonder at my <hi rend="italic">not </hi>advtg. in “Herald;” they refused to insert a letter I wrote (on “Chinese Immigration,” unless I left out the <hi rend="italic">Extract</hi>,—which, of course, I would not do: so, after 3 callings &amp; 3 talkings, I took back the Ms. I sent it to R.P., asking him if he would publish it, (telling him, it would <hi rend="italic">not </hi>break squares with us if he, <hi rend="italic">under all the circumstances</hi>, should refuse,) he however, did so directly &amp; freely;—so he, subsequently, <hi rend="italic">got my printing</hi>. Ever since, <hi rend="italic">Jas. </hi>Dinwiddie (a little <hi rend="italic">fussy </hi>pompous fellow) arrived, there had been a great difference—or growing coolness—between us; <hi rend="italic">James</hi>, too, is a great man (a Triton among the minnows!) at the Methodist School-room meetings, and as I had ventured to touch <hi rend="italic">them </hi>up a bit, the letter was <hi rend="italic">so </hi>dealt with.—</p>
         <p>We have had an <hi rend="italic">election</hi>! of 9 Councillors,—6 <hi rend="italic">old</hi> ones (<hi rend="italic">all who stood</hi>) &amp; 3 <hi rend="italic">new ones</hi> were returned: the 3 <hi rend="italic">new </hi>ones, J. Rochfort (<hi rend="italic">head</hi> of poll), Faulknor, &amp; <hi rend="italic">John</hi> Dinwiddie who came in <hi rend="italic">lowest</hi> of all, &amp; scarcely at all. But see the papers: I think you will laugh when you read <hi rend="italic">some </hi>of the <hi rend="italic">names</hi> of those who came forward.</p>
         <p>A <hi rend="italic">Working-Men’s Club </hi>is now the talk, &amp; will (if <hi rend="italic">managed rightly</hi>) prove a good thing: I have <hi rend="italic">long</hi> been in favour of it. Russell, M.H.R., Sutton, Sheehan, Rhodes, Buchanan, &amp; others, are <hi rend="italic">Honorary </hi>Members!!</p>
         <p>Another Club— “Union,”—has been also established at <hi rend="italic">Criterion</hi>. Ford is in the “Masonic.” <hi rend="italic">Fancy </hi>Balls are all the rage! one came off last night: see names &amp; <hi rend="italic">characters</hi> &amp;c &amp;c in this day’s paper! I hope none <hi rend="italic">owe</hi> any <hi rend="italic">old </hi>accounts.—</p>
         <p>The Education Act, has, at last, crawled through <hi rend="italic">Lower </hi>House, but with many alterations &amp; amendments: notably the striking-out of the “L. Prayer” &amp; Bible reading clause (at which <hi rend="underline italic">I am glad</hi>). The Inspectors are <hi rend="italic">now </hi>(by alteration in Comee.) under the E. Boards (local), &amp; also under one <hi rend="italic">Genl</hi>. Inspr. to be appd. by the Govt. This alone would (I think) determine me; as I don’t believe in 2 masters,–espy. at my age &amp; w. my experience: but <hi rend="italic">we shall see</hi>.</p>
         <p>And what do you think! Stokes’ overseer, (now the 2 S. have cleared out!) has come out with <hi rend="italic">no</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">roads </hi>from Hampden to Waipawa, or from H. to Kereru!! but has generously offered to shut up <hi rend="italic">all</hi> gates, only one day in the year—i.e. for the present. But see the papers. A great row, too, over Te Aute Estate—which “Herald” is <hi rend="italic">fomenting</hi>! Ch. of E. “Synod” is to meet here next week (what to do?)—Anderson is <hi rend="italic">gone</hi>—<hi rend="italic">wholly</hi>—to Akaroa: so that that feud has turned out just as I said it would &amp; must, at the very beginning: <hi rend="italic">all</hi> must go!—S.B. Hill takes the town; &amp; Irvine (<hi rend="italic">occasionally</hi>) Taradale. Sidey has been writing <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Education, <hi rend="italic">v. </hi>Catholics, &amp; they against him. Bp. Redwood has been here &amp; is returned to Wgn.</p>
         <p>In the “Waka Maori” Libel case, the Jury gave H.R.R. ₤<hi rend="underline italic">500</hi>.!!! (a very badly defended thing) R. is now ill at Wgn. <hi rend="italic">Sheehan</hi> questioned O. in House <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Ahuriri bridge, &amp; the Petane folks are wrathful agt. S. &amp; Capt. R. &amp; full of <hi rend="italic">thanks</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Sheehan</hi>. But as to the goings-on in the House! I lack words &amp; powers &amp; time to describe it! (see the Papers,) the worst is, <hi rend="italic">the end is not yet</hi>. The Govt. are now pledged (forced by Opposition) to alter taxation next year, so as to include property &amp; income!—will the <hi rend="italic">upper</hi> Ho. agree to it? Grubb has been writing &amp; <hi rend="italic">lecturing</hi>, against the Australian travelling Insurance Officer, &amp; G. <hi rend="italic">has the best </hi>of it. (see Papers.) Great trial case here all <hi rend="italic">this week</hi>—this the 5<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. day of <hi rend="italic">examination</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Committal</hi> only, &amp; not over yet! 2 lawyers on each side, &amp; Ct. Ho. crowded: R.D. Maney <hi rend="italic">v. </hi>G. Donelly for <hi rend="italic">Horse-</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">stealing</hi>, &amp;c.—(Hard swearing, I fear, on <hi rend="italic">both</hi> sides!) I believe the <hi rend="italic">real </hi>cause is, that <hi rend="italic">H. </hi>Donelly (both G. &amp; H. <hi rend="italic">formerly</hi> in R.D.M’s. employ) finding out a <hi rend="italic">flaw</hi>! in Renata’s big Lease, has succeeded in getting in the Patea land, for himself <hi rend="italic">&amp; Co.,</hi>—to the ruin (?) &amp; discomfiture of R.D.M., Studholme, Moorhouse, &amp; Bank of Australasia: (so I hear,—but I don’t know exact particulars).</p>
         <p>P.D.—shews <hi rend="italic">no sign</hi> yet! neither Sladen: &amp; 2 or 3 <hi rend="italic">P.N’s. </hi>(from<hi rend="italic"> old hands</hi>) are <hi rend="italic">again</hi> renewed!—</p>
         <p>“Helen Denny”—lately arrived at Port Chalmers; the Capt. (Ruth) married in England, Vaughan’s duaghter, who went home a passenger in her. You will find from my last, that Munn had sold his Sn. to Robjohns.</p>
         <p>Cable has sold out at Wairoa. I have <hi rend="italic">not </hi>been there yet! the Bar is again bad, &amp; the <hi rend="italic">end of </hi>the school Quarter is <hi rend="italic">near</hi>.—</p>
         <p>Oddfellows Hall is being <hi rend="italic">greatly </hi>enlarged, &amp; 2 story. Tennyson St.—in by W. Thomas’, is cleared (at last!) 20 ft. wide for carts, &amp; a high back curb, for the <hi rend="italic">present</hi>, to help the houses there on W. side. Raffles St. <hi rend="italic">across</hi> the big swamp is just finished—<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the running of it across, so that folks can walk over it (in <hi rend="italic">dry</hi> weather) to &amp; from Railway Station. Lyndon did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> sell any lot of Turner’s Section: <hi rend="italic">he </hi>valued the ½ ac. at ₤500., but the Trustees wanted ₤700: so none were sold. Early, one mg., Tuxford removed the Tel. post from <hi rend="italic">before </hi>his garden,—to just where his neighbour’s (Townsend—now gone!) fence joins his: I suppose he got leave. I asked him, Why? he replied, Because the old papers (ragged advertists.) blew into his garden!! The Gas Lamps are up, &amp; now it turns out, that <hi rend="italic">no</hi> contract for the supply of Gas has been signed!!! I have re-conveyed to Abbot the disputable bounds at Waipawa, &amp; have got ₤50. (3 mths. B.) from Lyndon &amp; I wish the grasping Ch. folks much joy! I fancy, they will regret they refused my repeated offers.—Mr. Sidey wants an Organist for St Paul’s, &amp; a Teacher for the <hi rend="italic">Port </hi>School.</p>
         <p>For a fortnight I have been “6’s &amp; 7’s”:—yesterday fortnight my man’s wife was suddenly brought to bed, &amp; the midwife, whom they had engaged, had gone to the Country: she is still very weak &amp; worn, &amp;, of course, has <hi rend="italic">not </hi>been <hi rend="italic">in here</hi>, to do anything for me: fortunately <hi rend="italic">I know</hi> how to work &amp; wipe &amp; dust, &amp;c &amp;c—but I don’t like it, &amp; I suppose this will (<hi rend="italic">must</hi>?) cause another separation! I <hi rend="italic">am tired</hi> of this kind of thing.</p>
         <p>Weather delightful! I am still keeping well: for which I hope I am thankful (I ought to be). May this find you <hi rend="italic">all </hi>well, and believe me my dear sir,<lb/>—with kind thoughts &amp;<hi rend="italic">remembrances</hi>, &amp; kind regards, Yours ever very truly,     W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>