<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0333">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1876 November 14: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1876-11-14">1876 November 14</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1876 November 14: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-278" place="foot" n="278"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand,<lb/>November 14/76.</p>
         <p>My dear Sir</p>
         <p>Last week (8<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) I recd. your long &amp; welcome letter of Sept. 15, &amp; was again gladdened with the sight of your well-known writing &amp; to find you were <hi rend="italic">all well</hi>!</p>
         <p>Our outgoing Mail leaves on 17<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. and I must write to you <hi rend="italic">now</hi>,—as this time is an over busy one w. me, I only having <hi rend="italic">this day</hi>! re-commenced my Inspection of Schools (which I ought to have begun in October—but Rheumatism &amp; <hi rend="italic">changeable </hi>weather (though <hi rend="italic">fine</hi>) hindered me,)—was at the U.M. School <hi rend="italic">all day </hi>&amp; feel <hi rend="italic">fagged</hi>—&amp; tomorrow I am off early to Meeanee &amp; so on.—When I go to Havelock, where I purpose spending a night, I will do all I can for you <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Jens Neilson.</p>
         <p>My last to you (w. papers) was on 19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. October, which I hope may duly reach you. I shall (if it arrives from Wgn. in time—having written for it) send you no. 34 “Hansard”—that you may see how Sir Donald has been “pitched into”—in the house, &amp; that, too, in his absence! His day is gone by!! (rather soon!) He has been <hi rend="italic">very ill</hi>, &amp; is only now slowly recovering: he has long been removed to Dr. Grace’s <hi rend="italic">house</hi>—for constant medical attention. The “Inverness” arrived, w. <hi rend="italic">our</hi> usual “luck”—<hi rend="italic">all well</hi> not a sound of sickness during the voyage, &amp; one birth.—Unfortunately there are <hi rend="italic">many </hi>hands still unemployed here,—&amp; no small grumbling.</p>
         <p>The Province of H. Bay is <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>! No P. Council, no Super., &amp; the Officers who remain in the Govt. employ are <hi rend="italic">now </hi>of the <hi rend="italic">Genl. </hi>Govt. Service. Sealy has <hi rend="italic">fully</hi> resigned: Tylee is <hi rend="italic">C.L.C.</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="italic">acting</hi>—for the present—w. G. <hi rend="italic">Richardson</hi> in signing cheques: I hear, <hi rend="italic">that</hi> work will fall to Tabuteau: a Mr. Beetham is to be our R.M., he has been some 5–6 yrs. a Warden in the S. Goldfields, so has had some experience w. the unruly! may he prove to be a worthy man!</p>
         <p>The last day that Sealy sat—some (<hi rend="italic">a </hi>few) of our J.P’s. went to bid good bye, &amp; Joe. Rh. (who was spokesman) made a great blunder—stating that “S. had been <hi rend="italic">25 yrs</hi>. in Govt. Service, &amp;c.” Sealy is selling his Woodville &amp; other land, &amp; is seeking to lend his money &amp; I don’t think <hi rend="italic">he </hi>will <hi rend="italic">return. </hi>I saw Tiffen <hi rend="italic">last week </hi>who is looking <hi rend="italic">well</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Fannin </hi>has not yet got a billett,—there <hi rend="italic">may </hi>be one for him somewhere,—I hope so—a <hi rend="italic">suitable</hi> one—for his family’s sake;—but (<hi rend="italic">entre nous</hi>) he has been much too careless of late; which I have grieved over &amp; told him of.—<hi rend="italic">The </hi>Education <hi rend="italic">Board</hi> (J.D.O., Chambers, J. Rhodes, Newton, &amp; Lee,) are to meet on Monday next, 20<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., – – – – <hi rend="italic">we shall see</hi>. Mrs H.R. Russell &amp; her daughter returned to Waipukurau last week,—amid a great to-do! (see Papers) An attempt at fire was made in White Road, &amp; fortunately discovd. <hi rend="italic">in time</hi>! ₤<hi rend="italic">200</hi>. Reward offered. The Crew of a boat belonging to the “Columbus” barque (our first wool ship) was upset on the bar last week, when Kraeft &amp; his crew put out &amp; saved them. P. Dolbel has brighter prospects!—at which I am <hi rend="italic">doubly</hi> glad! His petition to the House was successful, and the <hi rend="italic">letting</hi> of those back runs is to be <hi rend="italic">as Carter</hi> let them— “¼ per acre for the term”—this will save P.D. Further, Miller (the nipper) has told him, he will pay D. Cash (<hi rend="italic">less </hi>discount) for those outstanding Bills on the Run: (<hi rend="italic">I think </hi>Miller &amp; his partner wish to mortgage:)—and this <hi rend="italic">suits </hi>P.D. <hi rend="italic">His </hi>Ram, which (some say) ought to have had one of the many prizes for such sheep at the show, has been shorn, &amp; fleece weighed 23½ lbs.,—the heaviest of <hi rend="italic">all</hi>! it not being a full year’s growth. There is to be <hi rend="italic">another </hi>wedding at his house on Saturday next—one of his Jersey nieces to Balfour,—Kinross’ overseer: I have been warmly invited—but <hi rend="italic">cannot </hi>go. J.D.O. is away at Wallingford.—</p>
         <p>Another Artesian well is sinking—near to the last Corporation one, &amp; for them. Several houses building all around; I hear the Carpenter’s hammer continually: some on T. Section 288, and a 2-story one on 308; and one on 237; &amp; the space between Pat. Flannagan’s &amp; J.A.S’s. <hi rend="italic">old </hi>Ho. has now 4 addl. houses, the B.G. Trees having been felled! so here, opp. my gate, on Newton’s Sn., the trees <hi rend="italic">all </hi>felled and the earth hedge levelled, &amp; the old House renovated &amp; enlarged and twisted round fronting the street, and close to it; I suppose N. will build another. My gate (there) has been <hi rend="italic">removed</hi>! with all the lower fence; the mound (to right of entrance) is being levelled, &amp; thrown to fill up T. Sect. 108.—Cont. for filling-in, ₤<hi rend="italic">26.10</hi>. Wilson, Dentist, is enlarging his house w. a great addition, 2 story high, &amp; end on, joining the other, and blocking up entirely what small view J. Anderson had! Tuxford’s garden looks very well. Dr. Gibbes is going to build on the <hi rend="italic">corner </hi>Sn., opposite to Wilson’s;—he has leased ½ of it, @ 15/- pr. foot per ann.! It is Williams’. I have been over &amp; over asked to sell—good building sites, &amp; have at length consented—<hi rend="italic">on certain preliminary terms </hi>(I have written you out a copy ­­one of which I have sent to Gollan, to Canning, &amp; to Brandon)—but I am not anxious about it.—Lee told me, that J.A.S bought back the <hi rend="italic">one</hi> (&amp; the best) Section of his 8 ac. block sold at Auction,—for, I think, ₤15.—but John is a severe loser, <hi rend="italic">at present</hi>, by that whole transaction. I have written officially to Municipal Corpn. about Tennyson St. (S. end), &amp; about Owen St. N. The Contract has been taken for the filling-in the N. Swamp Roads, &amp; the work is just commenced—at the little hill, end of Thackeray Street. I hope they may <hi rend="italic">complete</hi> it!—J. Watt has just come hither to <hi rend="italic">reside</hi>; he has been <hi rend="italic">very ill</hi>—Bronchitis. I met the other day in town with a Mr. Paterson (now, the <hi rend="italic">Hon.</hi> Mr. P.) who, in ’61–’63, was in the House w. me: well, we talked of <hi rend="italic">old </hi>matters—&amp; I was surprised at <hi rend="italic">one </hi>thing,—he was <hi rend="italic">formerly very subject </hi>to the abominable sea-sickness,—but on his last voyage to Scotland &amp; back to N.Z. by sailing ship, was tolerably <hi rend="italic">free</hi> from it! Here is <hi rend="italic">hope</hi>: hurrah!<note xml:id="ftn2-279" place="foot" n="279"> Colenso was terribly sea-sick on his voyage to New Zealand, and later refused an invitation to botanise in the subantarctic islands for fear of it.</note> I have <hi rend="italic">no </hi>strawberries again this year! <hi rend="italic">Why</hi>, I don’t know. James says, they dried up—but the season is a <hi rend="italic">wet one</hi>—everywhere green. However, I have my <hi rend="italic">first</hi> gooseberry tart today. There are fine strawberries in the town for sale—but (I <hi rend="italic">hear</hi>) dear. I send you a copy of the Auckland “Graphic,”—drawings by Sam. Begg, Junr. I am sick at seeing so <hi rend="italic">much</hi> in the papers (Eng.) about &amp; <hi rend="italic">against</hi> the Turks! my sympathies (politically) are wholly with them.—Depend upon it—their <hi rend="italic">end</hi> is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> yet, despite Dr. Cummings (&amp; others) ratiocinations, &amp; Spurgeon’s (&amp; others) <hi rend="italic">prayers</hi>. People forget that the so-called Xn. “Church” (!!) has shed <hi rend="italic">more </hi>innocent blood and inflicted more tortures (in <hi rend="italic">cold-</hi>blood, too, &amp; under the guise of Xts. Religion!!) than all the Turks &amp; Mahometans under the sun. I must not forget to thank you for your Papers (still unread),—and I should tell <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, <hi rend="underline italic">confidentially</hi>, that Mr Symons of Walsall &amp; myself—do <hi rend="italic">not</hi> now correspond.—If I were <hi rend="italic">sure </hi>of remaining here—I would give you a little Commission to execute in London for me,—w. my old Agents, R. Dixon &amp; Co. Fenchurch Street: <hi rend="italic">I may yet</hi>.</p>
         <p>Today I walked by (<hi rend="italic">old</hi>) “London House;” &amp; thought of <hi rend="italic">absent </hi>ones &amp; <hi rend="italic">old </hi>times! N. &amp; C’s. 2 stores—are <hi rend="italic">fine</hi> ones, <hi rend="italic">particularly </hi>the last new one—nearly <hi rend="italic">all </hi>concrete, &amp; McVay’s looks well, too: but the <hi rend="italic">pavement there </hi>beats all! <hi rend="italic">fine </hi>good concrete work, quite <hi rend="italic">smooth</hi>: I thought on the <hi rend="italic">old </hi>front with its green grass edging! – – – but <hi rend="italic">now </hi>there is no one <hi rend="italic">there</hi> to speak to <hi rend="italic">me</hi>.</p>
         <p>And so, once more, Goodbye.—May this find you &amp; yours well. I <hi rend="italic">may not </hi>find time <hi rend="italic">next </hi>month to write.</p>
         <p>     Believe me always my dear Sir</p>
         <p>             Yours very truly        W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>How do you manage <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Income tax?—let me know.</p>
         <p>H.R.R. has just commenced an action for libel! against the printer of <hi rend="italic">Waka Maori</hi> &amp; Grindell for the letter wh. appeared therein written by a Maori. Damages <hi rend="italic">₤10,000</hi>!!!</p>
         <p rend="center">(Correct extract)</p>
         <p>1. The sites I would offer comprise the best pick of all the land I have here; and are I believe among the best situations (if not the very best) in all Scinde Island; to say nothing of their nearness to the Railway Station, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
         <p>2. They are situate on the flat-topped hill running parallel with Carlyle-Street, from entrance to Faraday Street nearly to Clive Sq.—through suburban Sections 39, 41, &amp; 42.</p>
         <p>3. They are laid off in ¼ ac. rectangular Sections, &amp; they are all level.</p>
         <p>4. The Street, or Road, in front (proposed to be called the Esplanade,) is nearly ¼ mile in length, level to straight, and is to be (say) ½ chain wide.—</p>
         <p>5. It is intended <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to have any houses on the E. side of the Road so as to keep the view open and unobstructed.—</p>
         <p>6. A chain, or chain &amp; half on the E. slope of the hill, would thus be left, which, on the W. edge, could be planted with a row of evergreen shrubs,—or, which might be also disposed of in corresponding lots to the respective takers of the building sections: such would form excellent gardens, the soil there being so very deep and rich.—</p>
         <p>7. From the laying-off the property, (sacrificing the <hi rend="italic">building sites</hi> on the E. side, as above, for the sake of the noble prospect,)—as well as from the extent &amp; number of the roads or streets leading to &amp; from the same, through other portions of my land, it is evident, that the value of those selected Building Sites is thereby largely increased,—to the detriment of course, in value of the remaining portions of the state.</p>
         <p>8. It is proposed that in selling by auction (or leasing, if preferred) the said Building Sites, the following conditions (or something similar) are to be <hi rend="italic">first </hi>agreed to,—in order to keep the locality respectable:—</p>
         <p>1. No House to be erected of less value (say) than ₤500.</p>
         <p>2. No public house to be allowed on the Terrace.</p>
         <p>3. The taker of any one ¼ ac. Section to have the option of taking also the next one at same price.</p>
         <p>4. No sale (or Lease) to be considered complete unless (say) six Sections are disposed of. [This will be seen to be absolutely necessary when it is known that there will be over 20 chains of <hi rend="italic">Carriage </hi>Roads to be formed through my <hi rend="italic">other </hi>land to give easy access to the said Esplanade].</p>
         <p>5. The upset price of each Section to be (say) ₤<hi rend="italic">300</hi>.</p>
         <p>9. I shall send a copy of these terms to one or two other gentlemen enquirers, but I shall <hi rend="italic">not </hi>advertise or seek to sell until these conditions, or similar ones, are by gentlemen desirous of obtaining a building-site agreed to.—At the same time I am open to their modification to suit <hi rend="italic">bona fide </hi>buyers. I am not, however, anxious of selling <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, believing that the proper time to do so will be when the N. swamp is filled-in.</p>
         <p>A plan of the said property (so laid out) can be seen at my house: it was laid out by Triphook in ’58, and will, I think, be found suitable. Mr Rochfort has also made <hi rend="italic">another</hi>.—</p>
         <p>In case <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the Sns. should be disposed of at once, then a percentage of the proceeds (to be agreed upon) to be laid out in forming &amp; making the road of the Esplanade.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>