<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0893">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1894 February 5: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1894-02-05">1894 February 5</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1894 February 5: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-675" place="foot" n="675"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Feby. 5<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>, 1894.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>I lit up! early this evg.—intendg. to write to you: but letter, &amp;c, came in, here I am! however, I <hi rend="italic">must begin</hi>. Before I do so—I <hi rend="italic">must </hi>mention <hi rend="italic">one</hi> of these letters, now to hand—from Mr. Tregear, and dated “<hi rend="italic">January 3</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">rd</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi> 1894” begging me to go on w. <hi rend="italic">Hawaiki Ms</hi>.!!—taking up <hi rend="italic">your </hi>brief, as a 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi> Daniel: it is a nicely written letter—which I must ansr. by &amp; by.—</p>
         <p>I duly recd. your long &amp; valued ep. of Jany. 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>.—&amp; thank you <hi rend="italic">much </hi>for it” I was greatly intd. in what you have told me of your <hi rend="italic">dear suffering </hi>boy: I hope he is <hi rend="italic">much </hi>better: this is one of those cases that <hi rend="italic">tries </hi>our faith: and <hi rend="italic">here </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">lately</hi> we have had another, Mrs Williamson died on Jany. 28 puerperal fever, much regretted, &amp; the poor dear husband (Chn. at Augustine’s &amp; a nice man) almost distracted! I went to the funeral—both there <hi rend="italic">in </hi>Ch. &amp; at the Cemetery—more to console him—the blow so <hi rend="italic">sudden</hi>, as always in such cases, &amp; he left w. 3 <hi rend="italic">little</hi> girls—perhaps you knew him—a Draper at Ringlands’:—he has acted as Lay Reader at Meeanee. I went thither again yesty. mg. (as one of Congn.) to <hi rend="italic">see him</hi>, &amp; speak a <hi rend="italic">word of cheer</hi>: but man, at <hi rend="italic">best</hi>, can do <hi rend="italic">little</hi> in all <hi rend="italic">such</hi> visitations.—Do not you &amp; Mrs. H. think—you are the <hi rend="italic">only </hi>sufferers.—</p>
         <p>I have been very busy of late—in seeing so <hi rend="italic">many </hi>of our Clerics, &amp; attending meetings, &amp; seeing Bp. <hi rend="italic">off</hi>!—<hi rend="underline italic">Dear</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>old man! he is<hi rend="italic"> gone</hi>: and I have lost my<hi rend="italic"> best friend </hi>I had<hi rend="italic"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">left</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>in N.—and <hi rend="italic">my views re</hi> his going away, have not altered: <hi rend="italic">another </hi>mysterious matter. I sent you Papers containing much about the <hi rend="italic">final </hi>meetings.—And now—who is to be Bp.? Ah, <hi rend="italic">who</hi>? I have not yet heard <hi rend="italic">a sound</hi>.—Rev. J.G. Paterson spoke <hi rend="italic">well</hi> at the <hi rend="italic">last</hi> meeting—not half reported.</p>
         <p>I think I must have told you, in former letters, that when the Bp. was gone I should be moving inland—if <hi rend="italic">well</hi>. Tomorrow was to be my day: but, 10 days ago, <hi rend="italic">O</hi>. Dean, came here, &amp; begged me to help! he nearly <hi rend="italic">done </hi>w. heat, &amp; only waiting for Bp. to go—to have 2 wks’. holiday. At first I cod. not—but, at last, <hi rend="italic">gave in </hi>for <hi rend="italic">1</hi> Sy.—next 11<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. (Bradbury takes 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) and <hi rend="italic">so </hi>I hope to leave here <hi rend="italic">on 13</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi> but I do not think I shall be long away. having <hi rend="italic">nothing </hi>to do in Bush District. I am pretty well, again, now, but weak in legs; flying Rheumc. pains, &amp; am therefore obliged to be careful.—</p>
         <p>On receipt of yours—I wrote to your Father, &amp; <hi rend="italic">sent him </hi>a copy (author’s C.) of my paper on <hi rend="italic">Moa</hi>, &amp; proverbs—as you had said, he would like to see it: he kindly came here to see me, bringing “Grongar Hill”, &amp; the “Brit. Printer” (your wish), most unforty. it was <hi rend="italic">the day</hi> of bustle &amp;c re Bp’s. leaving, &amp; Clerics <hi rend="italic">calling</hi>—so that I was <hi rend="italic">obliged </hi>to cut short our conversn. but he saw the position, still I was sorry for it. I suppose you saw the <hi rend="italic">printers’</hi> error in my letter in “Herald” <hi rend="italic">re </hi>“Californian Thistle”,<note xml:id="ftn3-676" place="foot" n="676"> Mountain grass. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> 2 February 1894.</note> &amp;c—This mg. Walker sent up “proofs” of my <hi rend="italic">long </hi>letter re <hi rend="italic">Taramea </hi>(I had offered to read &amp; correct), it was bristling w. errors, <hi rend="italic">strange ones</hi>, too,—and as to the composn., surely done by some <hi rend="italic">careless </hi>apprentice—but I let that pass.<note xml:id="ftn3-677" place="foot" n="677"> The “Wild Irishman”. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> 6 February 1894.</note> W. <hi rend="italic">had made </hi>enquiries <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the <hi rend="italic">plant</hi>, &amp; I responded: though, I confess, I scarcely thought he would insert my <hi rend="italic">long L.</hi>—I gave him leave to cut in &amp; out—&amp; so please himself.</p>
         <p>Your letter to the Auckland paper was a <hi rend="italic">good </hi>one, &amp; <hi rend="italic">needed </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">there</hi>: I return it, w. thanks. A Mr. Andrews from Whanganui (College?) has been <hi rend="italic">twice </hi>here to see me—I named for him his nice lot of Ruahine plants: young Hovell was <hi rend="italic">there </hi>w. him, &amp; is also gone to Wh-nui to be at his School.——–</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Feby. 6</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">: viii, p.m. </hi>I now go on w. my letter. I went down town this mg., &amp; did all my little business, &amp; returned by ’Bus to N. Terrace, &amp; Old Gramr. School—to see the Stuarts. I was much surprised to find there, outside old. sch. house, about 20 boys under drill! and from the Bp’s. daughter (Mrs. Clarke) I found, that the <hi rend="italic">new </hi>sch. masters (see advts.) had got <hi rend="italic">that </hi>school-house: they had advd. to open in Mrs. Heath’s (formerly Mrs May’s) but there was <hi rend="italic">no </hi>play-ground. I found the 2 ladies as well as one could expect—&amp; from them I learned, Bp. &amp; daur. were not long in Wgn., &amp; possibly might arrive at Sydney to nt. My <hi rend="italic">long </hi>letter was <hi rend="italic">out </hi>in “<hi rend="italic">Hd.</hi>” this mg., &amp; I recd. <hi rend="italic">many thanks </hi>in town for it; I must get some copies, &amp; send you one. The “Comps.” attended to my corns., but I did <hi rend="italic">not </hi>dare to touch pigeon-holes and broken letters: in <hi rend="italic">ptg. off.</hi>, there are some <hi rend="italic">failures</hi>. I was out in the sun 3 full hours, and returned very well—but <hi rend="underline italic">tired</hi>.</p>
         <p>Our Sy. should have held their annual Mtg. <hi rend="italic">tonight</hi>, but (as usual) they are <hi rend="italic">behind</hi>. I have lately recd. a <hi rend="italic">very long </hi>letter from Sir Jos. Hooker, mainly <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Banks’ Journal which he has had <hi rend="italic">copied </hi>in its entirety “for Press” (at an expense of about ₤30.)—but, <hi rend="italic">to date</hi>, the L. Bkrs. were shy about taking it in hand. A kind letter also from the Pres. of the <hi rend="italic">Great </hi>Sydney “Hortl. &amp; Promol. Sy.” wishg. me to accept <hi rend="italic">Hony. </hi>M-ship. I call it <hi rend="italic">great </hi>from the no. of its Members: I shall send you their little book (Rules, &amp;c) just for you to see the port. of the <hi rend="italic">Governor</hi>, because it seems (<hi rend="italic">to me</hi>) to be <hi rend="italic">so very much like </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">Hector</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> 20 yrs. ago</hi>. I see, Travers is become <hi rend="italic">French </hi>Consul! only last week I was thinking on <hi rend="italic">him</hi>, &amp; actually thought., from his <hi rend="italic">French </hi>n., &amp; versatility, that he was of F. extraction! &amp; <hi rend="italic">now</hi>—as above!!!—Your “British Printer” <hi rend="italic">surprises </hi>me! I am <hi rend="underline italic">lost</hi>: I suppose I am about the <hi rend="italic">only </hi>Printer living who has worked at the <hi rend="italic">old com. wooden. </hi>ptg. press!!——–</p>
         <p>I now purpose &amp; hope to leave N. for Bush <hi rend="italic">next Tuesday </hi>(13th) but, as far as I can see at present, I shall <hi rend="italic">not be long </hi>away.—I saw in paper—that Miss Burdett was appd. Sch. mistress at Tamumu School, and that Bibby &amp; wife, &amp; Miss Large, were shortly going to Engld.—also, yr. cousin Rechab. (<hi rend="italic">All</hi> from “know-all”: S.J., “<hi rend="italic">own </hi>correspdt.”) I was <hi rend="underline italic">much disappd</hi>., in not going to the A. Meeting at Havelock on 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. ulto.—I was <hi rend="italic">well enough</hi>, &amp; had got ready (day before) but heavy rain that nt., &amp; a <hi rend="italic">dk. lowering </hi>mg. up to x., <hi rend="italic">prevented </hi>me: I <hi rend="underline italic">was very sorry</hi>—for it cleared up afterwards.—</p>
         <p>I recd. a very <hi rend="italic">long </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">very good</hi> letter from Hamilton, after his return to D. H. is a lucky fellow and he <hi rend="italic">deserves </hi>it. Our Museum sadly wants a <hi rend="italic">Curator</hi>; &amp; (accdg. to H.) so does yours at Wgn. I learn from today’s P. that <hi rend="italic">Hill </hi>&amp; others <hi rend="italic">there </hi>w. you, are going in strongly for a <hi rend="italic">new </hi>ed. Flora N.Z.—good, perhaps, if done with proper care. I recd. a <hi rend="italic">nice </hi>note from Hector lately <hi rend="italic">re </hi>my Fijian “<hi rend="italic">Julus</hi>”—they there having also got a spn.—found, like mine, in Bananas, to cut the matter of enqy. short,—I made him a present of mine for Col. Museum. I have recd. several letters (N. &amp; S.) <hi rend="italic">re </hi>my long L. on the big Flood of ’47<note xml:id="ftn3-678" place="foot" n="678"> Floods. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi>. 16 January 1894.</note>—but from my <hi rend="italic">old friend</hi>, R.C.H., <hi rend="italic">merely, </hi>“<hi rend="italic">I recd. the Paper</hi>.” I told yr. F., I should like for him to see my paper on the Colour sense of the Maoris, also that “Essay”—I hesitate to lend to anyone from my Library <hi rend="italic">set </hi>of vols. Yet I <hi rend="italic">cannot </hi>possess them <hi rend="italic">much longer</hi>! It is <hi rend="italic">sad </hi>to see such a no. of vols. Trans. piled in our Liby. room! I do not understand it. I suppose you will have seen <hi rend="italic">Hill</hi> often during his stay.—Can. Fox told me, last wk., that he was much surprised to see in a <hi rend="italic">Douay </hi>B. (belg. to a R. Cath. at Gisborne) a copy of the Moabite stone, &amp;c!! Can. Webb came up this hill—puffing! to get mine, w. some other theologl. Bks.—</p>
         <p>Now Good bye! I have done my best.</p>
         <p>Kindest regards to you all, &amp; best wishes,</p>
         <p>Ever yours, sincerely—W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
