<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0839">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 July 27: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-07-27">1892 July 27</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 July 27: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-600" place="foot" n="600"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke<lb/>July 27, 1892.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I feel inclined to write to you this night—seeing it is about a month<note xml:id="ftn3-601" place="foot" n="601"> WC: error: <hi rend="italic">since </hi>ascertained, on 13th. inst.</note> since my last! and I have lately received a <hi rend="italic">very long </hi>letter from you, which however I do not intend to ansr. fully at this time, but merely acknowledge receipt &amp; <hi rend="italic">heartily thank you for it</hi>. I wish to send you enclosed clippings (in your lines), and to tell you a little of what may be <hi rend="italic">News</hi>.—First, I will quote from a letter from England by last Mail, from a clever &amp; good University man—an old Correspondent of mine: I had in one of my letters, praised <hi rend="italic">our </hi>poet Morris, &amp; quoted a few lines, &amp; recommended him to read the work, if still unknown; &amp; this is what <hi rend="italic">he says</hi>:—</p>
         <p>“I have heard &amp; read critiques of Morris’ poetry, but somehow I do not care to read the works of a man if he is a proved humbug as Lewis Morris is,—in other ways, he goes in for socialism and raves about the wrongs of labour, &amp;c., and yet is himself an employer who grinds the highest profit out of his wares at the expense of those in a small way of business—that, of course, does not prove his poetry good, but it does seem to me to take most of the enjoyment out of the reading of them.”—–</p>
         <p>I think I told you of a letter from Geo. White (offl.) <hi rend="italic">re </hi>“a <hi rend="italic">portrait</hi>—when the Sy. in funds”: I replied, better <hi rend="italic">first </hi>pay Buller for his vols. I being guarantee! this has called out Large—3 times! and at last L. wrote to B. to <hi rend="italic">lessen </hi>demand—reply—NO. Good—yesty. <hi rend="italic">the chq </hi>for £11.0.0 was sent to me, &amp; I remitted to B.—&amp; thanked L. for settling—<hi rend="italic">at last</hi>!—</p>
         <p>I note in “Herald” of <hi rend="italic">this mg</hi>., that <hi rend="italic">W.C. Smith </hi>had brought in a Bill for endowing a Museum <hi rend="italic">Napier </hi>w. £5000. I have long letter to hand from “Henry Wright, Wgn.” <hi rend="italic">re </hi>setting apart an Island, N. or S., to preserve N.Z. Fauna &amp; Flora: have not yet replied. (<hi rend="italic">Priv. </hi>Don’t think I could encourage that more.) Also, a pressing and long printed circular from Israel—on behalf of the “Salvn. Army”! surely the man is mad. And one today from London—asking for a subsn. to procure a portrait of Spottiswoode! Do you know anything of this new Ed. of an illustrated work by Whymper—travels &amp;c in the Andes? I find that that n. transl. of Ecclesiastes I was enqg. after, is (as I thought) by Dr Ginsberg—translator of “Moabite Stone,” &amp;c. &amp;c.,—&amp; subtitled “Coheleth” (its Heb. name) published by Reeves &amp; Co., L.—I have given Craig an order for a copy. There is a recent work (i.e. compilation) by old Field of Whanganui on N.Z. Ferns, price about £1.1.0 (I saw a copy at Crerar’s, 2–3 yrs. ago,)—should you meet with a 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. hand copy cheap (5/- 6/-) buy it for me. No copy yet to hand of “Trans.” vol. XXIV! In my letter yesty. to <hi rend="italic">President </hi>B. I mentioned my Paper—Memoir of Pope, <hi rend="underline italic">&amp;c</hi>.<note xml:id="ftn3-602" place="foot" n="602"> No paper of that title has survived, although on 10 September 1888 Colenso read “Pope, the English poet” to the HBPI and exhibited “original letters of Pope”!</note>
         </p>
         <p>I went to N. on 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. (through all the preceding week I was so-so w. Lumbago!) Got there <hi rend="italic">tired</hi>, &amp; w. <hi rend="underline italic">gt. diffy</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi> climbed my hill: (I had not gone up a hill since I last did this in April!) had 2 <hi rend="italic">wet </hi>days there, &amp; returned on Thursday, 21, to Waipawa in <hi rend="italic">fog </hi>&amp; rain! hither on 22—to Woodv. on 23—&amp; back on 25; wretched weather! particularly last <hi rend="italic">Sunday</hi>: Congns. very small. Snowing <hi rend="italic">here </hi>this mg, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">very cold</hi>. <hi rend="underline italic">I have felt it</hi> exceedgy.—yet am pretty well.—</p>
         <p>Hope you have your <hi rend="italic">full share </hi>of work: &amp; that <hi rend="italic">all yours </hi>are well. I do <hi rend="italic">not </hi>admire Ballance—wiring to Gladstone, &amp; think it wrong.</p>
         <p>With kindest regards &amp; best wishes</p>
         <p>Believe me yours always,—</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">28</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. night </hi>I had begun this letter to you yesterday, but Mr. Robertshawe coming-in, &amp; staying some time, hindered me but I sent you this mg. a “Herald” contg. Capt. R’s. speech, and <hi rend="italic">in it</hi>, a curious (?) recent advt. of a <hi rend="italic">new pen</hi>! (I now use the “planished pen” &amp; like them). Among many letters to hand is one from Hamilton, who (w. <hi rend="italic">others there</hi>) had evidently got the new vol. “Trans. N.Z. Inst.”—as he refers to my Papers therein: and Fannin tells me, that Mr. Hill had just given him a copy of his Geologl. Paper in that vol. <hi rend="italic">“contg. 7 plates.</hi>”—Hill wrote me a strong letter last wk.—to go down at once to the monster Mao. meeting at Waipatu: this howr. I could not do, without giving up Woodville work: I replied, tell Craig to send Hy. Tomoana, 3–4 copies “Signing Ty. Waitgi.”—I will pay. I have since heard, that Craig sent H.T. one copy. Hamilton informs me, of a vol. of <hi rend="italic">plates </hi>issued by Govt. of Jno. White’s work:—have you seen it? H. offers to send me a copy, but for me to <hi rend="italic">note on</hi>:—which, at <hi rend="italic">present</hi>, I am not willing to do. I think I told you of a letter in French to me from Madrid, contg. a <hi rend="italic">Spanish </hi>sentence: Hill <hi rend="italic">told me</hi>, G. White was from Spain &amp; knew Sp., so I wrote to him for its meaning: &amp; now, G.W. replies,—he knows <hi rend="italic">nothing </hi>of Spanish: &amp; had tried others there at N., but to no purpose, &amp; cannot find a Span. Dy. I <hi rend="italic">enclose </hi>the sentence, if you can render it, or find it out.—–</p>
         <p>Will Dr. de Lisle’s marriage surprise you or Mrs. Harding? no doubt you know <hi rend="italic">her</hi>. My people, I regret to say, are still unwell from La Grippe: &amp; several others in N.</p>
         <p>Now to your letter:<lb/>You<hi rend="italic">surprise </hi>me, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>not finding that Petn. v. Renata: when I return to N. (which may be <hi rend="italic">early</hi>, as I have priv. business there,) I will look into “<hi rend="italic">Journals </hi>H.R., 1861, &amp; see what is there said about it. You cause me to think afresh (<hi rend="underline italic">&amp; go back w. you</hi>) in your mentioning that <hi rend="italic">old matter </hi>re <hi rend="italic">Col. Russell </hi>and Scully &amp; self: It is not unlikely that <hi rend="italic">that</hi>, under Col. R., (who was made Native Minister, to <hi rend="italic">my loss</hi>, early in 1876,) <hi rend="italic">had to do </hi>with the early opposn. on part of House &amp; Govt. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Mao. Lex.—I have always thought so. I could tell <hi rend="italic">you</hi> a good deal about <hi rend="italic">this </hi>&amp; Col. R., &amp; I have more than once thought, that <hi rend="italic">one </hi>reason why Capt. R. has (not unfrequently) moved in the matter of M. L. was from <hi rend="italic">his knowledge </hi>of my having been ill-used (sat upon) by his Father.—</p>
         <p>Thank you for your keen &amp; critical remark re the R.C. Abp: Rome <hi rend="italic">is</hi>, still, &amp; ever <hi rend="italic">must </hi>be, “Semper eadem”: &amp; this is the Rock on which she <hi rend="italic">must </hi>infallibly eventually founder—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> her boasted <hi rend="italic">infallibility</hi>. I wholly (&amp; <hi rend="italic">again</hi>) go with you, re that sickening fuss! over the marriage of D’Arcy Irvine’s daughter!! also, the acquittal of that poor fellow. I did not see, or hear, of that wretch Bertrand, being about to be released!—am pleased at your having read that poem on the <hi rend="italic">Albatross</hi>, &amp; liking it: <hi rend="italic">did not remr. </hi>your having mentioned it. Thanks for clippings, &amp;c.—cannot take them up <hi rend="italic">just now</hi>: a large no. of letters to hand during the last 2–3 days, besides those by Eng. M. last wk. I sent “Herald” the <hi rend="italic">long </hi>(&amp; <hi rend="italic">interesting</hi>) account of a sheep Run &amp;c &amp;c <hi rend="italic">in Patagonia</hi>! They pubd. it in their suppt. last Saturday, thanking me heartily in a priv. letter for it, <hi rend="italic">it is worth reading</hi>. Fannin laid up w. gout! Mrs. F. with a <hi rend="italic">severe </hi>attack of La Grippe: ditto, Walker Ed. “H.”, ditto Younghusband, the Dean &amp; his family, &amp; <hi rend="italic">several others</hi>: the disorder is also at Woodville.—–</p>
         <p>While I am extremely glad to know of you &amp; yours being “all well”—I am sorry to find business slack w. you. What could you print (say) 100 copies of that Py. Paper <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Mao. Lex. (wh. you reprinted) for? let me know; as I am just run out.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">29</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>X. a.m. [I supp. If I were an American &amp; in the state of mind I am this mg.—I should recommence with—“Jehosaphat,” or “Jerusalem,” or “Great Scott,” <hi rend="italic">etc. </hi>Don’t laugh <hi rend="italic">at me</hi>.] Have <hi rend="italic">again</hi> (3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>–4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> time) read your letter, &amp; am now driven to write more—rubbish. Mail, S., won’t close till II p.m. Yes: <hi rend="italic">now I have read </hi>yr. clipping—“New poem by R. Kipling,”—thank you for it, &amp; would I could see the whole in “N. Observer” (is this to be had there w. you?) I much like the <hi rend="italic">main </hi>thought (like a golden thread) running through it—pervading it (like musk kept in a drawer!) &amp;—strange though it may seem, <hi rend="italic">even to you</hi>, it reminds me of my text &amp; Serm. last Sunday evening (1 Thess. v.9— “turned from <hi rend="italic">idols </hi>to <hi rend="italic">serve </hi>the <hi rend="underline italic">living</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">true </hi>
            <hi rend="underline smallcaps italic">God</hi>”: a highly <hi rend="italic">pregnant </hi>sentence: <hi rend="italic">they </hi>did so—have <hi rend="italic">we </hi>done so? &amp;c. On a former occasion I had preached from <hi rend="italic">last </hi>v. of 1 Ep. John, re “<hi rend="italic">idols</hi>”—those of <hi rend="italic">Xns. </hi>including <hi rend="italic">fads</hi>!): in the mg. it was x Acts, 46,— “tongues”: <hi rend="italic">dead against the popular view</hi>, &amp;c. (see how I run on, as if you &amp; I were in our old room at N. <hi rend="italic">closely chatting</hi>! shall we ever so sit togr. again?) I have also <hi rend="italic">read</hi>, &amp; consid. for 2½ min, yr. Riddle—but put that aside, have no time for it: <hi rend="italic">how can you find spare time for such exercitations</hi>? perhaps to <hi rend="italic">ease </hi>your over-worked mind. Hamilton has given me any amount of <hi rend="italic">questions</hi>—almost obsolete <hi rend="italic">re</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">old</hi> Maori matters, (this he has often done of late,) and I think, such are for <hi rend="italic">others there</hi>, as well as himself.——</p>
         <p>I should say—I <hi rend="italic">rarely </hi>ever see the “Evg. News”—tho’ it is taken in here, and is, I think, <hi rend="italic">the preferred P. of the 3 N. ones</hi>: as to Hagen’s, &amp; <hi rend="italic">this </hi>“Bush Adv.”—Ugh! No Paper exists in our Cy. hotels ½ a day after receipt! I have therefore bought <hi rend="italic">many</hi> single copies. Yesterday I was reading debate in the Ho. of Com. on Wom. franchise &amp; much pleased w. some of the speeches <hi rend="italic">against </hi>it, &amp; was glad to find that Bill thrown out! With you, I rejoice at Glasgow showing a true British “backbone”! May he <hi rend="italic">go on </hi>as he has begun. Is it not somewhat curious that <hi rend="italic">Ly. </hi>Fox, should so soon follow <hi rend="italic">Ly. </hi>Bell, &amp; both <hi rend="italic">Ly. </hi>Buller? I find Sir Wm. Fox is also ill, &amp; Grey (<hi rend="italic">absit omen!</hi>) ordered off to Australia—a <hi rend="italic">warmer </hi>climate—for his health. “Standard” partly reviews a Wk. lately issued on Names, (Scottish, I believe,)—in which it is shown, <hi rend="italic">no </hi>diff. between <hi rend="italic">Stewart </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>, &amp; that both derived from “<hi rend="italic">Keeper of the King’s pigs</hi>.” Heu! how often do we find— “from sublime to ridiculous only a stop.” Here, then I halt; If you are <hi rend="italic">not </hi>busy in Pg. off. reply, fully: if you <hi rend="italic">are don’t. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>With very affect. regards &amp; best wishes believe me </p>
         <p>Yours truly</p>
         <p>W. Colenso</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Weather wet, cold, wretched</hi>!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
