<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1055">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1898 July 6: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1898-07-06">1898 July 6</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1898 July 6: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-910" place="foot" n="910"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier July 6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. 1898.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I suppose &amp; <hi rend="italic">hope </hi>you &amp; yours returned in safety to Wgn., and, by this, have got over the fatigues, &amp;c, of your long jy.; fortunately you had fine weather <hi rend="italic">at this end</hi>, what at <hi rend="italic">that</hi>, I know not: I thought <hi rend="italic">much </hi>of you: and your account of your Uncle John (&amp; not having since heard any thing of him), the <hi rend="italic">deaths</hi> of Capt. Fairchild and of Saunders—&amp; severe illness of Fannin caused me to think still more.—</p>
         <p>You will remember <hi rend="italic">how </hi>I sought, over &amp; over, in my little bundle of rough drafts and memos. of letters, &amp;c, to Govt. Printers, for that <hi rend="italic">one </hi>to “<hi rend="italic">Burns</hi>”, re order for 500 copies &amp; <hi rend="italic">could not </hi>find it! Well: after you left I went at it again, &amp; <hi rend="italic">found it</hi>—but it was <hi rend="italic">not </hi>written to <hi rend="italic">Burns</hi> (hence the bother) but to “<hi rend="italic">Costall</hi>”—&amp; so I have <hi rend="italic">passed </hi>it repeatedly by! Was I not vexed?—I shall now send the <hi rend="italic">rough draft </hi>to you—as <hi rend="italic">you</hi> can make out my writing &amp; interlineations!—And (if <hi rend="italic">you think well </hi>of doing so) you may show it to Mackay: but <hi rend="italic">be sure to return the draft to me</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I shall send w. this your copy of letter “A.”, I think I told you, I have only given out 5 copies to <hi rend="italic">individuals</hi> in N.Z.—yourself, Hill, Stout, Hector, &amp; Hamilton.—Hill, I believe, is securely <hi rend="italic">blockaded </hi>in Wairoa! (to his grief—I know: I told him, how I thought it would be!) Fannin is <hi rend="italic">better</hi>, out of bed yesty., after 3–4 days in it, in much torment, from a <hi rend="italic">severe</hi> attack of gout, Drs. in attendance: his son was here seeing me last night, IX. o’clock.—</p>
         <p>Last night I recd. a letter from Under Secy., “Dept Justice”<lb/>—reply from Premier to my note of 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>., <hi rend="italic">re </hi>my going on with following portion of Mao. Lex. [E, H.] <hi rend="italic">prepg. for press</hi>: S. says,— “The work of ptg. &amp; pubg. should be proceeded with”. And then asks, as to “<hi rend="italic">terms</hi>”.—– “Whether on my own account and at my own expense; or, on the terms on which the ptg. of the letter A. was undertaken, namely that a certain definite sum be fixed, of which the Govt. defray one-half, &amp; the auther the other half”.—–</p>
         <p>After much thinking (&amp; no one to help! would <hi rend="italic">you </hi>were <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">near</hi>,) I have drafted my reply:—–<lb/>1. In note of 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. never thought of “<hi rend="italic">terms</hi>” for I had none to propose—not wishing to waste any more time about them:<lb/>2. Would not undertake to proceed w. wk. on my own account, &amp; at own expense.<lb/>3. Neither in term of letter A—seeing that there is to be no sale for any copies of the wk: and, while I could agree, under existg. circumstances, to work constantly at it for the pub. good &amp; honour of the Colony without receiving any pay I could not consent to do so and pay for printg. too. And so, I suppose, it is (as Major Withers used to roar out in Clive Sq. to his awkward squad)— “<hi rend="italic">As you were</hi>”. Sic transit gloriæ, &amp;c, &amp;c,</p>
         <p rend="center">_______</p>
         <p>Yesty. <hi rend="italic">late</hi> I finished my heavy <hi rend="italic">monthly</hi> labour of letters, papers, and books, for S.F. Mail, &amp; now I have lots of letters to ansr.—<hi rend="italic">N.Z. ones</hi>.—A note to hand from Rev. Mr. Tuke wishes me (for self &amp; <hi rend="italic">congn</hi>.) to take Ch. S. there on 24<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst., when he (leaving Home on Friday 22) would be absent: I suppose (D.V.) I shall do so.</p>
         <p>I also send you separately, Kirk’s Cat. of books:—the <hi rend="italic">markings</hi> are <hi rend="italic">not mine</hi>; yr. copy <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. being <hi rend="italic">made </hi>up.</p>
         <p>The day you left I was <hi rend="italic">expecting </hi>Hill, who generally calls at <hi rend="italic">noon</hi>, he did not come: <hi rend="italic">aftn. </hi>I sd. to Housekeeper I would go up to bed, feeling so exhausted, &amp; if H. should call, tell him my position, &amp;c.,—am pretty well today.</p>
         <p>With kind regards &amp; best wishes</p>
         <p>I am, yours truly,               W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
