<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0804">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 October 31: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-10-31">1891 October 31</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 October 31: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-554" place="foot" n="554"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Saty. Nt.,<lb/>Octr. 31/91</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Your letter of 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. to hand yesty. and I am pretty certain if I do not write to you <hi rend="italic">tonight</hi> (&amp; that briefly), I may not for all next week.—as a matter of course I had been long on the look-out for your delayed L.—in reply to mine of 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., but, perhaps, after all, there was little to reply to. I thank you for yr. item <hi rend="italic">re</hi> your Phil. Meeting, &amp; now hope to have something <hi rend="italic">full</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">good</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">re</hi> my Paper. I must look to <hi rend="italic">you</hi> for information. I almost marvel at your caring to look at <hi rend="italic">that</hi> Demonsn. Holiday—or its works! <hi rend="italic">N</hi>. knew <hi rend="italic">nothing </hi>of it—all hands at wk. as usual: I went to town &amp; was much pleased (<hi rend="italic">for once</hi>!) <hi rend="underline italic">w. N.</hi> I was greatly pleased in finding that you had your good Mother <hi rend="italic">w. you</hi>—this alone is quantum suff. for your not writing.</p>
         <p>One sent. in yours I do not understand mainly, however, to one word being indecipherable! (not unfreqy. the case in your quickly written letters—in this respect like Hill, <hi rend="italic">Fannin</hi>, &amp; Ormond!) You say <hi rend="italic">re</hi> P.C. judgt— “I’m inclined to agree w. Herald that the original  discovered by P.C. which seemed to decide their verdict.” &amp;c. &amp;c. I have <hi rend="italic">since</hi> read that judgt., &amp; also art. in H., but <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi> find out yr word!—[<hi rend="underline italic">To me</hi>: there is much in that affair that is <hi rend="italic">dark;</hi> and crooked. I dare not write (even to you) my thoughts. I have <hi rend="italic">ever</hi> believed that I could throw <hi rend="italic">light</hi> on Renata’s last words, &amp; possibly unravel their meaning. It is a curious fact, that I had recd. from R. a letter to attend the feast, &amp; also one from Airini D., but owing to their being delayed in P.O. here, they did not reach me in time—only on the mg. of his death! And then I recd. another to be at his funeral—but I did not go: <hi rend="italic">I was at Dvk</hi>]</p>
         <p>And now a few words about myself, no doubt I told you of Eccles having a month on sick leave, &amp; that the 4 Sundays at Waipawa, were to be served by Bp., W.C., St. Hill, &amp; Webb:—well on Saty. 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I went to W. having noticed in H. <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> said about S. in evg. Ch. there. and at W. I found it was the <hi rend="italic">same</hi>! in “W. Mail,”—what made it <hi rend="italic">worse</hi>, was the fact that <hi rend="italic">all the other</hi> Chs. were fully set forth as usual. So my Congn. on the Sy. mg. was very small, the weather fine, better in evg., but loud complaints on the Monday, &amp; blame thrown on each other,—Ch. warden, Vestrymen, Editor, &amp;c.—Before I had gone inland St. Hill wrote to me, asking me to take Ch. duty for him at Clive on <hi rend="italic">his day</hi> at W. (&amp; appy. as if he did not like to go thither), to this I had assented, but on the Monday, 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I wired to St. H., that as I was <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, I wod. take duty on his day, <hi rend="italic">if such suited him better</hi>: he replied <hi rend="italic">“</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">gladly</hi> &amp;c”—so I remd. for the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., spending <hi rend="italic">intervening</hi> days in Dvk. forests &amp; retd. to W. on 23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>.—&amp; to N. on 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, and am to leave for Taradale tomorrow (2 S. there) &amp; return by Rymer on Monday—to work hard for outgoing Eng. Mail.—Tuke left some days back for the hilly interior.</p>
         <p>I was in town on business on Wedy. but retd. immy. I saw Mrs Fannin out driving w. her husband, &amp; had some chat with her. She looks <hi rend="italic">well</hi>, &amp; talked <hi rend="italic">well</hi> too. Last evg. the Dean kindly called, &amp; from him I learned of Parkinson’s <hi rend="italic">illness</hi>! obliged last Monday to take to his bed, Drs. order, dropsy in legs. Sorry to hear of this—I, too, <hi rend="italic">fixed</hi> for Tarad. but, forty., the Bp. returned yesty. afternn, from Waikare-moana (unknown to D. when here w. me!) The Bp. did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> go to Waip. on his Sy! but sent Wills (Opokiti) who was taken <hi rend="italic">very ill</hi> there, &amp; got thro’ S. w. diffy.</p>
         <p>Thanks for clipping <hi rend="italic">re</hi> that Maori.—I shall enclose a fern w. <hi rend="italic">Coccus</hi> for M.—(tho’ he <hi rend="italic">deserves</hi> nothing from <hi rend="italic">me</hi>!) perhaps he knows it already: you can give it, &amp;c.—I also enclose a <hi rend="italic">proof</hi> sheet from Sir J.D. Hooker—this please return, anon: it reminds me of <hi rend="italic">old</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">times</hi>. The work, just begun ptg. at Oxford Uy.—has a long history.</p>
         <p>I cannot write any more now. <lb/>Good bye, Kind Regards, Yours very truly, W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
