<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0662">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1888 February 23: to Grey</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Auckland Council Libraries GLNZ C28.11 (Grey New Zealand letters).</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/48318/">Grey</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1888-02-23">1888 February 23</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1888 February 23: to Grey<note xml:id="ftn3-387" place="foot" n="387"> Auckland Council Libraries GLNZ C28.11 (Grey New Zealand letters).</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke,<lb/>(70 Mile Bush,)<lb/>Feby. 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. 1888.</p>
         <p>Dear Sir George Grey</p>
         <p>I came hither early in this month on my usual autumnal Botanical ramble in these sequestered woods and glens,—and since I have received a long and interesting (though painful) letter from our mutual friend Sir J.D. Hooker—which I have this day answered.</p>
         <p>In it he has given me a message for you, which I copy:</p>
         <p>— “Give Sir George Grey my warmest salutations when you see or write to him: and tell him, I keep the nuggets he gave me as a cherished keepsake.”—</p>
         <p>I had sent to Sir Joseph a copy of the Napier “Herald” containing the report of your speech there and Public Meeting,—besides my frequently writing to him.</p>
         <p>Hooker and his Lady had been having a <hi rend="italic">sad </hi>Xmas:—<lb/>1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. the death of her Father<lb/>2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. the death of her last surviving brother, Frank Symonds, at Tonga. I believe you knew him well: also, his brother Capt. Symonds,—as both had lived long near you.—</p>
         <p>I was much grieved, the other day, to see in the Papers, of your being severely ill at Kawau: I trust, dear Sir George Grey, that you are now quite recovered.—</p>
         <p>I am keeping well,—with the use of all my faculties, &amp; don’t need glasses: only I find my knees to be <hi rend="italic">not </hi>so strong nor so ready as of yore in our tangled forests.—–</p>
         <p>With kindest regards,</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Dear Sir George Grey,</p>
         <p>Yours truly,</p>
         <p>Wm. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>