<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0960">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1896 March 16: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1896-03-16">1896 March 16</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1896 March 16: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-776" place="foot" n="776"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, March 16/96<lb/>ix.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding—–</p>
         <p>I had determined at sunset this evening, to write to you, as I had <hi rend="italic">finished </hi>for S.F. Mail, and I found your last letter of Feby. <hi rend="italic">16</hi> unansd., and my last <hi rend="italic">to</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">you</hi>—alas! somewhere <hi rend="italic">near </hi>Xmas.!!! (<hi rend="doubleunderline underline italic">NO</hi>: “4, &amp; 5, Feby”: <hi rend="italic">good.</hi>) But while I was on my old sofa musing—candles not yet lit up, Mr. W. Welch <hi rend="italic">suddenly </hi>put in an appearance! (never before at this hour!) &amp; remained till now. I was at his Ch. yesty. mg., very weak, &amp; so he had kindly come up to see how I was: we spent a very pleasant 2 hours in chatting—such an event at <hi rend="italic">late </hi>hours, <hi rend="italic">candle-</hi>light! rarely happening <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, now that R.C.H. is gone.</p>
         <p>(17<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. night.) I could only write to end of page 1, last night—as Robert came up from P.O., late, and we had our usual nightly yarn.——</p>
         <p>And, really, I hardly know how to write to you—where to begin! what to say—to <hi rend="italic">select</hi>—having so very much in store—pickled, or lost!</p>
         <p>With your last paper came a portion of a poem by Mrs Hemans kindly copied by you for me at Tawa flat: now I have an A.1. edition (?) of Mrs H’s. poems here, &amp; it does <hi rend="italic">not </hi>contain this of yours.</p>
         <p>Of course you have heard of Tiffen’s death—&amp; all about funeral. On that day (20<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. ult.) I was to have gone inland, but put it off till Monday 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. One of my reasons and the <hi rend="italic">main </hi>one for going <hi rend="italic">then </hi>was, to attend Hortl. Show at Wdv. on 26<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., having long been a Member, &amp;c. So I went to Wdv. on that day, &amp; met there with Rev. R. Stewart &amp; wife from Greymouth, (we had half-appointed to meet,) returned at ix. p.m. to Dvk. <hi rend="italic">very tired</hi>. On Sunday 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. took mg. S. at Dvk., that R. with Bp. W. might go to Weber Dist.—Bp. preached at Evg. S. at Dvk., on Thursday, 5<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., left D. for Waipukurau (having <hi rend="italic">previously notified </hi>to Mr. Grant.) That evg. Mr. G. came to Gow’s to see me, &amp; remd. till x, a most <hi rend="italic">pleasant time</hi>: the next mg., with Mr. Tuke, thence to Manse, &amp; after dinner at Gow’s, to call on Hon. W.C. Smith, and Mrs Trestrail: poor dear lady! quite blind, &amp; <hi rend="italic">no hope </hi>of ever seeing again (this from Doctors), but <hi rend="italic">so content, so cheerful</hi>! <hi rend="italic">it was a good lesson to me </hi>to be with her, and <hi rend="italic">strange </hi>to say, she has a yg. woman (16–18, or so) from S. Island residing w. her, &amp; much <hi rend="italic">attached to her</hi>! This yg. woman came, w. her friends (relatives?) to Waipu., some time ago, and when they returned she chose to stay! her people (family) being well-off, too! I was pleased both w. her appearance &amp; manner: though it <hi rend="italic">seemed strange </hi>to me. Mrs. T’s. garden, alas! <hi rend="underline italic">is suffg</hi>., &amp; so <hi rend="italic">all gardens there</hi>! I never saw such a wretched sight: owing, to the <hi rend="italic">slight</hi> depth of the earth on the hard white <hi rend="italic">papa</hi> clay.—–</p>
         <p>I retd. to N. on Friday evg.—I was <hi rend="italic">very well </hi>in Bush, but, w. doors &amp; windows open in train, caught cold, &amp; so laid <hi rend="italic">up here </hi>for several days, venturing to town on Friday last, after 3 wks. absence, but <hi rend="italic">not feeling </hi>strong, especially in knees &amp; legs. Craig told me of his having <hi rend="italic">seen you </hi>at Wgn., &amp; of your doing well—getting on nicely: <hi rend="italic">I hope so</hi>.</p>
         <p>Hill &amp; wife had, also, returned to Napier, on Saty. 7<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>,—and late at night H. came here, and we arranged (D.V.) to be together at Annl. Mtg. Phil. Inst. on Monday, 9<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—but on Sunday I was suddenly severely seized—could not go to Ch.,—not do anything: so on My., sent word to Craig—to tell Hill, &amp;c. At vii, p.m. his daughter came w. a letter from H., asking, <hi rend="italic">pressingly</hi>, my consent to take Prest. office—which I had <hi rend="italic">not yet </hi>agreed to do. In reply, I said I wd. do so: provided (1.) unanimous: (2) H. to adhere to <hi rend="italic">his </hi>promise, to become V.P., &amp; to attend <hi rend="italic">every </hi>monthly meeting: well, they elected <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, but H. is <hi rend="italic">not </hi>V.P., &amp; I find (from Craig) that H. will not attend all our meetgs.—so I have been trapped!—I am sorry for <hi rend="italic">this</hi>—as it will not improve, strengthen, our pulling together for <hi rend="italic">good </hi>of Institute: I fear, H’s. “<hi rend="italic">Junior Club</hi>”, is in the way.</p>
         <p>While at Dvk. I recd. from Hector proofs of my last year’s rejected P.—on prodigies, &amp;c.—which I was glad to see.<note xml:id="ftn3-777" place="foot" n="777"> Colenso W 1895. Memorabilia of certain Animal Prodigies, Native and Foreign, Ancient and Modern. <hi rend="italic">Trans NZ Inst</hi>. 28: 87–97. </note>
         </p>
         <p>I expect to have to go inland for a few weeks <hi rend="italic">after Easter </hi>, as I have promised to help Tuke (for 1 month) on his finding another to take half the duty: T. wants, <hi rend="italic">needs</hi>, a rest or holiday &amp; is thinking of going to Australia, to see his brother, or brother<hi rend="underline">s</hi>: having <hi rend="doubleunderline underline italic">10</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>Last night, Sam Carnell M.H.R. came out, strong, at “Gaiety”, (<hi rend="italic">Swan </hi>Chn.) Capt. R. having broken ice the week before at Hastings.—I must refer you to their “<hi rend="italic">facts &amp; figs</hi>”.</p>
         <p>Bp. W. is now at Gisborne, but retg. this week: he suffers much &amp; <hi rend="italic">frequently</hi> from <hi rend="italic">lumbago</hi>: he could not preach at Cathl. on 8<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>, though previously announced: he seems <hi rend="italic">worn</hi>. I saw in same paper notice of Wgn. Phil., &amp; <hi rend="italic">new officers</hi> for ’96.</p>
         <p>I have sent you several papers, so, of course, you saw my advt. &amp; <hi rend="italic">long </hi>letter in “Herald”, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>trespassers.<note xml:id="ftn3-778" place="foot" n="778"> Short cut to Napier Terrace. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> 21 February 1896. </note>—“D.T.” would <hi rend="italic">not </hi>insert my letter! tho’ it had <hi rend="italic">the advt</hi>.: I went, same day, to “Evg. N.” office, <hi rend="italic">first </hi>time I was ever in that <hi rend="italic">den</hi>, and Ed. inserted letter! McD. wrote to me, telling me how it was! (K’s. doing:) &amp; sympathising. <hi rend="italic">I felt it</hi>: the <hi rend="italic">more </hi>that “Eg.N.” had so readily acquiesced: kept 3 advts. going a week in each: and I am happy to say—<hi rend="italic">I am free from trespassers</hi>! R.D.D. McL. has been here about Road, which he <hi rend="italic">does not like</hi>, &amp; proposes the <hi rend="italic">whole width of road </hi>to come thro’ <hi rend="italic">my land</hi>! which would absorb nearly all width of <hi rend="italic">flat </hi>in front of Ch. fence, &amp; McL. says, he will contribute money to do so, &amp; the Borough Council to <hi rend="italic">buy the land required</hi>: &amp; he left me to see Swan about it: my man R. tells me, he heard a petition is being got up.—–</p>
         <p>The hot &amp; dry weather still continues &amp; no sign yet of change! Several of my trees, 15–18 ft. high, are drooping, and paddocks, of course, pastureless! On Sunday last a horse here of Magill &amp; Campbell’s went over a cliff (nr. Rd. Williams’ section) &amp; broke <hi rend="italic">its neck</hi>; mainly owing (so Rob. says) to the yg. larrikins pulling out rails of fence there to get at blackberries!—–</p>
         <p>Have been <hi rend="italic">largely </hi>employed of late in ansg. letters: many to hand from strangers &amp; foreigners, &amp; on strange subjects!—</p>
         <p>I sent you that Germ. Gardeners’ Cat., as it seemed such a good one. What an <hi rend="italic">Aster </hi>field!! I fear Tiffen’s fine 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. rate garden must now <hi rend="italic">go</hi> but I have <hi rend="italic">not yet </hi>heard anything. What a change of scene! ’tween the 2 <hi rend="italic">Booth’s, brothers</hi>! When will the Xn. Ch. be on her guard, against <hi rend="italic">all </hi>such false prophets? Miss Stewart <hi rend="italic">Bp’s. sister</hi>, left for England on Saturday not to return to N.Z.—Who, or <hi rend="italic">what</hi>, is the person who has married Luff’s daughter?—–</p>
         <p>I see Buller is back again, &amp; <hi rend="italic">wkg. </hi>A very curious advt. is in papers <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Renata’s wardrobe &amp; <hi rend="italic">plate</hi>!—I will enclose it. I was amused a short time ago, on reading, in Papers, of a case in court, in which the Maori styled himself <hi rend="underline italic">Te</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> Renata</hi>. I have known Europeans (or <hi rend="italic">pakehas</hi>) to do so, thinking (!) the prefix of “Te” to add greatly to their names!! I saw <hi rend="italic">old </hi>Carroll of Wairoa in town last wk., had a chat w. him: he, too, is <hi rend="italic">greatly altered</hi>. My own <hi rend="italic">daily </hi>Rheum. (<hi rend="italic">if it be Rheumn.</hi>) is of a very peculiar char.—running all over body, attacking big joints <hi rend="italic">in pairs</hi>! and <hi rend="italic">seriatim </hi>2 ancles, 2 knees, 2 elbows, 2 shoulders, tops, 2 wrists, 2 thigh bones, &amp; fingers of both hands every mg. on rising, but it is comparably quiet, unless I move—save in bed: sometimes. To put my hands behind to brace button &amp;c, is torture! but must be done. I <hi rend="italic">cannot well </hi>lift a small book, nor teapot w. 2 cups tea in it: but it is continually changing about, always on big prominent joints, &amp; on the whole bearable, as to pain, when I am quiet—reclining or sitting, but woe’s me! on rising up for a minute or two.———–Yet how many 1000ds, are far worse off! So, I have much, very much, <hi rend="italic">to be thankful for</hi>: I have <hi rend="italic">long </hi>thought, that we do <hi rend="italic">not practise </hi>this great grace of thankfulness suffy., Calvin <hi rend="italic">truly</hi> says of <hi rend="italic">it</hi>, that it <hi rend="italic">includes </hi>all other Xn. graces. I am <hi rend="italic">told</hi>, that <hi rend="italic">our Inst. </hi>is bundled out, “neck &amp; crop” from the large Museum room! which is now <hi rend="italic">let </hi>to a gang of women—strangers—to form a “Kiosk”!! or tea-drinking club, whither the thirsty T-tot. &amp; others go every day to drink tea &amp; talk scandal.</p>
         <p>   Good bye: I am tired. Kindest regards to you &amp; to all of the Hdg. hive.</p>
         <p>           Yours ever,                     W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. What of the 2 <hi rend="italic">long </hi>advts. in “D.T.” from the ex-J.P.?—</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
