<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0772">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 March 19: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-03-19">1891 March 19</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 March 19: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-517" place="foot" n="517"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke<lb/>Thursday 19/III/91</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Your very kind most welcome &amp; long letter of the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. is to hand &amp; I thank you <hi rend="italic">much</hi> for it: it came together with 9 others from <hi rend="italic">all parts</hi> (England, N.York, Akaroa, &amp;c)—but <hi rend="italic">yours I preferred to them all!—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I feel very shaky “this mg.” (my bad writing will show it to you) but I will try &amp; persevere, so that you may get a reply from me <hi rend="italic">before</hi> Sunday.</p>
         <p>1. I note what you say, &amp; deplore, re Tregear’s Dy. (the great &amp; <hi rend="italic">sad</hi> omission), I <hi rend="italic">rejoice</hi> w. you that it occurred <hi rend="italic">before</hi> your advent. It is (to me) doubtful, of the 2 plans proposed, which is to be preferred. Perhaps <hi rend="italic">both</hi>—a <hi rend="italic">smaller</hi> page containing it to be inserted in its place which could be torn out &amp; also <hi rend="italic">in the Errata</hi>. If the wk. was mine this plan I should adopt.—</p>
         <p>I enclose P. Notes for £2.—to pay for my copy (31/6)when ready, also for 2 Reviews (recd.) &amp; also for Collier’s Biogy. 2/6 (or so), &amp; for a copy of Gammell’s Inqy. origin Pentateuch pubd. by L &amp; B. (Review., p.614: <hi rend="italic">note.</hi>)—</p>
         <p>I <hi rend="italic">now</hi> find I have <hi rend="italic">not sent enough</hi> in these P.Ns. obtained yesterday—but I will send deficiency shortly.—</p>
         <p>I thank you for your remark on my <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> Dy.—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> what D’y. told you—as that serves to <hi rend="italic">quiet</hi> me! If he should print it, I hope it will be done <hi rend="italic">first</hi>-<hi rend="italic">rate</hi>—as to size, type, &amp; paper: <hi rend="italic">not</hi> on that wretched <hi rend="italic">thin</hi> p. used in “Ty of Waitangi”: why not have <hi rend="italic">used</hi> such as in Hansard? By the way, I do not yet know <hi rend="italic">the size</hi> of Tregear’s.</p>
         <p>I return yr. clipping re Frith’s Moa. I did not want to see <hi rend="italic">this</hi>—but to know something of F’s. Book—but my curiosity is satisfied. I see, I had confounded it w. the <hi rend="italic">series</hi> of vols. (in L. &amp; B’s “My. Record” for Septr., &amp; well displayed) called “The Story of the Nations”, of which I have “The Jews under the Romans.” I also enclose a scrap from an envelope, just to hand, &amp; the notepaper is similarly <hi rend="italic">adorned</hi>!—&amp; a clipping from the Lond. “Standard.” Don’t trouble yourself to return L. &amp; B’s. memo. (Reviews) <hi rend="italic">receipted</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I shall write to Col. Secy. <hi rend="italic">re</hi> J. Whs. 4 vols.—next wk., I have much to do just now in wtg. way, as S.F. M. leaves soon.</p>
         <p>I have a long letter from a Mr H.W. Dawson, <hi rend="italic">Akaroa</hi>, (who, or what, is he?) <hi rend="italic">beginning</hi> thus—“Kindly send me your “3.Lity. P.,” &amp; a list of yr. other wks.”—enclosing 5/- P. Note, &amp; 6 1d. Stamps:—he must wait till I return to N. I don’t think Craig has a copy, &amp; I have only 2– or 3 left. He asks lots of questions!! re meaning of Maori words: more than I am willing to reply to: he had better get copy of Tregear’s Dy. (I shall tell him of it)—I have but <hi rend="italic">one</hi> copy left of “<hi rend="italic">Wi’s</hi> First Book,” <hi rend="italic">Part I</hi>:—more of II. I foolishly gave away a number.</p>
         <p>Your <hi rend="italic">critique</hi> on J. Wh.. is correct—<hi rend="italic">again &amp; I go w. you</hi>: am pleased to have your <hi rend="italic">interesting</hi> acct. of the <hi rend="italic">commencement</hi> of the exhuming of his papers! <hi rend="italic">Capital</hi>: good, you had got all that <hi rend="italic">from Tregear</hi>!!!—Then yours on Gudgeon &amp; Tam. McD., also <hi rend="underline italic">good</hi>. In looking into “Review” (at p.587) I find “<hi rend="italic">mana</hi> (force of character)” and “<hi rend="italic">karakia </hi>(creed)”—!!! from G. <hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi> Prof. Owen’s remark, p.73. vol. XIV. Trans. N.Z. I.—at close of my p. on “Color S.of M.,” (which you were lately reading)—so applicable <hi rend="italic">here</hi>.—Am not a little pleased to know that you found time to <hi rend="italic">read again</hi> that p.—it (w. <hi rend="italic">addendum</hi>) was one of my favourite ones; &amp; I have had letters from Doctors—at Home Germany, &amp; Melbourne, about it. I may <hi rend="italic">tell </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>—that I have often thought of reprinting, w. additions, all <hi rend="italic">those</hi> papers of mine (excluding Botanical) in Trans. including Essay on Maoris in Vol. I.—&amp; perhaps would do so, if <hi rend="italic">you</hi> were still here in business,—adding thereto, my unfinished one on Hawaiki.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">You say</hi>—“You say, yr. maternal grandfr. was a Wesleyan” (!!!) Nay, <hi rend="italic">not so</hi>, or if so, an <hi rend="italic">error</hi>: the Early Wesleyan Preachers (some of them) found harbour in his <hi rend="italic">large</hi> house, at a time when such was not readily afforded, (<hi rend="italic">before my </hi>day<hi rend="italic">.</hi>)—<hi rend="italic">He</hi> had a pew in the Wn. chapel, a <hi rend="italic">fine</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">stone</hi> building:—<hi rend="italic">also</hi> in the Baptist Ch., &amp; <hi rend="italic">also</hi> in the Congl. Chapel,—in <hi rend="italic">all</hi> I have often gone w. him to D.S. When he died he was buried (by side of his wife) in the <hi rend="italic">small</hi> ground of the <hi rend="italic">last</hi> mentioned.</p>
         <p>I can well understand yr. bror. getting a reply from you, <hi rend="italic">at Wgn</hi>. <hi rend="italic">before</hi> his obtaining one from <hi rend="italic">Norsewood</hi>.—</p>
         <p>You give a curious coincidence of the arrival of 2 letters on same matter, at 1 time: so, <hi rend="italic">here now</hi>: Your remark on the <hi rend="italic">Moa</hi>, as given by Buller in his big book, &amp; W.C.—is good: but here is Hill’s, written same time &amp; recd. by me at same P.O. delivery—in which he says—“I have just got Buller’s Birds: I have read his art. on the Moa, and <hi rend="italic">like it very much</hi>.” (!) [But I <hi rend="italic">don’t</hi> like the <hi rend="italic">tone</hi> of H’s letter: <hi rend="underline italic">long</hi> overdue.]</p>
         <p>I am very desirous of knowing something of Will’s case—Opotiki:—the Bp. is there now. Our N. papers are full of Racing &amp;c &amp;c.—<hi rend="italic">several sudden</hi> deaths lately: Sebley, Senior, among them. You may recollect him. I wholly forget <hi rend="italic">that</hi> p. of J. Wh. on the “Greenstone Mako.” Do you recollect <hi rend="italic">what year</hi>, pubd. in <hi rend="italic">D.T</hi>.?</p>
         <p>Now a last word about myself:—<lb/>1.) I am <hi rend="italic">here</hi> until (say) 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> or 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> proxo:—“time up” of Ret. Ticket.—so, should Ts. Dy. be ready some time before, add. <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, but if not, <hi rend="italic">there</hi>—N.—</p>
         <p>2.) Robertshawe has long wished to visit Weber Dist., &amp; he leaves today, rtg. on My. next: &amp; I have to take <hi rend="italic">both</hi> services <hi rend="italic">here</hi> on Sy. next: may my strength (physical, mental, spl.) be equal to the day! I feel weak, and so <hi rend="underline italic">waste</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">a deal of precious time</hi>: but the weather being again fine (it was wet on Monday), I took a long walk &amp;c <hi rend="italic">in forests</hi> on Tuesday, &amp; a still much longer one on Saturday last, &amp; though I return <hi rend="italic">completely knocked up, &amp; wet thro’ w. perspiration from sheer weakness</hi>, yet I believe such extra &amp; heavy exertions really do me good:—But I think, <hi rend="italic">I am failing</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">fast</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I feel your absence more &amp; more as the days roll by—but I see you are doing &amp; <hi rend="italic">gaining</hi> good for the <hi rend="italic">future</hi> where you are. Act, my friend like the Bee: gather <hi rend="italic">honey</hi> from <hi rend="italic">all</hi> flowers! &amp; store up.—If I feel, <hi rend="italic">here</hi> our separation, how much more shall I feel it at N. where I really have <hi rend="italic">no visitors now</hi>. By the way, Hill says—“had a Cl. mtg. on Thy. (12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>) a resoln. passed asking H. to send in a list of all his deposits in M. Also, to write to <hi rend="italic">all</hi> Mrs. likely to contrib. Papers, askg. for help this session.”—</p>
         <p>     Once more good bye</p>
         <p>     With kindest regards &amp; very best wishes. Bel. me ever</p>
         <p>                     Yours sincerely &amp; affy.</p>
         <p>                                             W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
