<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0370">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1878 May 21: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4. Letter addressed to “A. Luff Esq., 135, East India Road, Poplar, London” and endorsed “Rec’d July 9th./78”.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1878-05-21">1878 May 21</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1878 May 21: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-327" place="foot" n="327"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4. Letter addressed to “A. Luff Esq., 135, East India Road, Poplar, London” and endorsed “Rec’d July 9th./78”.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand. May 21. <lb/>1878.</p>
         <p>A. Luff Esq.,</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir</p>
         <p>Your welcome letter of March 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. arrived here on the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. inst., and I thank you for it, &amp; right glad was I to know that you were got through another Northern winter &amp; were <hi rend="italic">all well</hi>. A mercy to be thankful for! I was gratified in finding that you had received the Photos. (N.Z. Scenery) safely: I note what you say <hi rend="italic">re</hi> a view of Napier, &amp; if there were <hi rend="italic">such</hi> an one (or more) I would have sent it; I have 2–3 times spoken to Collie,<note xml:id="ftn2-328" place="foot" n="328"> W. Collie, Napier photographer.</note> &amp; to others here, about taking view<hi rend="underline italic">s</hi> of the town (some from my hill,) but not yet have they done anything. Yesterday I saw a new <hi rend="italic">one</hi> taken from “Mt. Helicon” way (<hi rend="italic">again</hi>!)—perhaps ere long they may take some others &amp; then <hi rend="underline italic">I’ll not forget you</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">With you</hi> I “feel annoyed” at Witty’s not paying you for the Land: can only say, hope he will <hi rend="italic">soon</hi>: his Wairoa lands have <hi rend="italic">all</hi> been advertised to be sold by auction, cut up into suitable lots, and I think the day of sale was <hi rend="italic">last</hi> week: I’ll enquire ere I close this; but, possibly, none were sold; he published <hi rend="italic">his Reserve</hi> p. with each section (<hi rend="italic">my old</hi> plan, you may recollect) but I fear much too high. Wairoa does not stand high in the market just now—the Bar is the drawback there; besides Pov. Bay lands are to the field (the <hi rend="italic">great auction</hi> at Gisborne took place there <hi rend="italic">this day</hi>, &amp; by telegrams in “D.T.” this evening, all town sections sold very high,)—I have had another letter from Black <hi rend="italic">re </hi>your land at Wairoa, which I enclose, also a copy of mine in reply. I had written to him on receipt of yours of Jany., telling him what you had said,—and that I, <hi rend="italic">then</hi>, hoped to be at Wairoa shortly, on school matters, when I would see him, &amp;c, &amp;c. I cannot learn that the piece in question is worth much; I have asked Mr. Grubb, your friend, to make enquiry (privately) for me,—or, rather, for you,—which he will do. I also enclose other memoranda relative to your Land at “Foxton,”—these will tell their own tale; I have kept the rect. I lost no time in seeing Capt. Bower (Town Clerk) <hi rend="italic">re </hi>your “Suburban Section No. 54”, and we <hi rend="italic">nearly </hi>got warm over it, B. asserting the correctness of the demand, &amp;c. &amp;c.—though, after much enquiry &amp; tumbling over Books, &amp; going to Regr. Office, it turned out that <hi rend="italic">you had a sub-section </hi>of Subn. Sn. 54 (next to P. Bourke’s I think)—<hi rend="italic">now</hi> occupied by Horace Baker!—I <hi rend="italic">wished</hi> you had told me <hi rend="italic">that</hi> in your letter—H.B. said, he would pay <hi rend="italic">the present Rates, &amp;c, &amp;c.</hi> However, I <hi rend="italic">never knew </hi>that you had any land <hi rend="italic">there</hi>:—I think there is <hi rend="italic">no chance</hi> of your old premises (Sea-Corner of Em. St.) ever coming onto the market, &amp; so into your hands.—I told you, in my last of Mackay’s new House thereaway; &amp; now Lascelles is thinking of building on the ground he holds on lease from Poole, w. <hi rend="italic">purchg. clause</hi>;—which is between your office &amp; Neal &amp; Close’s. I had omitted, when writing of your Wairoa land, to say, that I don’t think Black would, for a moment, listen to a <hi rend="italic">Lease </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">without</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>a<hi rend="italic"> pg. clause</hi>,—I believe you know that I have never attempted it,—but if B. again writes to me, &amp; so affords me the opportunity, I will try him concerning it.</p>
         <p>I fear the Grammar Sch. Co. is in a mess: I have long seen that <hi rend="italic">coming</hi>: I have a fancy that <hi rend="italic">you</hi> are a shareholder; but I hope not. Lately, the Co. held a meeting. Holder resigned his <hi rend="italic">Hony. </hi>Secy.-ship, &amp;c.—a call of £1. a share is made; I see <hi rend="italic">W.</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> Smith</hi> is now the <hi rend="italic">paid </hi>Secy., &amp; in this mg’s. Herald, <hi rend="italic">2</hi> advertisements, each offg. 5 shares in the Co. as a gift to whoever would accept them!!!—I will see W.S., &amp; if you <hi rend="italic">are </hi>a shareholder, <hi rend="italic">will</hi> (if needs be), <hi rend="italic">pay the demand on you</hi>.</p>
         <p>I was really grieved to read—in yours—that you had <hi rend="italic">again </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">lost</hi> on Inv. of Saddlery to Venney. Do you <hi rend="italic">act wisely</hi>—in <hi rend="italic">so</hi> sending out? I have heard it said, more than once,—that if <hi rend="italic">you would </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">act as an Agent</hi>, you might do very well.—</p>
         <p>I commence my own matters, proper, on another sheet. First (as I have been writing about <hi rend="italic">land</hi>,) I may tell you I have had my share of Lawyers &amp; Deeds, since my last to you;—the threat of an immediate Writ, brought Sladen to his senses, (after his <hi rend="italic">own two</hi> lawyers, Carlile, &amp; Cotterill, going <hi rend="italic">against him</hi>!) and so he has <hi rend="italic">paid</hi> that £1000. with all expenses:—obliged to <hi rend="italic">serve</hi> a <hi rend="italic">Writ</hi> of <hi rend="italic">re-entry</hi> on Mackey, which brought him to reason (?)—he employed Carlile, &amp; that at last, is just <hi rend="italic">settled</hi>,—M. borrowing £<hi rend="underline italic">900</hi>. from Lyndon at 9%, on the land in question &amp; paying me £600. for it: so that, within a few months, I have recd. £<hi rend="italic">2000</hi>. for Lands (viz. as above &amp; £400. from MacKenzie,)—never so much <hi rend="italic">Cash </hi>before!! but all the worse for me: I have banked it at 5½%—which will only give about ½ of what I was receiving from them; but I am <hi rend="italic">both apprehensive</hi> in lending on mortgage, &amp; utterly <hi rend="italic">dislike all such</hi> transactions: my disposition tends wholly another way.—McKay might have managed differently, &amp; far better for himself,—but he was ashamed to <hi rend="italic">see</hi> me;—one thing is certain M. will never possess it—never pay the £900. to L.;—&amp; L. will have his Int. when due. It grieved me (as I told Lasc. &amp; Carlile) in signing the Conveyance, that I was doing it to pay M’s. public-house, &amp; similar debts; his Creditors were all open-mouthed <hi rend="underline italic">waiting</hi>! That Land is now worth £9, £10 per ac. in market, &amp; sold by me for £4.—There are other leases, also, among minor tenants (Edser, &amp; Goddard, &amp; possibly T. Stewart, Porangahau) &amp; Scorgie gives up paddock—no grass—owing to long drought. I mention all this <hi rend="underline italic">to you</hi> because, as I am now <hi rend="underline italic">out</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>of Inspectorship, it will behove me to be careful,—&amp; so I have written to my Boys in England. However, it is what <hi rend="italic">I have always done</hi>, (from <hi rend="italic">before</hi> I came to N.Z.)—to live <hi rend="italic">within </hi>my Income; &amp; so I <hi rend="italic">can</hi> do it still.—</p>
         <p>My last to you was on 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. April; I was then about leaving for inland School Inspection, and <hi rend="italic">I had been given to understand</hi> that <hi rend="italic">if I would</hi> become a Candidate for the Office of Inspector, <hi rend="underline italic">I was sure</hi>. I<hi rend="italic"> believed this</hi>. (The <hi rend="italic">old</hi> Board (<hi rend="italic">individually</hi>) had wished me to withdraw my resign.—&amp; so w. several of the <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Board). The <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Board was to meet on 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. April &amp; I <hi rend="italic">expected</hi> a telegram on that day from Fannin at Waipukurau, where I had planned to be—at that school; (intending to go on by coach to Wallingford &amp; Porangahau)—night came, &amp; <hi rend="italic">no</hi> telegram! the next morng. got Herald, &amp; saw how things were, &amp;, as Board had adjourned till May <hi rend="italic">2</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">nd</hi>., I now <hi rend="italic">gave way</hi> to Teachers, Schools, old Settlers, Parents &amp;c, &amp;c., and sent in a Letter to the Board offering my services: but they would not have me!! At all events, Sutton, and J.N. Williams (<hi rend="italic">Archdeacon’s brother</hi>) were <hi rend="italic">absent</hi> pheasant shooting,—and the adverse party gained an easy victory. I regret that I wrote that <hi rend="italic">last</hi> letter, <hi rend="italic">under all the circumstances</hi>: I regret that Mr. Ormond &amp; Capt. Russell should have <hi rend="italic">so</hi> exerted themselves in vain on my behalf: and I regret that <hi rend="italic">your</hi> friend Mr. Sidey (whom I had also supposed to be mine, or, at least, <hi rend="italic">friendly</hi>,) should have <hi rend="italic">so gone against me</hi>, and joined Mr. Lee (the <hi rend="italic">R.C. servant</hi>) &amp; Rechab. Harding! I had heard inland a month before, that <hi rend="italic">John</hi> H. had been bragging what son <hi rend="italic">R</hi>. would try to do, (owing to their narrow Rechabite views),—and I did not expect any favour from the <hi rend="underline italic">High</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Church</hi> woman, Miss Herbert:—however, <hi rend="italic">it is done</hi>! I<hi rend="italic"> felt the shock</hi>: but now it is over, &amp; it <hi rend="italic">may</hi> prove for the best. To add to it however, they give the <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Inspector <hi rend="italic">£100. more</hi> (£400. and £150:) <hi rend="italic">Last</hi> year (Jany.) I had asked for increase—then only £150.—&amp; was refused. One thing is certain—that under the <hi rend="italic">new</hi> system, the Inspr. will <hi rend="italic">not</hi> have the mass of Clerical work (<hi rend="italic">figures</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">computations</hi> on Capitation, &amp;c, &amp;c,) I had to perform. I have recd. much of condolence, &amp;c, &amp;c. from Teachers &amp; from many others. You will see, in Herald, what took place at Board Meetings, &amp; <hi rend="italic">my letter</hi> also, which <hi rend="underline italic">I sent &amp; got inserted in its proper place</hi>—<hi rend="italic">it was omitted by Editor</hi>!<note xml:id="ftn2-329" place="foot" n="329"> Published with the Hawke’s Bay Board of Education report in the <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> of 4 May 1878.</note>
         </p>
         <p>But I have plenty to do. On my return from Waipukurau I set to “with a will” &amp; wrote a paper for our Institute, which I read last Monday (13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.)—not many (of course) were present, there being great “counter-attractions” that night, <hi rend="italic">viz</hi>., the last night of the Celebrated Opera Co.,—but among them were Dr. Spencer, Locke, Weber, Holder &amp; his son, J.A. Smith, Sturm, Dr. de Lisle, &amp; the new Bp. of Waiapu (these last 2, w. Dr. Frood of Waipukurau were afterwards elected Members: &amp; now I am preparing for our <hi rend="italic">Annual</hi> meeting (3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>. proxo.) and for future <hi rend="italic">Ordinary</hi> meetings—once a month, at each of which I hope to be a contributor—of a Paper. I was not a little surprised on seeing the <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Bp. (we were introduced by Dr. L.)—he sat the whole time (nearly 2 hours), &amp; seemed interested: my subject too was in many respects <hi rend="italic">suitable for him</hi>: I hope you may yet see <hi rend="italic">that Paper printed</hi>.—–</p>
         <p>And now I hope to have time to put my Herbarium, Shells, Fossils, Minerals, &amp;c, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">in order</hi>; (some have not seen the light for <hi rend="italic">over 30</hi> years!!) and my Papers too: so you may see, I have plenty to do. My health is very good just now, &amp; so it has generally been throughout 78, notwithstanding some trials, inland, in travelling in high winds, &amp;c. </p>
         <p>More than 2 years back I had let a section at Waipawa to Sebley (it was next to his own house), &amp; on Saturday last he called to ask me to take it back!—which I agreed to do, &amp; to give up the rent. Poor fellow! all those years struggling &amp; done nothing! now thinking of working as a journeyman,—or try his luck at Pov. Bay. He tells me, it is the same with Trestrail, who laments his leaving Holt’s; &amp; Moggridge is now working there as a Journeyman.—I feel sorry for Sebley w. his large family.</p>
         <p>I have seen <hi rend="italic">very little</hi> of your friend Grubb, I think he has plenty to do <hi rend="italic">during </hi>Off. hours, &amp; then after Off. hours he goes home: if he lived this way I might, <hi rend="italic">perhaps</hi>, see him. I shall give up looking-in at P.O. <hi rend="italic">Now</hi> I have <hi rend="italic">no</hi> place to go <hi rend="italic">into</hi> in the town, (save Athenæum, which I <hi rend="italic">dislike</hi>—this place too, I am told by Dr. S., is &amp; must come to grief!—unless something extraordinary is done for it,) so I shall go to town <hi rend="italic">but little</hi>. I almost wish I were a Memb. of H.B. Club!! Lots of petty Bankrupts! &amp; <hi rend="italic">Ingles</hi>, has, at last, joined the no., cheating poor P.D. his rent—nearly 2 years due! &amp; the fellow sitting on the Bench(!!) occasionally at Waipawa. Not but that he is just as good as Bridge, <hi rend="italic">Rechab</hi>. H., Sandy Grant, Herrick, &amp;c., a queer lot of J.P’s. A <hi rend="italic">new one</hi> just added—in Gaisford!!—thank H.R.R. for that, &amp; Birch. Old Hapuku is dying &amp; has been some time about it: such work for the Lawyers! in will making &amp; unmaking!! H.R.R. is suing Arihi in Sup. Court. for debt: I am told it is really awful to see R’s a/c.—Int. &amp; Compound Int., quarter after quarter!!!</p>
         <p>P.D. is very <hi rend="italic">much cast down</hi>—looking really bad; <hi rend="italic">great trouble</hi> and loss from staggers in sheep; 27 in one day, &amp; valuable animals: Ansel, Tiffen &amp; others, also, complain of the same. Our winter has begun,—I have a fire in parlour—but weather still delightfully fine,—sun-shiny, blue sky &amp; blue sea, &amp; bracing fine healthy weather.—A few showers have fallen, &amp; the hill is beginning to <hi rend="italic">look</hi> green again. Webb has <hi rend="italic">had </hi>to <hi rend="italic">make</hi> an apology!! Mrs Bousfield has been staying at Fannin’s, to his annoyance! Grindell, the <hi rend="italic">fool </hi>has been on a <hi rend="italic">spree</hi>. And now, I think, I am <hi rend="italic">out</hi> of your debt for Letter writing, &amp; something to my credit. Thanks for your many Papers—but “Statist,” “Financier,” &amp; <hi rend="italic">all of that breed </hi>I hasten off to Grubb without looking at them. I <hi rend="italic">do not read anything of theWar</hi>, save our short telegrams; neither do I read any of the articles—on <hi rend="italic">such matters</hi>—in the “Weekly Times,” possibly, I may give up Newsp. reading altogether.—–</p>
         <p>I intend enclosing some money,—also a small Order, which I will thank you to get executed for me. <hi rend="italic">If you think well </hi>of giving it to Dixon &amp; Co., or to any other;—but I leave that with you. I shall write to Wesley by this Mail, I send him an Order for Books; both for Institute &amp; for myself: we have a Council meetg.today. I am not algether satisfied w. Wesley, but I fear I cannot help myself.—I shall send him a Draft also, £50.—Now that I have determined on remaining here—during the remainder of my (<hi rend="italic">now, short</hi>) term, I shall do all the little I can to make myself comfortable: as this depends, mainly, on <hi rend="italic">myself</hi>.</p>
         <p rend="end">Saturday 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Yesterday was Queen’s Birthday—the town was shut up; Withers took volunteers &amp;c. to Green Meadows; the day was cloudy but fine. I send you this Morning’s paper, which will give you an account of their doings generally. Hapuku died yesterday. By a late copy of an Australian paper I find that <hi rend="italic">old</hi> Mr. Seed is dead—I suppose you knew him: I send you a large lot of Papers this time (24 packets in all), one being on Standards N.Z. today—you will find much to interest <hi rend="italic">you</hi> in <hi rend="italic">many</hi> of them—I only hope you do <hi rend="italic">not</hi> get them from <hi rend="italic">others</hi> here as well. On one I have placed our <hi rend="italic">new</hi> postal wrapper, sold 18 for 10d at P.O. with, of course, only the one ½d. stamp printed on them. In some of the papers you kindly sent you marked <hi rend="italic">Stanley’s </hi>proceedings: I never read anything of his,—I <hi rend="italic">dislike</hi> him <hi rend="underline italic">greatly</hi>—an <hi rend="italic">American </hi>mosstrooper &amp; trickster; he and the Czar of Russia I place together for their murderous villainous &amp; low cunning.</p>
         <p>I was in town on Thursday—to get Bk. Drafts &amp; to attend meeting of Robertson &amp; Drummond’s Creditors; hope these (R. &amp; D.) may yet be saved from smashing,—They are doing a great business (even Barry allows this). They have £600. <hi rend="italic">good</hi> debts (so B. says), &amp; only require £300. to pay off all their Creds. @ 10/-—Money cannot be got in—people will <hi rend="italic">not pay</hi>, is the cry every where,—I saw Kinross, also Tiffen, &amp; tried to learn <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Witty’s auction; both were of opinion that nothing was sold,—reserves much too high &amp; the “Bar” bringing Wairoa <hi rend="italic">down</hi> in the market: then there were the “counter attractions” at Gisborne! where the people seem to have been mad! Tiffen, &amp; J.N.W. had monies to invest at Gisborne, but wisely kept back. T. says, that, Witty has sold his house on hill to <hi rend="italic">Rees</hi>: but then Rees it is <hi rend="italic">too well known</hi> has no money.</p>
         <p>Two days ago I received <hi rend="italic">the official</hi> letter from the Board (see Paper) in which the Board thanks me for past Services &amp; regrets my having resigned! And O., as chairman, adds his testimony during the past when he was Super. to the same effect; had I time I would give <hi rend="italic">you</hi> a copy of it. I have been subsequently asked from Country to allow myself to be nomd. for vacant seat at Board—but I <hi rend="italic">have declined</hi>, although I have little doubt of being returned: <hi rend="italic">better</hi>, however, <hi rend="italic">away</hi>.—</p>
         <p>Ingles, I believe, will be saved from whitewashing, by L. &amp; Sydney J.,—the Creds. agreeing, at last to take 10/- (they would <hi rend="italic">not</hi> at <hi rend="italic">first</hi> meeting), hence the notice. Old Wilson got into a rage &amp; said, “there then, go into Court, you won’t have 1/- in the ₤!” I. does not owe much—poor P.D. is the greatest Cr., &amp; least able to bear the loss.</p>
         <p>I hope I shall <hi rend="italic">not </hi>displease you with the little Order; <hi rend="italic">but then you are at full liberty to pass it on, as I have said. </hi>Indeed I should have sent it to Dixon, but I don’t exactly know if he would care to execute it,—owing to the L.S. <hi rend="italic">Books. </hi>And I remember what you used to say about <hi rend="italic">good </hi>winds—port in particular. Not that I use much of that; though I do of <hi rend="italic">Porter</hi>, or stout, preferring Guiness to all other; of this I use “<hi rend="italic">pint</hi>” bottle daily; this is 10/6 doz. in town, here, which, w. breakage, &amp;c, is nearly 1/- and I think I can get it from England w. expenses at much less. I prefer the Cornish “Sardines” (small pilchards) to the French fish,—&amp; so do <hi rend="italic">all</hi> who have tried them <hi rend="italic">here</hi>. Let all the good (including Wesley’s) come together, even if one lot should be detained for the other—<hi rend="italic">to save expense</hi>.</p>
         <p>We have had a large no. of deaths, not confined to Town, &amp; most certainly <hi rend="italic">not owing to Swamp</hi>! Though <hi rend="italic">rabid R. Price</hi> says so! our <hi rend="italic">old Dr</hi>., H., is just the same. Fannin getting <hi rend="italic">redder &amp; redder.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>And now I must conclude. I hope this may find you &amp; yours well, and with kind regards and every good wish for your welfare, believe me ever,</p>
         <p>Yours truly</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>