<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0819">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 February 20: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-02-20">1892 February 20</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 February 20: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-572" place="foot" n="572"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke,<lb/>Saty. nt., X p.m.,<lb/>20/II/92</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>I duly recd. your kind &amp; long letter of the 14<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst.,—and it seems pretty clear to me, that if I do not begin a letter to you tonight (tho’ late) I shall not write one for several days, as early days of next wk. must be devoted to Eng. Mail.—As usual there is much in yours I should like to <hi rend="italic">talk over </hi>w. you: but I postpone yours.—</p>
         <p>Of course you will have heard of the death of the Bishop of Waiapu’s sister, from the fell Influenza! She died on the 7<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., the Bp. had come back purposely to see her on the 6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., spent more than a week at N., &amp; had just returned to Wgn. &amp; taken his seat in the Synod! I believe he is still there: but I <hi rend="italic">know </hi>nothing. I suppose you knew Shugar? he, too, died this mg. at Ormondville after only a few days illness! caught cold at Norsewood (an Influenza attack) and returned wet to Ormondville (to which place he had removed from Dvk. only a few days before), rapid Inflam. of lungs followed, all day yesterday in delirious agony!—Our Dr. <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, Macallan, went to see him on Thursday evg. but too late to be of any service: there are others very ill in this Bush Dist.—It has been raining <hi rend="italic">heavily </hi>here (&amp; I believe at Napier &amp; at Gisborne) for 3 days, with no present prospect of its clearing: notwithstanding, I went to Makotuku yesty. aftn. &amp; returned at night,—having arranged from Woodville last My. to meet some of my old Norsewood friends <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, and I did not like to put them off: in the train w. me from this place was Mrs Paterson &amp; her child, returning to N., they had been here at Wallace’s a week or more.—–</p>
         <p>Last Saty. I went again to Wdv. for the Sunday’s Ch. duty, weather fine; but the congn. small 45 (of adults—only 9 men!! in the mg., one of them being our friend Large from N., who w. wife on their way to Wgn.) but in the evg it was good, Ch. nearly filled: there had been some bungle, so that the folks were not <hi rend="italic">sure </hi>of any service; the advt. that Robertshawe wrote &amp; posted to Haggen on Friday, was only recd. on <hi rend="italic">My</hi>. by H.—I got through the duty <hi rend="italic">well</hi>—but <hi rend="italic">felt </hi>my exertions at night, restless, cough, &amp; no sleep. However I am I think, steadily improving in genl. health; though certain strange anomalous pains in my chest keep up, and I still <hi rend="underline italic">feel</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">weak</hi>—<hi rend="italic">go out nowhere</hi>! Robertshawe (who has long wished again to visit his old flock &amp; building) is gone thither today (in pouring rain) leaving me to do my best here in his Ch. tomorrow.</p>
         <p>I notice, in this mg’s. “Herald,” the <hi rend="italic">Ann. Meeting </hi>of our H.B. Instit. is called for Monday next, (at last!) &amp;, curiously enough, it is stated:—‘Business: annual Report and Balance Sheet.’ Is that to be <hi rend="italic">all</hi>? We shall see. Mr. Hill, in his late letters (2) doesnt allude to it at all.</p>
         <p>Another curious (<hi rend="italic">very</hi>!) item of news is, that of Hemi Carroll becoming one of Ballance’s Ministry!!! While from this Evening’s Papers I gather the “Evg. News” is again to be resuscitated!!—[Pain in chest severe, w. cough, <hi rend="italic">increased by leaning forward</hi>—so I <hi rend="italic">stop</hi>. <hi rend="underline italic">Good night</hi>.]</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="underline italic">24</hi>
            <hi rend="sup underline italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">. noon</hi>.—I have finished with my usual monthly <hi rend="italic">trouble</hi>, and so I go on here—for a short space. I was pleased to see in a late Wgn. paper, advt. of “Philosophl.” for <hi rend="italic">tonight</hi>: hope <hi rend="italic">you </hi>may enjoy a good Meeting. Strange to say, I recd. a letter from Hill <hi rend="italic">on My. evg. 22</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">nd</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>(written at Bluff Hill <hi rend="italic">that mg.</hi>), in which he says, he shall <hi rend="italic">nom. me </hi>as Presidenjt for ’92—unless he gets a wire from me to the contrary” now the T. Off. closes here at V, so <hi rend="italic">I could not wire</hi>: but in “Herald” of yesty. (Tuesday) in acct. of that Meeting—Hill <hi rend="italic">is </hi>Pt. The “Report” (as therein given) is a very <hi rend="italic">bald </hi>one: I hope they don’t intend to publish it thus! <hi rend="italic">I cannot understand </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">the whole proceeding</hi>. Hill was to leave yesterday on <hi rend="italic">his N. round</hi>: in his long letter to me, he says he should go as far as Bay of Plenty, climb Mt. Edgcumbe, &amp;c &amp;c, on to Taupo, Moawhango, and (perhaps) by Whanganui W. Coast, &amp; then Woodville, &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c. He sent me a copy of his paper on Volcanic appearances, &amp;c, &amp;c, pubd. in “Austral. Ass. Sc.” (as you have also kindly done in yours, and Dr. Hector, also, his 2 papers therein). Hill’s, if I mistake not, is <hi rend="italic">much the same</hi> as his paper read before the H.B. Inst. in August. <hi rend="italic">I sincerely hope his Geologl. &amp; Volcanic zeal may not interfere with, or lessen, his far more serious &amp; useful duties. </hi>Of your Paper, <hi rend="italic">anon. </hi>It took me by surprise, as I was not aware (or had clean forgotten) you had furnished one.—</p>
         <p>We had very fine w. on Sunday 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>, and I managed to get pretty well through the 2 services—though felt worn—fagged! at night, walked back to hotel w. difficulty, good Congn. at night: small in <hi rend="italic">morning</hi>, always the case in Bush in <hi rend="italic">fine</hi> weather! I have to go to Woodv. for <hi rend="italic">next</hi> Sunday,—and then—what?——</p>
         <p>I find our Bp. is still at Wgn.—I suppose, on acct. of Mules’ consecration <hi rend="italic">today</hi>: I say nothing <hi rend="italic">re </hi>those unseemly <hi rend="italic">rows</hi> in that synod: though such serve to remind me of those of the Bps. at the Council of Nice, when they hammered out the Nicæan Creed. I also noticed (for the <hi rend="italic">first</hi> time) some of Luff’s Land advtd. in the Wgn. paper.—I am still “confined to my rooms”—just walking, occasionally, to P.O. <hi rend="italic">nearby</hi>—the extreme length of my present tether: am very much better, but still <hi rend="italic">very weak</hi>—wholly interfused (as it were) w. this Codlin M. or Phylloxera, the <hi rend="italic">remaining</hi> spawn of that Influenza, which is pre-eminent &amp; “runs through all things;”—several possess the same kind of feelings:—Waterworth, has been staying here seeking health and is ½ mis. about it: his Infl. attack was at Xmas. Just so,Robertshawe; Cowper (Knight’s partner a very strong man). I suppose you know Lymburn? formerly at Hastings: he is now here travg. exhibiting views &amp; lecturing on “Missions” and (I believe) collecting for Ch. “at Martinborough” (where that is I don’t know!)—Of course I lost my <hi rend="italic">return </hi>T. to N.! (16/6) and, if I don’t <hi rend="italic">see </hi>our Bp. on his returning to N. so as to talk w. him,—or hear from him—I purpose returning to Napier next week.——</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">25</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> night. </hi>Again I jog along! Have been very listless careless all this day!! and I confess <hi rend="italic">without</hi> feeling shame at my laziness! Yesterday I ordered from Bates, Bookseller, &amp;c. here, copies of “N.Z. Times” of <hi rend="italic">this mg. </hi>hoping to know something of <hi rend="italic">your Phil. </hi>Mtg. last night, but on recg. was woefully disappointed. I could almost fear Wgn. had too many good, or <hi rend="italic">big</hi>, things yesty—all in <hi rend="italic">one </hi>day!—I had a very long &amp; tiresome dream last night of your Phil. Mtg.—Mantell was the great, &amp; the <hi rend="italic">only </hi>speaking <hi rend="italic">opponent</hi>; Sir J.H. taking him up manfully, &amp;c, &amp;c.—<hi rend="italic">We</hi>, here (ex self) had expd. Bp. Waiapu would put in an appce. today, on his <hi rend="italic">return </hi>jy., but not so; of course we are anxious to know what he <hi rend="italic">may </hi>have done for Woodville,—as that, in a great measure, affects me &amp; my movements N. I enclose a curious clipping,<note xml:id="ftn3-573" place="foot" n="573"> It was about Lew Wallace’s <hi rend="italic">Ben Hur</hi>.</note> can you throw any light on it: it has been sevl. times advertised. C. has, at last, sent me “Whitr. Almc.” (but it is still <hi rend="italic">unopened</hi>!) On enquiry I obtained the names of Members who attended “Annl. Meeting” on Monday night, viz. Hill, Dr. Moore, Heath, Platford, Craig, Ringland, Lessong, Puckney, T.R. Cooper, &amp; G. White: <hi rend="italic">heoi ano</hi>!—now I will look (again) into your letter.—</p>
         <p>1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. You omitted to return my draft letter to Arnold—so I could not write by this M. <hi rend="italic">Don’t forget to send it back</hi>;—I was much pleased to find you agreed with it.</p>
         <p>2. I <hi rend="italic">smiled </hi>at an error of yours, you say, “stayed Sy. heard Mr. K. preach (<hi rend="underline italic">Fraser</hi> at Havelock)” Of course you menat our friend <hi rend="italic">Gt</hi>.</p>
         <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Re </hi>books: yes, get me a copy of Morris’ “Epic” (if to be had): I have seen, several times, in “Standard”—“<hi rend="italic">Little</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Minister</hi>” pubd. separately &amp; at a low fig. I suppose it to be the same as that in “G. Words.” 4. Right glad to know of yr. son being so much better. I will defer the <hi rend="italic">remr. </hi>of your letter till my next. I hope you are keeping well &amp; <hi rend="italic">not </hi>overworkg. yrself. If you write, say, on Thursday next that will find me here.—</p>
         <p>With kindest regards,</p>
         <p>Bel. me Yrs truly W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
