<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0866">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1893 April 12: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1893-04-12">1893 April 12</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1893 April 12: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-641" place="foot" n="641"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier<lb/>Wednesy. night<lb/>12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> Apl. 1893</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Your kind letter—with a choice lot of sundries. Ms. &amp; typl.—to hand last night—thanks for <hi rend="italic">all</hi>—but <hi rend="italic">this </hi>letter must be considered an irregular one—<hi rend="italic">out </hi>of due &amp; proper running, &amp;c.—–</p>
         <p>I write now for 2 reasons: 1.) I am off to Waipukurau—&amp; <hi rend="italic">there </hi>for <hi rend="italic">2 </hi>Sundays (16<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. &amp; 23<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>.)—so I purpose paying a visit to <hi rend="italic">Dvk</hi>. for 2–3 days, (2) I am sending Mr. Maskell—<hi rend="italic">through you</hi>—a lot of filthy blight spns. in a tin cannister—please take them to him, &amp; learn something about them. They <hi rend="italic">may </hi>have been already described by him—but it is only recently they have done me <hi rend="italic">heavy damage</hi>, which is also (at present) local &amp; peculiar. You may recollect my rather tall “cabbage trees” (Maori <hi rend="italic">Tii</hi>: = Cordyline australis)—about 20–25 yrs old &amp; tall: well this pest has <hi rend="italic">destroyed </hi>their bushy heads every leaf—&amp; that in a <hi rend="italic">very short</hi> time: my man knew of it <hi rend="italic">before</hi>, but he took me into the Garden (where, you know, I never <hi rend="italic">now </hi>go!) and showed me the piteous sight!!—what I send are cut from the bases of the leaves of Cordyline. Don’t trouble to write <hi rend="italic">purposely </hi>about them:—anon.—</p>
         <p>I have <hi rend="italic">recently </hi>(yesterday) received from Mr. Atkinson, Nelson, a copy of his book—ptd. <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, 70 close pps. small type—being a severe <hi rend="italic">critique </hi>on Tregear’s Dy. <hi rend="italic">You must see it some early day. </hi>It is in 3 papers read before their Socy., ’92: and I should suppose from his ptg. it <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, the said Papers have <hi rend="italic">not</hi> been sent to Sir J. Hector. Of course, I have <hi rend="italic">not yet </hi>read it—scarcely looked into it, but shall take it with me; moreover, I am still a stranger to Tregear’s Dy.—</p>
         <p>Last night more proofs from Sir J. Hector—my paper re T. White’s “Dog”. <hi rend="italic">Wholly </hi>composed, but with a judicious obsn., <hi rend="italic">written by H.</hi>,—asking me to “agree to suggestions made (portions <hi rend="italic">struck out</hi>—1 line at commencement, &amp; <hi rend="italic">last par.</hi>) to strike them out—such are all right for our Socy., but better not be pubd. for abroad”: and I have “readily &amp; thankfully acceded” to his request.————–</p>
         <p>C.D. Kennedy goes <hi rend="italic">Home</hi> by “Ruahine”—6 months leave. Walker (Herald) confd. to bed. Last wk. I wrote a note to Moreton (owner &amp; skilled painter of Pictures of S. Alps, &amp;c.)—which he has pubd. in 2 evg. p. I send you my copy.<lb/>—I fancy, “Herald” (swelling w. importance) must have<hi rend="italic">declined </hi>to come out on the follg. day <hi rend="italic">after </hi>them! For in M’s. latter of thanks—he says he had sent my L. to <hi rend="italic">all </hi>our p. for pubn.</p>
         <p>One word <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Bidwill—Chapman went but a <hi rend="italic">very little way </hi>into Taupo Dist.—just to <hi rend="italic">N. </hi>end of lake (I have been shown the spot!) C. was very <hi rend="italic">timid</hi>, &amp; was <hi rend="italic">not there </hi>(at Rotorua) in the time of the fighting—neither was <hi rend="italic">Brown at Matamata</hi>—both were at Paihia—with me. I can tell you a <hi rend="italic">lot</hi>—re same!—</p>
         <p>I may not write again, till <hi rend="italic">after </hi>my return to N., on (say) 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>             Kind regards &amp; best wishes—</p>
         <p>                             Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>                                                     W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>An advt. in p. from Jardine: 2 Bankrupts,—<hi rend="italic">together </hi>in 1 small advt.—1, a Maori (n. given) 20/- in the ₤. 1, young Dennett of Hastings—1/- in the ₤. (!!) and both <hi rend="italic">final</hi>.</p>
         <p>P.S. I was at Taradale last Sunday—staid all night, &amp; retd. by Rymer on My. Weather: <hi rend="italic">very fine 2 </hi>days, &amp; am well.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
