<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0583">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1884 November 23: to Balfour</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73378/">Balfour</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1884-11-23">1884 November 23</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1884 November 23: to Balfour<note xml:id="ftn3-272" place="foot" n="272"> ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier Sunday night <lb/>Nov 23rd 1884</p>
         <p>Mr D.P. Balfour</p>
         <p>My dear Sir</p>
         <p>Very likely you have been expecting a line from me before now, and in order that you may not be disappointed by next mail your way, I write to you this night. I think my last to you was about a month back—­the week before I went to the “Bush”. I left here on the 28th Oct, &amp; retur­ned last Wednesday night, Nov 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>—and found a rare lot of letters, papers, Books, &amp;c, awaiting me—among them your letter of 15th inst,—a bottle, a box, and a book:—aye, &amp; a small thin packet!!!. Well done Glenross; and I may add that I opened all of yours among the very first,—and now to your letter. The 2 “Lattice” Orchids complete (in 3 lots—blossoms, leaves, &amp; roots), are just what I supposed the plant to be—a <hi rend="italic">Pterostylis</hi>,<note xml:id="ftn3-273" place="foot" n="273">
               <hi rend="italic">Pterostylis patens</hi> Col.</note> &amp; very near a Pt. Banksii, but may be a difft. species,—this I cannot say until I examine &amp; dissect the hidden inner &amp; fine column of the flower; it seems to be a <hi rend="italic">new</hi> one I reared here, (of which I suppose I must have told you in my last)—I cut off the flower (unwillingly) &amp; put it into spirits the day of my leaving; it is much larger than these 2 of yours. I fear the roots (tubers) you so carefully sent,will be of no service—as to growing again—because it is the <hi rend="italic">wee new white</hi> one that is the tuber for next season, and this, I think, has been taken up too early; but I will try it.</p>
         <p>The “<hi rend="italic">barren</hi> seed stem of the Divot Orchid,” is (as I take it) <hi rend="italic">not</hi> such, but an <hi rend="italic">old</hi> fl<hi rend="underline">g</hi> stem that bore flowers.<note xml:id="ftn3-274" place="foot" n="274">
               <hi rend="italic">Sacrcochilus breviscapa</hi> Col. = <hi rend="italic">Drymoanthus adversus</hi>
            </note> I do not think that the reason of your D plants not blossoming is to be found in their being (now) on dead wood, as they all always do in the Orchid houses at Home; but, perhaps, owing to the <hi rend="italic">change</hi> from shade to sun, or from damp shelter to open dry exposure; or to winds. Your “<hi rend="italic">Corysanthes</hi>” I should like to see— “lock, stock, &amp; barrel”. You could put them up <hi rend="italic">loosely</hi> in thin paper, each sort separate &amp; marked 1, 2, 3, &amp;c, first marking on the papers in pencil, or ink, putting fine <hi rend="italic">damp</hi> (not wet) Moss loosely below &amp; above,—&amp; put all into a small tin box, <hi rend="italic">no earth</hi>. Better so than in spirits for first exam, as I can then see their natural colours, and can <hi rend="italic">report</hi> to Glenross.</p>
         <p>Your “Catalogue” surprised me; took away my breath!!; so many books, &amp; such a rare lot of <hi rend="italic">good</hi> ones, too; and then to put W.C. (or his wee bairnies) into it. However since you have done so, I must add thereto—have you a copy of Vol I “Trans N.Z. Inst”?. I think not; that contains two of my larger essays—one being <hi rend="italic">the</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">prize one </hi>(according to your Countrymen at Otago; <hi rend="italic">be sure, you let me know</hi>. Also; have you a copy of the Parliamentary Paper (of 1875), about the Maori Lexicon? let me know.</p>
         <p>You have had wet days at Glenross; so I, at the Bush, <hi rend="italic">a full share</hi>—never did less;. A few Mosses, Hepaticæ, &amp; Fungi were my gains!! some however, are <hi rend="italic">new</hi>. I left the Bush on Saturday 15th, for Waipukurau &amp; stayed there till the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>—<hi rend="italic">fine weather every day</hi>; I purpose returning to the dense Bush 1st week, or so, in Jany, Orchid hunting; in quest of my big <hi rend="italic">Gastrodia</hi>,<note xml:id="ftn3-275" place="foot" n="275">
               <hi rend="italic">Gastrodia leucopetala</hi> Col. = <hi rend="italic">G. cunninghamii</hi>.</note> mentioned in “Ruahine”.</p>
         <p>In returning from inland, Lascelles was in train with me. Next mng he sent me a small box of beautiful plants, flg spns, in lovely order from <hi rend="italic">Patea</hi> among them are some <hi rend="italic">new</hi> ones, of very large and difficult Genera (mostly Australian) and I have been working on one (off &amp; on) all day, &amp; hope to get through with another tomorrow. On Tuesday I <hi rend="italic">must be out</hi> on business. You will perceive that I have been writing to you as if it were holiday time at Glenross—instead of the middle of <hi rend="italic">heavy work</hi>—pardon me this. I would the weather were finer for the shearers. I, too, have lots to do; mostly for others. Hoping you are all well at Glenross, &amp; with kind re­gards,</p>
         <p>believe me </p>
         <p>Yours truly </p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>