<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1091">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1890 January 10 to Russell</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
         <p>Archives New Zealand</p>   
         <p>Transcription by Ian St George</p>
            <p>encoded into TEI by Melissa Bryant, 23.10.15</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1890-01-10">1890 January 10</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/72672/">Russell</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1890 January 10 to Russell (National Archives, Wellington)
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
      <p>
Napier</p>
<p>Jany. 10/90</p>
<p>My dear Capt. Russell</p>
<p>Your kind &amp; thoughtful note of the 7th. inst. (with Revise, &amp;c.) only reached me late this afternoon,—I reply at once.</p>
<p>1. I have made those alterations in pp. 13 &amp; 14, pointed out by you:—and I agree with you: indeed, such had occurred to me when making the Copy for Press,—only I thought it better to adhere to the old Ms. in its entirety (as stated by me in the Preface): Bp. P., also, being dead.—Further, you, my dear Sir, little know the abuse—the scorn—we had to endure from him and his officials. It rose to such a pitch, that, only a short time before the arrival of Capt. H, we had held our Public Meeting at Kororareka with him &amp; his priests—within his own bounds! Which lasted 2 days, and in the open air, too!!–</p>
<p>2. I have also, in accordance with your wish, made the alterations necessary, through the Appendices not being printed: please note, all I have written on the Revise is in red ink: of course, any further correction you may require, please make.</p>
<p>3. In accordance therewith I have written a fresh table of “Contents”.</p>
<p>I regret very much your not publishing with the brief Memo. 
some portions (at least) of the Appendix no.1,—especially those early public documents, petitions,—letter from Viscount Goderich, &amp;c.——I cannot help thinking, they very properly appertain thereto—as a kind of prologue to the Play:—also, my enquiry relative to the exact day in which Capt. Cook took possession of N.Z., &amp;c.—not yet commonly known!</p>
<p>I suppose, the little map of the locality in the Bay of Islands will also share the fate of the Appendices.—</p>
<p>I would that I had earlier known of the intention of the Government: as such would have saved me a deal of worry and labour.</p>
<p>Again thanking you my dear Capt. Russell—</p>
<p>I am, with kind regards, </p>
<p>yours faithfully,</p>
<p>Wm. Colenso.</p>
<p>Please direct that all Papers of the 2 Appendices may be returned to me. W.C.
</p>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI>