<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1003">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1897 August 30: to William Colenso</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL 88-103-1/17.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1897-08-30">1897 August 30</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1897 August 30: to William Colenso<note xml:id="ftn3-838" place="foot" n="838"> ATL 88-103-1/17.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand. <lb/>August 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., 1897.</p>
         <p>My dear Nephew William,</p>
         <p>Your short kind note of 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. June is to hand, and I write you a few lines in reply by this S.F. Mail—to thank you for it. I wrote to Willie by the last mail (August 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>.), and send him now a lot of papers, as usual—<hi rend="italic">one</hi> paper I send to <hi rend="italic">you, </hi>as it contains a Public letter in “Herald” about doings of my old R.C. antagonist,<note xml:id="ftn3-839" place="foot" n="839">
               <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald </hi>24 August 1897.</note>—and by last mail I sent you a copy of my Presdl. Address—then only just to hand. Both of these have been well received here: among papers to W. is Father Grogan’ s reply(?) I have only been <hi rend="italic">once</hi> into town since my last, weather against my going out—besides to ride to and from town, below, costs five shillings and as I have no business there, and walk <hi rend="italic">badly</hi>, I don’t go thither. My arm and hand are much better—I, last week, buttoned my shirt collar for <hi rend="italic">first time</hi>—after many trials! a great victory—but cannot yet hold a knife to cut a slice of bread, or penknife to sharpen lead pencil! fingers, however, are becoming more supple, but will not grasp.</p>
         <p>Am <hi rend="italic">very pleased</hi> in hearing of the success of your Son Ad. Hy. I hope <hi rend="italic">you</hi> and all our family are keeping well. Have been <hi rend="italic">extra</hi> busy of late w. much writing: arm and hand sometimes <hi rend="italic">complain</hi>. Our winter is past—but weather wet, yet mild: peach trees in fine bloom, Nature once more rejoicing.—</p>
         <p>Kindest regards to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>—<hi rend="underline italic">all</hi>.</p>
         <p>Your affect. Uncle</p>
         <p>W. Colenso</p>
         <p>31<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. Beautiful Day!</p>
         <p>A letter to hand from Palmerston N. (120 miles S. from Napier)—from a lady there:—“only fancy, a washerwoman had a child about 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. July and it is christened, “<hi rend="italic">Record Reign</hi>”.</p>
         <p>Mails lost nearly a month ago in fine steamer “Tasmania”—(not far from us), and now, at last! given up. Perhaps Penzance and other letters, etc., to me were in those mails.—W.C.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>