<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0940">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1895 July 14: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1895-07-14">1895 July 14</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1895 July 14: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-748" place="foot" n="748"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, July 14/95: <hi rend="italic">night</hi>.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>Your note of 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> (to hand <hi rend="italic">late </hi>last nt., &amp; by chance, too!) serves to remind me, I had <hi rend="italic">not </hi>ansd. your former one—of June 16<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. and so I write to you this nt. having no Ch. duty—&amp; this mg. <hi rend="italic">as a bearer</hi>, at Augustine’s. You <hi rend="italic">seem </hi>to forget the <hi rend="italic">state </hi>of my hand, loss of use of rt. thumb, &amp; always “<hi rend="italic">in</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">the way</hi>”—making it irksome to do—or rather <hi rend="italic">attempt </hi>to do—many things: it was only last week that I succeeded in buttoning collar of shirt! however the poor thumb is slowly getting round, a trouble to dress it every morng., w. <hi rend="italic">left </hi>hand. I have been backward in <hi rend="italic">many </hi>matters, &amp; the worst is—<hi rend="italic">alone</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">no help</hi>, neither friend at hand, &amp; lots of things <hi rend="italic">to do</hi>—awaiting me,—and <hi rend="italic">plenty </hi>of <hi rend="underline italic">outside</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">un</hi>necessary <hi rend="italic">trials</hi>—all coming together! Fortunately I have kept pretty well, save severe Rheum. <hi rend="italic">left </hi>arm last wk.</p>
         <p>You say you have yr. vol. “Trans.” ’95, I have not seen it—I suppose not yet <hi rend="italic">here</hi>: I sent a copy of “Waikare-m.” to McDougall (as it was owing to an art. in “D.T.”, last yr., that I took it up) &amp; he has <hi rend="italic">just noticed</hi> it: I am obliged to withhold sending copies to several<hi rend="italic"> members </hi>of N.Z.I., because I have <hi rend="italic">not enough </hi>to go round, &amp; <hi rend="italic">they </hi>will see my p. in <hi rend="italic">their vol.</hi> I hope you may read &amp; like the “Greenstone” p. I should have said a good deal more anent <hi rend="italic">Pounamu</hi> &amp; allies, had not Chapman (Dunedin) already a <hi rend="italic">long </hi>p. on it—of wheat &amp; <hi rend="italic">tares</hi>, as I told him.—–</p>
         <p>Of course I could do nothing for our <hi rend="italic">June </hi>mtg., and was <hi rend="italic">pressed hard </hi>by <hi rend="italic">all hands </hi>(D—, Hill, Craig, Large, Moore, Ringland, &amp; Co.) to do something for <hi rend="italic">July </hi>one (that <hi rend="italic">should</hi> have been on 8<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>)—well, I agreed;—&amp; worked <hi rend="italic">very hard</hi>, &amp; in <hi rend="italic">much pain</hi>. I found, however, <hi rend="italic">on 5</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>that the <hi rend="italic">next Room </hi>(!) was to be occupied with the <hi rend="underline italic">outrageous</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> Liedertafi</hi>! and so I wrote off to D.—that <hi rend="italic">I would not read, neither be there, on 8</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi>—<hi rend="italic">neither promise for Augt. Mtg.—</hi>and on 6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> aftn. D. &amp; Hill came hither—&amp; finally it was detd. to have it <hi rend="italic">tomorrow</hi>. My p. will be “On Tin Mines &amp; Mining in Cornwall”—<hi rend="italic">better still</hi>, 40–50 val. spns. of ores from those mines, recd. by me some 55 years ago, from my Uncle (Bp’s. father), &amp; packed by me in Bay Islands in ’44! &amp; now again seeing light!! but such a hunt I had for the case contg. them, &amp; shells, &amp;c, &amp;c.—I quite expect this <hi rend="italic">must </hi>be my <hi rend="italic">last p</hi>. save a small one on Botany—at, perhaps, <hi rend="italic">last mtg. </hi>Hill, is gazetted for <hi rend="italic">another </hi>“Ruapehu” p., and Lund, of Makotuku for one on ancient coins. For my part—I wish tomorrow nt. was <hi rend="italic">over</hi>! I take no pleasure in those Meetings now.</p>
         <p>Although I had <hi rend="italic">not </hi>written, I sent you sevl. Papers (D.T. &amp; H.) I hope you recd. them. Sunday 7<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> was a great day at Cathl. our <hi rend="italic">navals</hi>, &amp; those of “Ringarooma” &amp;c &amp;c—day too gloriously fine: I read Lesson, mg. &amp; evg. The Dean preached a <hi rend="italic">suitable </hi>serm., mg. (text—“they lightened the ship”) and Evg. Rev. <hi rend="italic">Haweis </hi>preached, text “unjust steward”, began vii.50—find. ix.7: such a discourse! “<hi rend="italic">greased lightg</hi>.” Jonathan would term it: from beg. to end no stop, no hesitation, &amp; such a clear ringing voice throughout!—Congn.—big, <hi rend="italic">crammed </hi>(&amp; <hi rend="italic">so</hi> in mg.) as still as mice! he said <hi rend="italic">many good </hi>things, <hi rend="italic">many </hi>deep ones (<hi rend="underline italic">stabs</hi>) warnings to yg. m. &amp; yg. w. (if <hi rend="italic">any present</hi>) who had <hi rend="italic">just left </hi>the narrow path, &amp; to <hi rend="underline italic">money</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> lovers</hi>! &amp; <hi rend="italic">in beg. </hi>he sd. “many of the Clergy did not open their mouths &amp; should not go into the pulpit”. What <hi rend="italic">I </hi>liked, above all, was his <hi rend="italic">long </hi>S., I wrote <hi rend="italic">same </hi>night inland upbraiding them for their <hi rend="underline italic">choice</hi> “15m Sermon”, &amp; no surrender!—When I last pd. at Dvk., I told them “I had heard of it, &amp; I hoped <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> would forgive them” &amp;c, &amp;c, &amp;c. I was w. Mr. H. in vestry, some time (only we 2). He knew my family at Home—party. late Bp. Natal, his son (now a Surgeon in Engd.) &amp; his daughter. Haweis is a <hi rend="italic">most peculiar looking </hi>very short man, obliged to use stick in Ch., &amp; also to get up into Cathl. pulpit! I thought he would “come down by the run”. Perhaps you have seen him—he has a most wonderful <hi rend="italic">memory</hi>! and also any amount of popular sayings—old &amp; new, but the “<hi rend="italic">unco guid</hi>” would not admire his Sermon.<note xml:id="ftn3-749" place="foot" n="749"> Reverend Hugh Reginald Haweis, incumbent of St James's, Marylebone: his unconventional methods of conducting the service, combined with his dwarfish figure and lively manner, attracted crowded congregations. He contributed largely to periodical literature and travelled a good deal abroad.</note> I send you a lot of clippings, and I have <hi rend="italic">found </hi>a copy (my <hi rend="italic">only</hi> one?) of an old tract printed w. Mr. Cotton’s w<hi rend="sup">c</hi>. of which I hadtold you, (my cat, somehow, had found out a box of papers &amp; clawed them to make a lair—kittens!!) I send it for you to <hi rend="italic">see</hi>, and <hi rend="underline italic">return</hi> (Don’t lose it, as you did the Printer’s letter (Ms.) I had lent you).</p>
         <p>I trust you &amp; yours are <hi rend="italic">all well</hi>. You say nothing of them—tho’ you do of your sister visitor. My man “Bob.” has been 3–4 wks. very unwell with a raging cold &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">cough</hi> (common here &amp; in Bush), he has called in Dr. Moore. Of course, has ceased going to P.O. at nights, &amp; sometimes in day—which, with many other shortcomings &amp;c &amp;c does not add to my comfort! I had to “dress” <hi rend="italic">purposely</hi> a few days ago to go to P.O. to post a L. Weather <hi rend="italic">very fine</hi> for nearly 3 wks. (one mg. only rain) but severe frost at nights—<hi rend="italic">ice</hi>. I am <hi rend="italic">glad </hi>to find you have <hi rend="italic">plenty </hi>of wk. but <hi rend="italic">don’t </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">wk. too hard</hi>—and <hi rend="italic">do </hi>take yr. <hi rend="italic">rest </hi>on the 7<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> day: <hi rend="underline italic">you require it</hi>. Did you know Whytock? Bookseller Hastings: a sad Bktcy. our friend Rev. R. Fraser let in for ₤120! which he <hi rend="italic">cannot </hi>well afford to lose (it was <hi rend="italic">lent</hi>, too, at 10%). I have not touched on <hi rend="italic">politics</hi> in this letter—“pitch – – – defiled”!—–</p>
         <p>Very kindest regards &amp; best wishes</p>
         <p>Bel. me, Yours very truly, W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">No. 2.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="end">Monday night, xi.15</p>
         <p>I detained my L. of yesterday, as I could not make up the little packet in time to post this mg., and so I have <hi rend="italic">got </hi>something additional, in a Pamp. to hand <hi rend="italic">this day </hi>(in a box), please return carefully when done with—as I have not yet run through it, but I noticed on 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. p. at bottom a <hi rend="italic">face </hi>reminding me of Rev. David S.—–</p>
         <p>Went <hi rend="italic">early </hi>to Instit. Room (vii.10) to set out box of minerals, &amp;c.—Pinckney Chn. (several <hi rend="italic">Dons not there</hi>—Carlile, Humphries, Dr. Moore, Large, &amp;c,—yet about 30, including visitors from Xt.Ch. I read my paper (husky!) showed spns. &amp;c then Hon. Secy. read Lund’s on “Coins”—a good p. but unfitted for an <hi rend="italic">audience</hi>. Coins of Charles I, then mottoes obverse &amp; reverse, &amp;c, &amp;c. Scarcely understood! Then Hill began (or rather <hi rend="italic">after </hi>the Coffee Interlude. Hill’s p. very long—and his <hi rend="italic">extras </hi>longer! All about Ruapehu &amp; Tongariro, over &amp; over!—Kept at it till x.30. No remarks: no votes thanks save at close, by the Dean (who came in <hi rend="italic">late</hi>, after my p. &amp; while Lund’s was in reading.) D. propd. v. for Hill I seconded, while folks were rushing out. I came back <hi rend="underline italic">tired</hi> carrying my lantern—night very fine &amp; <hi rend="italic">mild</hi>; met no one!—</p>
         <p>I don’t think I shall venture there again: of course, no one had anything to say! I made some remarks <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Coins, &amp; Hill’s <hi rend="italic">Dactylanthus, he </hi>stirring me up to do so, he having lately secured some new specimens, which were shown:—and now I must go thither tomorrow to put up my spns. securely—more time lost! In “Dy.T.” this evg., Newman offers ₤<hi rend="italic">4 </hi>reward, to any one who will inform agt. <hi rend="italic">St. John’s </hi>Sunday Sch. Boys for ill-using his timber on Sunday—opposite “D.T.”</p>
         <p>Well, once more Good bye</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely,           W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
