<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0799">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 August 27: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-08-27">1891 August 27</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 August 27: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-549" place="foot" n="549"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier Thursday nt.,<lb/>August 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 1891</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Your long &amp; interesting letter of 23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>. I duly recd., &amp; thank you for it—I have been charmed w. it! So many refreshing topics!!—But, to tell you the truth, I had almost made up my mind <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to write to you <hi rend="italic">this</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">week</hi>, believing I should be <hi rend="italic">fully</hi> employed. I went to town on Tuesday—&amp; I determined to commence my heavy job of Botanical work (already too long delayed!) on Wedy. mg. w. a “good heart”; I did so: but the weather changed at 1 p.m.—from fine to <hi rend="italic">dull, cloudy </hi>&amp; rainy,<hi rend="italic">&amp; darkish here in my room</hi> so that I have been obliged to throw aside my botanical labour—not being light enough for <hi rend="italic">analysis</hi>, &amp; I never use microscope by night. Such being the case, I began ransacking among my <hi rend="italic">old letters</hi>, &amp;c., as I wished to find one in particular from the late Bp. W. to me, written early in ’42, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the Moa, and in the course of my exploration I came on such <hi rend="italic">a lot</hi> of old letters! as <hi rend="italic">to make me think </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">much of you</hi>!!—how gratified you would have been to see &amp; read some of them. There are <hi rend="italic">many more</hi> from <hi rend="italic">Woon; </hi>and from other old missionaries &amp; Clerics., England, Australia, Tasmania, &amp;c—&amp; from <hi rend="italic">great men</hi> too! A large no. of them had been wholly forgotten by me. I have however selected <hi rend="italic">two</hi> (referring to Printing in N.Z.) as these must interest <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, and I enclose them—but, <hi rend="italic">please return them to me when you next</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic"> </hi>(or first <hi rend="italic">after</hi> that)<hi rend="italic">write</hi>: You may copy—if you please to do so.—Some day we may have a talk about them. I am not a little pleased w. Mr R. Watts!—</p>
         <p>And now to your letter:—The clipping you enclosed of Fenton’s remark— “when the Mao. chief was a Gentleman”,—is a good one: I have a <hi rend="italic">similar one</hi>, which occurred a few years (or <hi rend="italic">many</hi>) before, &amp; curiously enough Tirarau was also <hi rend="italic">the chief actor</hi>. I have several times related it, to Maori Chiefs (Hapuku &amp; others) as well as to Whites—to Jas. Wood, in particular, on his arrival here:—it is too long to write about, in a note, &amp; too good to be curtailed.—</p>
         <p>You say, yr. vols. “Trans”. begin w. XIV, I must send you (anon) a copy of my p. on “<hi rend="underline italic">Veg</hi>. food of Maoris,” (in vol. XIII,) this being (in my estimation) one of the most val. of all my papers—I class w. it mine on their “colour sense” (wh. you have in XIV.) I will myself take your copy of Vol. XXIII to your brother, when I next go down to town.</p>
         <p>Two <hi rend="italic">more</hi> statements in Papers of today—<hi rend="italic">re</hi> “Sea Serpent”—that in “Herald,”—a triangular fight between Whale, Swordfish, &amp; Thrasher Shark: this in D.T.—a big tree; both fully stated as from eye-witnesses.</p>
         <p>Was much pleased to find my fears <hi rend="italic">re</hi> yrself. were <hi rend="italic">ground</hi>less: &amp; hope you &amp; yours are <hi rend="italic">now well again</hi>.—</p>
         <p>That author of “Barbados” (tho’ dubbed <hi rend="italic">“FRS.”</hi>) evidently knew little if anything of Natural Science. All he has written <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Natl. Productions of B. is almost childish:—and I fear his <hi rend="italic">Theologl.</hi> attainments were not much higher: <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> he endeavours to discourse learnedly (!) <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the <hi rend="italic">Deluge</hi> of which he has “<hi rend="italic">clear proof</hi>” in the formation of that Island! (this forcibly reminds me of Gill’s 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> book “Myths” (or something of that kind) of <hi rend="italic">the Pacific</hi>”) whereas G. was <hi rend="italic">all his lifetime</hi> merely on the Isle of Mangaia! (<hi rend="italic">smaller</hi> than the Barrier I. in the Thames, N.Z.) I early got a copy from Engd. &amp; when I saw <hi rend="italic">that</hi> Gasconade I closed the Book.—and, I fancy, Tregear is greatly inclined that same way.—</p>
         <p>And mentg. <hi rend="italic">this</hi> brings me to your remark, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> my “applying to Govt. for <hi rend="italic">authority</hi> to pub. this 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. pt. Mao. Lex.”—You add “<hi rend="italic">new</hi> men may have new ideas.” You forget, however, that it was <hi rend="italic">Ballance</hi> himself who treated me w. contumely about this very M.S. in 1886. Moreover, what chance is there <hi rend="italic">now? </hi>w. Tregear’s out &amp;<hi rend="italic">supported by Govt</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">now openly</hi>—<hi rend="underline italic">before</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> privately</hi>)<hi rend="italic">—</hi>&amp;<hi rend="italic"> </hi>mine<hi rend="italic">rejected!—</hi>I have<hi rend="italic">often </hi>of late wished, that T. had <hi rend="italic">not</hi> sent me a copy: and I have several times thought of returning it—but I do not see my way to do so—<hi rend="italic">sans</hi> precedent. <hi rend="italic">I have studiously avoided looking into it</hi>;—<hi rend="italic">including</hi>, of course, <hi rend="italic">my own</hi> copy. <hi rend="italic">Very likely</hi>, had T’s book <hi rend="italic">not</hi> been pubd., I wod. pub. this 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> part (or, instalment) right off—&amp; that <hi rend="italic">without thinking of looking</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">any more to Govt.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I like your notion, of “protesting agt. hybrid-<hi rend="italic">generic</hi> names”:—but I go further, &amp; utterly dislike many <hi rend="italic">specific</hi> ones—of this new school; e.g. maorium, maoricum, maoriella, dunstanensis, otagoicum -cus, nelsonicum -cus, pakawauica, &amp; malvernicum, &amp;c, &amp;c.—all that arises from ignorance <hi rend="italic">or</hi> carelessness (laziness),—the nam<hi rend="italic">er</hi> will not trouble himself (?can not) to seek out (1) what name has been <hi rend="italic">already used</hi>: and (2) what Gk. or Lat. derivation is a <hi rend="italic">fitting</hi> one!—</p>
         <p>You are right <hi rend="italic">re</hi> prevalence of suicide in Colony—that, and sudden accidl. deaths, are of daily occurrence.—</p>
         <p>Last Sy. I was <hi rend="italic">twice</hi> at Augustine’s: mg. assg. Bp.: evg. ditto the Dean, and I believe I am down for the whole S. there next Sy. mg. &amp; to assist in evg.—</p>
         <p>Thanks for your information <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Opotiki.—</p>
         <p>I passed up &amp; down your <hi rend="italic">old</hi> street, since my last: sorry to see so many vacant houses: one thing however pleased me—Holt’s <hi rend="italic">old</hi> buildings completely renovated, put to rights—new fences, gateways, lamps, &amp;c &amp; all newly painted.—</p>
         <p>I have had some extra work of late—for Profr. Hutton—re Moa, making measurements, descriptns. &amp;c, of own M. bones, &amp; that mounted spn. in Athenm.—&amp; finding he still required more—or better (?)—I sent him my best bones.—While engd. in Athenm. old Pirani came in looking very so-so!—we shook hands <hi rend="italic">cordially</hi>—and remarked—“<hi rend="italic">nearly at the end</hi>,” &amp;c.—I had not seen him for a long time, &amp; I saw <hi rend="italic">great</hi> alteration.</p>
         <p>Mrs Margoliouth tells me (in her reply)—that what had served to <hi rend="italic">shock</hi> her greatly arose from the fact of having had her daughter out w. her for a drive on <hi rend="italic">the day before</hi> her death, and both thought she was better!—a <hi rend="italic">com</hi>. feature in Consumption.</p>
         <p>[See <hi rend="italic">more</hi> of “Sea Serpent”, in <hi rend="italic">Tuesday’s</hi> “Evg. News”—this from Bob.]</p>
         <p>I am, on <hi rend="italic">the</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">whole</hi>, keeping pretty well: but <hi rend="italic">can never rely on myself for the morrow</hi>—&amp; this is very awkward (to say the least of it) for <hi rend="italic">Sunday</hi> duties.—When I feel well &amp; pretty free from Rheumc. pains (never wholly clear, though <hi rend="italic">less severe</hi> than formerly) then I can get on w. my wk. steadily <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, &amp; I am happy: but when unwell yet not confined to bed—I would prefer being at Dvk.—to see (at least) a little of humanity!—</p>
         <p>Mrs Fannin, is unwell, again! Dr. visiting daily, &amp;c. Poor F. has had &amp; <hi rend="italic">still has</hi> a “time of it.”—</p>
         <p>With many kind regards &amp; best wishes, believe me ever—</p>
         <p>                             Yours faithy.</p>
         <p>                                             W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S.—Are you going on w. Archdn. Dictionary?</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
