<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0645">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1887 July 2: to Bibby</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Colenso set the following problem for students at Waipawa School during his 1873 visit: “A B C D went into partnership. A put into the business £674/13/6 for 4 yrs, 5 mths, 19 days. B put in £2463/14/8 for 2 yrs, 3 mths, 24 days. C put in £896/17/9 for 6 yrs, 8 mths, 17 days. D put in £346/18/7 for 3 yrs 4 mths. Their gross gain was £2487/13/2 and expenses in working the business was £596/15/9. I wish to know the nett gain and what was each partner’s share.” The problem was answered correctly by James Woodhouse Bibby (1862–1959) an 11 year old Form I boy. Inspector Colenso presented him with a book as a prize.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/74704/">Bibby</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1887-07-02">1887 July 2</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1887 July 2: to Bibby<note xml:id="ftn3-365" place="foot" n="365"> Colenso set the following problem for students at Waipawa School during his 1873 visit: “A B C D went into partnership. A put into the business £674/13/6 for 4 yrs, 5 mths, 19 days. B put in £2463/14/8 for 2 yrs, 3 mths, 24 days. C put in £896/17/9 for 6 yrs, 8 mths, 17 days. D put in £346/18/7 for 3 yrs 4 mths. Their gross gain was £2487/13/2 and expenses in working the business was £596/15/9. I wish to know the nett gain and what was each partner’s share.” The problem was answered correctly by James Woodhouse Bibby (1862–1959) an 11 year old Form I boy. Inspector Colenso presented him with a book as a prize.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, July 2/87</p>
         <p>E. Bibby, Esq.<lb/>Waipawa.</p>
         <p>Dear Sir</p>
         <p>Permit me to trouble you with the following request:—</p>
         <p>About 10 days ago I received a note from your C.C.C. Tuely—informing me, he had to proceed against defaulters for Rates, &amp; so he called on me for 6/3, without saying, what for, or for what period:—I replied, saying, I was not aware I owed any, &amp; <hi rend="italic">doubted it</hi>:—last year I had leased to B.B. Johnson my only remaining unlet section at Waipawa, &amp; <hi rend="italic">he </hi>was to pay all local rates, &amp; <hi rend="italic">I</hi> the Propy. Tax: so I referred him to Johnson.—</p>
         <p>As I have not heard from him (or anyone there) since, and have seen in our papers a statement <hi rend="italic">re </hi>many Voters losing their votes at the coming election, owing to their non-payment of Rates;—and not wishing to lose my vote, I have thought of asking <hi rend="italic">you </hi>to <hi rend="italic">ascertain how it stands with me</hi>. It may be “all right,” and I hope it is: of one thing I am <hi rend="italic">quite sure</hi>—I never received any “demand for Rates” that has not been paid. If this sum (or any sum) is still debited to me for Rates—will you kindly pay it for me—and I will repay with thanks.—–</p>
         <p>I hope you are keeping well, also Mrs. Bibby: our winter is passing by: here we have had a few cold mornings. With kind regards, I am, Dear Sir</p>
         <p>Yours truly</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. Do not trouble yourself to write a reply.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>