<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0487">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1882 March 1: to Balfour</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73378/">Balfour</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1882-03-01">1882 March 1</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1882 March 1: to Balfour<note xml:id="ftn3-126" place="foot" n="126"> ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier March 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> 1882</p>
         <p>Mr D.P. Balfour</p>
         <p>Many thanks for your kind, &amp; full, &amp; welcome letter of the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb, &amp; for its accompanying packet—all right to hand Sunday evening,—(26<hi rend="sup">th</hi>). Before however that I reply, I will just ask you one question, lest I forget, (as I see in the beginning of yours, you say that you had “received the report­ <hi rend="italic">last night.</hi>”) Do you get your mail oftener than once a week?, &amp; if so, when?, because I have been always under the impression that yours was a <hi rend="italic">weekly</hi> mail, &amp; that on Saturday.</p>
         <p>First, to the remark in the Report re “2, Orchid plants, from you &amp; Mr W”.—these were <hi rend="italic">quite distinct</hi>—One, (yours) Epiphytical (your divot lot) only in leaf from you—(but in flower from Mr Hamilton &amp; self)—and I wish greatly for more <hi rend="italic">flowers</hi>, which however are very small &amp; insignificant, almost hidden under leaves; his were terrestrial (from Masons run) finely in flr, &amp; a large single flower too, for the plant, but <hi rend="italic">not new</hi> (one, no doubt, of Hookers <hi rend="italic">Corysan­thes</hi>, which are all much alike, at <hi rend="italic">first</hi> sight, and are difficult of discrimin­ation)—and were, unfortunately, too much crushed (squeezed together flat) in his pocket book to be of any use;—he has <hi rend="italic">now</hi> (on Saturday last) sent me a lot of the same in spirits (as I had requested <hi rend="italic">at the time</hi>)—but all long <hi rend="italic">past</hi> flg &amp; so (again) useless;—W is zealous, but needs a little instruction.</p>
         <p>Now to your <hi rend="italic">present</hi> specimens, and first, the 2 “living insects”—on opening the box, in which they were, they seemed to all intents &amp; purposes—dead; &amp;, of course, very dirty in their “clay”. However I got a basin of water &amp; a feather, &amp; after some considerable time one showed signs of life, &amp; in another hour or so, the other also slowly revived. I cleaned them, &amp; put them into fresh wat<hi rend="italic">ers</hi>, &amp; they are now in a large glass bottle, with water, &amp; a big stick &amp; “dry ground” to rest on, if they choose, but they generally keep in the wa­ter, &amp; <hi rend="italic">under</hi> the water. They were, (in the main) new to me; I soon decided they were <hi rend="italic">not</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">perfect</hi> insects, but in their metamorphic state,—but whether <hi rend="italic">larva</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">chrysalis</hi>? took me some time. I now believe them to be the chry­salis of a <hi rend="italic">Neuropterous</hi> insect, &amp; I am almost sure of the Genus, (<hi rend="italic">Libellula­</hi> of Linn, but cut up of late years, &amp; now, either of <hi rend="italic">Petalura</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Cordulia</hi>, to which the Dragonflies belong (Scotch, perhaps, Horsestingers, but <hi rend="italic">none of them sting</hi>) and there are several sps in N.Z., and nearly all known described, that is, the perfect winged insect, though their preceeding states are unknown. I shall keep these in water, &amp;c, in hopes (faint ones though) of their changing; but then it is known that <hi rend="italic">some</hi> sps remain 12–24 months in this state!. See if you can get me <hi rend="italic">bigger</hi> ones; from in <hi rend="italic">the water</hi> in Europe, &amp;c, they are al­ways in the water (from the egg), &amp; your account of their holes, &amp; long ones too, in the clay, bother me; write me all about their holes, &amp; galleries,—do they run under the level of the water?—Their big pellets, too, surprise me; how are these formed?, are they <hi rend="italic">in</hi>, or at <hi rend="italic">Entrance</hi> outside of their holes? can you (or your son, Entomologist? junior,) find out what they feed on. I am pleased with their <hi rend="italic">masked mouths</hi>; but there is one thing I want to find out.</p>
         <p>On 3–4 occasions of going to the bottle to look at them, I find a quantity of largish air bubbles on the surface of the water, just over each one; now these must have been <hi rend="italic">caused</hi> by them, but how? I am inclined to think by their blowing(?) through their hinder parts, &amp; not their mouths; but I must watch &amp; find this out.</p>
         <p>I thank you for them; &amp; if I can make <hi rend="italic">sure</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">species</hi> (the perfect in­sect), these will be doubly valuable—to science.</p>
         <p>And, while on this head, I will further express my pleasure in finding that you “Bottle all” fish which comes into your nets (or hands). <hi rend="italic">Ka pai</hi>; do so, on, on, on; but I am a trifle better pleased, still, in finding that your little <hi rend="smallcaps">son helps you</hi>, &amp; that you so <hi rend="italic">properly</hi> encourage him in it; You are laying the sure foundation of <hi rend="italic">future</hi> good usefulness, &amp; pleasure.</p>
         <p>And now to your little box of bones, or, of <hi rend="italic">fragments</hi>, of bones—this lot has also pleased me, but I cannot say much (if anything certain,) about it at <hi rend="italic">pre­sent</hi>; fortunately a few of the <hi rend="italic">molar</hi> teeth (enamel surfaces only) are in good preservation, but I do not perceive any incisor, or canine, teeth; how­ever, I am going on the hunt after <hi rend="italic">teeth</hi>, fossil &amp; recent—in our books (&amp; all others comeatable;) &amp; if I can find out anything worth writing, I will fur­ther write.­</p>
         <p>Dr Hector went <hi rend="italic">through</hi> here 10 days ago, on his way to Auckland. I did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> see him,—he came by rail &amp; left by Taupo Coach, 6 next morning—should he return to Wellington by Napier, (which I doubt) I will try to see him, &amp; to show him these bones &amp; teeth. I hope you may get something more (in the ve­ry <hi rend="italic">small</hi> way), where you found those bones &amp; teeth, and keep your eye open on any old “Middens”.</p>
         <p>(afternoon)</p>
         <p>Since writing the foregoing I have again been studying your “box of bones”; and I find fragments of incisor teeth, strange, there is no portion of the skull nor back-bone; so, do, at some early convenient hour, try again. I am in hopes that these may turn out to have belonged to some animal of the <hi rend="italic">In­sectivora</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Rodentia</hi> orders—&amp; not unlikely to be the (so called) ancient Maori <hi rend="italic">Rat</hi>?—which I have never believed to be a <hi rend="italic">true</hi> rat, time will show. I now note, on <hi rend="italic">close</hi> examination, several peculiarities in structure.</p>
         <p>You mention having a “Small spring in a scrubby gully in your garden”, (how I wish I had such;) have you not some <hi rend="italic">Liverworts</hi> growing by its sides? <hi rend="italic">small</hi>, <hi rend="italic">low</hi>, &amp; often creeping, moss like plants, but with thicker &amp; plainer (not nerves leaves,—such are by all springs &amp; water courses, (as well as on trees in damp woods,) send me a few sprigs, or small tufts, of whatever you have there grow­ing.</p>
         <p>It is time to bring my long letter to a close. Hope I may not have tired you. <hi rend="italic">Heavy</hi> rain today (began yesterday)—spoiling their races; at which <hi rend="italic">I am not sorry</hi>.</p>
         <p>I <hi rend="italic">was sorry</hi>, however, to hear from P.D. of measles being severe at Springfield; I feel anxious about <hi rend="italic">young Richard,</hi> &amp; have written to know how he is. No doubt your children will also have it,—but on <hi rend="italic">first</hi> blush of disorder, keep the child from <hi rend="italic">cold</hi> &amp; draughts,—aid nature quietly, &amp; the disease is soon over, and with kind regards</p>
         <p>                             believe me</p>
         <p>                                             Yours truly</p>
         <p>                                                                     Wm Colenso</p>
         <p>The flat piece of bone sent, may have been part of a bone of a whale.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>