<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0373">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1878 July 18: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4. Letter addressed to A. Luff Esq., 135, East India Road, Poplar, London. Endorsed “Rec’d Sep/78. Reply Sept. 12/78”.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1878-07-18">1878 July 18</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1878 July 18: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-333" place="foot" n="333"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4. Letter addressed to A. Luff Esq., 135, East India Road, Poplar, London. Endorsed “Rec’d Sep/78. Reply Sept. 12/78”.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand,<lb/>July 18, 1878.</p>
         <p>A. Luff Esq.,</p>
         <p>My dear Sir,</p>
         <p>Your welcome letter of May 22nd. reached me on the 7th. inst.—I was much pleased to find you were all well when you wrote. My last to you (and a <hi rend="italic">long one</hi>) was on 17th. June—I hope it may reach you safely—it contained 2nd. of Draft for £<hi rend="underline italic">50</hi>.</p>
         <p>I <hi rend="italic">feel</hi> as if I had a larger budget—than usual to send you this month; how to <hi rend="italic">compress</hi> all I have to report I don’t know! Would that I could <hi rend="italic">talk</hi> it with you.—But first to <hi rend="italic">business</hi>.</p>
         <p>Finding that Witty was last weak at the Empire (late Mayo’s) I went there to see him: he is still half laid up w. his sprained knee. I found that he had just finally concluded sale of his house and grounds to Bell of Tautane for £3000. cash, down—to be paid when Deed is drawn, &amp; B. gets possession—which will be <hi rend="italic">very soon</hi>. The Bp. is in it now, but will leave it as soon as Beetham R.M. leaves Archdn. W’s. house into which the Bp. goes.—And Beetham is removed by Govt. to the South, &amp; only awaits arrival of his successor—then, Witty said, your money should be paid w. interest.—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Self</hi>. Had news from Taradale while I was inland 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>–24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. ulto.), R. &amp; Drummond told Barry &amp; Williams (H.) a cock &amp; bull story that <hi rend="italic">I</hi> (!!) was willing to release from mortgage 3 acres of the land there to make up the deficiency of the £300.—then, they (who had <hi rend="italic">each </hi>promised £50.—if needed—to help R &amp; D., drew back from that, &amp; so R. &amp; D. saw Neagle &amp; signed a stamped &amp; witnessed memo. to that effect, viz. 3 ac. @ £40 = £120.—I knew <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> of all this: &amp; when I came back from Waipukurau. R. &amp; D. came to see me—(having also dissolved partnership!)—to get my signature to conveyance! For once I spoke <hi rend="italic">plainly</hi>: and for a long time refused to do so; but, finding the creditors were waiting &amp; clamorous,—and Lawyers too, joining them,—I gave way, taking, however, instead a B. of Sale over tools, Furniture &amp; Stock for the amount. This I did more to <hi rend="italic">keep out others. </hi>I then warned R. before witnesses, that while I should honourably keep my word to <hi rend="italic">end of 2</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">nd</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>year<hi rend="italic"> </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">no Interest paid</hi> (viz. 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. November next) that I would wait no longer. We shall see. P. Dolbel &amp; others tell me, it is a good thing that young D. is separated from R. (D. is gone to Ongaonga, Ruataniwha, Smithy)—but R. tells me (privately) that his <hi rend="italic">mother</hi> (now R’s wife w. <hi rend="italic">young</hi> family) helps her eldest son <hi rend="italic">to</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">cash</hi>! So I shall have to go to Taradale to warn her. I fear I am in for <hi rend="italic">loss </hi>there.—And there are <hi rend="italic">others</hi>—which I won’t trouble you with—altogether, a <hi rend="italic">bad</hi> beginning for me, now that I am entirely on my own resources.</p>
         <p>Writing “Ongaonga” brings me to say we are to have a new township up in that part of the world on Glenny’s land, to be called Ongar—it is now being laid off. Miller (the Nipper) has sold Lambert’s run for £30,000!!!—nearly £10,000 more than it is worth, to some one down S., and now (some) folks ask whether L. will pay what remains of Inglis’ debts (I. only paid 7/6): I have also heard that Miller has sold Burnett’s Run to Heslop for £20,000,—and that <hi rend="italic">B.</hi> would have <hi rend="italic">let H. have</hi> it for £18,000, or less! Verily, M. is a nipper! “A <hi rend="italic">good</hi> fellow,” <hi rend="italic">P.D.</hi> says, “for selling for anyone, but an awful – – – – – for charging” !!</p>
         <p>C. Collins is leaving Waipawa having bought a place for his son down Manawatu way,—<hi rend="italic">all to</hi> be sold next week. He did wrong in selling his Run (late Abbott’s) to Rathbone.—</p>
         <p>Foan’s property was sold last week &amp; brought good prices. And a Sn. of Grubb’s (cunning fellow!) which he had lately bought off Trestrail, in Emerson St., next to T’s. old shop, for (I think) £250. &amp; sold for nearly £350—but Grubb will, I dare say, tell you all about it.—</p>
         <p>Bryson is building 4 shops next to his Hotel, &amp; so filling up that plot. A house is building on hillside, on Burton’s land, just opposite here, for his daughter lately married,—but how they are to get to it, <hi rend="italic">I don’t see.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Again I have been served out by O. &amp; Lee. In Jany. I wrote offg. to E.B., as required, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> good site for Public Schools in N., laying it down for the B’s. consideration that no large school should abut on public roads, if possible: &amp; pointing out, among others, an excellent site, nearly opp. Cotterill’s, where the N. end of the Town Hall R. had been cleared away, as there they could have 1–2 acres of flat land (if they chose), and <hi rend="italic">this</hi> side of Railway, &amp; free from much public thoroughfare &amp;c &amp;c. However, guess my astonishment, when I saw, in paper, a fortnight ago, that they had “cut &amp; dried” a plan, &amp; the E.B. agreed to it, without a word, viz. to give to <hi rend="italic">Weber</hi> (lucky Weber!) and others £<hi rend="italic">650</hi>. cash, to surrender Leases of land at the corner of Milton Rd. and Cl. Square, and there on that ½ ac. (2 Sns.) to build the great com. school!! and this is to be done.—</p>
         <p>I felt it: I wrote to O. (a <hi rend="italic">temp</hi>. &amp; <hi rend="italic">well considd</hi>. letter), shewing how I had suffered by <hi rend="italic">their acting</hi>, 1. In leasing those 2 sns. without any clauses as to size &amp;c. of buildings to be thereon erected, so that the Wesleyan Trustees would not have my section 108 (which I had walled on 2 sides, &amp; filled in) owing to Knowles’ &amp; Weber’s “piggeries” &amp; stables, <hi rend="italic">adjoining</hi>.—And, 2. That now my property was still more depreciated, besides the intrusion of 300–500 boys on that lower hill &amp; fences, &amp;c., &amp;c., in play hours:—however all I asked was (since the plan was left to O.) so to have the buildings erected—seeing thay had two frontages—as to cause me the least annoyance; warning them also of “excavating” the side of the hill—foot of it—as it was all <hi rend="italic">loose </hi>earth, &amp; springy underneath.</p>
         <p>O. has not even acknowledged my letter, nor have I seen him for a month—he is now off to Parliament. The worst is that my outlay <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, on 108, was <hi rend="italic">more</hi> than £<hi rend="italic">100</hi>. &amp; now the Rates are increased because it is <hi rend="italic">improved</hi>!—</p>
         <p>But we are not yet at the bottom—of <hi rend="italic">Rates </hi>&amp;c. by a long way! Plenty more <hi rend="italic">ere long</hi>!!—This very night there is to be a large (mob) meeting in “Theatre Royal,” to borrow money, on <hi rend="italic">rates</hi> to any amount to fill up the swamps!! But you will see all about it in the Papers I send you. Price, is raving! owing to his losing <hi rend="italic">½ of his </hi>overcharge on Corporation printing (see Papers). A <hi rend="italic">rare </hi>scene last night! At the <hi rend="italic">working</hi> men’s Club: Hon. J. Sheehan, Hon. H.R. Russell. Hon. J.N. Wilson, Mayor of Borough &amp;c &amp;c.—Sheehan said, that had he not got a cold he should sing a song, &amp; then, call on Mayor! or <hi rend="underline italic">J.N.W</hi>. to do so!! That is your democratical touting for votes!! Miss Russell is to be married to Gaisford (!!) in Septr., &amp; so is the Dr. there (Frood) to Campbell’s daughter of E. Cape—who, strangely enough, has been <hi rend="italic">visiting at Mt. Herbert</hi>. I had supposed Russell to have been <hi rend="italic">above</hi> that! </p>
         <p>Tiffen, as Chm. C. Council, gave his casting vote to keep up the toll gates! so this will cost him his seat there.—But it is <hi rend="italic">said</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>that he is going to resign as he is off for Japan &amp; China. He came here to see me last week, the first time for 2–3 years; he looks well.—I fear our old friend, Fannin, is going down-hill <hi rend="italic">rapidly</hi>: I fancy he will <hi rend="italic">lose his</hi> situations ere long. It is sad to see him, as red as a soldier’s coat, bloated, rough &amp; rude, and stinking of whiskey, before 9 a.m. However, I (as a friend) have done my duty—&amp; that <hi rend="italic">very plainly</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">again</hi>, this very week,—but I fear to no purpose. Fox (in barracks), did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> hold his office long. Tylee has got <hi rend="italic">that also</hi>—as Immigration Agent, &amp; Fox has just reported something nasty to headquarters <hi rend="italic">against</hi> Fannin.</p>
         <p>Strange to say, the Thomas’ have <hi rend="italic">gained</hi> their case at Fiji,—a telegram to that effect 2 days ago, that the Govr. had granted <hi rend="italic">them</hi> the said land! I saw it. The land is said to be very valuable: the Bank, I hear, has offered George T. many thousands for it. May it (the treasure) not prove <hi rend="italic">injurious</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">old</hi> couple!</p>
         <p>Major Withers is leaving for the Thames under <hi rend="italic">orders</hi>: and they are getting up a subn. for him. Lambert asked me yesterday to subscribe: I sd. what for? Is he <hi rend="italic">poor</hi>? No. Has he been <hi rend="italic">overworked</hi>? No. Has he exposed himself? No. Has he been <hi rend="italic">underpaid</hi>? Oh, no! I won’t give anything: and I would rather not have seen <hi rend="italic">you</hi> so employed. What! £400. a year for years past, just for playing a few hours a week—after time too,—w. a handful of Cadets, &amp; Volunteers. But such is the way of the world. Alfred Carter (who went home w. Willie) is just married to B. Taylor’s daughter—<hi rend="italic">I</hi> don’t like the match: she is a poor weak little thing. Just now I am offering to B. &amp; Brooking that place at Awanga (near K. Hill’s), &amp; Karaitiana is about it again: all end, perhaps, as before, in smoke!—–</p>
         <p>I had fully hoped to have had vol.X of “Transactions” for you by <hi rend="italic">this</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Mail</hi>, but you must wait a little longer. (I send a report of our Branch). On the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. June I recd. a case containing 40,—the rest to follow, when finished: that now so many Copies were required it took the Binder a long time to do all: I had an ugly task, to carve up my fowl among twice the proper number, so some had to go without, <hi rend="italic">including myself. </hi>I have just told my boys, that could I have supposed such a thing, as that the 2nd. lot would not be here in time, I would have kept three copies for you &amp; for them. I find my papers in that vol. (4) generally spoken well of—Wellington, Auckland, Xt.Church, &amp;c.—in their “Reviews” &amp; “Notices”,—&amp; I have had plenty of congratulations from all sides: but the old adage is still true— “A prophet is <hi rend="italic">without </hi>honour in his own place.”—This has just been painfully shown. I had advertised, as usual, for our meeting last Monday night, and had got ready <hi rend="italic">fully</hi>, should Sturm <hi rend="italic">not </hi>arrive. I looked out Specimens, Books, plates, Drawings of my own (1838), &amp;c &amp;c—which took my man 3 trips—and I had written a paper which occupied me a fortnight: at 7.30 (the time) Mrs May with 4 fine young women her Boarders walked in,—&amp; there we sat till 8! When J.A.S. came in—in his way! he was horrified in seeing how things were, &amp; after apologizing, said, to Mrs. May, that he would go &amp; beat up for recruits; 8.15, he returned—w. <hi rend="italic">not one</hi>. And at 8.20, the ladies left, after sitting 50 minutes! Oh! How I <hi rend="italic">felt it</hi>! <hi rend="italic">I did all that I could</hi>, as you may suppose. Yesterday I had a short letter, in the paper, about it,<note xml:id="ftn2-334" place="foot" n="334"> Philosophical Society. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> 17July 1878.</note> (<hi rend="italic">to our members</hi>) and the “Herald” added a very good sub-article, which I heard much praised both by members &amp; by outsiders. Yet, to make the matter <hi rend="italic">worse</hi>, the Herald of this morning had a <hi rend="italic">nasty</hi> letter, &amp; that, too, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Mater </hi>familias! as if any decent woman in this place would have so debased herself. I have written them (D. &amp; Co.) a <hi rend="italic">private </hi>letter upon it, and I shall send <hi rend="italic">you </hi>a copy of it in this day’s paper.—<hi rend="italic">Low </hi>theatricals, <hi rend="italic">low </hi>singing, low politics &amp;c. will go down very well in <hi rend="italic">this place</hi>, but nothing <hi rend="italic">higher</hi>: in this respect, think yourself, and <hi rend="italic">your young ones</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>well off in England. However, this matter will not now stop where it is:—one thing, or the other, must speedily follow: it will be for <hi rend="italic">them </hi>to decide. Nairn wrote to me last week to propose Rev. Mr. Simcox, Clergyman of Porangahau, &amp; Miss Herbert’s name is also set down. The Bp. came to me, in town, yesterday to apologize for <hi rend="italic">his </hi>absence, but, as I told him, there was no need for that, as he was on duty (2 services) on the Sunday at Waipukurau. O. has never attended a single meeting! &amp; I have (hitherto) striven to get him elected <hi rend="italic">President</hi>!! But——I have had offers from S. members at Xtchurch to read my papers for me <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, and I am still a member of Wellington Society, where I can always send them; and perhaps I may do so.—</p>
         <p>Would you believe it? Grubb actually came here to see me, two Sundays back!! We talked about many things but mostly about you &amp; <hi rend="italic">yours</hi>.—lands here, prospects, return, doings, &amp;c. I fear, myself, that your <hi rend="italic">old</hi> and <hi rend="italic">good</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">chance</hi> as a L. Agent here is gone; so many in the field now, &amp; that “Dragon of Wantley” (Miller) takes all the fat ones!—</p>
         <p>Speaking of Theatricals! We have now our <hi rend="italic">own </hi>home lot (Swan, Jacobs, Bean, &amp; Co.) On Tuesday last they performed here (bumper Ho. of course!) tonight at Waipukurau,—and (don’t let the Railway <hi rend="italic">Managers</hi> at home know of it,) special train is to leave W. for Napier <hi rend="italic">after </hi>performance!! xi or so!!! Then tomorrow night here again!—</p>
         <p>I had a very handsome letter written to me early last week, by <hi rend="italic">old </hi>Catholic Scholars of Rearden’s School—several of whom are now filling situations—to present their piece of plate to Mr. R. on the Friday night: to which I <hi rend="italic">cordially </hi>agreed. However, that very afternoon (4 p.m.) heavy and continuous rain set in! then they wanted me to go &amp; return in a close carriage, but as I must walk up &amp; down this hill in the pouring rain, I could not agree to that—fearing the consequences: so I was <hi rend="italic">greatly disappointed</hi>: see the Paper.—</p>
         <p>I have not yet <hi rend="italic">seen </hi>the Inspr., neither do I care to see him. The small Country Schools will suffer much, I fear, through O’s. acting in the way he proposes: <hi rend="italic">over</hi> £13,000 he wants from the Govt. for School-<hi rend="italic">Houses</hi> along in a <hi rend="italic">few bigger</hi> places—while the smaller ones must go without—both Houses &amp; <hi rend="italic">Teachers</hi>. To <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, it is saddening: <hi rend="italic">knowing</hi>, as I do, the <hi rend="italic">good formerly done</hi>, &amp; the <hi rend="italic">real wants</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">scattered</hi> children. Inspr. has <hi rend="italic">not</hi> been inland yet: I hear that <hi rend="italic">he</hi> has increased F’s. salary £50 a year. F. has had the priv. of franking taken away! (O. will feel that,) and Hill has got it! The weather is still very fine: Acacias in all their golden glory! Ruahine <hi rend="italic">covered </hi>looking grand.</p>
         <p>Now I think I must close. My back (lower part) is aching from rheumsm. I hope this may find you <hi rend="italic">enjoying</hi> your summer, <hi rend="italic">our </hi>days are beginning to grow longer. With kind regards to all &amp; best wishes, believe me always,</p>
         <p>Yours truly</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>—Go on again!—xi p.m.!!</p>
         <p>I find I have not said a word about the war—Congress &amp;c.–</p>
         <p>Right glad am I, that war is staved off—for a time: that the Congress managed to do so well as they have done. (Who can say if those two shots at Berlin, had not something to do with it?). However, I am glad that the British occupy Cyprus:—&amp; that an alliance has been made w. Turkey <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Asia Minor: that may stop the Bear’s moving in a S. direction. Hurrah! For Beaconsfield, I say—were I there, I would throw up my cap for him. Vexed I am at the conduct &amp; language of Quaker Bright,—though, generally, I love the “Friends”. Don’t like Lancashire revolters; but the <hi rend="italic">same </hi>spirit, is <hi rend="italic">here</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>&amp; everywhere; and all Governments will have to guard against it.</p>
         <p>Several of the Papers you sent me <hi rend="italic">this time </hi>contained <hi rend="italic">portions</hi> of interesting matters, but so fragmentary, scarcely anything complete. In one was the charge of that <hi rend="italic">Jew </hi>Judge Jessel to Mrs. Besant (I thought on an old Jew, &amp; an old Roman Judge, to a Great Teacher!!) In my boyhood that Jew—as a Jew—might have been <hi rend="italic">so </hi>tried and <hi rend="italic">so </hi>spoken to! But those laws affecting them, &amp; R. Catholics, &amp; Nonconformists, have since been abolished, &amp; so it will be with <hi rend="italic">these</hi>—ere another generation passes away. Our grandchildren will wonder at our stupidity. In that same Paper was the Countess Russell’s address to the Nonconformists! And there, in the next scene, was Mrs. Besant—a talented, good, moral lady called upon to suffer for her <hi rend="italic">conscientious </hi>opinions! (Just as Calvin helped to burn poor Servetus!) Mrs Besant was to have her daughter torn from her, &amp; perhaps brought up by a Ritualising person!! Or a High Church one, which is much the same. Now, my good friend, if you had sent me Mrs Besant’s address (which I am sure was published in same paper) &amp; not that time-serving Jew’s charge—albeit a Judge &amp; learned in the law!—then I should have thanked you heartily. I was very, very greatly disappointed; but that was not for the first time. And here I would observe that of all the papers you send me, these Weekly Times are about the worst. I find scarcely a <hi rend="italic">single </hi>article in each paper worth reading; just because what these articles <hi rend="italic">were written on at the time </hi>was <hi rend="italic">then </hi>future &amp; unknown, now (when they arrive out here) we know all the results by telegram; just so with the <hi rend="italic">heaps </hi>of war news, which I never once look at. The “D. Telegraph” is, on the whole, the best paper—but then they are rarely ever consecutive, &amp; always get more or less torn &amp; ragged &amp; worn in transit, owing (I suppose) to the poor weak rotten paper. I hope mine hence are not so torn.</p>
         <p rend="end">Friday, 19th.</p>
         <p>I have lots more to say!—</p>
         <p>Young Duncan was nearly drowned a few days ago, went <hi rend="italic">outside </hi>in a canoe, got upset &amp; had to swim to shore!!—nice, in winter too! lucky for him.</p>
         <p>Cottages (below) including fences &amp;c.—sold for a trifle over £100. O. <hi rend="italic">said </hi>they would bring <hi rend="italic">£200</hi>—towards the £<hi rend="italic">650</hi>. (In my letter I also gently reminded him how I had suffered (&amp; am still suffering) in loss of property in Carlile Street—through the Govt. (of that day) <hi rend="italic">and Weber</hi>. W.W. Carlile got £<hi rend="italic">4,200.</hi> as his share (in Cash, too)—on dissolving partnership! his brother told me so. C &amp; wife are voyaging, somewhere. Gleadow, I see, will now have a Toll-gate <hi rend="italic">again</hi>!—<hi rend="italic">for a</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">season</hi>. </p>
         <p>You will see in this day’s paper all about last night’s meeting. <hi rend="italic">I agree with Wilson. </hi>Young Tabuteau lately married at Wellington. Dinwiddie &amp; Co. have not replied to (or noticed) my letter, &amp; now I know I am right—as to author. Man just come in with 11/- worth of postage stamps—all, I believe, will be used. I must not forget to <hi rend="italic">thank </hi>you for the Pictorial World (one copy) containing view of F. Exhibition Buildings: several have seen it: only one here, I think. <hi rend="italic">Our Dr. </hi>H. was very glad to get your message, &amp; to know you were all well. He still looks very well—barring his not having any teeth! Four strange birds here in garden—Tui, Owl, Pigeon—&amp; <hi rend="italic">fourth</hi>, quite new; and 2 Rabbits in field—<hi rend="italic">these </hi>are <hi rend="italic">doomed</hi> &amp; will pay the penalty. Brandon sent me this afternoon a fine Kingfisher he had found dead in his paddock choked by a mouse he was swallowing!! Half of the m. is in his throat, “hard &amp; fast”!!―N &amp; Close’s <hi rend="italic">new</hi> store is above level of land now, <hi rend="italic">concrete</hi> foundations, &amp;c. finished.—Fannin was summonsed a few days ago by N. Williams for £3.16.0, &amp; F. allowed judgment by default!!!</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="italic">latest </hi>paper is put up in an <hi rend="italic">Envelope</hi>. I shall endeavour to do this in future. I send you 2 <hi rend="italic">packets</hi> of Papers, just equal to 40 papers. I have often thought that <hi rend="italic">you </hi>must get some of your H.Bay papers <hi rend="underline italic">3-fold</hi>! I feel sure you do much of the <hi rend="italic">news </hi>I send.</p>
         <p>Among our <hi rend="italic">deaths</hi> is poor Mrs Bowerman, who was a great sufferer. And among the <hi rend="italic">Births</hi> is the wife of <hi rend="italic">your old </hi>friend, Rev. Mr. Morice, of a daughter.</p>
         <p>I forgot to mention (from the fact, I suppose, of its having happened while I was at Waipukurau)—the fire in McVay’s back premises—the <hi rend="italic">second</hi>, too! They fortunately soon put it out; but they made (or <hi rend="italic">he did</hi>!) a great fuss—as if it were the work of an incendiary!! So that Scully offers a <hi rend="italic">great</hi> Reward!! To <hi rend="italic">me</hi>—even from the <hi rend="italic">poor</hi> evidence at the Inquest—nothing is clearer, than that it arose from Spontaneous Combustion—a leak in the <hi rend="italic">iron roof</hi> (from our first rains of last month) would have been quite sufficient for that, aided by the enormous heat concentrated from <hi rend="italic">such a roof</hi>! (and it had been very hot <hi rend="italic">several days</hi> before, which was noticed). But <hi rend="italic">that </hi>jury had brought themselves to believe it was the work of an Incendiary <hi rend="italic">before </hi>they sat—just like the Woodville fellows in that murder case!—You will have it all in the papers I send.—Curiously enough, I have just put up in <hi rend="italic">today’s</hi> paper, the half of an <hi rend="italic">old</hi> one containing the fire! (it came so by mere chance).—</p>
         <p>The longer I live the more difficult I find it,—to fall in w. persons who are able—competent—to draw <hi rend="italic">reasonable, unprejudiced, </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">deductions</hi>. Education, alone, won’t give it,—nor will Experience. A man with untrammelled mind is <hi rend="italic">rare</hi>,—generally all have so much to unlearn—<hi rend="italic">first.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Adieu. Yours ever, W. Colenso.</p>
         <p rend="end">Friday July 19/78</p>
         <p>After some deliberation (in bed last night) I have determined on ordering some more Books from Wesley, &amp; so take advantage of their <hi rend="italic">coming out together</hi>,—thinking I shall <hi rend="italic">be in time</hi>:—I therefore shall enclose a Draft payable to you <hi rend="italic">for </hi>₤30., and if I am in time, and if he can get those Works ordered, <hi rend="italic">all</hi> I mean—only some 5 sets), then you may hand him this ₤30. to my credit; but if he obtains only a part, then do you pay him a little money on account: one set will cost about 30/- another 21/- another 25/-—another (from his own Catalogue) ₤8.8.0—and for another, if <hi rend="italic">to be had</hi>,—I have said to him I would go as high as <hi rend="italic">₤20.</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">if required</hi> for a perfect set,—<hi rend="italic">this work </hi>is the “Zoology of the Erebus &amp; Terror,” and (I hear) is only <hi rend="italic">recently </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">completed</hi>!!</p>
         <p>My words to him, on this head, is,— “Should you be able to obtain <hi rend="italic">all </hi>these additional Books for me, and should this order reach you in time, my friend Mr. Luff, to whom I am writing, will pay you some money on my account.”—</p>
         <p>I have also told him that if I <hi rend="italic">am too late</hi>, then to hold over the said Books (if he obtained them) until he hears from me again.</p>
         <p>But <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> may</hi> (in that case) have something to send, or to ship, and then they might come together—but this I leave with you.</p>
         <p>I have already found out—that Wesley is just like many others of <hi rend="italic">that</hi> trade in London:—1. A terrible fellow for charging high—&amp; always some <hi rend="italic">plausible</hi> excuse!—you send for a Book marked at a certain figure in his Cat.,—10 to 1, but <hi rend="italic">that copy</hi> has been sold &amp; then he will look out for another—which is <hi rend="italic">sure to be higher priced</hi>: 2. And if you only <hi rend="italic">enquire</hi> after a work, you<hi rend="italic"> </hi>stand a fair chance of having <hi rend="italic">it sent</hi>; he sent me a work (all in <hi rend="italic">numberg. </hi>some 30!<hi rend="italic"> </hi>but no index, &amp;c) which I only enqd. after, adding I should like a copy if <hi rend="italic">low</hi>—stating too, (from a letter Lascelles shewed me, only just to hand,) the price of it in rupees at Madras,—where it was published. He sent me one (as above!) with his usual plausible tale <hi rend="italic">₤3.15</hi>:—when told his Brother-bookseller, Quarritch, in <hi rend="italic">his Catalogue </hi>of same <hi rend="italic">date</hi>, has it marked at ₤2.15.0!! I cut that out (last Mail) &amp; sent it to W. These are some of my reasons for not leaving too much money in his hands: when I sent him my Order in May—he has a few pounds to <hi rend="italic">Credit</hi>—&amp; then I sent him ₤<hi rend="italic">50</hi>. I tell <hi rend="italic">you</hi> all this <hi rend="italic">privately.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I am, my dear Sir</p>
         <p>Yours truly</p>
         <p>W. Colenso</p>
         <p>Finally closed Saturday afternoon, July 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1878. <lb/>  Weather<hi rend="italic">delightful</hi>!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>