<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0162">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1862 November 11: to McLean</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL Object #1015759 from MS-Papers-0032-0221.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70546/">McLean</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1862-11-11">1862 November 11</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1862 November 11: to McLean<note xml:id="ftn2-64" place="foot" n="64"> ATL Object #1015759 from MS-Papers-0032-0221.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, November</p>
         <p rend="end">11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1862.</p>
         <p>D. McLean, Esq.,</p>
         <p>     &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c</p>
         <p>             Napier</p>
         <p>Dear Sir</p>
         <p>I do not know whether you are aware of the Government of New Zealand having requested me to surrender Waitangi to them, promising me compensation for the Improvements, &amp;c. thereon. I have agreed to do so, (and, in fact, have left never more to return,) and the Arbitrators appointed by the Government and myself, (Messrs. Chambers &amp; Alexander,) have sent in their award.—</p>
         <p>I, yesterday, received a letter from the Under Secretary, enclosing a copy of a Letter from Bishop Williams to the Hon. the Col. Secretary, respecting myself and Waitangi.—</p>
         <p>This Letter has been sent to me by Mr. Gisborne,—“in order that I may make such remarks thereon, for the information of the Government, as I may consider necessary.”</p>
         <p>I am truly sorry to find, that Bishop Williams’ Letter is (to say the least of it) altogether of a highly depreciatory character.</p>
         <p>As, however, the concluding paragraph of Bishop Williams’ Letter is wholly concerning information which he states to have been given by <hi rend="italic">you</hi>: and as I know nothing whatever of any such circumstance as he relates,—I am necessitated to ask you if you know any thing of it? I enclose a copy of that portion of Bishop Williams’ Letter.</p>
         <p>Also:—as Bp. Williams (in his said Letter) further says—“the original raupo house was in some way (!!) burnt down, and Mr. Colenso then lived in a <hi rend="italic">small raupo </hi>building:”—which words, without explanation, being of a nature to mislead the Government,)—I will also thank you to state your opinion of “the <hi rend="italic">small raupo</hi> building,” abovementioned,—which stood, and still stands, in the garden at Waitangi. I do this, not merely because of your often having been in it, (before the time of the fire above alluded to,) but because (if I mistake not,) you were so much pleased with it, that you employed the Natives of Ahuriri to erect a <hi rend="italic">similar </hi>one for the Government in this town; and which was afterwards occupied by the Crown Lands Commissioner (Mr. Domett), and since, to the present time, by the Resident Magistrate (Capn. Carling).</p>
         <p>             I am</p>
         <p>       My dear Sir</p>
         <p>       Yours very truly</p>
         <p>             Wm Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>