<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0773">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 March 25: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-03-25">1891 March 25</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 March 25: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-518" place="foot" n="518"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke,<lb/>Wedy. nt., 25 March, 1891.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Your welcome &amp; prized letter of 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> (dated by you “<hi rend="italic">21</hi>”) came to hand <hi rend="italic">very opportunely</hi>—for I was <hi rend="italic">very ill</hi>, &amp; even now can hardly manage to sit up &amp; write—but I won’t put it off till tomorrow for I <hi rend="italic">may</hi> be worse.—I was taken rather suddenly the night of date of my last (19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>)—owing in part to sudden change of weather, wet windy &amp; <hi rend="italic">very cold</hi>, from S. Friday &amp; Saty. were sad days with me—pains heightened thro’ fears of not being able for Sundy. duty, Mr Robertshawe having gone off to the Weber Dist. however I rallied a little by Sundy. Mg. &amp; so was (once more!) enabled to get thro’ both services—and really at night, on my return to lodgings, was <hi rend="italic">much better</hi> than I had been!—–Monday however was a <hi rend="italic">very bad</hi> day w. me, <hi rend="italic">one of the worst I have known for ’91</hi>: Yesty. easier: today <hi rend="italic">much better</hi>. I cannot tell you in a letter <hi rend="italic">all</hi> I have had to endure,—my complaint<hi rend="italic">s</hi> (2–3 together!) Rheumatism, <hi rend="italic">piles</hi>, Diarrhoea, making me all but <hi rend="italic">helpless</hi>!—Your letter served to cheer me a little, for on <hi rend="italic">that day</hi> (23) I saw <hi rend="italic">no-one</hi>!—it was a long &amp; dreary day.—–<hi rend="italic">Enough</hi>!—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Re</hi> your letter: I <hi rend="italic">had</hi> that <hi rend="italic">asinine</hi> Hymn—but I fear the book it was in, I <hi rend="italic">lent</hi>, &amp; has never come back—w. several others, only <hi rend="italic">lately</hi> found wanting by me.—[I fancy, Locke had it.] I can imagine your delight at seeing the Fuchsia <hi rend="italic">in</hi> the Gorse bush: also, that nice evergreen hedge you so happily describe. “Tregear Dy.” must remain at N. till I return. I wish you had told me, <hi rend="italic">who</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">what</hi>, Davidson <hi rend="italic">is</hi>.—Rather curious that, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> “Fern-leaf Note-pr.”, &amp; I <hi rend="italic">never to have seen it before</hi>! I return yr. par. for next “Typo”, with a corr. or 2 in it, thinking such <hi rend="italic">may</hi> have escaped yr. sharp eyes: it is a <hi rend="italic">nice</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">little</hi> “skit”. <hi rend="italic">Re</hi> Opotiki libel cases: I note, while <hi rend="italic">petit</hi> Jury found W. “<hi rend="underline">N</hi>.G.”—<hi rend="italic">the Judge</hi>, in passing his <hi rend="italic">delayed</hi> sent. on B., <hi rend="italic">let him off</hi>! So I suppose, t’was—“six to the ½ doz”. The Bp. is <hi rend="italic">there now</hi>, &amp; I suppose will have <hi rend="italic">something</hi> to say to W. Shall endeavour, on my return to N., to find out yr. Father’s scrapbook contg. “Green Stone Mako”.</p>
         <p>I have <hi rend="underline italic">much</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">deplored</hi> loss of yr. Almanac: it has ever been such a <hi rend="italic">useful</hi> faithful &amp; loved companion w. me, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> stars, planets, &amp;c. &amp; fear I must go in for a rant! one in future—I will never buy another of D. &amp; W’s.—dirty, beastly, thing! There is a <hi rend="italic">good sheet</hi> Almc. <hi rend="italic">here</hi> now from Evg. News off. <hi rend="italic">well-displayed</hi> w. advts. all round and <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Ry. timetables in centre: it is varnished &amp; hung on sm. rollers. Have you seen a copy of the “Akaroa Mail”, of 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. inst., I have one from Dawson (much of interest in it). Some 2–3 yrs. ago, a yg.(?) man named <hi rend="italic">Gordon</hi> wrote to me from Taranaki a very nice letter of Enqy. re some Mao. words. (I think he was in the survey off., &amp; I also <hi rend="italic">thought</hi> he might be a ½-c.) I ansd &amp; <hi rend="italic">encouraged</hi> him to write again: he did so after rather a long interval, when I wrote to him fully: and to my <hi rend="italic">surprise</hi> I got an acknowledgement, &amp; a request—that “<hi rend="italic">I wod. not write to him such long letters</hi>”!!!<hi rend="italic"> </hi>Could you, <hi rend="italic">quietly</hi>, learn anything of him from Tregear?—<hi rend="italic">he is a Genius.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Following up your kind hint I wrote to Col. Secy. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>J. Wh’s. books, of course, offg. to pay highest price, but no reply yet.—</p>
         <p>Last night, VIII. who should suddenly pop in—but J.W. Craig!! on his way to N. Plym. for holiday: spent a nice ½ hour together. I saw Welsman passing through this aftn. on his way from Wgn.—</p>
         <p>Colliers “Bibliography” is just to hand, from Didsy., and I have been looking into it:—<lb/>1. Surprised at the <hi rend="italic">great no.</hi> of books referred to by C.—<lb/>2. Several I had never heard of.<lb/>3. Some I should <hi rend="italic">like to have</hi>, or to borrow.<lb/>4. I marvel at his <hi rend="italic">omitting</hi> our “N.Z.I. Trans.” (I know he says, p.102, “Vol I.” &amp; “pubd. annually,”—but he should have said <hi rend="italic">more than that</hi>, as <hi rend="italic">many</hi> of its papers are <hi rend="italic">far before</hi> much of his rubbish!)<lb/>5. I wholly demur to what he says (p.134) re self &amp; <hi rend="italic">first</hi> Moa paper.—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">I never saw Owen’s paper nor ever heard of it</hi>: &amp; that those <hi rend="italic">big</hi> folks at Home, &amp; in Tasmania knew: but more (perhaps) when <hi rend="italic">I send</hi> you “Authors’ Copy” of <hi rend="italic">Moa</hi>. Haast &amp; myself had <hi rend="italic">agreed to write</hi> against Quatrefages—just bef. H. went to Eng.,—and then H. died shortly after his return!!</p>
         <p>This book is nicely printed by Didsy., &amp; good paper too.—I shall again &amp; again look into it. I wonder if “<hi rend="italic">Hutton</hi>” (as you say) is really out with a <hi rend="italic">Botanical</hi> book? or, rather <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>?—if <hi rend="italic">low p.</hi> send me a copy.—</p>
         <p>Capt. Preece called on me on 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Maori</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Dog</hi> of <hi rend="italic">old</hi>: &amp; borrd. my paper on it, which he had not seen: spent a <hi rend="italic">nice hour</hi>.</p>
         <p>Eccles, too, came purposely from Waipawa that same day to get me to Lecture <hi rend="underline italic">there</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> this week</hi>, that, howr., I <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi> do: &amp; as he (and they) wish it to be on a <hi rend="italic">moonlight</hi> night, (rightly so,) it is put off till <hi rend="italic">next</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">moon</hi>: &amp; <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, I see, that their Races are on “St. George’s Day,”—&amp; further, that Native Ld. Court. commenced there on 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Apl., and “it is feared—<hi rend="italic">not room for all</hi>!”—and, as an <hi rend="italic">old</hi> unalterable rule w. me, I <hi rend="italic">never</hi> stay at a <hi rend="italic">private</hi> house—neither take any meal there: so I suppose it may <hi rend="italic">not</hi> come off.—I purpose, if well enough, retg. to N. on 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> &amp; 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., proxo. Here I halt: <hi rend="italic">Goodnight</hi>.—</p>
         <p>P.S. I see, Tregear’s paper (I had mentd. to you), “the Maori &amp; the Moa,” is at p.170 Collier: (have you seen it?) and <hi rend="italic">at top</hi> under <hi rend="italic">Rusden</hi>, a clumsy hypercritical alteration of a pure Mao. word!</p>
         <p>Do you know, if a copy of “<hi rend="italic">Bidwell’s Rambles</hi> in N.Z.,” is in any Liby. at Wgn.?                                                                       <hi rend="italic">Goodnight</hi>.</p>
         <p>Thursday, 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, X. a.m.—I now finish &amp; take (or send) to P.O. I am better (I hope!) but very so-so—not myself. However, I can be <hi rend="italic">free from pain</hi>, &amp;c, by lying on my back: &amp; <hi rend="italic">pain</hi> I have always disliked—<hi rend="underline italic">greatly</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I think you sd. you recd. the Opotiki paper? If so, send on to me those contg. reports of 2 trials—I will return carefully w. thanks, &amp; repay any outlay, &amp;c.</p>
         <p>As far as I can see <hi rend="italic">at present</hi> I purpose leaving here this day wk.</p>
         <p>My eyes are undergoing a curious change, I was first sensible of it during the spring: viz. that my writing <hi rend="italic">by night seems small</hi> (as, for inst., in this note) yet by daylight I am astonished!—</p>
         <p>Weather here very fine again, I hope settled, for a time: I am <hi rend="italic">much</hi> of a prisoner, only been 2ce into the neighbg. woods! Hope you &amp; yours are <hi rend="italic">all well</hi>, &amp; boy improving.—</p>
         <p>With kindest regards, &amp; best wishes,</p>
         <p>Yours Ever, W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
