<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0169">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1863 November 25: to Catchpool</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL Ms-Copy-Micro-0193.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73058/">Catchpool</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1863-11-25">1863 November 25</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1863 November 25: to Catchpool<note xml:id="ftn2-81" place="foot" n="81"> ATL Ms-Copy-Micro-0193.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Auckland,<lb/>Novr. 25/63.</p>
         <p>Dear Catchpool</p>
         <p>Your most welcome letter of the 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. I duly recd. I thank you much for it, for all news, and for <hi rend="italic">all kind words &amp; </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">feelings</hi>—of which one sees little nowadays. I did hope to write you fully, but I must refer you to the Papers. I have not <hi rend="italic">done</hi> any thing for you yet—but I have been supporting the Ministry strongly &amp; openly, &amp; I <hi rend="italic">see</hi> that will be of service when the time comes. Since your letter reached me, we have been doubly busy (I mean particularly the My.) so that to seek to do any thing with the My. <hi rend="italic">now</hi>—or, until Mail leaves for Engld.—wod. be injurious. The <hi rend="italic">war</hi>—the <hi rend="italic">House </hi>crying give, give,—answers to queries, Papers, &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c,—the despatches in &amp; out: wait a bit—I’m here, &amp; have made up my mind, even if house is prorogued by sailing of Ashley, <hi rend="italic">not </hi>to leave by her but by Ranga.—if requisite—so as to finish if poss. your case.</p>
         <p>I beat Ormond openly &amp; fairly on his Ld. Req. Bill-division, which he demanded, 24 x 12: O. is very savage, &amp; ungenerously in reply, told the Ho., I opposed the Bill, <hi rend="italic">because </hi>I had lost my sit. He is going to try again! under <hi rend="italic">another </hi>title but he won’t find me asleep or absent from my post.</p>
         <p>I “shewed up” Dr. F. &amp; Fitzd. &amp; Mantell in Renata’s matter, having got copies of R’s. letters in Mail affair on table; and house went w. me.—On the Estimates—sent down by Govr. in n. of Queen in due form—is £<hi rend="italic">350</hi>. Compens. for me. Ormond <hi rend="italic">kindly </hi>wrote to me that he must oppose it conscientiously!! &amp; demand papers, &amp;c—He may do so, &amp; he may be unpleasant, (he can) but he won’t succeed in stopping it.—</p>
         <p>The My. did not speak of <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, in the matter of the P.M. but it was offered to <hi rend="italic">me</hi>—I refused it. More anon.</p>
         <p>I shall never take any <hi rend="italic">Provincial </hi>Office: if I cod. get an easy &amp; <hi rend="italic">suitable</hi> one at say £100. per ann. <hi rend="italic">in </hi>Napier, (or higher out) I would close.—I may.</p>
         <p>The Papers teem with news: the victory at Rangiriri, saddened by our severe loss, will be productive of good. Our soldiers are more plucky than ever. The Maories may give trouble, but are now nowhere, &amp; ’tis only a matter of time: several of the Head Waikato Chiefs are either killed (2) or prisoners—but I refer you to the Papers. The Govr. told me, the Genl. had in his reconnaissance mistaken the height of the parapet &amp;c (21 feet high!!) hence the loss of Officers &amp; men—4 times did they advance to the Charge—only to be shot down, had they not surrend. they would have been taken by storm in the morng., the forlorn hope was told off, &amp; they thirsted now to avenge their comrades. In the S. Cross you will see the Estimates pubd. Note yr. P.O. &amp; Customs (<hi rend="italic">Private</hi>) O. told me he should seek to lessen your Cust. Expend.—as he knew some of yr men had nothing to do! But I shall be there. In 2 nos. of the N.Zealander, you will find reports of 2 of my sayings, tolerably faithful.—</p>
         <p>I have had no Eng. Letters by last mos. Mail: just see if there are any for me &amp; forward.</p>
         <p>I had a kind Invit. fm. Govr. to go to Kawau in steamer w. him, but, poor devil! I could not face the sea before “100 ladies.” I dined there (Govt. Ho.) on Saty. last.</p>
         <p>A Dieu!</p>
         <p>Believe me ever</p>
         <p>Yours</p>
         <p>Wm. Colenso</p>
         <p>Hand better today: yesterday dreadful.</p>
         <p>Yesterday I went to the funeral of 3 Officers—3 bands (abt. 60) concourse prodigious dust dreadful.</p>
         <p>Memorandum by Wm. Colenso. M.H.R. to accompany Mr. Catchpool’s papers—</p>
         <p rend="center">
            <hi rend="doubleunderline underline">_____</hi>
         </p>
         <p>“The two copies of Letters which I have taken, are those addressed by Mr. Catchpool to The Hon. the Secy. of Cr. Lands Auckland; (1.) Augt. 27 1861, and (2) Decr. 16 1861.</p>
         <p>“I have taken these, 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>., because Mr. C. had no copies of them by him, and I was under engagement to return them; and, 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. because Mr. Fox can very easily see the Originals. I would earnestly recommend the speedy settlement of this long outstanding matter to the early consideration of Mr. Fox.</p>
         <p>“Mr. Catchpool is now advanced in years, is, and has been for many years, a most zealous &amp; deserving Govt. Offr.—has evidently shewn a good deal of patience in the matter, (owing, no doubt, to his being a general Govt. Officer,) and his original land-order is now only worth half of its first value in the market (apart from what it might have been worth to him—as he truly states in his <hi rend="italic">private</hi> letter to me (left for Mr. Fox’s consideration,)—if laid out by him on his arrival at Napier, or, indeed, in Wellington Province.”</p>
         <p>(signed)</p>
         <p>W. Colenso, M.H.R.</p>
         <p>Auckland<lb/>  Decr. 18, 1863.</p>
         <p rend="center">(true copy:</p>
         <p rend="center">W.C.)</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>