<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0777">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 April 24: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-04-24">1891 April 24</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 April 24: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-522" place="foot" n="522"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke, 24/IV/1891.</p>
         <p rend="end">(night)</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding,</p>
         <p>—I must no longer defer writing to you: I should have done so before now, but for <hi rend="italic">outgoing</hi> Eng. Mail,—&amp; other postponed matters. I sent you, however, a copy of “Waipawa Mail”, that you might know a <hi rend="italic">little</hi> of me. I was never more surprised in my life than when McLean (Ch. Wdn.) came into Vestry after Evg. S. &amp; said, “I had been 55 min. preaching”!! Ch. crammed, &amp; Congn. excy. attentive: &amp; now I have <hi rend="italic">requests</hi> to officiate again <hi rend="italic">both</hi> from Eccles &amp; people.—Here, too, last Sy. I preached in the Evg., text <hi rend="italic">Eph. </hi>III/8—“the unsearchable riches of Xt.”—but, who is sufft. for these things?</p>
         <p>I staid 2 days at ’Pukurau, had a <hi rend="italic">pleasant</hi> 2 hours with Rev. Mr Grant, also a long one with dear Mrs Trestrail: to <hi rend="italic">both</hi> I spoke of <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, &amp; was <hi rend="italic">pleased</hi> to find they were your good friends. At Waipawa, on Monday 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., I fell in with Rev. E. Robertshawe, and as I found, if I came on here &amp; staid a while to aid him, in his absence, he would then be able to visit the scattered settlers in the Weber District; I consented to do so:—so here I am perhaps for 1 month.—</p>
         <p>Before I left N. I received my copy of T’s. Dy. from L. &amp; B.—<hi rend="italic">and</hi> I sincerely trust <hi rend="italic">they</hi> are <hi rend="italic">satisfied about it</hi>—not having been sent before.</p>
         <p>Two days ago I recd. vols. 3–5 of J. White’s work from Didsby.—in reply to my letter to Col. Secy., but <hi rend="italic">no letter</hi>, only a memo. inside, to forward <hi rend="italic">£1.2.6</hi>, which I did yesty. I have only<hi rend="italic"> </hi>just peeped into them: I find that J.W. had <hi rend="italic">again</hi> used <hi rend="underline italic">largely</hi> my historical &amp; quasi-legendary papers in “Trans. N.Z. Inst.,” and acknowledging same in preface:—I am glad I have got this work; if vol.VI should be pubd., be sure to get me a copy. In vol.V(?) J. Wh. copies from “Saty. Rev.”—its <hi rend="italic">loud &amp; </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">lengthy</hi> praises of him &amp; his work.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Yesterday</hi> a letter of mine was pubd. in “Bush Advocate”<note xml:id="ftn3-523" place="foot" n="523"> Keep holy the Sabbath Day.<hi rend="italic"> Bush Advocate</hi> 23 April 1891.</note>—in sending it to Clayton—I had particularly ordered <hi rend="italic">6 copies</hi>:—none however came to hand, so this mg. I saw him, &amp; there were <hi rend="italic">none</hi>!! Not <hi rend="italic">one</hi>! C. said, so many sheets were spoiled in ptg. We rushed together immy. to his retail Agent here, Bates,—but not a copy left! I am vexed at this: I wished to send <hi rend="italic">you</hi> one, so I have prevailed on Baddeley to let me have the House copy (tho’ soiled &amp; torn), this I shall post w. this—but <hi rend="italic">you will please return it to me</hi>—as I should much like to keep a copy.—</p>
         <p>I recd. but a <hi rend="underline italic">short</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> note</hi> from Dawson—thanking me. I had written pretty fully to him!</p>
         <p>Here is a letter (O.P.S.) to hand this day from Hobart, <hi rend="italic">inviting</hi> me to meetg. “Australn. Ass. Sc.” to be held there, &amp;c.—but I must (alas!) give a similar reply to mine to Xt.Ch.</p>
         <p>I recd. the copy <hi rend="italic">Cat</hi>. Carpenter’s Books you kindly sent me—several therein I should like to <hi rend="italic">see</hi> (at least), and now I wait to hear from you, how you sped.—</p>
         <p>While at Waipawa I made up matters w. “own correspdt.”—he showed me his copy “Bibliography of N.Z.” by J.D. Davis (pubd. by L. &amp; Blair.) &amp; kindly lent it to me:—I have it here:—I notice several errors, and (of course) one <hi rend="italic">re</hi> self &amp; the M. Dicty. See p.38, at bottom, a note:—and at p.25 (as per <hi rend="italic">Index</hi>, my <hi rend="italic">only</hi> job!) “1845. <hi rend="italic">N.Z. Ferns</hi>. Launceston”: and “<hi rend="italic">Excursion N. Island.</hi> Ditto.”—Perhaps you have seen this book?—</p>
         <p>While writing <hi rend="italic">this</hi> page a letter to hand from G.S. Cooper (Col. Secy’s. Off.) ackng. mine, &amp; granting “3 vols. as reqd—<hi rend="italic">at the usual price</hi>”.</p>
         <p>Now I will turn to your letter <hi rend="italic">of 13</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>. recd. <hi rend="italic">here</hi> on 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.—with 8d. postage on it! 4d. by you there, &amp; 4d. <hi rend="italic">addl. at</hi> N. I had supposed that you knew of my having to be at Waipawa on 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I am thinking of writing to Postmr. Genl. re this kind of imposition for re<hi rend="italic">-addressing</hi>—surely 1d. fee should be sufficient! If I close I will enclose this envelope.</p>
         <p>Am <hi rend="italic">glad</hi> to find your dear little boy was <hi rend="italic">better</hi> again when you wrote.—may this find him still improving. As you truly observe—“his restoration to strength will be a very slow process”:—hope on, hope ever.</p>
         <p>I feared young Crerar was absent ill, when I called there to inquire re “Torch” &amp; to see the Drawings, <hi rend="italic">I always liked him</hi>, so amiable, ready, attentative, unassuming.</p>
         <p>I do not know Wilson’s “Zoology.”</p>
         <p>I have <hi rend="italic">not </hi>recd. a “wire”, or anything from Tregear: better not<hi rend="italic">, at present</hi>: I can <hi rend="italic">fully</hi> understand your kind &amp; friendly remarks on my letter to him—“that I was <hi rend="italic">hard</hi> on him”—but then you are quite ignorant of our <hi rend="italic">former</hi> free &amp; full correspdce on Maori matters, &amp;c. &amp;c.—some day <hi rend="italic">you</hi> may know <hi rend="italic">all</hi>:—<hi rend="italic">till then</hi> suspend yr. judgment.</p>
         <p>I am pleased at your getting a copy of his p. on the Mao. &amp; the Moa. But how you could say—“I am not sure whether you have ever had it,”—puzzles me! As it was <hi rend="italic">through my getting a copy from him</hi> that I had written about it to you.—Depend upon it, that <hi rend="italic">now</hi> my Dy. will <hi rend="italic">never</hi> be pubd.—I have little doubt but that the Govt. of the day <hi rend="italic">knew</hi> of Tregear’s work, “So many years in prepn.,” and that <hi rend="italic">this</hi> was a reason (if not the only one) for their conduct towards me.—(Bide-a-wee.)</p>
         <p>—When I left N. I did not know certainly of my coming on to the Bush—indeed, I did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> leave word with Jago, Herald, &amp; D.T. to forward to me,—so I brought but <hi rend="italic">few</hi> things with me. I sent last week for some books, rug and Elect. Band: one of the books was Ts. Dy. (my purchd. copy): judge my horror, &amp; disappt., on finding my man sent me, <hi rend="italic">instead</hi>, a big book package (unopened) weighing “10lbs.,”—from London early last year!!!—He, too, had exultingly brought up to me L. &amp; B’s. book, 2 days before I came away—for we had often talked about it:—I told him too, where it was. So, I have not got it here w. me.</p>
         <p>If you have any more informn. <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Opotiki matters—how it <hi rend="italic">may</hi> have <hi rend="italic">subsy</hi>. fared w. Wills, please let me know: as the Bp. was <hi rend="italic">there</hi> staying.</p>
         <p>Should you have acquired those 2 books at Carpenter’s Sale (or one of them) send it on to me <hi rend="underline italic">here</hi>.</p>
         <p>And now my dear Sir, good bye, with kindest regards,</p>
         <p>Ever yours,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
