<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0115">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1852 March 3: to the CMS Secretaries</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0492. Hocken MS vol 63.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
          
               <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/70244/">Waitangi</name>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="organisation" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/72116/">the CMS Secretaries</name>
               <name type="place" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/5754/">London</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1852-03-03">1852 March 3</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <front>
         <p>1852 March 3: to the CMS Secretaries<note xml:id="ftn1-161" place="foot" n="161">ATL qMS-0492. Hocken  MS vol 63.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Church Mission Station,<lb/>Waitangi, Hawke’s Bay, N. Zealand.<lb/> March 3, 1852.</p>
         <p>Secretaries, <lb/>C.M. House, <lb/>London.</p>
         <p>My dear Sirs, </p>
         <p>1. My last letter to you was (I think) dated October 30/50; since which, however, I have sent you two portions of my Journal—one, in January, 1851, containing my Journal down to May 11/50, with a copy of my report for that year (1850),—and one in September. 1851, containing my Journal down to March 12/51,—all which, I hope have long ago safely reached your hands. </p>
         <p>2. I had hoped to have sent you some more or my Journal, as well as to have written to you fully before this; but want of time has hindered my doing the former, and my not having heard from you respecting my two letters of Decr./46, and Feby./49. prevents my fulfilling the latter. </p>
         <p>3. I only returned from my exceedingly heavy mountain journey (Patea), on Sunday morning last, the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. ulto. (To which place I have been <hi rend="italic">twice</hi> within 5 months, owing to the sad state of things, which existed there.) And have to commence, according to appointment, my usual long autumnal journey to Wairarapa, &amp;c., next week.—</p>
         <p>4. I write, at this time, principally to inform you of the Bishop having very recently visited us; and to enclose a copy of my Report for the last Year; as well as a copy of a memorandum concerning the two Roman Catholic priests who reside near us, which (after a conversation held with Mr. McLean, the Government Land Agent, and with his concurrence,) I wrote for the Governor’s consideration. </p>
         <p>5. On the 3rd or January last, I most unexpectedly received a packet from the Bishop, containing printed notices informing us that he intended to be here to hold a Confirmation on Sunday the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of that month. The packet, however, had been despatched in November, and,—though our time for preparation was exceedingly short, and at a bad season or the Year (owing to the potatoe crops not being ripe, and the natives engaged in cutting their wheat),—we exerted ourselves so as to be ready against his coming. The Bishop arrived here, via Manawatu, on Saturday afternoon the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of January, (on Sunday morning administered the Lord’s Supper to 40 selected and previously confirmed Natives,) and on Monday evening confirmed 229 persons. On Tuesday morning he publicly restored our ex-teacher Leonard Te Kawepo, and left for Te Wairoa. On Wednesday morning he confirmed 19 more (aged) persons at Tangoio; and on Thursday at noon we parted at Waikari,—whither I had accompanied him. He evidently suffered much from his heavy walk against time from Manawatu; fortunately I had been enabled to obtain him horses &amp; a canoe to assist him, both in coming to and going from the Station; so that, when he left me at Waikari, he appeared to be very much better than when he arrived at the Station. </p>
         <p>6. During his short stay one of the two R. Catholic Priests who live near us wrote him a long letter of accusation against myself &amp; Rev. J. Hamlin, and our people,—which letter the bishop answered from Te Wairoa, in a manner which has pleased me not a little. </p>
         <p>7. The Bishop expressed himself gratified with the alteration which has taken place among these Natives since he last saw them.—But, upon this head he will, I dare say, write you fully. Among other important matters which he mentioned, he wished me to prepare for Priest’s Orders; to this, however, I am not inclined, owing, in great measure, to my growing opinion, that <hi rend="italic">I have not the confidence of the C.M. Society.—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>8. For, during my seven years residence here, devoted as I have been to your service,—and exposed as I have been to numerous (and almost unprecedented) assaults—from the Natives, the Settlers, and the Government,—and, also, referring, from time to time to you, respecting matters between myself and the Local Committee—(of all which you have had, long ago, full &amp; reiterated accounts,) you have never communicated with me <hi rend="italic">once</hi>!</p>
         <p>9. Such, I cannot but think, would not have been the case had I been filling but a very low position under the smallest of the Colonial Governments. </p>
         <p>10. Your recent painful decision in the case or the oldest Missionary in New Zealand—and the one to whom (notwithstanding his failings) you, <hi rend="italic">and all</hi>, (and none more than the Government,) are the most indebted—strengthens me in my opinion.— </p>
         <p>11. The last year—or, rather, 16 months, (from the time we first heard of our old Pastor being openly “Gazetted” in the Colonial Papers to the exultation of our numerous enemies,) has been a most particularly painful period to me (and to many more). I cannot tell you a tithe of what I have felt, and still feel. I cannot venture to write you upon the subject. For, “out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaketh,” and the hand writeth; and I know that “in multiloquio non deerit peccatum”;<note xml:id="ftn1-162" place="foot" n="162"> Proverbs 10: 19: “There is always a lie in too much talk”.</note> still, I dare not be altogether silent. Under these circumstances I cannot perhaps do better than give you an extract from a friendly yet confidential letter, which I wrote to our Archdeacon on his leaving N. Zealand, and which, I think, he has subsequently received in England; “I assure you, (and it is with highly painful feelings that I write it,) that I have not that confidence in the Society which I had, and it may, ere long, grow to a separation. You know somewhat of my situation: I am all but friendless, and that <hi rend="italic">for</hi> the C.M.S.—namely, in carrying-out to the letter—rather, to my utmost ability—those principles which were their delight, and which they valiantly upheld, careless alike of the frowns or the smiles of the titled and honoured of the world. On the one side, I have the Government and Settlers more or less against me; on the other side, I have many of the worldly and evil-disposed Natives, the whalers, and the Papists; while behind, those on whom I relied are fast altering—the C.M.S. If, as you truly say, the C.M.S. will not defend their Servants from the men of the world; then, I had better cease to occupy a situation, which, sooner, or later, must bring my disgraceful dismissal. I firmly believe that a Missionary cannot any longer serve his Society than so long as he has their full and entire confidence. I am but a poor man, but the C.M.S. <hi rend="italic">should </hi>believe my words <hi rend="italic">before </hi>those of a Governor, or a Minister of State—even when backed by the influential and imposing authority of the Queen herself. If not, then the sooner we part the better. I am getting old,—<hi rend="italic">prematurely </hi>old—in the Society’s service; and, if the end is to be, my being thrown aside for any and every thing which man may consider to be erroneous, the sooner I look out for a shelter from the storm the better.—For I am in an enemy’s land, and I have <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> to fall back upon.”— </p>
         <p>12. Yes, my dear Sirs,—with my present belief and under present existing circumstances,—of the two—to take Priest’s Orders, or, to retire upon a small allowance, I would prefer the latter; if, in so doing, I should both meet with your approval, (for I still consider myself the property of the Church,) and see a <hi rend="italic">fit</hi> person in Priest’s Orders sent here to take charge of this people. As, in retiring from Public life I should spend the remainder of my days quietly, (at least, comparatively so,) and be able to educate in a plain way our 2 children (one 8, and the other 6 years of age,) <hi rend="italic">who cannot yet speak</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">English</hi>. </p>
         <p>13. Do not, however, for a moment suppose, that, in proposing—or, rather, barely mentioning—such a thing as retiring from Active Service, I have any such thing in view as Farming, or any money-getting occupation: for all such matters I feel myself altogether disinclined and utterly incompetent.— </p>
         <p>14. Your allowance (strange as it may seem,) will <hi rend="italic">not</hi> enable us to give our children a plain education; for, £<hi rend="italic">40</hi> per ann. is demanded for <hi rend="italic">boarders</hi>, which, with the many incidentals peculiar to a new country, would amount to £<hi rend="italic">100</hi> per ann. for our two children; to meet which you allow us £<hi rend="italic">20</hi> for each child:—More than enough in some cases—where Missionaries reside in or near towns,—yet, in our case, the very reverse. Further, in a letter which I have just received from the local, committee at Turanga, they inform me, that I have “overcharged in my account £20.”—in putting down, as hitherto, £<hi rend="italic">40</hi>. for the two children; thus reducing the sum to £<hi rend="italic">20</hi>., which is what I have been allowed (erroneously, I still hope,) for this Year.— </p>
         <p>15. You may, my dear Sirs, answer this by saying,— “Send them to England &amp; we will educate them.”—And (while I have my doubts whether such a step is quite in accordance with the Divine will,) I readily acknowledge that such would be in many cases,—(e.g., a numerous offspring,—an unhealthy climate,—one not subject to British rule,—no Schools in the country,—children not likely to return,—etc.,) a boon, for which, as one of your old Missionary Servants, I would gratefully thank you;—still, it does not, in my opinion, meet our case.— </p>
         <p>16. Further<hi rend="italic">: there must be an immediate reconsideration of the allowance for Travelling expenses</hi> (not to say of that for <hi rend="italic">Native Teachers</hi>,) in <hi rend="italic">this </hi>(Waitangi) District. It cannot be supposed, as the Bishop himself remarked, that Natives will work for you for less than they get from every one else. The Government—the Surveyors—and the Settlers would more than employ every spare hand, and their pay now is 2/- per diem. Hitherto my baggage-bearers, etc., have scarcely received more than 6d. a day; so that nothing is more clear than that my Travelling Expenses will not be less than £60.–£70. per ann., unless my Journies are made fewer, or shorter—and even then the Sum will amount to nearly £50. per ann.—The same reasoning also applies to the <hi rend="italic">Native Teachers</hi>; these cannot be any longer expected to give up their time &amp; wear out their few clothes and bodies for little or nothing,—while their people are (comparatively) abounding. To insist upon their doing so, is, to place them in a most dangerous temptation, which will finally be most injurious to our cause.— </p>
         <p>17. I wish you would write me—as I have endeavoured to write you—plainly and with candour. I may, perhaps, have erred in speaking too warmly; which may possibly be construed into a sad want of courtesy; such, however, is very far from being intentional on my part. I have, I believe, served you faithfully &amp; devotedly for 18 years, and the Searcher of hearts knows, that if I had ever any preeminent wish, it was, to serve you in the Mission field until the hour of my release.—</p>
         <p>18. I also enclose a Copy of “Return No.1”, (as I know not whether you have copies sent you,) by which you will know the amount you are still indebted to me upon this Station. This sum, be it observed, is independent of the Sum for Medicines, Tools, Nails, Iron, Glass, etc., (as per account rendered in 1846,) with which your Native converts have been benefitted and your numerous Chapels built &amp; rebuilt.— </p>
         <p>19. In conclusion—and, especially as I suppose that this will find our Archdn. still with you—I once more venture to express a hope, that you will not only notice but reply fully to this Letter; and so do much towards enlightening &amp; easing my mind upon more than one subject mentioned herein.— </p>
         <p>I am, </p>
         <p>my dear Sirs, </p>
         <p>Yours very truly, </p>
         <p>William Colenso. </p>
         <p rend="center">
            <hi rend="bold">[1] </hi>Waitangi Station; Ahuriri District.</p>
         <p rend="center">E. Coast of New Zealand</p>
         <p rend="center">
            <hi rend="underline">—————</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="center">Report for 12 months, ending December 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. 1851.</p>
         <p rend="center">———————</p>
         <p>During the past year I have been engaged as follows:—on the Lord’s day, in holding Divine Service twice, and in Catechizing and Teaching in the Schools.—On the week-days, in attending to the Adult Male Schools; in Instructing &amp; Examining the Candidates for Baptism and the <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord’s</hi> Supper; in holding Bible and Teachers’ Classes, in visiting the Sick, and dispensing Medicine; in Translating &amp; Printing Tracts; in Settling Disputes, &amp;c., &amp;c.,—and in attending to the many Secular duties of the Station.—</p>
         <p>On the 20<hi rend="sup ">th.</hi> December, 1850, I left the Station on a visit to the Natives of Petani &amp; Tangoio; and returned (late at night) on the 24<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of that month.—</p>
         <p>On the 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. of March I again left the Station, on a visit to the Natives of those (&amp; neighbouring) villages, and returned on the 10<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> of that month.—</p>
         <p>On the 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. of March, I left the Station, on a general visit to the villages throughout this District, and returned on the 28<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of May.—</p>
         <p>On the 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. of June I left the Station, on a visit to the of Natives of Petani &amp; Tangoio, to exhort and instruct them preparatory to their receiving the <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord’s</hi> Supper, and returned on the 5<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of that month.—</p>
         <p>On the 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of July I again visited those villages and Natives, returning to the Station on the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of that month.—</p>
         <p>On the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of August I left the Station, on a visit to the of Natives of Waimarama, Kohinurakau , Ngawakatatara, and Patangata; and returned on the 12<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of that month.—</p>
         <p>On the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of September, I visited the Natives of Tangoio and Petani, and returned to the Station on the 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. of October.—</p>
         <p>On the 13<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of October I left the Station, on a visit to the natives of the interior (Patea District) and returned on the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. of November.—  <hi rend="bold">[2]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of November I again visited Tangoio, &amp;c., &amp; returned to the Station on the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.—</p>
         <p>Total number of days absent from Station visiting Natives, 131. (occasional visits to Natives, within one day’s journey from the Station, are not herein enumerated.)</p>
         <p rend="center">
            <hi rend="underline">—————</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The number of Baptisms performed in this District, during the present year is, Men, 79, Women, 88, Children, 81, total 248.—</p>
         <p>The number of marriages performed, 12.—</p>
         <p>The number of persons admitted for the first time to the Holy Communion, 40.</p>
         <p>Although 45 persons of both sexes have been received as Communicants during the year, which with 706, (as per last year’s Return) makes a total of 751, only 297 have actually partaken of the<hi rend="smallcaps"> Lord’s </hi>Supper. Of the remainder, 48 have been suspended for misconduct, (36 at Wairarapa, and 12 at the Station) while the majority have not had the opportunity afforded them of partaking. There has, also, been an increase of Communicants at Manawatu, during the year; (as by arrangement made between Archdeacon Hadfield &amp; myself, the converts there, do now,—after four years patient, though fruitless waiting for an opportunity—partake with his flock at Moutoa, near the mouth of that river,) but I do not know the number of those who have recently been for the first time, admitted—perhaps 20, additional.—</p>
         <p>The number of Candidates for Baptism is still on the increase; a few more of the Heathen having come over during the year. Of late however, there has been no meeting of Candidates living in the neighbourhood of the Station and Ahuriri harbour, owing to their very unsettled state and excessive worldliness.—</p>
         <p>The Mission Station Congregation and Schools, at this time last year and in the beginning of this year, averaged 160—<hi rend="italic">now</hi> they are considerably under half that number; and such is also, I regret to say, the case generally in the Native Villages.—</p>
         <p>Three Chapels have been erected during the year; namely at <hi rend="bold">[3] </hi>Mataikona, Waipupu, and Turanganui. At these two last mentioned villages, there had not hitherto been any place set apart for Divine worship. The new one at Mataikona, is the second which the Natives of that place have erected, the former one (built in 1843) having fallen. The Chapel at Turanganui (Wairarapa) is wholly of timber, and erected by European workmen at the Native expense; toward which, upwards of £100, in cash, has been already paid. Both the patience and faith of the Subscribers have been sorely tried during the erection of this building, it having been blown down <hi rend="italic">twice</hi>—each time when nearly finished! a circumstance in great measure owing to the carelessness of the builders.—</p>
         <p>Mrs. Colenso has attended, as hitherto, to the daily female and Infant School; but, the general attendance, (both in this and the adult male School,) save on Sundays &amp; Mondays, is very irregular. Several have, notwithstanding, learned to read, write, &amp; cypher (in the more simple rules) during the year.—</p>
         <p>My Annual Teachers’ School, commenced on the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. of September, and continued, daily, until the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. (inclusive) of that month. Sixteen Teachers &amp; Monitors were present from all parts of this District, of whom seven were from Wairarapa &amp; Manawatu. This year we were engaged upon S. Pauls Epistle to the Hebrews; devoting, also, an hour and a half every afternoon to figures. </p>
         <p>During the year several of the first class Teachers have been actively employed in visiting the more distant villages.—</p>
         <p>Several Natives of both sexes and of all ages, have died during the year, particularly in the Wairarapa valley. A few of them have, I firmly trust, departed in the Faith; leaving a testimony behind them to the power of the Truth, which will not easily be forgotten, and which cannot be gainsaid.</p>
         <p>The Popish Priest who, last year, came to reside in the neighbourhood of the Mission Station, has, lately been joined by another! Hitherto, however, they have not only not succeeded in making proselytes, but have lost some of the few who did belong to them, who have voluntarily come over to the Truth.— <hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In December 1850, the Government Agent for purchasing Native Lands (Mr. McLean,) visited these parts, and remained in the neighbourhood (with a Surveying party,) until the end of April, 1851. When having purchased 2 large blocks of Land for the Government, he returned to Wellington. He arrived here, again, in October last; and paid, in gold, to the Natives, the first instalment for the Land, viz.:—£1800 at Te Waipukurau, on the 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., and £1000, at Ahuriri, on the 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. ulto. He is now at Mohaka, (in Revd. J. Hamlin’s District,) there to pay another first instalment of £200, for a third block which he has purchased in that locality. These several purchases—amounting, in all, to £7100 are to be paid for in 4 instalments, viz.,—one in each year, until the whole is paid. The present great decrease in our Congregations &amp; Schools, and the general unsettled and careless state of the Natives towards Spiritual things, is, therefore, easily accounted for; and, I confess, that I fear, <hi rend="italic">the worst is yet to come</hi>.</p>
         <p>Never, until the present year, have these tribes been in possession of so much current worldly riches!—especially of wheat and Money. Would that they knew how to use them, or, that they would be advised in doing so! The contrary, however, is the case. Last Autumn, they every where had a fine crop of wheat, which they most impatiently disposed for horses, to which purpose, also, by far the greater number of those who have received a share of money for their alienated Lands have wilfully squandered it—giving so much as £40, £45, and even £60. for a horse! Upwards of 50 horses have been bought into this neighbourhood during the last six months; some of which have already died; one native has, also, been killed, and several others more or less injured by falling from their horses.  I almost fear to state the hundreds of bushels of wheat, which they raised and sold last autumn lest it should be thought improbable:—especially when the short time which has elapsed since I first procured them seed wheat from Auckland and the great distance many of them have to bring it to the market, is considerable. Yet, should their present crops succeed as well, (and they are now lookingvery promising,) they will surpass those of last year by 10-fold!—And all, I fear, <hi rend="bold">[5] </hi>or nearly so, will, also, be hastily got rid of for horses. At present the Natives are in many places, almost starving—and that with their idolised horses before their eyes, and gold in their pockets! We have assisted several who were very greatly in want, (including our best Native Teachers, and Chiefs of the highest rank,) with Potatoes and Wheat for food. So that, what, to the Colonists, and to others at a distance, may appear to be a sure indication of prosperity, and a rapid advancement in civilization, is, to <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, quite the contrary, and fills me with concern for this poor deluded people.—</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="italic">only</hi> European-built dwelling at present at Ahuriri, has lately been “licensed” as a bush Public house! And this has already drawn aside several Natives. In consequence of the altered state of things, and the gloomy prospect which surrounds me, I have deemed it necessary to give public notice and warning to the Baptized Natives and Communicants, as to how I shall act in admitting persons to the Communion; which I have also printed and circulated throughout the District.</p>
         <p>I ought not, perhaps, wholly to omit mentioning, that—in consequence of a Sermon which I preached here, on Tim. v. 8, a short time before the payment of the first instalment—a few days ago, I received a Love-sign, each, from 5 individuals, communicants, towards a fund for purchasing some simple stores for the sick. The conduct of <hi rend="italic">one</hi> of these persons, (the Native Teacher of the Station, Noah Huke,) deserves to be more particularly remembered; as, from his not being immediately concerned in the Sale of those Lands lately transferred to the Government, he had only received <hi rend="italic">that one</hi> Sovereign, which he so willingly gave for such a good purpose.—And I have good reason to know, that he had not received any other money for the year, (save a pound, which I paid him in May last, for repairing the Verandah of our house,) and that he is, also, now almost in want of food himself, as well of several household articles.</p>
         <p>I have not yet been enabled to obtain a site, eligible, in every respect, for a Mission Station. The Governor has (verbally) offered me the <hi rend="bold">[6] </hi>choice of selection from the blocks of Land which have lately been purchased for the Government; but one very great drawback is, the distance of the suitable spots thereon from the Native villages; not again to mention certain reasons mentioned in my last Report. I may, however, very soon have it in my power to make a choice; and in due time, a removal.—</p>
         <p>My own and Mrs. Colenso’s general health, as well as that of our two children, has been, and is, much the same as mentioned in the two last years’ Reports—not particularly good, nor yet seriously ill.—Notwithstanding, there have been many days throughout the past year, when, from headache, or rheumatism, or influenza, or some general, but undefinable, indisposition, we have scarcely been fit for anything.—But this, I have long felt assured, is owing to the unhealthiness of our Station. Our gracious <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> has, however, again mercifully brought us to the close of another year’s residence here, and we would dare to believe, that notwithstanding our manifold infirmities, daily short-comings, and utter unworthiness, <hi rend="smallcaps">He</hi> will ever be with us, even unto the end.—</p>
         <p rend="end">William Colenso</p>
         <p>Waitangi,</p>
         <p>Decr. 3/51.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>