<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0895">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1894 March 2: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1894-03-02">1894 March 2</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1894 March 2: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-680" place="foot" n="680"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke,<lb/>March 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>, 1894.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>I shall begin my letter to you tonight, though I do not intend to close it till next week.</p>
         <p>Of course you will have heard of the death of our <hi rend="italic">useful old Dr.</hi>,<note xml:id="ftn3-681" place="foot" n="681"> Thomas Hitchings MRCS.</note> and will (with <hi rend="italic">many others</hi>) have mourned over it and sympathised with his 4 daughters! Possibly you may have heard the sad news before me: I only first knew of it on Tuesday night (27<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.), <hi rend="italic">after </hi>my return from Woodville—not having seen a “Herald” of that mg. Moreover I had <hi rend="italic">not </hi>heard of his illness, just the contrary: it was <hi rend="italic">a shock </hi>to me, (much like that of the Bp’s. determination—which <hi rend="italic">I first heard of </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">here</hi>, when staying in Septr. last) he was one of my oldest acqs. left in Napier,—my neighbour, &amp; Doctor, and hearing <hi rend="italic">late</hi>, &amp; situated as I am, I could not possibly be at his funeral,—an additional sorrow! I wrote a note of sympathy to the daughters.—</p>
         <p>When I last wrote a few lines to you I was <hi rend="italic">unwell </hi>from severe &amp; obstinate diarrhoea, that continued 4 days, so that I was obliged to see Dr. &amp; take med.,—it left me <hi rend="italic">very weak</hi>! I could not go to Wdv. on the Thursday (as arranged) but went on Friday aftn.–evg., weather fine <hi rend="italic">then </hi>also on Saty., but Saty. nt.—<hi rend="underline italic">rain</hi> &amp; so on Sunday! pouring (my <hi rend="italic">old Wdv. </hi>luck!) Mr. Eccles prevailed on me to take evg. S., Congn. 60, or so, far more than I expected in such weather:—Monday stormy &amp; showery, so I kept my room all day, &amp; returned on Tuesday. Found <hi rend="italic">several letters </hi>from all quarters awaiting me, &amp; also a prodigious batch of “proofs” from Dr. H.—of <hi rend="italic">all </hi>my 4–5 papers read at N. (<hi rend="italic">more </hi>than I had expected to see), these had been nearly a week from date of sending! of course, addd. to me at Napier, &amp; reaching Dvk. on the <hi rend="italic">Friday</hi>, so I had to <hi rend="italic">read </hi>until my eyes ached! and, as hitherto, <hi rend="italic">no copy </hi>sent w. them! Consqy. I could only read for Com. errors, but now &amp; then marking— “see copy”: as to the <hi rend="italic">many </hi>references, I could do nothing. But the “proofs” were remarkably clean,—who, or what, is the Mr. “Bothamley”, who sends them out? I sent them back next day. <hi rend="italic">Another </hi>letter from “Herbert Jones”, which I have ansd. pretty fully, telling him, “I must beg to decline <hi rend="italic">writing </hi>anything for his book”—but pointing out—several of my papers in vols. “Trans.” including 2 “essays” in vol. I, that might be of service, and also giving him my reasons: I shall send you his <hi rend="italic">additional </hi>and <hi rend="italic">fresh </hi>paper of names of Co-adjutors, and you may smile over some of them—particularly in our H.B. lot! I have also warned him against taking up informn. from the man-in-the-street: he had been N. as far as Hokianga, &amp; got hold of Winkelmann—who, actually, also wrote me a letter to <hi rend="italic">aid</hi>—giving it open to Jones, who enclosed it.</p>
         <p>A long &amp; intg. letter from Hamilton, written nt. of 20<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., he was leaving <hi rend="italic">next mg. </hi>for Macquarie Islands, &amp; expd. to be absent 3–4 weeks: I hope the dear fellow will do well there, &amp; go &amp; return in safety—he has Jennings—the taxidermist, with him; his <hi rend="italic">bark </hi>is the “Gratitude”, 100 tons:—keep a look-out for <hi rend="italic">name</hi>.</p>
         <p>Also, a long &amp; good letter from Hill, he leaves for the N. about 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. and wished to see me at Napier! but he should have arranged to do so <hi rend="italic">here in Bush</hi>—instead of <hi rend="italic">rushing </hi>through! <hi rend="italic">as he knew of my days</hi>.——</p>
         <p>I had a bit of ugly adventure on Wedy. last, that might have terminated seriously. I had recd. a note from Miss (?) “P. Grant” of Ormondville, enqg. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">seeds of ferns</hi> for a friend in Melbourne, and the day being fine I went into the neighbouring Bush to get a single small spn. of a tree-fern bearing seeds: for a <hi rend="italic">long </hi>time I could not find one, &amp; when I did—I was unable to find my way out! &amp; thus for a long time &amp; getting worse &amp; worse, mainly <hi rend="italic">from excess of weakness in knees</hi>, and the knowledge I had no <hi rend="italic">matches </hi>with me; however, <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> being gracious, I did emerge. exhausted! nearly 3 hours spent in extricating myself, &amp; reached hotel <hi rend="underline italic">w. diffy</hi>. by 5 p.m. A glass of wine proved of service, but I have felt it ever since, &amp; have done nothing, save ansr. letters. Rev. Robertshawe is gone to “Weber District”, for Sunday, &amp;c., &amp; I have to do my best here, on that day. The weather at <hi rend="italic">present</hi>, fine but chilly.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">3</hi>
            <hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. Mg. fine: would go to Makotuku Hortl. Show this day, were it not for my Sunday’s duty tomorrow; Your cousin R. is to open it; I see in Waipawa paper, he will soon be leaving for England. I note in “D.T.” last night H.S. Tiff., G. Richardson, &amp; Cotterill, Dr. H’s. 3 Executors: also, a letter from a correspdt. saying the Dr’s. <hi rend="italic">Son</hi>, who died at Wairarapa some yrs. ago, left a <hi rend="italic">son </hi>who is now at Whanganui school. Do you recollect the Dr’s. <hi rend="italic">Son</hi>? (I feel shaky this mg., need to <hi rend="italic">get out</hi>!)</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">5</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. Evg. </hi>Yours of 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. is to hand, and I thank you for it: one (at least) good bit of news in it, your having employ in P.O., I would I had <hi rend="italic">better </hi>from you <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Victor, but there might have been worse, &amp; I will still <hi rend="italic">Hope </hi>for the best. I think you omitted (?) 2–3 queries in my last (<hi rend="italic">not </hi>the memo.) but I do not recollect them, save <hi rend="italic">one</hi>—the likeness of the Govr. N.S.W. to <hi rend="italic">Dr. H.</hi>—from memory. I had only <hi rend="italic">one reason </hi>for asking you to say a wd. to T. (<hi rend="underline italic">if you could well do so</hi>) viz. that S. <hi rend="italic">had promised </hi>such to <hi rend="italic">R. &amp; S. early</hi>; &amp; then <hi rend="italic">at close </hi>of Sess., R. &amp; S. left a joint memo. w. S. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>same; &amp; if <hi rend="italic">not done before </hi>Pt. meets, it won’t be after! and I don’t like to write to Capt. R. again—after treatment at last election.—–</p>
         <p>And so <hi rend="italic">you </hi>had rain at the Hutt! as I at Wdv. Your mention of <hi rend="italic">that </hi>old Ch. at the Hutt has interested me: I held Service in <hi rend="italic">one </hi>there in ’45 or ’46: my tent was in the Maori <hi rend="italic">pa </hi>at Pitoone (close to sea) &amp; I had to walk about 2 miles (or more)—perhaps the same aftn. S., &amp; a <hi rend="italic">good </hi>Congn., &amp; many thanks at close. I (also) have a copy, large size, of Burton’s “Anatomy of a My.”—I see it is <hi rend="italic">now </hi>being brought out in 6 vols!! &amp; much said in its favour in cols. of “Standard”: by the way, I send you a p. of “St.”, just to have yr. opinion as to <hi rend="italic">cost </hi>of one whole p. advt.—this the 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. time, too; &amp; with it I send a N. Hy. “prospectus” for V., I <hi rend="italic">did think</hi> of becoming a subsr., but have abandoned it: also, a Circular of a “Calg. Machine”! <hi rend="italic">new to me</hi>—<hi rend="italic">this </hi>please return, anon. And send on the ptd. Lexn. letters, at yr. convenience, as I have recd. 6 from you, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">w. these yr. Memo. of cost</hi>. I suppose you know Clayton has sold out here—he goes to Blenheim—he has been there before, so he told me. Yesterday Sunday (4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) was a fine day—a little rain early—8–10p.—sufficient to keep <hi rend="italic">some </hi>from Ch., Congn. mg. small—40—evg. good, 120. I preached from Ps. xxii. 22— “I will declare thy N. to my brethren” (part of Ps. for that Evg. S.) &amp; I could not refrain from mentioning an idea that occurred vividly to me—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the Bp. in reading prayers, &amp;c, at sea—preaching from <hi rend="italic">same </hi>text! Service was not over until viii.40—partly owing to the <hi rend="italic">very long </hi>Hymns (4 Hymns—1, 7 v. 4 l.—1, 5 v. 12 l.—1, 6 v. 8 l.) which had been selected! moreover (as I hinted), probably <hi rend="underline italic">my last</hi> Sn.</p>
         <p>I have recd. an excellent letter from Belle Hitchings, in reply, <hi rend="italic">long </hi>too! they are much “cut up” at <hi rend="italic">their loss</hi>:—&amp; so the G.O.M. <hi rend="italic">has resigned</hi>! well, we will hope for the best. Bp. Selwyn is <hi rend="italic">out </hi>for <hi rend="italic">Melanesian </hi>Mission <hi rend="italic">funds</hi>. I do not like “Herald” today, saying, the 2 most unhealthy towns are Hastings &amp; <hi rend="italic">Waipukurau</hi>—because, recently 3 deaths Diptheria childn. in <hi rend="italic">one</hi> family at W., &amp; <hi rend="italic">one </hi>ditto typh. fever at Hgs.—in my opinion (<hi rend="italic">old one</hi> too!) far too much said &amp; done <hi rend="italic">re </hi>sanitary matters nowadays in small Country places. I purpose returning on Thursday next. I am well—but not <hi rend="italic">very </hi>well; yet <hi rend="italic">am comfortable </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">here</hi>.</p>
         <p>     And now w. kindest regards, I am, Yours ever.</p>
         <p>                                                                             W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>“Herald”—3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. R.T. Walker &amp; wife, daughter living, son still born.</p>
         <p>P.S. I sometimes fancy, <hi rend="italic">yours </hi>are in Lg. Primer—mine (w. abbns.) in Nonp. or Ruby—!!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
