<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0770">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 March 2: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0495.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-03-02">1891 March 2</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 March 2: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-515" place="foot" n="515"> ATL qMS-0495.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>From D.T. Feby 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>.</p>
         <p rend="justify">About a year ago a gentleman lecturing in the bush, referred to the Rev. Mr Colenso as the only living witness of the signing of the Treaty of Waitangi. Having a facsimile copy of the various sheets of signatories appended to the Treaty I found Mr Colenso’s name was not among the witnesses, but the Rev. O. Hadfield’s was, and said so in one of my letters at the time. I was recently called to account for this, and referred to a book written by the rev. gentleman and published last year, for proof of the original statement. I have it now before me, and it is entitled “The authentic and genuine history of the signing of the Treaty of Waitangi.” It is a very interesting narrative, giving the speeches made by Captain Hobson and the various natives at two meetings held at Waitangi on 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb. 1840, and it shows that Mr Colenso was present at the signing of the treaty by forty-five chiefs, but was not a witness in an official sense. To him, however, is done the credit of being the only person who has reported fully that momentous occasion. As I have no copy of what I actually wrote, I am unable to explain further, but I am very sorry that it should have caused any unpleasantness, as I always endeavour to avoid saying anything in a way calculated to hurt anyone’s feelings and it was the last thought in my mind to show any disrespect towards Mr Colenso.</p>
         <p>Rev. O.H. was <hi rend="italic">not </hi>there.</p>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Monday night<lb/>March 2, 1891.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>Having recd. a line, from you (tho’, as you say—“not a letter,”) I will commence my jottings.—</p>
         <p>On receipt—I sent off a <hi rend="italic">delayed</hi> telm. as requested—to purchase 6 vols. J.Wh. as high as pubd. price: and, to intimate, “I do not <hi rend="italic">care</hi> for Hochstetter”: I had it once (Lyon obtd. it for me on its publn.) but I never thought much of it, &amp; so I parted with it: of course, it was only a transln., &amp; <hi rend="italic">disfigured</hi> by drawings—unnatural—by <hi rend="italic">Heaphy </hi>&amp; others: the same errors in it, as in later works on N.Z., inserting every bit of<hi rend="italic"> </hi>garbage, <hi rend="italic">no matter by whom</hi>! (as in “The Monthly Review,” &amp;c. &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>I was rather surprised to find my long letter (closed &amp; posted on 25<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> ult.) had <hi rend="italic">not</hi> reached you on 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.—however, I suppose it did soon after.—</p>
         <p>I was down in town, on business, (long delayed,) on 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., but went forth <hi rend="italic">fearing</hi>—I felt so <hi rend="italic">very weak</hi>, however I managed to get through all: I go again <hi rend="italic">tomorrow</hi> for the last time before I go inland, which I purpose doing on Thursday. Yesty. tho’ <hi rend="italic">fine</hi> I stayed at Home, fearing draughts, &amp;c. in Ch., &amp; Parkinson’s (which I prefer) being rather a long &amp; dark jy. to and fro by night.—</p>
         <p>Today I was engaged in “a <hi rend="italic">hunting</hi>” among <hi rend="italic">old</hi> stores (proofs, sheets books, unfinished, Mss. &amp;c, &amp;c.) in my back lumber room (over Library), &amp; I was pleased w. some of my “<hi rend="italic">finds</hi>”,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>(I would <hi rend="italic">you</hi> were present!)—I shall send you, w. this, a copy (or two) of my tract <hi rend="italic">v. </hi>R.C.—of which I had told you, viz. “<hi rend="italic">The reception of 3 R.C. Priests into the Ch. of E. by the Bp. of London</hi>: this caused me some trouble &amp; (?) persecution from some of our own party! I had printed it at my <hi rend="italic">own expense</hi> (as others of a similar kind), and by <hi rend="italic">working after hours</hi>. This caused my <hi rend="italic">first</hi> tussle w. Bp. Selwyn—thro’ the crass stupidity of <hi rend="italic">Burrows</hi>—who was <hi rend="italic">here</hi> last wk. Also, some of my Paihia “Chqs” (or order)—of an <hi rend="italic">early</hi>, date before Ty. Waitgi.—<hi rend="italic">Also</hi> some more spns. of my ptg. at Waitangi—to me <hi rend="italic">very interesting</hi>! Recalling <hi rend="underline italic">much</hi>, and, a copy of the <hi rend="italic">first</hi> little book printed at the Bp’s. press, “Agathos”, (this <hi rend="italic">unique</hi> vol., I can only<hi rend="italic">lend you</hi>, it must be returned <hi rend="italic">by-&amp;-by</hi> with those letters:)—a similar book was published <hi rend="italic">there</hi> in 1844, but in this last one Rev. W. Cotton’s new type (wº) was used for <hi rend="italic">wh</hi>. I may mention a curious fact,—the wrappers (old newspapers) of my little “<hi rend="italic">Sheets</hi>”! ea. <hi rend="italic">2p.</hi> separately put up, were devoured all round their edges, but the sheets themselves <hi rend="italic">untouched</hi>!—</p>
         <p>Would you kindly enq. of Tregear (but <hi rend="italic">not</hi> as coming from me,) what plant, or shrub, it is that the <hi rend="italic">Taranaki</hi> Maoris call <hi rend="italic">Turuhuhu</hi>? (The question has been put to me,)—the Maoris of Taranaki differ from others in <hi rend="italic">many</hi> words.—</p>
         <p>What is the meaning of “<hi rend="italic">F.R.S. Hist. S</hi>.”? <hi rend="italic">after</hi> Tregear’s name?.—</p>
         <p>Who is “Twiselton”?—</p>
         <p>I hope you may obtain those 6 vols. of J.W’s. from the Hutt;—and if so, I leave it to you <hi rend="italic">how best</hi> to send them on; together with a <hi rend="italic">Pinchd</hi>. copy of “Tregear’s Dy.” well-bound; 2 copies of <hi rend="italic">last</hi> no. of “Mthly. Review”, &amp; 1 copy “Collier’s Biog. Dy.”—&amp; I will <hi rend="italic">immy. remit</hi>.</p>
         <p>I shall send in a separate small packet, the few printed things mentioned on t’other side.—I think they will <hi rend="italic">interest you</hi>, in more ways than one. I hope you may be able to <hi rend="italic">read</hi> Karepa.—</p>
         <p>I find (from you), that Tregear’s big book is <hi rend="italic">finished</hi>: and that the “Monthly Review,” is also <hi rend="italic">ended. </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">How</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> does all that affect you</hi>? Has L. &amp; B. <hi rend="italic">sufficient </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">future</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> Book work</hi> to <hi rend="italic">keep</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">you on</hi>? (<hi rend="italic">Don’t think </hi>I am prying into your own private affairs.) <hi rend="italic">I much wish to know</hi>.</p>
         <p>If you <hi rend="italic">succeed</hi> in obtaining those 6 vols. at Fitz. sale then, please, let Didsbury (or his factotum) know—I don’t want any from him.—</p>
         <p>I much fear, Dy. will be sending up <hi rend="italic">proofs</hi> of Lex., A., when I am leaving—or at Dvk!</p>
         <p>The Copy of “My. Review” (you sent) is also to hand, I purpose going into it tomorrow: I have been writing, &amp; putting-up Papers, for this Eng. Mail leaving <hi rend="italic">here</hi> tomorrow, to make-up, &amp;c, for my omissions in the last wk’s. S.F. one—</p>
         <p rend="end">—So, Good night.</p>
         <p>Tuesday, 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>—VII. p.m.—</p>
         <p>This mg. in town I recd. yr. letter of 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>—thanks. (anon.) While there I saw Large, <hi rend="italic">first</hi> since Annl. Mtg., on going up to speak, &amp;c, L. was <hi rend="italic">rather</hi> stiff,—but my <hi rend="italic">bonhommie</hi> prevailed! and for some time we talked.—I had been, by note, urging White to get Report ptd., offering to aid (if reqd.) in correcting, &amp;c., but from L. I found—it is to be delayed until they were <hi rend="italic">well</hi> in funds! (Will that be before Xmas!?) For <hi rend="italic">late</hi> Curator’s demand is £60.!!! 3 yrs. salary, &amp;c. (Quite new to me.) And nothing will be done until <hi rend="italic">he</hi> turns up. Further, L. spoke of getting <hi rend="italic">it</hi> ptd. by contract. This aftn. I sent him £1.1.0., <hi rend="italic">yr. subsn</hi>.—but <hi rend="italic">this is to stand over between us</hi>. I have sent to P.O. 2 papers for you, 1 E.N., &amp; 1 H.,—in <hi rend="italic">former</hi> Mr Paterson’s sermon: in <hi rend="italic">latter, </hi>art. on <hi rend="italic">libel case</hi>.</p>
         <p>If I mistake not, you told me—that yr. vol. Trans. commence w. XIV? If so, I fear you <hi rend="italic">may not </hi>have a copy of my paper on the <hi rend="italic">Moa</hi>—&amp; of another (or 2?)—M. Proverbs, &amp; M.<hi rend="italic">Poetry</hi>?—be sure <hi rend="italic">to let me</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">know.</hi> Without these you could not have a correct notion of Smith’s paper on <hi rend="italic">M. Proverbs</hi>: &amp; more recently of Stack’s outrageous pillaging—without the <hi rend="italic">least acknt!</hi> Tregear <hi rend="italic">does</hi> (in a way) acknge., in his Ethnological Paper—pubd. in London:—if you can not <hi rend="underline italic">well</hi> get this from T., I will send you my copy. Moreover, have you a copy of my “<hi rend="italic">3 Lity. P</hi>.”? pubd. at D.T. Office—let me know.—</p>
         <p>I have hastened to run through your review of Tregear’s Dy. in <hi rend="italic">Mthly. Rev. </hi>&amp; think it well &amp; clearly &amp; briefly written.—ably, too, <hi rend="italic">a-la-R.C. Harding.</hi> But there are some items therein <hi rend="italic">new</hi> to me.</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">Re: </hi>John Wesley.</item>
            <item>“  <hi rend="italic"> </hi>Fire<hi rend="italic">brought from Hawaiki.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>“  Maori &amp; wife, a few yrs. ago, emigrating from E.C. to Hawaiki.—</item>
         </list>
         <p>Further,—“barbaric jargon”—<hi rend="italic">good</hi>: Fitst. lately decd. <hi rend="italic">thus</hi> spoke of it <hi rend="italic">to</hi> me, &amp; <hi rend="italic">in the Ho.,</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">agt.</hi> the Lexn—alas!—<hi rend="italic">no</hi> Hansard then!—</p>
         <p>“Songs from <hi rend="italic">old</hi>”: true: &amp; yet Gill (of whom <hi rend="italic">so much</hi> is, &amp; has been, made), gives in his vol. the “<hi rend="italic">circa</hi>” when ea. was written—or, burst forth from the Poet’s brain!—<hi rend="underline italic">that</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">disgusted</hi> me w. his Book: and I <hi rend="underline italic">closed</hi> it!—</p>
         <p>“<hi rend="italic">Standard</hi> work Wms. Dicty.” I would you had said—<hi rend="underline italic">only</hi>.</p>
         <p>T “<hi rend="italic">14 yrs</hi>. lity. toil.” <hi rend="italic">this</hi> serves to make <hi rend="underline italic">me</hi> ashamed of <hi rend="italic">his early letters </hi>to <hi rend="italic">me</hi>.—</p>
         <p>“<hi rend="underline italic">Endless</hi> lexicons.”—(?)</p>
         <p>If T’s. Dy. is <hi rend="italic">such</hi>, as <hi rend="italic">you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">state</hi> in close, then my part A. there had better <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be ptd.—</p>
         <p>I thank <hi rend="italic">you much</hi> (and <hi rend="italic">again</hi>) for your kind &amp; truthful remark on my <hi rend="italic">old</hi> labours <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Dy.</p>
         <p>Both of your late letters came to hand <hi rend="italic">without</hi> stamps on them! owing to their <hi rend="italic">shameful</hi> gumming: Jago told me today, he had returned £100 worth! &amp; Craig &amp; man half wild.</p>
         <p>I knew Carpenter <hi rend="italic">well</hi>—<hi rend="italic">often</hi> in his shop, &amp; bought 1–2 books from him: at one time he was M.P.C.—</p>
         <p>Re my own Liby—I am puzzled: think—all (of <hi rend="underline italic">service</hi>) should be sent to L. to Quarritch for sale. Had our <hi rend="italic">precious</hi> (!!) Instit. turned out <hi rend="italic">better</hi>: had the Athenaeum folks acted more wisely, instead of <hi rend="italic">letting</hi> that remg. bit of ground to <hi rend="italic">Large</hi> for a timber yd.,—and my offer of £300—(to head a subsn.—for building Liby. &amp; Museum), refused in consequence—then, no doubt, my books, spns &amp;c. would be given there—but <hi rend="italic">not now</hi>. I bear, also, in mind w. increasing bitterness of soul! as the years roll by, that I have <hi rend="italic">no road to my house</hi>! neither will the Borough Council help, or care the least about it!! While they would, &amp; will, tax me for road to their Breakwater &amp; for <hi rend="italic">Tourists</hi> (!!!) <hi rend="italic">to Taupo</hi>.—</p>
         <p>By the way, I hear from my man Robert, &amp; from others, that the damage done to Breakwater is not very great. (And Robert, like myself, always <hi rend="italic">against</hi> it.)</p>
         <p>[Some day I may tell <hi rend="italic">you</hi> a lot about Kirk, Senr. (originally an <hi rend="italic">Auckland</hi> settler—in a <hi rend="italic">very poor way</hi>) thro’ <hi rend="italic">me</hi>—he came S. I <hi rend="italic">did much for him</hi>, in many ways: but – – – <hi rend="underline italic">private this.</hi>]—</p>
         <p>I wholly agree w. you in your clear &amp; trenchant remarks on “Necromancy”—of <hi rend="italic">all kinds</hi> of sorts, ancient &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">Modern</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I suppose you could <hi rend="italic">not</hi>, <hi rend="underline italic">well</hi>, let me know, whether that part of Lex. A. is being carried on by Dy? I am leaving on 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. for Dvk.—&amp; if I were pretty sure of being called on to <hi rend="italic">read proofs</hi>, &amp;c, &amp;c, I would take a <hi rend="italic">Return</hi> ticket, &amp; so save 10/-.—but I must “<hi rend="italic">chance it</hi>.”—Let your next be addd. to me at Dannevirke.—</p>
         <p>Much pleased to know you both saw &amp; heard <hi rend="italic">Mr. Sidey</hi>.—Parkinson, today, in town, told me of Wills (Opotiki) being prosecuted for <hi rend="italic">criminal libel: </hi>of course I had heard of that before.</p>
         <p>Thanks for your pretty—<hi rend="italic">neat</hi> card w. “Typo’s Compliments”: I had sent t’other to England.—</p>
         <p>I recd. the 2 dz. Cartes from Wrigglesworth, of my <hi rend="italic">old</hi> photos. (I think this lot must be the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.!) I thought his charge high, &amp; <hi rend="italic">curious</hi>— “£<hi rend="italic">2.0.6</hi>.”</p>
         <p>Weather continues <hi rend="italic">very fine</hi>: I never saw N. looking better! Such a lot of green &amp; yg. grass, &amp; my trees &amp; shrubs, <hi rend="italic">rejoicing!!—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Very little of Rheumatism, and I find my strength, appetite, &amp;c, returning, &amp; good—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> for my age. I sincerely hope that you and <hi rend="italic">all</hi> yours are <hi rend="italic">well</hi>.—</p>
         <p rend="end">[<hi rend="italic">Goodnight</hi>.]</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">4</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>. I now proceed to close.</p>
         <p>Among several other books lately to hand from Engd. is “Lux Mundi”:—I have cut it, &amp; peeped here &amp; there—but had I known it is written by <hi rend="italic">Puseyite</hi> Clerics (<hi rend="italic">officials</hi> of Pusey &amp; Keble Colleges) I should not have ordered it. Still there are some good things in it. I hope to read it in Bush quiet.—</p>
         <p>And with <hi rend="italic">kindest </hi>regards and<hi rend="italic">best</hi> wishes, I am,</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
