<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0164">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1862 December 10: to the Colonial Secretary</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Archives Ref No. IA1 242; 1863/2384. A Domett.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9457/">the Colonial Secretary</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1862-12-10">1862 December 10</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1862 December 10: to the Colonial Secretary<note xml:id="ftn2-66" place="foot" n="66"> Archives Ref No. IA1 242; 1863/2384. A Domett.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, December</p>
         <p rend="end">10<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., 1862 </p>
         <p>The Hon The Colonial Secretary</p>
         <p>Auckland.</p>
         <p>Sir, </p>
         <p>On the 14th ult. I did myself the honor of acknowledging the receipt of your letter of the 6th ulto. (with enclosure being a copy of a letter from Bishop Williams to the Hon. the Colonial Secretary, dated September 5, 1862):— at the same time informing you, that, in consequence of my then approaching official visit to the Wairoa district as Provincial Inspector of Schools, I could not possibly answer your letter by return on the steamer “Queen” to Auckland. Having, however, returned from my tourof Inspection on the 28<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. Ulto., and having also just concluded the common heavy monthly duties of my Office as Provincial Treasurer, I have now the honor of replying to your Letter, and of making such remarks on Bp. Williams’ letter, for the information of the Government, as will, I trust, be found suitable and conclusive, and at the same time as brief as possible.</p>
         <p>2. Before, however, that I proceed to notice Bp. Williams’ Letter, I would beg to call your attention to a slight clerical error in your Letter of the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. November. You there speak of “land occupied by me at <hi rend="italic">Te Aute</hi>”:—I presume that you mean Te Awapuni, or Waitangi,—from which Te Aute is 25 miles distant.—And, further, to be allowed to refer you to my letter to you of the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. September last, especially to clauses marked, <hi rend="italic">b</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> c</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>and <hi rend="italic">d</hi>, when considering the Copies and Extracts enclosed.—</p>
         <p>3. Permit me also, Sir, at the outset, to state:— that— while I clearly perceive both the spirit and aim of Bp. Williams, in his letter to the Hon. the Col. Secretary concerning me,—and am sensibly alive to all the charges so Christianly (?) expressed and implied by the writer,—and strongly feel that (if really necessary) I could easily answer and refute them;—that were all Bishop Williams has stated in his letter perfectly correct, such (both in the opinion of several judicious friends to whom I have shewn his letter, as well as in my own) has nothing whatever to do with the real matter at issue:—viz. my receiving equitable compensation for my property and improvements recently abandoned at Waitangi, at the desire of the General Government.—May I be allowed, Sir, to call your attention for a moment to clause E. par 1, of my letter to you of September 20th 1862?— </p>
         <p>4. Bp. Williams, in par 3 of his letter, states:—that, about the year 1844 or 1845 I had received from him the sum of £70 (seventy pounds) to cover the expenses of a temporary raupo building and of fencing at Te Awapuni; (also, intimating that I had received no more;) and, further, in par. 4, that in 1853 (December) my connection with the C.M. Society was dissolved.— </p>
         <p>5. The said £70 was indeed received by me from Bp. Williams in the Bay of Islands in October 1844, (when preparing to remove to Hawke’s Bay, after a residence of ten years in th Bay of Islands,) not merely, however, “to cover the expenses of a fence and a temporary <hi rend="italic">raupo</hi> dwelling,” but as the first instalment towards the expenses of forming a Mission Station in a distant, wild, and (then) little-known part of New Zealand,—including, also, my own expenses incidental on removal, (which expenses were by him, as Archdeacon, increased, through my having to call at ASuckland for the Rev. J. Hamlin and family, and all his household goods and Station Stores, he also then removing from Manukau to Te Wairoa in Hawke’s Bay.) While in the Bay of Islands, (in October, 1844,) and <hi rend="italic">with Bp, Williams’ (then </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">Archdeacon of this district</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">,) express sanction , and, indeed, advice</hi>, I purchased 2000 feet of timber, 4000 bricks glass, iron, paints, oils, doors, and window sashes, (this last item alone, cost me <hi rend="underline italic">£9.0.0</hi>, being ordered by himself of his brother’s carpenter,) and also took from Rev. W.C. Dudley Mission Station stores, (nails, paint, saws, etc.) amounting to <hi rend="underline italic">£26.14.10</hi>; which stores had also been ordered purposely for him by Bp. Williams for Te Wairoa Station in Hawke’s Bay, (to which Mr Dudley was originally appointed):—all which, and much more is clearly shown in an abridged copy of my first (original) half-yearly station account (<hi rend="italic">Enclosure No.1</hi>,<note xml:id="ftn2-67" place="foot" n="67"> WC: Enclosure No. 1: copy of ½ yearly Station acct.</note>)<hi rend="italic"> </hi>forwarded by myself from Ahuriri to the Committee of Missionaries held at Poverty Bay in June, 1845; by whom, however, all building and station expenses above <hi rend="underline italic">£73:10:0</hi>. were disallowed!! (“<hi rend="italic">original</hi>,” because it is the account returned to me by the said Committee!— and, note, that the prices charged by me for goods provided for the Maories, (money being of no use <hi rend="italic">here </hi>in those days) were those of the wholesale English manufacturer:—e.g. best 9/4 blankets 5/9, and 10/4 ditto 7/- each:—whereas, in cases not altogether dissimilar, Bp. Williams and his friends were not only allowed “Sydney prices” for goods so sold, but “3 times that amount”! </p>
         <p>6. Further: Bp. Williams, at that very Mission Committee, held in July 1845, at his own house in Poverty Bay, (while disallowing my necessary outlay,) actually paid himself the sum of <hi rend="underline italic">£15.13.4</hi>, being his own demand for <hi rend="italic">additional nails</hi>, hinges, gimlets, locks, etc., being a further part of the Mission Station building stores originally ordered by him for the Wairoa station, and which had been landed at Poverty Bay, and having been there drenched with salt water in landing by native canoes, were <hi rend="italic">almost useless</hi>; in fact, the locks had to be taken to pieces and cleaned, and the nails bad to be <hi rend="italic">burnt</hi> before they could be sundered: a copy of this account I also enclose (<hi rend="italic">Enclosure No.2</hi>).<note xml:id="ftn2-68" place="foot" n="68"> WC: Enclosure No.2: copy of Archd. Williams’ acct.</note>
         </p>
         <p>7. Moreover, and as being further confirmatory of the above, I beg to proffer (<hi rend="italic">Enclosure No. 3</hi>)<note xml:id="ftn2-69" place="foot" n="69"> WC: Enclosure No. 3: Extracts from 2 Letters.</note> extracts from two Letters from myself to the C.M.Society, in June and December, 1846,—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> of so much of each of them as related to the Mission Premises at Waitangi. Also, (<hi rend="italic">Enclosure, No.4</hi>,)<note xml:id="ftn2-70" place="foot" n="70">
               <p> WC: Enclosure No.4: Copy of a letter &amp; Resolution from Secys. CMS. Appended to this enclosure is a “Note by Wm. Colenso. N.B.—it will be seen from the foregoing Letter, that the <hi rend="italic">Duplicate</hi> letter I had written to the C.M.S.,( enclosing a copy of my outlay,) <hi rend="italic">in December 1846</hi>, and had transmitted to Archdn Williams <hi rend="italic">to be by him </hi>(as Chairman of the Eastern District Committee) <hi rend="italic">forwarded to the C.M. Society, </hi>
                  <hi rend="underline italic">had been retained</hi>,—such not having reached them by Feby. 1848. Wm. Colenso.”</p>
            </note> a copy of a letter from the Secretaries of the C. Missionary House, London, to Bp. Williams, respecting the same. And, also, an Extract from another letter of mine to tyhe C.M. Society in 1849, (<hi rend="italic">Enclosure, No.5</hi>).<note xml:id="ftn2-71" place="foot" n="71"> WC: Enclosure No.5: Extract from a Letter of mine to C.M.S.—1849.</note>
         </p>
         <p>8. Bp. Williams in par. 5 of his letter, further states, that “The original raupo house was <hi rend="underline italic">in some way</hi> burnt down.” Unfortunately for me <hi rend="italic">I was not in it at the time of its taking fire</hi>, but an intimate friend of Bp. Williams was, and therefore <hi rend="underline italic">he may know</hi> more of that calamity than I do. One thing, however, was well-known here,—that I lost nearly everything I had by that fire. Bp. Williams goes on to say (par.5) that, after the fire, “I <hi rend="italic">then</hi> lived in a <hi rend="underline italic">small</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> raupo</hi> building,” —as if it were merely some make-shift—such building, however, was a very strong and nice cottage, 26 x 18, wholly floored with <hi rend="italic">kauri</hi> on double joists, having two rooms, a brick chimney, 2 doors and 4 windows,—being, in fact, a beautiful specimen of strong and ornamental Maori work, in tracery, colouring, and <hi rend="italic">totara </hi>carving:—a building, known to yourself, Sir, and also to your predecessor Mr Fox. The “<hi rend="italic">small</hi> weather-boarded store” (also mentioned, in par. 5, by Bp. Williams,) measures 30 x 22, is high, divided into two rooms by a planed wooden partition; has 5 windows and 2 doors,—one room being laid with a mud floor, and the other floored with <hi rend="italic">kauri</hi> timber.—</p>
         <p>9. In par. 7 of his letter, Bp. Williams further states,— “For the buildings therefore which had been erected” Mr Colenso had received a <hi rend="underline italic">stipulated</hi> sum, &amp;c. &amp;c.—This I utterly deny; and believe, the documents now enclosed are fully sufficient to disprove all such “<hi rend="underline italic">stipulation</hi>.” No doubt, (as he states in the same par.,) “I incurred expenses on my own responsibility, and laid out my money upon land over which I could have no [legal] claim.”—This I have proved to my cost and extreme dissatisfaction.— </p>
         <p>10. Bp. Williams’ statement in par. 8 has been fully answered by me when before the Civil Commissioner. I had invariably replied to that demand, (vide my published letters to the Bp. of N. Zealand’s attorney, Mr Brandon,)—“<hi rend="italic">If I</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">must</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">leave all I require is equitable compensation</hi>”—I should also add, to prevent misconception, that I was never once requested to remove from the said spot by the C.M. Society; although I had early made them acquainted with my determination (they being willing) to end my days on it.—</p>
         <p>11. As to par. 9 of Bishop Williams’ Letter, all I can say is, that I am totally ignorant of every portion of it. I beg to enclose a copy of a note of enquiry which I wrote to Mr. McLean, and also a copy of that gentleman’s reply.<note xml:id="ftn2-72" place="foot" n="72">
               <p> WC: Enclosure No.6: note to Mr. McLean and his answer.Although Colenso certified enclosure 6 as a “true copy” it differs somewhat from the original (above).</p>
            </note>
         </p>
         <p>12. Bp. Williams, in par.3 of his letter, after mentioning “the <hi rend="italic">temporary</hi> raupo building,” says,— “that a weather-board house was not erected, nor was it indeed required for the reason which is given below” (<hi rend="italic">viz</hi>. the dissolving of my connexion with the C.M. Society, in 1853)—But, surely, there must have been some other reason. For this “<hi rend="italic">temporary raupo building</hi>,” (mark, not merely “<hi rend="italic">raupo</hi>”, but “<hi rend="underline italic">temporary</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> raupo</hi>,”) was ordered by Bp. Williams and myself when in Hawke’s Bay in 1843,—and yet, by his own voluntary admission, no weather-board house had even been commenced 10 years after! Why was this? Because the said “temporary raupo building”,—or, the Mission house,—(which Bp. Williams well-knew, having several times been hospitably entertained under its roof,)—was a strong, well-built, commodious house; the main part of the building being 50 x 36,—neatly reeded in imitation of cane-work, and highly ornamented with native carving;—(some of the posts were nearly two feet across,—all of them were of hard-wood, and dubbed down smooth with the adze;)—containing 12 rooms and two large corridor-like passages, floored, (including its large verandah 46 x 8) with <hi rend="italic">kauri</hi> and <hi rend="italic">totara</hi> timbers; having 16 windows all glazed, three of which were 6ft. 6in. folding french sashes,) and 17 doors, and two excellently well-built brick chimnies, (which, spite of earthquakes, are still standing and good). A house, which all who saw it admired, and which the Bishop of New Zealand more than once said, he very much and greatly preferred to a weather boarded one.—Sir, I am happy in being able to enclose an accurate ground-plan of it, faithfully taken from the old original (<hi rend="italic">Enclosure No.7</hi>.)<note xml:id="ftn2-73" place="foot" n="73"> WC: Enclosure No.7: ground-plan of old Mission House at Waitangi.</note>—</p>
         <p>13. Moreover, I should state, that, in addition to the <hi rend="italic">one</hi> “temporary raupo building” of Bp. Williams, there were also, (<hi rend="italic">besides</hi> the weather-boarded store, and snug study, already mentioned,) <lb/>  1.<hi rend="italic">A totara framed raupo house</hi>, 27 x 14, having 3 rooms, 4 glazed windows, and 3 doors, and a good chimney; used for Maori male domestics—(this building was <hi rend="italic">twice</hi> erected). <lb/>  2.<hi rend="italic">A School-house</hi>, for women and children, 40 x 20, having 4 glazed windows, a door, and a pair of gates, and neatly enclosed within a paled totara fence. <lb/>  3.<hi rend="italic">A roomy store-house</hi>, (or “<hi rend="underline italic">rua</hi>”,) for potatoes, pumpkins, &amp;c., raised on four strong posts, native fashion. <lb/>  4.<hi rend="italic">A boat-house</hi>, also <hi rend="italic">twice</hi> erected. <lb/>  5.<hi rend="italic">A privy</hi> properly finished. <lb/>  6.<hi rend="italic">A Stock-yard</hi>, all totara, brought from the interior. <lb/>  7.<hi rend="italic">A goat-house and yard</hi>.<lb/>  8.<hi rend="italic">A fowl-house and fence</hi>. <lb/>  9.<hi rend="italic">A well</hi>, dug, enclosed, and arched over with totara slabs. <lb/>  10.<hi rend="italic">A house for bees and for garden tools</hi>. <lb/>  11.<hi rend="italic">4½ acres of fields, garden and orchard ground, and court and farm yards</hi>, well fenced in 8 compartments, having also 8 gates.—<lb/>  Together with<hi rend="italic">many choice fruit trees and perennial roots</hi> of various kinds, purchased at Auckland and the Bay of Islands, and <hi rend="italic">Grass</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Clover seed</hi> from England.</p>
         <p>14. In concluding my review of Bp. Williams’ letter, I may be allowed to make a passing remark on the beginning of hios par. 4,—where he says,— “About the year 1853 <hi rend="underline italic">it became </hi>known “that Mr. Colenso had been guilty of gross immoral conduct, in consequence of which he was suspended by the Bishop, &amp;c.” Sir, I will not ask the necessity of this “voluntary” statement on the part of this Christian Bishop in writing to the Government about Waitangi, concerning a matter which occurred 12 years ago—concerning a person with whom he had been on terms of intimacy throughout a period of nearly 20 years!—but, I think Sir, I may justly complain—first,—of his entirely overlooking (or hiding) the fact, of my having become my own accuser to my Bishop of my conduct—(whether “<hi rend="underline italic">grossly</hi> immoral”, or not,)—and secondly that Bp. Williams, in addition to his sad want of charity, (in thus voluntarily opening old sores) shews his utter forgetfulness of that memorable classification by his Great Master,—viz. that “out of the heart proceedeth”—not only “fornication”,—but, “<hi rend="italic">Evil thoughts, and false witness</hi>, <hi rend="italic">which</hi>” (He said, <hi rend="italic">equally with that</hi>,) “<hi rend="italic">defileth a man</hi>.” —It would appear, however, as if this Bishop only knew of <hi rend="italic">one</hi> kind of “immorality.”— </p>
         <p>15. And, I cannot but deem it proper (in my own defence) to inform you, Sir,—that the real cause, or causes, of dislike (so correctly and plausibly concealed,) on the part of Bp. Williams against myself, arise from <hi rend="underline italic">other sources</hi> than that alluded to in par. 4 of his letter; but of which (although I may justly enough do so) I will not <hi rend="underline italic">now</hi> say any thing. </p>
         <p>16.Since commencing this Letter I have received answers from Messrs. Alexander and Lowry to a note of enquiry which I wrote to each of them respecting the old Mission House at Waitangi: they being the only Settlers in this District who saw the Mission Premises previous to the fire. I enclose copies of my notes to them,—(<hi rend="italic">Enclosure, No.8</hi>,)<note xml:id="ftn2-74" place="foot" n="74"> WC: Enclosure No.8: copy of a note to Messrs. Alexander and Lowry. <hi rend="italic">[see below].</hi>
            </note> and of their answers to the same (<hi rend="italic">Enclosures, Nos. 9 and 10).</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">
               <note xml:id="ftn2-75" place="foot" n="75"> WC: Enclosure No.9 &amp; 10: copies of replies from Messrs. Alexander and Lowry.</note>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>I have the honor to be </p>
         <p>Sir, </p>
         <p>Your most obedient servant </p>
         <p>Wm. Colenso.<note xml:id="ftn2-76" place="foot" n="76">
               <p> A minute by Reader Wood is appended: “Minute—I think that the interference of the Government in this matter at all is most unfortunate. The quarrel is clearly between the C.M.S., Mr Colenso and the natives. How to get out of it now that it has gone so far it is difficult to see, but if a loophole should appear we ought I think to take advantage of it, perhaps this very question of the Arbitrators award may afford one, &amp; I quite agree with Mr Bell in thinking that if the value of the house that was burned has been included in the £350-0-0 that it ought not to be paid. As regards the fund from which the compensation is to be paid when the amount is agreed on, there is only one available namely native purposes. The most important question is what is to be done with the land? The deed of cession is not forthcoming, and until we get it, or a true copy of it, no action should in my opinion be taken, as this is manifestly not an ordinary case of sale for a valuable consideration but a cession to the Queen subject to certain conditions. Reader Wood,  Jany. 28/63”.</p>
            </note>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>