<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0748">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1890 September 10: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0495.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1890-09-10">1890 September 10</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1890 September 10: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-482" place="foot" n="482"> ATL qMS-0495.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Sept. 10/90.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I <hi rend="italic">must</hi> begin a letter to you to night even if I do not finish it;—for, since my last to you (on 31<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. ult) I have recd. 2 from you! both good, long &amp; friendly—epitomes of yourself: your last of 7<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst. to hand yesterday.</p>
         <p>Weather suddenly altered in the Bush last week, heavy continuous rain, so I remained at Dvk. until Thursday aftn. &amp; then left <hi rend="italic">in rain</hi>, &amp;c.—storm all the way! I do believe it was at its height when I clambered this hill in pitchy darkness, slipping &amp; staggering—the wind &amp; rain being right in on me from the S. I <hi rend="italic">scarcely managed </hi>to reach my door. I was indeed surprised at the quantity of surface water on open flat lands—after only 24 hours rain, at Takapau, a lake! all around station up to Hotel under water, and so in <hi rend="italic">many</hi> places where I had never seen water lodged before—also all Clive Sq., &amp; down by my gate a foaming torrent!—However, I escaped a cold (tho’ cold enough in <hi rend="italic">train</hi>), I would have remd. at Dvk. till Friday, had there been a train on <hi rend="italic">that day</hi>. I did not go to town until Monday—when it was fine, &amp; so also on Sunday: I saw Mr. Paterson, Sidey, Craig, Jago &amp; others—all well. Went <hi rend="italic">purposely </hi>to your well-known estab. to see your Brother, &amp; found him well &amp; <hi rend="italic">glad </hi>to see me (though I thought he was looking very thin, &amp; as if fagged at work), while talking—your good Father came in, looking <hi rend="italic">remarkably well</hi>—rosy cheeked, fat, smiling,—I told him he should have his photo. taken, we conversed about 5 min. (partly about you,) the <hi rend="italic">place </hi>seemed <hi rend="italic">so natural</hi>, &amp; recalled many <hi rend="italic">old interviews </hi>(you &amp; I) that I came away musing!! shall I say a <hi rend="italic">sadder</hi>, if not a wiser, man? Your bror. remarked, that Father’s rubicund cheeks arose “from his being then employed in calculating” (Perhaps <hi rend="italic">you </hi>may<hi rend="italic"> understand </hi>this.)—Both Mr. Paterson &amp; Mr. Sidey were greatly pleased at my coming out on 24<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. at Wdv.—in a Lect. “Aid of Presbytn. Ch.”—and, as I found <hi rend="italic">from Mr. P</hi>., that Mr. R. Stewart’s ordn. will (D.V.) take place in Octr. I <hi rend="italic">may </hi>be there—to see. I purpose going again to town tomorrow, as I wish to see the Bp., to know how he has sped at Wdv.—<hi rend="italic">He did not </hi>start in the bad weather, so he &amp; Mr Clarke the student, to be resident Lay Reader at Wdv., had to leave on the Saturday &amp; go right through—and, as <hi rend="italic">no </hi>train there on Tuesday, the Bp. must <hi rend="italic">wait</hi> until today. I purpose leaving <hi rend="italic">here </hi>(say) on 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. for Dvk., and on 22<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. for Wdv.—where I <hi rend="italic">may </hi>spend <hi rend="italic">that week.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Altho’ I had been in town all My. mg. I went to meetg. Instit. on My. night, (as a rule, I never go to town 2ce. in 1 day,)—for, I feared, if I did not “show up”—remarks might be made, &amp; I am pretty sure I shall <hi rend="italic">not </hi>be at their mtg. in Octr.—it was held in the Museum room, a fair attendance—mostly ladies (about 20) but the most wretched dreary meeting I ever remembered! How the audience sat it out so quietly, enduringly, is a mystery!—1. a paper by Dr. Moore, on fleas in dogs! (what a subject!!) he lugged in, abouta scorpion committing suicide: &amp; about Darwin’s Lizards on the Gallipagos <hi rend="italic">not </hi>caring to take to the water, though good swimmers: but the worst was <hi rend="italic">to come. </hi>2. Secy. M. produced a <hi rend="italic">thumping</hi> packet from Hill—on Geologl. Structure of H.B.<hi rend="italic"> </hi>(on folio fcp. &amp; on <hi rend="italic">both </hi>sides!) M commenced reading, &amp; after 15–20 m. <hi rend="italic">agony </hi>(over 3p.) gave it up!!—I, sitting w. Chn. (Dr.S.) asked, “If there were any other p.?” “No.” Then I volunteered to go on w. Hill’s MS.!!! (as I knew his <hi rend="italic">caligraphy</hi>, and a little about his subjt.)—but I, too, was soon floundering! however I kept on (say ¼ hour) when, no use! gave it up. I did <hi rend="italic">not</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">feel disconcerted</hi>—more <hi rend="italic">disgusted—</hi>the p. <hi rend="italic">seemed</hi> to me, a wretched one, so much <hi rend="italic">tautology</hi>, &amp; certainly only a rough draft—no Compo. would care to look at it. (Hill will get it <hi rend="italic">hot </hi>from me.) Then, to my astont., the Dr. began, (in his low prosy mumbling way,) from notes, on slips, to refresh us w. all about the ancestors of our Horse, &amp; megatheriums, &amp;c, &amp;c, (I really thought he would never stop!) more than ½ hour was <hi rend="italic">thus occupied</hi>, I sitting <hi rend="italic">very close </hi>to him scarcely caught a single sentence: he was, moreover, suffg. from a cold;—and put on his glasses about 20–25 times!!</p>
         <p>All over: I showed a photo. (I found here from Hamilton) of a most curious unique “neck ornament of anct. Maori,”—such as I never saw, or heard of, before; it was very large and more like the snout of a sawfish! It was well-exd., but no letter nor memo. w. it; still it was——a <hi rend="underline italic">refresher</hi>! all hands wished <hi rend="italic">me </hi>to attend again <hi rend="italic">last night there </hi>(Concert &amp; Coffee!) but as I don’t care for either I <hi rend="italic">did not go</hi>. I should state, I told them <hi rend="italic">plainly</hi> I should not be there. Large told me, he had sold that precious possession—the House! but the Deed must be sent both S. &amp; N. for H. &amp; B. to sign! &amp; when completed, to be squared—I did <hi rend="italic">not </hi>enq. the sum: our <hi rend="italic">talk between </hi>“acts.”—Hill is away Waip. &amp;c. examg., &amp; Fannin was engaged in R.M. Court. Weather today altered again, <hi rend="italic">cold raw strong </hi>wind from N.—unfitting <hi rend="italic">me </hi>for everything, but much better tonight.——“Typo” to hand, but no time to look into it.</p>
         <p>Now to your letters: am <hi rend="italic">pleased </hi>to find you writing in such <hi rend="underline italic">good</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>spirits, under change of circumstances; hope you will not suffer in any way from these <hi rend="italic">wretched </hi>“strikes”: I note all you say <hi rend="italic">re </hi>same, &amp; agree w. you. I shall not enter on the subject here—but refer you to our locals (as you receive them). Some more youths &amp; yg. men dead, among them the only son (21) of Ellis, Hastings:—he was w. Wilson, Dentist, perhaps you knew him. The <hi rend="italic">new </hi>applicant (mentioned in my Bush letter) for “Memoirs,” &amp;c.—was “I. Bassett, <hi rend="italic">Effective </hi>Advertiser Office, Ludg. Hill, L.” (I cd. <hi rend="italic">not </hi>remr. at Wdv.) Any amount of circulars, prospectuses, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>new works! &amp; <hi rend="italic">this night</hi> (Eng. Mail just to hand) from “Lity. Agency, A.P. Worth, 2 Paternoster Sq., L.”—Prospectus of superb work—Dedd. by <hi rend="italic">perm. </hi>to Queen—“Westminster Hall”—2 large vols. £2.2. to subsn. and (<hi rend="italic">strange </hi>to say!) by “Treadwell Walden, <hi rend="italic">Boston, U.S.A</hi>.——Good night.</p>
         <p>11<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. (p.m. vii.)—I now go on. In town early Sy. mg. I called on Bp. (going up <hi rend="italic">that </hi>steep hill!) he retd. <hi rend="italic">late</hi> last nt. from Wdv., and I think (from his acct.) all things went off pretty <hi rend="italic">well. </hi>I was pleased to find, he (with Mr Clarke) had called on my good friend Rev. R. Stewart, &amp; also on Rev. J. Saunders; and they had fine weather there. In town I met with Large (in a bit of a <hi rend="italic">stew</hi>! <hi rend="italic">vowing</hi>, &amp;c.—he had <hi rend="italic">again </hi>been to Logan about <hi rend="italic">the </hi>Deed,)—the house he had sold for ₤<hi rend="italic">50</hi>. <hi rend="italic">2wce </hi>the Society’s loss (in money &amp; in fame) by that transaction? a letter just to hand from Sir J. Hooker—full of warm praise for <hi rend="italic">your</hi> “Typo” w. portrait. And a strange letter—ptmkd. “Dunedin” &amp; <hi rend="italic">no </hi>stamps! Ergo—cost “4d.” sent by some one from “Helsingford” (w. an unpronounceable name!) to <hi rend="italic">someone there—not named </hi>in the letter—to ask me for lots of N.Z. Mosses—the Helsingford savant to send me lots of N. European ones in return: &amp; so, <hi rend="italic">sent on</hi> to me!!!</p>
         <p>I may mention, R. Stewart told the Bp. of my promised Lect. (which he had also heard from me before he went to Wdv.) and the Bp. <hi rend="italic">strongly </hi>wishes me to take Ch. Service there on 28<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—which I decline (not wishing to renew grief!)—but if he still continues to press it—why, like the good obedt. Centurion, <hi rend="italic">I obey</hi>:—but would <hi rend="italic">rather </hi>not.—He found lodgings for Mr. Clarke, at Crawford’s—whom you may know.—While I was absent in Bush your uncle John came <hi rend="italic">here </hi>&amp; got 2–3 plants, which he had long wished for. I see, in papers, “₤300.—in Suppy. Estimates for Mrs. Featon’s Botanl. Work”: this surprises me, <hi rend="italic">in these times </hi>too, seeing there is <hi rend="italic">nothing new </hi>in it, &amp; in addition to <hi rend="italic">Hooker’s</hi> there is Kirk’s compilation (“Forest Flora of N.Z.”), which must have cost a <hi rend="italic">good deal</hi>, &amp; is certainly <hi rend="italic">poorly </hi>executed.</p>
         <p>Your forceful &amp; truthful remarks <hi rend="italic">re</hi> our boys, struck me, again, this mg. in going down hill, early bef. school, &amp; seeing hundreds swarming below. And what I have <hi rend="italic">long</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">seen</hi>, aye &amp; <hi rend="italic">dreaded</hi>! will now, I fear, the <hi rend="italic">sooner</hi> burst upon us—through this <hi rend="italic">single vote </hi>plan. A few months will show.</p>
         <p>You ask, If I saw Saunders’ S. on “the Gorge Mystery?”—I thought I had called yr. attention to it—&amp; <hi rend="italic">to its </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">text</hi>!! I see in the Papers that <hi rend="italic">other </hi>Ministers, N. &amp; S., are also acting <hi rend="italic">unwisely. Re </hi>that Gorge affair, I, <hi rend="italic">at present</hi>, do <hi rend="italic">not </hi>think it was <hi rend="italic">suicide</hi>, <hi rend="underline italic">more anon</hi>: I mean to carry out my private enquiry there, &amp;c.—I hope your missing box may turn up, all right. <hi rend="italic">Glad</hi> to know of improvement (tho’ small) of son: keep me informed.</p>
         <p>Bear in mind—to address—<hi rend="italic">Dannevirke</hi> but <hi rend="italic">don’t trouble </hi>yourself <hi rend="italic">shortly</hi>.</p>
         <p>And now w. kindest regards——</p>
         <p>Bel. me, Yours faithy, W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
