<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0973">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1896 September 13: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1896-09-13">1896 September 13</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1896 September 13: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-795" place="foot" n="795"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Sunday,<lb/>Septr. 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>/96: viii, p.m.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>Here, <hi rend="italic">alone</hi> (save my thoughts &amp; Books) and <hi rend="italic">thinking on </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>—I have resolved to <hi rend="italic">begin </hi>my letter to you tonight, and to thank you for your long &amp; excellent letter of the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>—found <hi rend="italic">here</hi> on my return on 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>My last to you (&amp; ansd.) was from Dvk. on 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. ulto. On 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I went to Woodville: staying at my old hotel, “Commercial,” near Ry. station, I did not quit my room until I came back to Dvk. on 31<hi rend="sup">st</hi>., mainly owing to wet. I was well, however, there; but on my return to Dvk. caught a <hi rend="underline italic">very severe</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> cold</hi>, which—with <hi rend="italic">continuous </hi>rain <hi rend="italic">all that week</hi>—shut me up a prisoner in my room till Monday 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., when it being <hi rend="italic">fine</hi> (at last!) I ventured out, &amp; came<hi rend="italic"> </hi>to Waipukurau on Tuesday 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>—to Waipawa, 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., back to Gow’s,—and to Napier on 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., weather fine, but I caught a chill on leaving the warm carriage, &amp; climbing this wet &amp; cold steep hill—reaching house <hi rend="italic">w. difficulty</hi>,—Mrs. A. coming through paddock to look me up! I have not been out since, save yesty. a few steps at noon, weather very fine. Our Inst. mtg. is advd. for tomorrow, (for <hi rend="italic">which</hi>, indeed, I came down this week,) but I have just written a note to Dinwiddie to say, that, unless <hi rend="italic">very fine</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">no wind</hi>, I may not be there tomorrow night. Dr. Moore &amp; Hill are advd.—1 paper ea., M. “On Egypt”, H., “The Maori today &amp; future”, (this <hi rend="italic">latter </hi>I should like to hear). I was <hi rend="italic">much </hi>disappointed inland: Mr. Tuke &amp; his congn. had wished me to preach again while inland, &amp; this I had agreed to do on the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">return</hi> jy. to N.)—but my heavy cold &amp; the continuous rain—not to mention the slips in Ry. line at Papatu, and near Matamau—quite prevented me. And (worse still!) on my arrival at Waipukurau on Tuesday aftn., I found Mr. Tuke had left that mg. for his <hi rend="italic">long </hi>round, (not having been able to move out all the preceding wk.) &amp; would not return till Thursday nt. or Friday noon, (Synod, also, beginning this wk. here,) so that, <hi rend="italic">I could not see him</hi>! he was to take me across to Mt. V., to see your Cousin:—and then at the Manse, Mr. Grant was <hi rend="italic">absent all the wk. </hi>at Dvk., retg. on Friday nt., so my whole time seemed to be lost. Of course I called to see <hi rend="italic">our </hi>dear old friend Mrs Trestrail: I found her at Home (having <hi rend="italic">returned</hi> that mg.!) &amp; sitting on the verandah, feet on ground, w. all her loved spring flowers blooming around her, &amp; her attached female friend &amp; helper weeding in the garden and gathering <hi rend="italic">snails</hi>! which I was sorry to see, were very numerous. I sat nearly an hour by Mrs. T’s. side, and was almost sorry to come away. Dear soul! she is much the same as ever, <hi rend="italic">cheerful </hi>&amp; resigned, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">hopeful</hi>. Join w. me, in remg. her in prayer. During my 4 days at Wdv. I saw no one save my old man—Jas. Morgan, who kindly came from Woodlands (4 m.) to see me. And, at Dvk. <hi rend="italic">very few</hi>!—Have nothing good to write about from that quarter—only buildings still erecting, some (stores) very pretentious! <hi rend="italic">panes </hi>of glass (say) 10 ft. high. Mrs Wm. Hunter, Sen., called several times to see me: a lady settler of the good old type. As I could not possibly be at Newton’s funeral (one of my oldest European acquaintances here in N.) I wrote a note to sons, &amp; recd. a nice reply.—–</p>
         <p rend="end">(<hi rend="italic">Continuation:—Tuesday 15</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">., vii, p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Yesty. I put up for you a rare lot of N. papers &amp; cuttings: I do not understand the <hi rend="italic">long </hi>story in suppt. “Herald” <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Tregear: <hi rend="italic">you may</hi>. Last night, <hi rend="underline italic">fine</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">no cold wind</hi>, I ventured out, to Inst. Mtg. Met <hi rend="underline italic">scores</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>wending their way to Royal Theatre, &amp; really supposed—<hi rend="italic">none</hi> for us. Arriving there—only D.! who said, “But for my note” (Sunday night) “he should have gone in for ppment.” (I had reminded D. that My. 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>., both Hill &amp; self, &amp; Dean, &amp; others would be <hi rend="italic">at Synod</hi>.) However, to our great delight, there was a very fair attendance, I suppose 30—more than I had seen since <hi rend="italic">first </hi>mtg. in May: and Dr. Moore (in evg. dress!) read a very fair, long &amp; interesting p. on ancient Egypt—of course, mostly, if not all, from publications—he brought 2 big 4to. vols. (by Hebers (?) I think but not down to date,) the plates of which were shown round by D.—<hi rend="underline italic">while Dr. read on</hi>!! At close: <hi rend="italic">no one </hi>caring to speak, I was obliged to say a little, in addition, having <hi rend="italic">newer </hi>discoveries, &amp;c.—Then Hill came on, w. a <hi rend="underline italic">long</hi> p. (as usual w. him!) at close—in response Craig made 2 remarks, disputing the correctness of the last Census, and, for postponement of discussion—so <hi rend="italic">many </hi>important branches of subject. No one else speaking (&amp; being a <hi rend="italic">Maori </hi>matter, &amp;, seemingly, all looking on me), I felt obliged to say something (first, <hi rend="italic">agreeing</hi> w. C., re discussn. ppd.) and perhaps, said more than I ought to have done—but all were attentive, Mr. Hill’s <hi rend="italic">high-flown </hi>scheme for the Maoris—including their <hi rend="italic">pa’s. </hi>built a-la-Anglaise, w. sanitary improvements, w. Cottage Hospitals, trained Eng. Nurses, resident Doctors, telephones, &amp;c, &amp;c, &amp;c,—I consid. Utopian; and told some <hi rend="italic">plain truths</hi>—reflecting on <hi rend="italic">our </hi>traders (<hi rend="underline italic">Drapers</hi>, &amp;c.)—Lawyers, and, above all, that <hi rend="italic">insatiable </hi>demon pakeha-Maori <hi rend="underline italic">Interpreters</hi> at Ld. Courts. Dinwiddie—<hi rend="italic">after </hi>meeting—said, I was quite right in those remarks. I shall send you “Herald” (15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>) &amp; “Dy.T.”, &amp; you will see (espy. in <hi rend="italic">latter</hi>)—what is <hi rend="italic">said</hi>, &amp; may <hi rend="italic">guess </hi>what <hi rend="underline italic">omitted</hi>! there was no “Discussion” (proper) as no one spoke but myself: but I have had <hi rend="italic">ample </hi>reasons of <hi rend="italic">late</hi>—why those papers so studiously (unfairly) omit me.—In “Herald” you will also see J. Hosking’s <hi rend="italic">reply </hi>to Sutton.—–</p>
         <p>I went to town <hi rend="italic">to day</hi>—first, (day time &amp; business) for a month: &amp; went to <hi rend="italic">Port A. </hi>to see Ellison &amp; D., <hi rend="italic">re </hi>shippg. big case for <hi rend="italic">Kew</hi>; this will be done in “Hawke’s Bay”—due here about Monday next. Saw but few of <hi rend="italic">our</hi> old acqs., Craig, Lyndon, Newton (called on him <hi rend="italic">re </hi>d. &amp; funl. of <hi rend="italic">father</hi>: mother keeping pretty well: of course, <hi rend="italic">all</hi> long prepared for <hi rend="italic">his departure</hi>, &amp; he (poor fellow! <hi rend="italic">from pain</hi>) desirous of leaving) A large addition is being built, <hi rend="italic">all brick</hi>, to Bk. N.Z., extendg. corner &amp; side opp. P.O., w. door <hi rend="underline italic">at corner</hi>. What a revelation of late bef. the Bk. Enqy. Comee. I hear of more of our <hi rend="underline italic">old </hi>Settlers being ruined.</p>
         <p>Last nt., on retg., found Eng. letters, &amp; among them one from Sir J.D. Hooker (being the <hi rend="italic">3</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">rd</hi>. within 1 month!!) this containing 3 beautifully exd. photos., 2 of Sir J. Banks &amp; 1 of Lady B.; 2 of them from a medallion of him on some of Wedgewood’s famed pottery (or china), &amp; 1 from an engraving on glass done by a celebrated Lond. artist of the day: <hi rend="italic">said </hi>to have been <hi rend="italic">good </hi>likenesses, H. says, he had “<hi rend="italic">that day </hi>sent the revise of the <hi rend="italic">last proof </hi>of Banks’ Journal to p.” I see, in p., the mge. of John Beggs ygst. daughter, at Dunedin. I saw Cotterill Lawyer in t. today, &amp; shook hands. Lookg. well. There is some small (?) flutter here in town (I hear) <hi rend="italic">re fulfilment </hi>of prophecy &amp; the <hi rend="italic">very near </hi>advent of Xt.! my housekeeper went this aftn. to Crerar’s, &amp; to Craig’s to invest her 2/6 in pamphlet—lo! all sold: Paterson here today, in my absence, told her, he should preach on it on Sy. evg.—I, in town, spoke of it as a “<hi rend="italic">fad</hi>” of the day! have neither time nor <hi rend="italic">inclination</hi> for <hi rend="italic">such matters</hi>!——Mark xiv. 22, 32.</p>
         <p>Now for yr. letter: am rt. glad to find that <hi rend="italic">you</hi> are again well—and hope Willie will soon become so, &amp; that your good wife may ere long &amp; in due time “<hi rend="underline italic">rejoice</hi>” over her <hi rend="italic">past</hi> trouble. Thanks for your <hi rend="italic">graphic </hi>record of Wgn. Sy. proceedings: <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the ptg. &amp; <hi rend="italic">your obtg. </hi>my p. on “Cornwall” (cast bef. h.!) <hi rend="italic">bide a wee</hi>—<hi rend="italic">more anon</hi>. The old spns. you sent me, in letter, are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> (I think) sea-weeds, but Land do. I don’t envy your task of <hi rend="italic">cutting</hi> the thick vol. of “Trans.” at <hi rend="italic">one sitting</hi>! I took 3, if not 4, “spells” at it.—The author’s copies, this year, are barbarously put up! w. their horrid <hi rend="italic">wires </hi>on the <hi rend="italic">outside</hi>!! it is dangerous to handle them. I marvel greatly as those wires being so commonly used: they always <hi rend="italic">rust</hi> in a short time &amp; injure the books.—–</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Re </hi>your clipping— “<hi rend="italic">mild</hi> cure for bacon”—in my <hi rend="italic">old </hi>Mission days—<hi rend="italic">here</hi>—we always <hi rend="italic">cured </hi>bacon &amp; pork chiefly w. sugar; I could wish I had some such <hi rend="italic">now</hi>. Never bef. heard of yr. “<hi rend="italic">Am. Printer’s Dicty.</hi>”!!!</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">16</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>. I now conclude (“<hi rend="italic">high time</hi>!” you may say,) I send you “Herald” <hi rend="italic">also</hi> of today: mark, Dolbel’s case: F. Sutton’s reply to J. Hg. Did you note in vol. XXVIII, “Trans.”, Kirk’s naming <hi rend="italic">Hill’s Veronica</hi> after him, which I had also done, but <hi rend="italic">before </hi>K.? Kirk’s, p.524: Colenso’s, p.606: yet my paper was read Octr./9<hi rend="underline">5</hi>: Kirk’s Feb./9<hi rend="underline">6</hi> (K. has got <hi rend="italic">his p. pubd. before mine</hi>!!): and K. <hi rend="italic">may </hi>have seen my paper! This is rather awkward! but fortunately, both K. &amp; C. gave <hi rend="italic">same </hi>sp. name:—I warned Hill, (as, also, Hamilton, Olsen, Howlett, &amp; all others (<hi rend="italic">not </hi>to give <hi rend="italic">me </hi>spns. togr. with Kirk; I had <hi rend="italic">long ago </hi>heard of Kirk’s <hi rend="italic">underhand </hi>proceedings in <hi rend="italic">such </hi>matters: in p. 509, <hi rend="italic">l.c.</hi>, Kirk mentions my findg. a plant at the N. “<hi rend="italic">nearly fifty yrs. </hi>ago,”—he should have said, <hi rend="italic">sixty</hi>. I was sorry to see K., again! on <hi rend="italic">Dactylanthus</hi>: &amp; <hi rend="italic">more </hi>so to see his <hi rend="italic">rubbish </hi>on Ballast plants!—after my letter of exposure in our papers, showing that such (<hi rend="sup">7</hi>/<hi rend="sub">10</hi>ths) were <hi rend="italic">known </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">pubd.</hi> by Hooker in <hi rend="italic">Handbook </hi>Fl. N.Z. 30 years ago!! <hi rend="italic">Jam satis</hi>! And so, you, <hi rend="italic">also</hi>, have 2 copies of that old book “The New Zealanders”! many good things in it. With you I <hi rend="italic">dislike </hi>those (so-called) Botl. signs: you will not find the Hookers (<hi rend="italic">pat. et fil.</hi>) nor <hi rend="italic">our principal E. Botanists, </hi>using them: (1) pedantic (2) a gasp after notoriety—<hi rend="underline italic">exactly</hi> suiting <hi rend="underline italic">K</hi>!! <hi rend="italic">Re </hi>“Rutherford”,—did I tell you I had seen such a <hi rend="italic">tattooed European</hi> (indeed, 2–3, or 4!) saw one <hi rend="italic">in Engd</hi>. but the <hi rend="italic">story</hi> (as <hi rend="italic">given</hi> by R.) is false: I had <hi rend="italic">thoroughly examd. that</hi>—&amp; on <hi rend="italic">that ground</hi>, too—in the ’30’s, only a <hi rend="italic">few </hi>years <hi rend="italic">after </hi>R’s leaving N.Z. for Engd.; all this I sd. at our Mtg. T.Wh.!, alas! is <hi rend="italic">out again</hi>—in “Herald” on Maori Rat. It is a great pity that <hi rend="italic">his papers</hi> (somehow!) find such preference at head quarters: I am getting tired correcting <hi rend="italic">old errors</hi>! <hi rend="italic">Much pleased </hi>to read your remarks—so fully agreeing w. my own thoughts—<hi rend="italic">re </hi>police &amp; that foul murder at Pitoone: I have <hi rend="italic">ever </hi>had the <hi rend="italic">lowest opinion</hi> of a Wgn jury in <hi rend="italic">murder cases</hi>: &amp; perhaps in some others. I think I cod. throw light on that (so-called) “offl. letter” in “<hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>.” Baker &amp; <hi rend="italic">Capt.</hi> Hobson:—C. Baker, was the <hi rend="italic">lay</hi>man,-“Catechist”, &amp; had to be almost always on the look-out to purchase com. necessaries for the Mission Station (Eur. &amp; Mao. nearly 100 persons!) viz. potatoes, pigs, firewood, fish, &amp;c.—also, from shipping (or stores at Kororareka, &amp;c) Flour, Rice, Biscuit, Oil for lamps—<hi rend="italic">all</hi> hands only the <hi rend="italic">com. whale </hi>oil!—tobacco, &amp;c, used in barter: his duty was to go off to all ships arriving in harbour for <hi rend="italic">letters</hi>, &amp;c—and <hi rend="italic">so </hi>he <hi rend="italic">early saw </hi>Capt. H. at the anchorage, 3 m. from M. Station: &amp; B. <hi rend="underline italic">knew well</hi> how <hi rend="italic">to make the most of circumstances</hi>; [“cheeky”, nowadays] <hi rend="italic">N.B. only that </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">first</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> early </hi>note: aftds. (no doubt) <hi rend="italic">Rev. </hi>H.W.; &amp; as for <hi rend="italic">ptg., direct w. myself</hi>: see “Sg. Ty. Waitangi”, Hobson &amp; self, p.28. I had much <hi rend="italic">direct </hi>comm. w. H., &amp; w. his Govt., some of <hi rend="italic">this </hi>I wished to have ptd. w. my booklet but Capt. R. (then Col. Secy.) declined. Did they take copies of my curious &amp; unique <hi rend="italic">un</hi>pubd. p.? I fear Buller can scarcely escape <hi rend="italic">smirching</hi>! N.B. prov. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">Pitch</hi>!—would you were nearer!</p>
         <p>Trust you &amp; all are well. May the Lord bless you.</p>
         <p>Ever truly yours,                        W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
