<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0358">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1878 January 31: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4. Letter addressed to A. Luff Esq., 135, East India Road, Poplar, London. Endorsed “rec’d March 18/78”.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1878-01-31">1878 January 31</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1878 January 31: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-311" place="foot" n="311"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.<hi rend="italic"> </hi>Letter addressed to A. Luff Esq., 135, East India Road, Poplar, London. Endorsed “rec’d March 18/78”.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, New Zealand.<lb/>Jany. 31<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. 1878.</p>
         <p>A. Luff Esq.,</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir,</p>
         <p>Last week I was much gratified in receiving your letter of Dec. 12,—doubly so, I may say, because those to me from the Country (dated 11th.) mourned the non-arrival of the N.Z. Mail, while you, living in London, had got yours <hi rend="italic">that morning</hi>! and so, through you, I knew the mail had arrived &amp;c., &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>Much pleased to find you were all well &amp; comfortable in the prospect of an Eng. winter! May this find you still well, &amp; long past the worst of the northern cold!</p>
         <p>I last wrote to you on the 5th. inst., which, I hope, may duly reach you. I have been thinking on you this month (<hi rend="underline italic">extra</hi>) because of the work I had given you w. the <hi rend="italic">Linn. Society and Dixon! </hi>
         </p>
         <p>But, first, (as you say) to business. I had Mr. Parkin here yesterday (he is Redstone’s successor in U.M. Church here)—he is going to Wairoa, &amp; came to enquire if <hi rend="italic">I</hi> had any Sns. there for sale,—I told him him of yours, &amp; he is going to W. next week &amp; will have a look at it. (He had heard that I had 7–8 Sns. there!) I hope to sell this for you also.—In town today I saw Grubb (only the 2nd. time for this year!) he told he had just finished his L. to you, &amp; so, I suppose, will have told you of the demand made for Rates, <hi rend="italic">to him</hi>, for your land at Wairoa (£2.5.0. I think). I hope that Black’s offer may suit you—as I dread those Rates—or rather <hi rend="italic">Rates on Rates</hi>!—Early in December I paid my Rates at Waipawa, for my few unlet sns. there—(over £4.)—to mid. of ’78: last Friday I had a similar demand for “Waipawa <hi rend="italic">County</hi>” rates!! and, finding I must pay, I sent the amount in yesterday, but it is for the <hi rend="italic">same</hi> ground! T’other was “Road Board”. So <hi rend="italic">here</hi>: I was in town to-day &amp; with the Town Clerk <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Rates, &amp;c.—Scraps of Sns. 309, 311, (Rated <hi rend="italic">last year</hi> at £5 each, &amp; against which I had appealed &amp; got these lowered to £3 each) were now raised to £<hi rend="italic">4.10.0</hi>.!! &amp; that by <hi rend="italic">same</hi> valuator! who was beaten in Court!! What’s the use of <hi rend="italic">appeal</hi>? However, I <hi rend="italic">caught </hi>old Ellison, in T. Clerk’s Office, &amp; he got a bit of my mind!! for it is no use to waste a day (or more) &amp; catch cold for the sake of appealing—though it be for a principle—just to save 5/-. Judge Gillies has just given a decision at Auckland <hi rend="italic">against</hi> a <hi rend="italic">Road Board</hi> (£50. for damaging property) just for all the world like my case at Waipawa (see Acct. in Wkly. News).</p>
         <p>H. Mackenzie has just <hi rend="italic">paid</hi> for his land at Havelock (end of 2nd. 7 yrs. lease) &amp; Troy has also paid his ½ year’s rent. I walked from Taradale to P. Dolbel’s (about 3 weeks ago on one of the <hi rend="italic">hottest</hi> days of this summer) purposely to get some money—if to be had. (I had the week before sent in my acct. to Dec. 31st., &amp; told them of my day of visit). Would you believe it? the <hi rend="italic">old story</hi>!! “Do you <hi rend="italic">want</hi> any money?” was P’s. mild question! He <hi rend="italic">promised</hi> to do something by <hi rend="italic">tomorrow</hi> (1st. Feb.), we shall see. One thing struck me, the handsome way they had <hi rend="italic">finished</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">furnished</hi> their house, particular­ly the large drawing room!! Lined with beautiful panel-work in picked <hi rend="italic">Kauri</hi> and varnished, all looking A.1. It seemed a fine room <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to be used. I could not help <hi rend="italic">having thoughts</hi>. Mackay, &amp; others, gave <hi rend="italic">no sign</hi>. Ditto Robertson &amp; Drummond: I told Barry (Trustee) you &amp; H. Williams seem mad! suppose <hi rend="italic">I press</hi>—where is your remaining ¾ths? Suppose I were <hi rend="italic">Land­lord</hi>, would you not have to pay rent? to <hi rend="italic">both which</hi> B. ansd.Yes: but they <hi rend="italic">know</hi> that I will <hi rend="italic">not</hi> “Chaw up the 2 poor hard-working fellows.”—M. Boylan, poor fellow! is <hi rend="underline italic">out</hi> of his ironing &amp;c., &amp;c.; what he will, or can, do, I don’t know. I am sorry for him. J. Chambers’ 2 daughters were married in one day: one to a Quaker from Engd, &amp; one to Giblin. So Mrs. C. has now lost them all!! Poor Rees Watkins, the steady &amp; much liked Railway Guard,—first lost his <hi rend="italic">only</hi> child, then his wife (he absent), &amp; now their <hi rend="italic">twins</hi>—both within a few days. There has been a great mortality among the children, both in T. &amp; in Cy.,—fortunately it began before the arrival of the immigrants or they would have been blamed. Mrs. Gibbes &amp; Child are going to Engd. by ship, hence, in hopes of the voyage doing her good; their only living child has been very “unlucky”; first through carelessness of girl nurse had its teeth knocked in (or out), then an arm broken and last week the Dr. was summoned home from Napier as the child had fallen &amp; broken the other arm!</p>
         <p>There have also been several accidents, &amp; deaths (drowning &amp;c.) for which I must refer you to the Papers.</p>
         <p>The Quarantine folks came all right at last (but, I fear, a <hi rend="italic">loose</hi> set). The Dr. (Dale of notoriety here) is <hi rend="italic">now</hi> prosecuting the Captn.—he, yesterday, did the steward,—&amp;, I hear, he will get <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> from Govt. </p>
         <p>I have had a bit of a tussle with Irvine, &amp; Holder, &amp; Newton, re our dividing fence—<hi rend="italic">broken down</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">used</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="italic">destroyed</hi>, by the G. School Boys—still in <hi rend="italic">agitation</hi>.</p>
         <p>Sorry to have to say,—that my man has given notice to leave!! Of course I have accepted it. They say “it is for my comfort seeing they have 2 childn.” I say, “Time enough when I complain or find fault”.—What <hi rend="italic">lots</hi> of partings <hi rend="italic">I have</hi> seen!! </p>
         <p>I have been (&amp; still am) very busy w. Education Board &amp; <hi rend="italic">such matters</hi>. The B. meets on Monday, 4th. proxo, when (I suppose) my<hi rend="italic"> fate</hi> will be decided: in a certain sense I am care­less about it—as to which way it goes. I wd. <hi rend="italic">prefer</hi> resigning at once (or from 31st. Decr.) &amp; getting a little compensation; or, I could hold on—though <hi rend="italic">greatly increased</hi> work—visiting outlying places <hi rend="italic">once</hi> a year, &amp; an increase of pay. We shall see: by the way I may be able to tel. a brief letter to you on Tuesday mg., which if I do <hi rend="italic">you will understand it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>During first 3 weeks or more of this mo. I suffd. daily from Neuralgia &amp; Ear-ache, &amp; had <hi rend="italic">much</hi> to do in way of writing,—figures &amp;c. for Govt. I am now better,—but <hi rend="italic">frail</hi>. The Railway is now open to Kopua, 7 miles, or so, from Takapau. I have been called on by His Worship to abate the “nuisances” on my lands (316, 28, 29) see Advt. in Paper: not much on <hi rend="italic">mine</hi>! Bryson’s big Hotel has its framework up, &amp; it looks well, &amp; will fill <hi rend="italic">that</hi> corner, would the Blks. shop, opp., were away. The road round <hi rend="italic">your dear old</hi> office corner (leading to Councillor Williams’) is substantially begun, &amp; 30 feet wide!!!—</p>
         <p>You will see in Herald a letter of mine <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Archdn. Williams’ 2!—he did not reply &amp; I have been privately thanked for it,—<hi rend="italic">but not by him.</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">
               <note xml:id="ftn2-312" place="foot" n="312"> The Education Act. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> 19 January 1878.</note>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>For 8 days I have had an Advt. in paper—calling on Members H.B.P.I, to pay their subs.—only 3 have done so!! (&amp; one of these—Willis from Wn.) there are more than <hi rend="italic">40 unpaid</hi>!!! It is disheartening.—</p>
         <p>Wesley writes me, saying, the Books are again sent—this time in <hi rend="italic">Khedive</hi> steamer, left Ln. Dec. 9th. I believe there are errors (!) in his acct., but I’ll wait till <hi rend="italic">next mail</hi>.</p>
         <p>I send you in a Registered packet, 10 photographs of striking natural scenery in N.Z., which <hi rend="italic">please accept from me</hi>
            <hi rend="bold">.</hi> I hope they may reach you safely.—</p>
         <p>Karaitiana v. Ormond—has been heard at Wgn., but judgment not yet given. This, I believe, is the contesting of a Grantee’s <hi rend="italic">right</hi> (A. Pahoro) to sell to O.,—A.P. died &amp; gave his trust right to a young man of the tribe; a nice legal point. Lee went to Wgn. on behalf of O. Sir G. Grey left A. yesterday to see “King Tawhiao”.—</p>
         <p>Human Bones (&amp; a skull!) &amp; parts of <hi rend="italic">good</hi> cloth-covd. coffins have been found disinterred &amp; scattered in our cemetery!! Tiffen, Fannin, &amp; Kennedy are <hi rend="italic">there</hi> (privately) to day. Thanks for Paper <hi rend="italic">re</hi> mortgages (6!!) &amp; <hi rend="italic">other Papers</hi> a <hi rend="italic">lot</hi>. As to Temple Bar <hi rend="italic">site</hi> they should neither leave nor place <hi rend="italic">anything in centre</hi>.</p>
         <p rend="end">Feby. lst.</p>
         <p>The “Wanaka” Str. is just gone in with lots of bunting, having the Australian 11 on board: too much fuss nowadays about this <hi rend="italic">Cricketing</hi>!—Mayor, as you will see, has proclaimed a Holiday! last Friday there was another—additional 7m. of Railway to Kopua (or to nowhere!!).—</p>
         <p>Coleman &amp; McH., have <hi rend="italic">dissolved</hi>: C. is going home w. his swag, see Papers! <hi rend="italic">Giffard’s</hi> property will soon be in the market; deeds are preparing to pay off Read—the <hi rend="italic">brother</hi> in Engd. has sent out the needful.—</p>
         <p>You will see in Papers, that the Dr. of “Renfrewshire” <hi rend="italic">lost</hi>, and rightly so. Rees, of notoriety, (who only came here this week,) was at it again! 40 m. <hi rend="italic">talk</hi>!! &amp;, on his <hi rend="italic">first</hi> case, told R.M.—<hi rend="italic">he </hi>would <hi rend="italic">report</hi> it!!! (If I had been R.M. I would have sent him up the hill!)</p>
         <p>The Wesleyan “Parsonage” is to be built on Sealy’s land, near to Miller’s new house: Boyland had bought it, ½ acre;—and now sold for £360, 11% on money. Holder refused (me) to subscribe to Sir. D. McL’s monument! I had thought that he had had his share of sops!!</p>
         <p>You will note my letter in a D.T., <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Hospital site;—it attracted attention, &amp; several (Kennedy, J.N. Smith, Garry &amp; others,—besides those in Country) have highly approved of it: we shall see.—</p>
         <p>I send you in a <hi rend="italic">pod</hi> (only gathered yesterday) seeds of the Red Kowhai (or Kowhai-ngutu-kaakaa = <hi rend="italic">Clianthus puniceus</hi>) &amp; shall be glad to hear of their growing &amp;c., &amp;c.–</p>
         <p>Young Dransfield, at Spit, is <hi rend="italic">our</hi> new J.P. Among the Waipawa County Rates was 4d.!!! for 2 Blkhead Sections. <hi rend="italic">Barney Rhodes</hi> is dying, &amp; Joe (&amp; <hi rend="italic">son</hi>) are gone down,—this is Joe’s <hi rend="underline italic">2</hi>
            <hi rend="sup underline italic">nd</hi>. move <hi rend="italic">within 1</hi> mo.</p>
         <p>(<hi rend="underline italic">Night</hi>) I proceed to close: I have more letters to write, &amp;c. I send you a <hi rend="italic">full share</hi> of papers. This day I opened the 2 tenders for filling-in that corner (part of 316):—one, £148.10!! &amp; one, £85.—My man &amp; myself had thought about £50 or £60.</p>
         <p>—The steamer w. “the Australian 11” arrived this mg. w. all her bunting! they are gone to Hastings to play our <hi rend="italic">picked</hi> men—we shall see.</p>
         <p>I had all but given up P.D.—but, lo! this afternoon he turned-up; he tells me he has paid some money in to the Bk. to my credit, but <hi rend="italic">not so much</hi> as we had both hoped to do &amp; promised—which was ⅓rd. of my account sent him.—</p>
         <p>I have not said half my say. Any papers contg. ecclest. trials &amp; judgments, (as Tooth’s, MacKonochie’s, &amp;c.) send me them. Goodbye, w. kindest wishes &amp; regards—Believe me ever—</p>
         <p>Yours faithfully,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>