<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1013">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1897 October 17: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1897-10-17">1897 October 17</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1897 October 17: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-851" place="foot" n="851"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier<lb/>October 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1897.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Late</hi> last nt. I recd. your very kind letter of 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., and according with my usual custom, deferred opening till this mg., and I now thank you heartily for it (and, I may <hi rend="italic">tell you</hi>—<hi rend="italic">God</hi> also,)—it has helped to remove, or greatly to lessen, a load on my mind, during last fortnight from receipt of your <hi rend="italic">former</hi> letter: indeed, I had determined <hi rend="italic">yesterday</hi>—If did not hear from you again, I would write this day: your <hi rend="italic">former</hi> letter was a very good one, open confiding friendly, but with <hi rend="italic">one uncertain</hi> element in it <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the <hi rend="italic">future—</hi>“<hi rend="italic">Paulo post futurum</hi>”<note xml:id="ftn3-852" place="foot" n="852"> A little after the future: eventually; sometime in the distant future, or possibly never. </note> if you will—and what you had therein told me, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> that <hi rend="underline italic">situation</hi> in G.P.O., rather upset me, it being so unexpected &amp; <hi rend="italic">you</hi> so <hi rend="italic">well-fitted</hi> for that very office : however I <hi rend="italic">joined you</hi> in looking up—daring to hope for the best, and entertained thoughts of writing to Dr. S. in <hi rend="italic">your behalf</hi>—but I was not <hi rend="italic">sure</hi> of his now possessing <hi rend="italic">rule</hi> over the P.O., &amp; feared his passing it on to someone of his <hi rend="italic">Co</hi>. (neither friendly towards <hi rend="italic">me</hi>; nor to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, remembg. the <hi rend="italic">cartoons</hi> of last summer) but I waited until I should hear from you again, &amp; now that has come: <hi rend="italic">Laus Deo</hi>! I am vastly pleased with your cheerful tone, also that things generally are showing so well—<hi rend="italic">favourable</hi>: may such continue and increase.—</p>
         <p>I will notice a few items in yours: <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Travers and <hi rend="italic">patellæ</hi>: Dieffenbach, <hi rend="italic">before</hi> T’s. time, has <hi rend="italic">10</hi> sps. in his work and I added consy. thereto (mention made in <hi rend="italic">early</hi> p. in “<hi rend="underline italic">Tasmn.</hi>” Jl. Science”, &amp;c., &amp; in Sir <hi rend="underline italic">W</hi>.J. Hooker’s “London Botl. Journal”.)—Your “E.P.” <hi rend="italic">sent</hi>, not yet to hand. I have this mg. looked out a copy of Ruahine p. for <hi rend="italic">your friend </hi>in Manchester, (have only 2 copies left in bundle! Craig, &amp; Crerar <hi rend="underline italic">may</hi> have 2 or 3 unsold)—which you can send him. I add a <hi rend="italic">little</hi> wk. <hi rend="underline italic">lately</hi> from Engd.—<hi rend="italic">from yourself</hi>: have refused new correspdts. Seeing it advd. I ordered ½ dozen copies,—have not yet read it myself—I have Bp. C’s. works, &amp; “Memoir”—2 thumping gr. vols. by his friend Cox.<note xml:id="ftn3-853" place="foot" n="853"> Bishop JW Colenso of Natal &amp; Cox, his biographer.</note>—I have also put up a “H.B.H.” that you might see my letter on “<hi rend="italic">Daffodils</hi>” (my <hi rend="italic">last</hi>!).<note xml:id="ftn3-854" place="foot" n="854"> Daffodils. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> 15 October 1897.</note> By the way you scarcely sd. a word respecting my <hi rend="italic">last long</hi> L. v. Father Grogan<note xml:id="ftn3-855" place="foot" n="855"> Mr. Colenso in reply. Hawke’s Bay Herald 24 August, 8 &amp; 22 September. </note>—you <hi rend="italic">barely mentd</hi>. it, &amp; then wound up by saying you did not like term “<hi rend="italic">Father</hi>” applied to him (&amp; to <hi rend="italic">them</hi>), in which I go w. you—so also the term “<hi rend="italic">Salvation</hi>” used (!!) by the wretched “Army”.—You have <hi rend="italic">not</hi> returned my <hi rend="italic">Dedication</hi> scrap (all I have)—please do so with your remarks: I will tell you <hi rend="italic">all about</hi> it anon (a <hi rend="italic">secret</hi>): curiously enough <hi rend="italic">since</hi> I sent that to you, in overhauling &amp; putting to rights a bundle of <hi rend="italic">old letters</hi>, I found one from Sir G.G.—from Kawau <hi rend="italic">mainly</hi> on Mao. Lex.!! I will copy a portion &amp; enclose.<note xml:id="ftn3-856" place="foot" n="856">
               <p> The “portion” is at ATL Ms Copy Micro 485 1:extract.)                                           Kawau, Feby. 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., 1868</p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item> —</item>
               </list>
               <p>“I will write to Mr Stafford expressing a strong wish to have the pleasure of seeing the Maori Lexicon completed. Such a work will hereafter be of the greatest possible historical interest. I will also speak to Mr. Williamson. It would have given me very great pleasure to have seen how much of the work you have done—and the plan on which you are carrying it out. My manuscripts are all packed up—and I am still quite uncertain when I may be able to get” — <hi rend="italic">[***]</hi> “But if I come across any thing which I think will be useful to you I will lay it aside for you.”—</p>
               <p>                                 (signed)<lb/>                           Faithfully yours<lb/>                                   G. Grey.”</p>
               <p>“Revd. Wm. Colenso<lb/>Napier”</p>
               <p>* When he was last at Napier:—he very kindly <hi rend="italic">called</hi>, &amp; I was <hi rend="italic">out</hi>! &amp; the auld wifie did <hi rend="italic">not know him</hi>! &amp;c &amp;c.</p>
            </note> I have recd. several letters of thanks (N. &amp; S.) for my 3 letters re “Dr. Clifford, Augustine, &amp; Grogan”—some <hi rend="italic">notable</hi>. I note well what you say <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Spencer but (<hi rend="italic">knowing</hi> what I <hi rend="italic">do</hi>) fear there can be <hi rend="italic">no hope </hi>w. Bp.W.—(to cut the matter <hi rend="italic">short.</hi>)—Sp. <hi rend="italic">resigned</hi>: (I fear in a pet!)—Bp. was much put-to for some one to fill his place there; some time afterwards, Sp. wrote to Bp. W. wishing earnestly to <hi rend="italic">recall his resignn.</hi> but Bp. W. <hi rend="italic">would</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">not</hi> listen to him. I think that, what Sp. has told you, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> “a Bp. &amp; others wishing him to <hi rend="italic">remain</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">in N.Z</hi>. and not go to China”—was with reference to Bp. <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>, or the <hi rend="italic">former</hi> Bp.W. Unforty. for Sp (as far as I have ever heard) he was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> liked by his Cl. Brethren: though <hi rend="italic">near me</hi> in seat, &amp;c, Synod, he<hi rend="italic">never spoke to me</hi>; though I knew his parents <hi rend="italic">well</hi>, &amp; had nursed him when a child! <hi rend="italic">Re</hi> your wish—when I next overhaul my Botl. spns. to remr. yr. Manchester friend &amp; Botanist—but he wants “<hi rend="italic">Herbarium </hi>spns.” (well laid out, &amp;c.) I have never had such: not caring to collect and preserve—<hi rend="italic">neatly and well</hi>—save <hi rend="italic">one</hi> or <hi rend="italic">two</hi> for Kew: in<hi rend="italic">many instances</hi> have only a bare leaf! left, &amp; sometimes none! as I told Kirk the other day: he &amp; others like him <hi rend="italic">collected</hi> for <hi rend="underline italic">sale</hi>—<hi rend="underline italic">money</hi>! <hi rend="italic">I never did</hi>. Last year Hutton begged me earnestly to allow him to <hi rend="italic">see</hi> my described <hi rend="italic">Weta</hi> spns., as we was about to write a monograph on the family, and only had some (a few) there. I sent him <hi rend="italic">all</hi>—with <hi rend="italic">other</hi> new Insects (at no little trouble &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">expense</hi>): he has not yet returned them—though his paper appeared in Vol. xxix—&amp; cut mine up into some ½ dozen <hi rend="italic">genera novæ</hi>!! Well a fortnight ago, H wrote to me that he was now going in for the (walking stick) Bacillus family—&amp; (of course!) to lend him all I had described “Trans N.Z.I.”—I replied, last week that “I was neither able nor willing to do so”—telling also a bit of my mind, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> paid fireside workers (<hi rend="underline italic">at Home</hi>) obtaining spns. &amp; then ignoring those who had already described them, who had also, at heavy expense and no small labour collected them, &amp;c,—splitting them up into hundreds of <hi rend="italic">new</hi> genera! I had told K. much the same and perhaps displeased both. I pretty well guess why H. has detained my box of Wetas, &amp; other curious insects,—as he had <hi rend="italic">hinted</hi>—<hi rend="italic">no</hi> Musm. <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, to give my unique lot to Xt.Ch.!!!—–</p>
         <p>In that same bundle “<hi rend="italic">old</hi> letters”, I found a scrap—<hi rend="italic">part</hi> of a letter to Balfour who was overseer at Glenross for Kinross, &amp; <hi rend="italic">lost his all</hi>! as it is curious, &amp;, in part, pertaining to present eccl. matters, I send it, that <hi rend="italic">you</hi> may more surely know my opinion on such.—<hi rend="italic">Do not fail to return it</hi>: and, also, <hi rend="italic">if found &amp; handy</hi> that missing letter re the old C.M.S. pg. press—requisite to complete the lot. Of late I have been overwhelmed with letters—4–5 daily! mostly <hi rend="italic">rubbish</hi>—several wanting to <hi rend="italic">borrow</hi> money, or to give!—I have refused point-blank “<hi rend="underline">NO</hi>”—3 of these to <hi rend="italic">our</hi> Churches (<hi rend="italic">not</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">all</hi> of this diocese). Quintrell (a new Wesleyan Mr. at Waipawa) wants money to <hi rend="italic">paint</hi> their Ch! Dean Hovell was at Wgn. for <hi rend="italic">one</hi> clear day: he kindly called here last Tuesday: seemed to have enjoyed his jy. &amp;c. Mr. Welsh, poor dear fellow, is going Home in March, leave granted by his Vestry for 6 months; I don't think he will ever return.—</p>
         <p>I have not yet been to town—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> since I last wrote, only 3 times since July 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. I shall have to go this week—business: and next week to Waipawa—money hunting! a thing <hi rend="italic">I detest</hi>:—making my short stay at Waipukurau, shall not go further inland on this occasion—as <hi rend="italic">our</hi> Bp. is expected Nov. 1<hi rend="sup">st.</hi>, &amp; Synod called for 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., I may go inland <hi rend="italic">after</hi> Synod, though, truly speaking, Synod is of little consequence to me—not having a charge (“parish”) I have no vote there! Maori clerics have!! and so <hi rend="italic">young</hi> ones, and <hi rend="italic">new</hi> arrivals! I have not yet got full use of arms &amp; hand, perhaps never may: the <hi rend="italic">weakness</hi> in my legs, however, is <hi rend="italic">the chief injury</hi>: I walk, in fine w, out of doors—<hi rend="italic">in front of house—</hi>but find I am gaining strength <hi rend="italic">very slowly</hi>. I can write (<hi rend="italic">use</hi> pen) better than anything else. Do not fail to let me <hi rend="italic">know</hi> all about your doings, &amp;c, &amp;c, especially if you <hi rend="italic">gain</hi> that situation in G. Pg. O. and, when you are <hi rend="italic">clear</hi> from your trammels w. Fraser &amp; Hayward, &amp; others, dinna forget—you have <hi rend="italic">that</hi> £50. <hi rend="underline italic">here</hi>: I shall keep it in reserve for you.—–</p>
         <p>Am <hi rend="italic">glad</hi> to hear that Mrs. Harding keeps up so well: kind regards to her—love to bairns. Ever yours,</p>
         <p>                                                         W. Colenso</p>
         <p>(Hand and arm aching.)</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
