<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0780">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 May 13: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-05-13">1891 May 13</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 May 13: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-526" place="foot" n="526"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke,<lb/>Wedy. Night,<lb/>May 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1891.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding,</p>
         <p>Yours of 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I duly recd. &amp; thank you for it. And, as I don’t feel inclined this nt. to take up any thing of importance I will just commence a scrawl to you:—much in <hi rend="italic">our</hi> old way of convn. at N.—I am extra inclined to do <hi rend="italic">this</hi>—because I have this day written to Postm. Genl. <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the <hi rend="italic">heavy</hi> fees on re-addsg. a letter—entered pretty fully into the subject, annexed the envelope of yours bearing “<hi rend="underline italic">8d</hi>” paid on it! and suggested (at close) that if a fee must be paid—a 1d. uniform one should do. Another item I will (again?) bring to your notice—because I, <hi rend="italic">somehow</hi>, think it escaped your generally keen observant eyes, viz. the extracts I made for you when last at Napier, from Owen’s “Extinct wingless Birds of N.Z.”—which to <hi rend="italic">me</hi> were <hi rend="underline italic">very</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">satisfactory</hi> completely upsetting what Collier had sd. (or quoted) <hi rend="italic">re</hi> my paper on Moa, and, as far as I know, you never remarked thereon: what has served to bring it <hi rend="italic">afresh</hi> to my memory is the <hi rend="italic">pencilled memo</hi>. I made at Athenm. now here before me.—</p>
         <p>I fancy “Hill, B.A.” had not much of an audience (though the Bp. was one) last Monday night—I gather this from “D.T.” <hi rend="italic">report</hi> (?) of the meeting.—</p>
         <p>Robertshawe left here on Monday 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., <hi rend="italic">early</hi>, &amp; will not return (he said), until Friday 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>—when I hope to be at N.—I purpose leaving on 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>, breaking long jy..at Waipukurau: I have to <hi rend="italic">return</hi> on Monday 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. to Waipawa—to meet Lawyers there on 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi>—on business which <hi rend="italic">requires</hi> me <hi rend="italic">personally</hi>: at <hi rend="italic">present</hi> I don’t exactly know what I may do <hi rend="italic">after 26</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>—return probably to N.—</p>
         <p>The Ch. duty here next Sy. is left <hi rend="italic">on me</hi>, though I scarcely feel fitted for it—my cold (cough, &amp; pains in chest) being still heavy on me, &amp; (I must say, in truth<hi rend="italic">to you</hi>) partly my own fault! For my severe cold of last week (when I last wrote) had almost disappeared through 3–4 <hi rend="italic">gloriously, heavenly</hi> days, (7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>–9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> particularly,)—when on Saturday night, at VIII,—I writing here in my warm room (from lamp &amp; very mild weather), &amp; hearing Robertshawe strike up his Hymn just outside at the corner (as he always does on <hi rend="italic">Saty</hi>. nights &amp; preaches briefly &amp; offers a short prayer) I went out &amp; <hi rend="italic">stood</hi> by his side—as I generally do—&amp; so caught a return of cold: which has been heavy, but is now a little lighter. You may see I have freely confessed, <hi rend="underline italic">so</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">don’t</hi> scold me greatly.—</p>
         <p>The fine weather of <hi rend="italic">last</hi> week disappeared on Sunday—which was a cold &amp; damp day, &amp; since rain, &amp;c. I see, by Papers, that you <hi rend="italic">there</hi> had also rough weather on Sunday last. Smith &amp; Mackenzie (Cr. Lands) are here today. A letter to hand from Geordie Richardson, informs me of a subsn. getting up for W. Miller from his friends to show their appreciation of his priv. &amp; offl. char., &amp; that more than £220 has been subsd. <hi rend="italic">there</hi> at N.—12 of our townsmen came out w. £10. ea: I am pleased w. this. Another death here at Ormondville (i.e. of the people) making 5 within a month: perhaps you knew Mrs Brabazon. I am right glad that the (foolish shortsighted) “Social Option” folks got well-beaten at Norsewood this time, I would that yr. cousin R. had <hi rend="italic">not</hi> come out. There was a <hi rend="underline italic">good</hi> Leader in “Herald” of Friday last, showing the Lord High Chancellor’s opinion <hi rend="italic">re</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">private judgment influencing Licensing Bench</hi>:—this will have to be acted on.</p>
         <p>Here, I am attacked (again!) in yesterday’s “Bush Adv.”—in a letter, <hi rend="italic">said</hi> to have been written by 2 of <hi rend="italic">our</hi> prominent <hi rend="italic">Teetotallers</hi>! Let them go on in that way—I shall <hi rend="italic">not</hi> notice them.</p>
         <p>Now to yours:—thanks for the ext. from Montgy’s. “Omnip. of Deity”: I have the book—it was one of the <hi rend="italic">few</hi>, selected, I brought out w. me: and I quoted from it in my <hi rend="italic">first paper</hi> (“Journey” &amp;c) written for “Tasm. Jl. Nat. Sc.” By the way, I ansd. last wk. the warm invitn. I had recd. from the Secy. Roy. Sy. there (wh. Sy. succeeded the <hi rend="italic">former</hi> one, or was grafted on it,)—to attend Australn. Assn. Sc. Mtg. <hi rend="italic">there</hi> in Jany next: of course I <hi rend="italic">again</hi> declined—but in doing so lamented it—as I have always had a great desire to see Hobart, from the fact of Sir Jno. F. &amp; Ly. F. having been so kind to me in those early days, &amp; got me to write those <hi rend="italic">first</hi> Sc. papers, &amp; also made me a Mr. of that Sy.—all this I have touched on in my letter to the Hony. Secretary.—Perhaps I mentd. this in my last!!!</p>
         <p>You mention “Hildebrand Bowman, Esq.” (his wk.) quoted by me, in <hi rend="italic">part</hi>, from Davis’ Bibliography, as being <hi rend="italic">also in Collier</hi>:—I have <hi rend="italic">not</hi> my copy of Collier here, but I notice you say “pp.13–165:” Davis gives, “<hi rend="italic">800.400” </hi>pp. I think (indeed, am <hi rend="italic">sure</hi>) there are many good &amp; <hi rend="italic">useful </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">notes</hi> in Davis’ which are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> in Collier: e.g. J. White’s, <hi rend="italic">at p.38</hi>—under “Maori Superstitions 1856”.—Get (borrow) a copy of Davis’ &amp; compare.—</p>
         <p>I am very pleased &amp; rejoice w. you in your grand &amp; unexpected catch from France, surely you are (at last!) in Luck!! and you deserve it. Only your account of your Parisian gifts has swallowed up 2 of the 4 (&amp; only 4!) pp. of your letter.—How I should like to see them!—</p>
         <p>There is a mob of players <hi rend="italic">here</hi> to night: ditto last night: and on Saturday night, boxing matches, &amp;c., all <hi rend="italic">largely</hi> attended!! While Ch. Congns. small. The folks <hi rend="italic">here</hi> are trying to resuscitate their Pub. Liby., but, I fear, will <hi rend="italic">not</hi> succeed: Shugar resides here now, and is correspdt. to our Town Papers.</p>
         <p>I posted a portion of a Londn. paper to you this day, as I thought you would be interested in a Leader there on L. Booksellers. I notice in “Herald” your brother’s advt.—is he doing much now? (X p.m. good night.)</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">14</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>. I now go on w. my scrawl:—the weather is still showery &amp; <hi rend="italic">very cold</hi>, so I am confined—making the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day, and I <hi rend="italic">feel it</hi>: cough &amp; cold less, but pain in chest still there &amp; <hi rend="italic">voice</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">affected.</hi> I much fear for next Sunday, but a day, or so, of <hi rend="italic">fine</hi> &amp; mild weather, such that we had last week, will work wonders w. me: forty. <hi rend="italic">little</hi> Rheumatism.</p>
         <p>I was surprised this aftn. to see F. Sutton outside, &amp; mounting a horse, gun in hand! On speaking with him I found, he had been to Wgn. &amp; was now returng., &amp; (as he said) to stay here a day or two for sport (shooting) would cost him <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi>, he should do so: he was off to Mr Cowper’s at Kaitoki.—</p>
         <p>Some of the “Knights of Labour” were here yesty. and I was thinking of investing 2d. in a “Bush Adv.” of this evg. wh. contains their programme in full—as read by Pirani (is this P. a son of old P. of N.?)—but I suppose you already know it. A few other old Napier faces turned up today—on their business visits—Cooper, Architect, among them. It is <hi rend="italic">pleasant</hi>, sitting here in my room, close to window, readg., wtg. &amp;c to see folks passing—even if you don’t know them: <hi rend="italic">this street</hi> being <hi rend="italic">the thoroughfare</hi> to the P.O., Ry. St., Tel. Off. &amp;c &amp;c. Also, to see the bairnies (dozens!) going to &amp; coming from S., and <hi rend="italic">all this</hi> I <hi rend="italic">must miss</hi> in my Hermitage on the hill!! And, unforty., my old &amp; valued visitors (3 H’s.!) are all <hi rend="italic">gone</hi>—I may say so, as Mr Hill has left off climbing my hill.—</p>
         <p>I suppose this will be my <hi rend="italic">last</hi> to you <hi rend="italic">from this place</hi>—Of course I will write to you from N. I find I have to write <hi rend="italic">by Eng.</hi> M. before I leave.—</p>
         <p>Goodbye: Kindest regards, &amp; every good wish—yourself &amp; <hi rend="italic">yours</hi>.</p>
         <p>Yrs. faithy,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. I think, 2–3–4 matters in my last, <hi rend="italic">not</hi> touched on by you.—</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
