<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL1079">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 March 8: to Russell</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Transcribed in St George "Personal letters" book.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               <correspAction type="sent">
                  <date when="1892-03-08">1892 March 8</date>
               </correspAction>
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Russell</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 March 8: to Russell
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         
         <p>The Hon. Capt. W.R. Russell MHR<lb/>Flaxmere<lb/>Hastings<lb/>March 8—1892.</p>
         <p>My dr Capt R.</p>
         <p>I am just retd. to Napier from the Bush Dist. whither I had come, trying to get rid of those unpleasant secondary symptoms, a remainder of La Grippe &amp; his 3 visitations (relapses). I am very much better but still not well—sadly wanting strength espy. in legs—as a proof to you I have been here in Dvk. for 8 wks. &amp; not yet stg. eno. to visit the neighbours! You too have been laid aside thro yr. untoward accident to your leg but I hope you are now quite recovered, &amp; well &amp; hearty as usual.</p>
         <p>My object in writing to you now is—<hi rend="italic">re</hi> the (unfort.) Mao. Lex. wh. you espy. know so well! and this has very recently cropped up, in fact, in this way. Last wk. the annual mtg. of the Wgn. Phil. So. took place—one of the chief dishes was a Paper by me (as a member) on the famed Moa—but more w. the intention of rescuing Mr Mantell’s <hi rend="italic">father</hi> (the late famed Geologist &amp;c.) from the adversions on his sc. &amp; moral char. made by the Quarterly Reviewer 45 yrs. ago! but only last yr. detected by me &amp; you, <hi rend="italic">aiding</hi> in so kindly sendg. me the vol. reqd. from the G.A. Ly. Well there was a good attdce, &amp; a large no. of savans &amp; scientists, including Hector, Buller, Mantell, Travers, Maskell, &amp;c &amp;c. Sir J.H. kindly read my paper; great &amp; warm discussion followed (<hi rend="italic">not</hi> howr. agt. my paper) mainly thro Mantell coming <hi rend="italic">boldly</hi> &amp; filially to the fore in support &amp; to defend his father. The Mao. Lex. was soon on the <hi rend="italic">tapis</hi>, thro Travers (my old foe—ever since I summarily disposed of John White’s Moa— “killed at Waipukurau 45 yrs. ago”!!!—wh. T. so chuckled over! at the time, J.W. being then pd. by him for his wonderful discovery!!) And now I quote verbatim &amp; largely from Mr. R.C. Harding’s intg. letter to me re that meeting, he having been present,—</p>
         <p>Travers said— “the Govt. had pd. enormous sums during long years on account of a Mao. Lex. &amp; had never recd. anything in return.” I could not stand this: and spoke rather warmly “Mr. T. was quite in error</p>
         <p>No enormous sum has been pd. The Govt. after making 7 yrs. arrgt. had stopped the supplies at end of 3 yrs. Nevertheless, the author had contd. for many years to work at it, &amp; had never been reimbursed the money actually spent out of pocket. Further that to my cert. knowledge fair copy of Vol. 1 had actually been in the hands of the Govt. Ptr, w. order to proceed w. work but that on present govt. taking off. that order has been countermanded &amp; Ms. sent back to author. That throughout Govt. had been solely responsible for non-appce. of wk.—had played part of Dog-in-mgr. refusing to pt. themselves or allow author to deal w. Ms. Meetg. was somewhat astonished. Evidently <hi rend="italic">absolutely new</hi> to them. No one attempted to bear out Mr Travers’ contention, but Sir W.B. followed me and in some measure bore out what I had said.– – – then we adjourned (x.20 p.m.) for coffee. Sir W.B. said to me that I had done rightly in standing up for my townsmen &amp; he was “very sorry that your Lex had been dragged in. Perhaps after all it was as well. The ignorance of that learned Assy. on that subject is stupendous! I verily believe that some of them thought that for the past 20 years or so you had been drawing about ₤1000 a yr on the job &amp; had been doing nothing for the money.<note xml:id="ftn3-578" place="foot" n="578"> WC: Rev. Dr Stuart of Dunedin when last in N. told me much the same how my <hi rend="italic">still </hi>recg. gt. pay &amp; doing nothing was currently held. <hi rend="italic">there</hi>.</note> I think that delusion has been a little shaken. Mr Travers himself was staggered to hear that finished press copy had actually been in the hands of the printers.” This inform. H. had early appd. from Didsbury.</p>
         <p>And my main object is troubling you with all this is to ask If you will kindly undertake the presenting of a Paper on this sd. M. Lex. explanatory of it, <hi rend="italic">present position</hi>, &amp; in conty. of that printed in 1875, wh. I think you have seen (I will enclose a copy resume Py.P.). That P. has, in the form of a letter add. to the N. Mr.—this one of course; cod. not well be so add., I think, neither in form of a Petition but possibly as a <hi rend="italic">continuation</hi> of that former one;<note xml:id="ftn3-579" place="foot" n="579"> WC: [illeg. marginal note].</note> you however can well guide me in this matter. Of course my aim is, to get it made, a <hi rend="italic">pub</hi>. paper, &amp; so preserved like that former one. I would send you my draft when ready for yr. supervision, if required. Further should you my dear Sir <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be willing to present it, &amp;c.—please inform me as in that case I wod. get it printed at Wgn. for distribn. among Members when the House meets—</p>
         <p>I may also mention that I have lately recd. a Book Cat. from a Londn. Bookseller &amp; Publisher—E. Arnold, Bedford 61 Strand, in which in bring. ford. (w. some eclat) Tregear’s Maori Dictionary he says— “In 1822 the Rev. W.C. issued the prospectus (<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>) of a great Mao. Lex., wh. was not only to contain numerous examples from indigenous sources but also refs. to the cognate languages. This wk. has so far remained locked up in the author’s desk.” I shall write to A. by next Mail &amp; send him a copy of that Py. P.—</p>
         <p>Bearing in mind the kind interest &amp; trouble you took in this matter when in office, I trust I shall not have <hi rend="italic">bored</hi> you with this <hi rend="italic">subject </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">long</hi> letter.</p>
         <p>             And w. kind regards<lb/>                        Believe me my dr. Capt. R. yrs faithy,<lb/>                                                                                     WC.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
