<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0974">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1896 October 4: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1896-10-04">1896 October 4</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1896 October 4: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-796" place="foot" n="796"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Sunday night,<lb/>Octr. 4/96.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Your interesting letter of the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. ulto I duly received, also, 2 (or 3, w. one last night, not yet opened) copies of your new pol-squib-serial<note xml:id="ftn3-797" place="foot" n="797">
               <hi rend="italic">X-rays</hi>.</note> and, I think, a newspaper—all since I last wrote on <hi rend="italic">13</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>—just 3 wks. ago, but <hi rend="italic">closing</hi> later.—–</p>
         <p>I little thought then what was awaiting me: I have scarcely been <hi rend="italic">out </hi>since—at all events, <hi rend="italic">not </hi>since Sunday 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. ulto. Ch. of Ed. Synod opened here, in school-room, on Friday 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. at iv. p.m., over a little after v. p.m.—for <hi rend="italic">that day</hi>: I was there (and that was <hi rend="italic">all </hi>I saw of Synod), and on Sunday 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> being pretty well, was at Cathedral mg. &amp; evg.—evg. S., place crowded to hear Bp. Wms.’ address (some, I fancy, were disappd.) At close, long service, <hi rend="italic">very warm</hi>, I in vestry threw off Ch. robes &amp; came away—<hi rend="italic">slowly</hi>, crawling up this steep hill, dark &amp; cold:—and got (I suppose) a <hi rend="italic">relapse </hi>of that severe cold I took at Dvk., so I was shut up a <hi rend="italic">close </hi>prisoner all that wk. w. a <hi rend="italic">fearful</hi> cold &amp; cough—indeed (I may tell <hi rend="italic">you</hi>) I thought it might, or would, prove to be my <hi rend="underline italic">last</hi>: Mrs Anderson very much afraid. And then, since (this last wk.) the weather so <hi rend="italic">very changeable</hi>—and it is only <hi rend="italic">just now</hi> that I really begin to rally! I much want to go to town on <hi rend="italic">business</hi> (self &amp; others), but I cannot do so yet. Much pain in chest, at times, &amp; last wk. spitting blood: no marvel, through that outrageous cough.—I have had scarcely any visitors, save Mr. Welsh frequently, and the Dean once.—Mr. Welsh went to Pakowhai on 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. to marry Pirani (of Telg. Dept.) to a Miss Bee of Mohaka: Pirani’s mother going w. W. to wedding: I never knew any of P’s. family, only himself—the old man. My big case for Kew was duly shipped per “Hawke’s Bay”, now, I think, in your waters: [5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. arrival at Sydney;] to the honour of Wms. &amp; Kettle be it recorded it went “<hi rend="underline italic">Freight free</hi>”. This place with Hastings (and, I suppose, <hi rend="italic">all around</hi>) is all “agog”! on the <hi rend="italic">terrific increase </hi>of <hi rend="italic">Harbour Rates</hi>: <hi rend="italic">both </hi>papers (for once!) agreeing in writing <hi rend="italic">against</hi> it: w. <hi rend="italic">lots</hi> of letters (<hi rend="italic">6</hi> at one t. in “D.T.”) and no marvel—for, it stated, the increase is 16 times above what it was! some say— “a blunder”: some, “a deep-laid scheme”, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">My </hi>paper (<hi rend="italic">demand</hi>) came in last night, but I have not opened it—&amp; shall not until <hi rend="italic">after </hi>breakfast tomorrow. The <hi rend="italic">unpleasant </hi>matter (doubly so on “<hi rend="italic">call</hi>” of Bk. N.Z.) will be known time enough.——</p>
         <p>Now my chief reason for writing to you tonight, arises from what took place <hi rend="italic">this day</hi>—<hi rend="italic">here</hi>. I sought in my lower corner, old theologl. works,—Bp. “Pearson on the Creed”—a fine old <hi rend="italic">folio</hi> vol. of 1676—which I had not opened or seen for (say) 30 years, or more—having handy a 12mo. copy—<hi rend="italic">without </hi>notes—which <hi rend="italic">I had bought in London</hi> in ’34, on leaving. I wanted it, to see his <hi rend="italic">learned </hi>notes on the , στανςοσ being originally the Greek word for a <hi rend="italic">stake</hi> &amp;c.<lb/>—Well on looking it up, I came on what strongly reminded me of your last letter, &amp; I copy a <hi rend="underline italic">small</hi> portion of it—for the Bp’s. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> are very copious &amp; learned. After his <hi rend="italic">authorities </hi>that <hi rend="italic">stauros</hi> was used for a stake, &amp;c., from Homer, and many other after him—he says:— “Now because the extremities of the antenna are a kind of κέςατα (as Virgil, <hi rend="italic">Cornua velatarum obverrimes antennarum</hi>;) therefore in C-K a kind of κεςαία is antenna; &amp; from thence the Gk. Fathers applied the word of our Saviour Matt. v. 18 Іώτα, K.T.A. to the Cross of Xt.—Because Іώτα is like the straight piece or mast of the Cross, and κεςαία the yard or transverse part; therefore some of the ancients interpreted this place of the Cross, says Theopylact, or Gregory Nysson. – – – Not that this is the true interpretation of that place; (for κεςαία signifies a part of a letter, as in Apollonius Syntax, l.1, 7, &amp;c.,) but by that they testifie their apprehension of the figure of a Cross” (and a <hi rend="italic">great deal </hi>more.)</p>
         <p>And so your remarks on the 2 Heb. letters (caph &amp; beth)—first mooted by Origen: and so other <hi rend="italic">pairs </hi>of Heb. letters, G, N: H, CH: D, R:—I have often (in years long passed!) marvelled how the originators of the Heb. Alpht. could have put up w. such <hi rend="italic">similar </hi>chars: and now, of <hi rend="italic">late years</hi>, we already know of <hi rend="italic">certain </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">errors</hi> through them—and the transcribers: e.g. 2 Sam. viii. 13 &amp; 1 Chron xviii. 12;—in <hi rend="italic">first </hi>“Syria”: in <hi rend="italic">second</hi>, Edom: and no doubt parallel passages—in Heb. A R<hi rend="sub">a</hi>M = Syria; A<hi rend="sub">e</hi>D<hi rend="sub">o</hi>M = Edom. See, also, <hi rend="italic">title </hi>of Ps. IX.—</p>
         <p>Just so, the old contention (i.e. Vulg. &amp; Douay <hi rend="italic">v. </hi>Authd. transln.) in Gen. xlvii. 31: “bed’s head” = in Ep. “Hebrews”: “staff” the origl. word is H<hi rend="sub">a</hi>M<hi rend="sub">i</hi>TT<hi rend="sub">a</hi>H—the bed: H<hi rend="sub">a</hi>M<hi rend="sub">a</hi>TT<hi rend="sub">e</hi>H:<lb/>—but this, of course, is from <hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi> having read it diffy—without vowels.—Both renderings are nearly equally good; i.e. <hi rend="italic">not </hi>injurious. A curious error? in Josh. ix. 4, “The Gibernites went-and-made-as-if-they-had-been-ambassadors” (Authd. Vers.) = “The Gibernites took them provisions (Revised V.)</p>
         <p>Hitztayaru = acted as amb.—–</p>
         <p>Hitztayadu = took them provisions.</p>
         <p>Again: “Bring hither <hi rend="italic">the Ark of </hi>God”—(Authd. V.). “Bring hither the <hi rend="italic">Ephod</hi>”—Reviser’s marg. <hi rend="italic">from </hi>Sept., which no doubt is correct, though the two words in Heb. are slightly different. I, long ago, noted a <hi rend="italic">curious </hi>ancient reading of <hi rend="italic">the Jews</hi>—and, no doubt, “a tampering or corruption” of the Heb. text <hi rend="italic">by them</hi>—in Judges xviii. 30— “Gersham the son of <hi rend="italic">Manarses</hi>, Authd. readg.—is <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, son of <hi rend="italic">Moses </hi>Revised readg.,—see, also, Gen. 30. 11, “Leah said, A troop” (Authd. V.) “Leah said, <hi rend="italic">Fortunate</hi>” (Rev. V.) Leah’s word was, <hi rend="italic">Gad</hi>: it <hi rend="italic">might </hi>mean a troop: but LXX has,— “In good fortune!” Vulg. has,— “Fortunately!” The Syriac reads, “My fortune cometh!” The Turgum of Oukelos, “Fortune cometh”! the Turgum of Jonathan, “My good star cometh!” so that ancient testimony favours the alteration. Lastly, a chap. I had to read in Ch. a short time back, 1 Kgs. xxii, at 38v.— “they <hi rend="italic">washed his armour</hi>,” (authd. reading:) “now the harlots washed themselves there,” (Reviser’s reading) The Heb. word <hi rend="smallcaps">zonoth</hi> means both “<hi rend="italic">armour</hi>”, &amp; “harlots”—this latter much more frequently. See, also, Judg. 8.13. A.V., and R.V., and <hi rend="italic">compare</hi>.—–</p>
         <p>I sent you several papers—the whole of Hill’s paper (w. <hi rend="italic">additions</hi>—one, in particular—<hi rend="italic">used by me</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">not</hi> in original as read—the word “<hi rend="italic">Utopia</hi>” &amp; <hi rend="italic">that sentence—</hi>&amp; perhaps others:—H. is now at P. Bay, &amp;c. I shall be glad when Monday week is <hi rend="italic">passed</hi>, <hi rend="italic">then</hi> I shall feel clear—&amp; breathe.–</p>
         <p>I enclose a clipping contg. my letter to “D.T.”<note xml:id="ftn3-798" place="foot" n="798"> Mr. Colenso explains. <hi rend="italic">Daily Telegraph</hi> 28 September 1896.</note> I tried <hi rend="italic">hard </hi>to get some informn. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>M.A. Henderson, but <hi rend="italic">failed</hi>: yet from the Dean (who knew her well) I have lately heard, she was a very decent old widow her husband, a gardener, died some years ago. Of “<hi rend="italic">politics</hi>”—I know <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi>—don’t care to trouble my head about them. <hi rend="underline italic">Good night</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">5</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>(night) This mg. x.30, a <hi rend="italic">severe</hi> hail-storm—big hail and dug <hi rend="italic">ground white</hi>: “D.T.” (as usual) says this evg.—<hi rend="italic">no such </hi>a hail-storm before in memory of oldest! (<hi rend="italic">bosh.</hi>) I have been keeping pretty well today—busy on some Ferns for Monday next. Have run through your X Rays, <hi rend="italic">No.3:</hi> and have thought—I should like for <hi rend="italic">you </hi>to be <hi rend="italic">well able </hi>to be above the printing such: it is just possible that <hi rend="italic">harm </hi>(serious) may arise among the Maoris through such caricatures—especially if fomented by designing pakeha-Maoris.—</p>
         <p>Six months ago I wanted Zola’s wk. “<hi rend="italic">Lourdes</hi>”: applied to Craig: “No, he wd. not keep, nor order, Zola’s trash”: I said, “I did not want any of his novels only this <hi rend="italic">re </hi>“Lourdes”, the R.C. &amp; Pope.—So C. relented &amp; ordered the book: I had seen that the Pope &amp; Co. had placed in the “<hi rend="italic">Index</hi>”. <hi rend="italic">This wk. here </hi>is wholly high Carnival. I want to go to town on business, but must <hi rend="italic">patiently</hi> wait. I am <hi rend="italic">not </hi>pleased in looking over what I wrote in this letter last evg.—<hi rend="italic">not clearly </hi>expressed, &amp; poor extracts—but <hi rend="italic">you </hi>must take it <hi rend="italic">as it is</hi>.</p>
         <p>I trust your good wife will in proper time return to you rejoicing &amp; <hi rend="italic">very well</hi>—ditto family with her: and that <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, during her absence will not be any thing the worse for it. I have a suspicion that there were several (?) enquiries, <hi rend="italic">or</hi> remarks, in my last, unnoticed by you! <hi rend="italic">With me</hi>—l. writing should be <hi rend="italic">in lieu</hi> of <hi rend="italic">conversation</hi> &amp; conseqly. replied to: but perhaps I am wrong: one thing I <hi rend="italic">certainly know</hi>—&amp; that is, you are far too busy to write: &amp; so, I forgive you.—</p>
         <p>I recd. a curious note from a “Mr. Hy. Wilson”, at Mangatainoka, asking me to <hi rend="italic">write</hi> an old Maori story he had heard from the Maoris: I referred him to “In Memoriam = Ruahine” there he would find something about it; so, he replied, (a curious note) saying, he had written to Craig.</p>
         <p>There is nothing in this to <hi rend="italic">reply</hi> to: so <hi rend="italic">don’t write</hi> in a hurry. I shall <hi rend="italic">hope</hi> to go inland towards end of month if <hi rend="italic">able</hi>: believing such will do me good. Mr. Luff sent me 2 4to. photos, mounted of scenery in <hi rend="italic">his </hi>forest freehold: one is very good. <hi rend="italic">A Dieu</hi>: yours ever</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">5</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. night</hi>: One good thing I should not omit is, during the <hi rend="italic">whole</hi> of the attack scarcely any Rheumatism.—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">P.S. </hi>I find, my L. is over ½ oz.! and so “I go at it, again”!—</p>
         <p>My eye-sight is (at last!) failing me fast for <hi rend="italic">small </hi>type; &amp; not yet <hi rend="italic">fitted </hi>w. specs. I want a pocket, or <hi rend="italic">small</hi> size Bible w. marg. ref.—in Long Primer, or Brevier, or Bourgeois, full-face: my old one is “Ruby 24mo”. Neither Craig nor Crerar has one. I had 2 (new) Bibles: one would have served, but I gave both away as Xmas. gifts: one of them was a (so-called) “Teacher’s B.”, with copious modern variorum rendgs. &amp; notes, &amp; maps, I would <hi rend="italic">not </hi>have that. If you should see one such in your visits to Bookshops—take note, &amp; let me know.—</p>
         <p>As you have read my paper on “Monster at Rhodes” (extract) <hi rend="italic">be sure you read </hi>the corresponding Maori tales, referred to, in vol. XI Trans.<note xml:id="ftn3-799" place="foot" n="799"> Colenso W 1895. Memorabilia of certain Animal Prodigies, Native and Foreign, Ancient and Modern. <hi rend="italic">Trans NZ Inst.</hi> 28: 87–97. </note>
         </p>
         <p>I sent to Craig’s for extra copies of “Herald”, and also “Evg. News” of Tuesday—just to see if any thing <hi rend="italic">re </hi>our mtg. And to my <hi rend="italic">surprise </hi>I find, H. <hi rend="italic">has handed over his p.!! </hi>H. took it away (vi et armis!) against my protest, sayg., it was rough &amp; he wished to correct, &amp;c. (but it was <hi rend="underline italic">not</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> rough</hi>). He is <hi rend="italic">now </hi>in <hi rend="italic">same box w</hi>. Atkinson in his p. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Tregear.—I send you this “Evg.N.” Hill also said, <hi rend="italic">twice</hi>, to audience, “<hi rend="italic">he had scribbled the whole of it </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">yesterday</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi>” (I <hi rend="underline italic">doubt</hi> it).</p>
         <p>In “D.T.” of Augt. 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.— “Death of <hi rend="italic">another</hi> of old Identities of Napier”: Mrs Mary Ann Henderson—the <hi rend="italic">first white </hi>womn. who came to H. Bay, &amp; was <hi rend="italic">certainly so </hi>as to the S. portion, where she settled at Patangata.” (!!!) I have written to Kn. denying this, &amp; asking for authority. <hi rend="italic">Also</hi>, pointing out, how ugly it looks in “D.T.” of <hi rend="italic">Monday</hi> night, in Bush, to see, “<hi rend="italic">Tomorrow’s Services</hi>”: subjects of Sermons burials on <hi rend="italic">Sunday</hi>—steamers leaving <hi rend="underline italic">on Sy</hi>. w. notices to papers:—Concerts, <hi rend="italic">Sy. aftns</hi>. in Bot. Garden, &amp; <hi rend="italic">Sy. nights</hi> Theatre, &amp;c &amp;c—–. I fancy Kn. will not like it! no reply yet.</p>
         <p>Hope Robley may <hi rend="italic">forget me </hi>w. his book of <hi rend="italic">preserved heads</hi>!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
