<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0283">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1874 December 20: to Emily Tucker</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL Ms-papers-10535-1. What follows is a paraphrasing of excerpts from sermons by Frederick W. Robertson, written by Colenso for his sister, probably Jane Emily Tucker (1817–1896).</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73335/">Emily Tucker</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1874-12-20">1874 December 20</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1874 December 20: to Emily Tucker<note xml:id="ftn2-211" place="foot" n="211"> ATL Ms-papers-10535-1. What follows is a paraphrasing of excerpts from sermons by Frederick W. Robertson, written by Colenso for his sister, probably Jane Emily Tucker (1817–1896). </note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="center">Written for my Sister,—far off in body, but with me <lb/>in thought this day, Sunday, Decr. 20<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>./74.</p>
         <p>Opportunities of doing good do not come back. (Much have I missed the doing of—through life, by not more closely attending to this: may I be forgiven!) We are here in this world for a definite purpose—to educate our own hearts by deeds of love, and to be the instrument of blessing to our fellow men. There are two ways in which this is to be done, 1. by guarding them from danger,—2. by soothing them in their rough path by kindly sympathies. (Jesus asked his apostles to do this for him in Gethsemane—Mark xiv.) And it is an encouraging thought, that he who cannot do the one has at least the other in his power. If he cannot protect he can sympathise. Let the weakest, let the humblest remember, that in his daily course he can, if he will, shed around him almost a heaven! Kindly words, sympathizing attentions, watchfulness against wounding men’s sensitiveness—these cost very little, but they are priceless in value. Are they not almost the very staple of our daily happiness? (<hi rend="italic">I</hi> value them perhaps the more from my <hi rend="italic">not</hi> meeting with them: it has been my <hi rend="italic">lot</hi> to know <hi rend="italic">much</hi> of what the Psalmist speaks, Ps. cxx. 4–6: notwithstanding it has not changed me, nor the desires &amp; aspirations of my soul.)—From hour to hour, we are supported, blest, by <hi rend="italic">small </hi>kindnesses. And when we consider that our life, it may be, is nearly run out,—and that we love &amp; desire such things,—how much (<hi rend="italic">we may ask ourselves</hi>) have we done in <hi rend="italic">that way</hi>? Let us awake in time; and dread the remorse of conscience when at last awaked to brood over the irreparable past!  In the few words which Jesus said (41, 42) was a most cutting self-reproach, for they contained all the desolation of that sad word<hi rend="italic">never</hi>. Who knows not what that word wraps up—<hi rend="italic">Never—</hi>it<hi rend="italic"> never </hi>can be undone. Sleep on! But yet there was no sickly lingering over the irreparable: the moment was come for action, “Rise, let us be going”. Now the broad general lesson which we should learn from this is,—that a Christian is to be forever rousing himself to the duties which lie before him <hi rend="italic">now</hi>. Cease lamenting the past—the past is <hi rend="italic">past</hi>—rise &amp; be going—doing—count your resources; learn what you are <hi rend="italic">not </hi>fit for and give up wishing for it: learn what you <hi rend="italic">can </hi>do and do it with the energy of a man! That is the great lesson of this passage. Jesus <hi rend="italic">went </hi>to <hi rend="italic">meet </hi>the soldiers. In after years the disciples understood the lesson and acted on it:—they braved the Sanhedrin—they fronted the world. Under this there lies a great principle. Under no conceivable set of circumstances are we justified in idly sitting— “By the poisoned springs of life, Waiting for the morrow which shall free us from the strife.”——Under no circumstances, whether of pain, or grief, or disappointment, or irreparable mistake, can it be true that there is not something to be <hi rend="italic">done</hi>, as well as something to be suffered. And thus it is that the spirit of Christianity draws over our life,—<hi rend="italic">not</hi> a leaden cloud of Remorse and Despondency, but a sky—not perhaps of radiance, but yet—of most serene and chastened and manly hope. There is a <hi rend="italic">past</hi> which is gone forever! but there is a <hi rend="italic">future</hi> which is still our own.– – –</p>
         <p>“If any man will do His will he shall know.” John vii. 7—That is, if any man wills, resolves, has the mind to do the will of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>. It is not written, If any man does His will,—but if any man has the spirit and desire. If we are in earnest we shall persevere like the Synphenician woman,—even though all around discourages, and God’s word seems to drive us back! Many people go to Church because it is the custom, and all Christians believe it is right to do so. But there are hours, (and they come to us all at some time of life or other,) when the hand of Mystery seems to be heavy on the soul—when some life-shock scatters existence, leaves it a blank and dreary waste henceforth frozen, and there appears nothing of hope in all the expanse which stretches out before us, except that merciful gate of death which opens at the end—hours when the sense of misplaced or ill-requited affection, the feeling of personal worthlessness, the uncertainty and meanness of all human aims, and a doubt of all human goodness, unfix the soul from all its old moorings—and leave it drifting—drifting over the vast Infinitude, with an awful sense of solitariness. Then the man, whose faith rested on outward Authority and not on inward life, will find it give way: the authority of the <hi rend="italic">priest</hi>: the authority of the Church: or merely the authority of a document proved by miracles and backed by prophecy; the soul—conscious life—<hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>—will be an awful desolate Perhaps. Well, in such moments you doubt all—whether Christianity be true: whether Christ was man or god or a beautiful fable. You ask bitterly, like P. Pilate, “What is Truth?” In such an hour what remains? I reply, Obedience. Try to leave those thoughts for the present. Act: be merciful and gentle—honest: force yourself to abound in little services: try to do good to others: be true to the Duty that you know. <hi rend="italic">That </hi>must be right whatever else is uncertain.—And by all the laws of the human heart, by the word of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>, you shall not be left to doubt. Do that much of the Will of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> which is plain to you (however small), and “You shall know of the doctrine, whenever it be of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>.”—(Some of this I have experienced. W.C.)</p>
         <p rend="center">A few thoughts on the Nature and Laws<lb/>of Revelation.</p>
         <p rend="center">____________</p>
         <p>First.—Remember Revelation is made by a Spirit to a spirit,— “<hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> hath revealed them to us by His Spirit.” Christ’s words—is the voice <hi rend="italic">without</hi> the man, the Spirit, is the Voice of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">within </hi>the man. The highest revelation s not made by Xt., but comes directly from the universal Mind to our minds.—Now the Sp. of <hi rend="smallcaps">God </hi>lies touching, as it were, the soul of man,—ever around &amp; near. In every man this is true. The Spiritual in him, by which he might become a recipient of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>, may be dulled, deadened by a life of sense, but in this world never lost. All men are not spiritual men, but all have spiritual sensibilities which might awake. All that is wanted is to become conscious of the nearness of <hi rend="smallcaps">God. God</hi> has placed men here to feel after him, if haply they may find Him, albeit He be not far from any one of them.—</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="italic">condition</hi> upon which this self revelation of the Spirit is made to man, is Love. These things are “prepared for them that love Him,” or, which is the same thing,—revealed to them who have the mind of Christ. Let us look into this word <hi rend="italic">Love</hi>. Love to man, may mean several things: love to <hi rend="smallcaps italic">God</hi> can only mean <hi rend="italic">one </hi>thing: <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> is a Spirit, <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> is a character: to love <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>, is, therefore, to love His <hi rend="italic">character</hi>: for <hi rend="italic">instance</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> is love,—<hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> is Truth,—God is infinite.–</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> is Love—and to love men till private attachments have expanded into a philanthropy which embraces <hi rend="italic">all</hi>—at last even the evil &amp; enemies with compassion—that is to love <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> is Truth!! to be true, to hate every form of falsehood, to live a brave–true–real–life, that is to love <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>.—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> is Infinite—and to love the boundless reaching on from grace to grace, adding Charity to faith, and riding upwards ever to see the Ideal still above us, &amp; to die with it unattained, aiming insatiably to be perfect even as the Father is perfect—that is to love <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>.—</p>
         <p>This Love is manifested in obedience,—Love is the life of which obedience is the form. “He that hath my Commandments &amp; keepeth them he it is that loveth me.”—Now here can be no mistake. Nothing can be love to <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> which does not shape itself into obedience. It may not have full fruit as yet, but it is growing tending that way. God doth not despise the day of small things—neither does he quench <hi rend="italic">the </hi>smoking flax: We know who said— “Gather up fragments—let none be lost:” and, “<hi rend="italic">First</hi> the blade, then the <hi rend="italic">ear</hi>, <hi rend="italic">then </hi>the full corn in the ear.” So with <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>—strong feelings, warm expressions, varied internal experience co-existing with continued disobedience—<hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> counts not as Love.</p>
         <p>To this Love, adoring &amp; obedient, <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> reveals His truth. For such as love, it is <hi rend="italic">prepared</hi> (or, rather, by the well-known Hebrew manner of speaking by inversion of words,—<hi rend="italic">such are prepared for it</hi>. Love is the condition without which revelation does not take place. As in the natural, so in the spiritual world: by compliance with the laws of nature, we put ourselves in possession of her blessings: obey the laws of health &amp; you obtain health: temperance, sufficiency of light, and air, and exercise,—these are the conditions of health. Arm yourself with the Laws of nature, and you may call down the lightning from the sky: surround yourself with glass, &amp; the lightning may play innocuously a few inches from you—It cannot touch you—you may defy it—you have obeyed the conditions of nature, and Nature is on your side against it.—</p>
         <p>In the same way there are conditions in the world of Spirit,—by compliance with which <hi rend="smallcaps">God’s</hi> spirit comes into the soul with all its Revelations,—as surely as lightning from the sky, and as invariably,—such conditions as these:— “The secret of the <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord</hi> is with them that <hi rend="italic">fear</hi> Him.”— “No man hath seen <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> at any time,” but “with this man will I dwell, even with him that is of a <hi rend="italic">meek</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">contrite</hi> spirit,”— “If we <hi rend="italic">love </hi>one another <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> dwelleth in us”:— “If any man <hi rend="italic">will</hi> to <hi rend="italic">do </hi>his will he shall know of the doctrine,” &amp;c. Reverence, love, meekness, contrition, obedience, these conditions having taken place, God enters into the soul, whispers His secret, becomes known, and imparts the knowledge &amp; conviction and holy hope and trust in Him.—</p>
         <p>Now these laws are universal &amp; invariable—they are subject to no caprice: there is no favourite child of nature who may hold the fire in his hand without being burnt:—there is no selected child of grace who can live an irregular life without unrest,—or be proud, &amp; at the same time have peace,—or indolent, &amp; receive fresh inspiration,—or remain unloving &amp; cold, and yet see &amp; hear &amp; feel the things which <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> hath prepared for them that love Him.—</p>
         <p>Therefore the Apostles preached the Cross to men who felt, &amp; to men who felt not, the Revelation contained in it. The Cross is humbleness, love, self-surrender: these the Apostles preached. To conquer the world by loving it:—to be blest by ceasing the pursuit of happiness, and by sacrificing life instead of finding it: to make a hard lot easy by submitting to it:—this was their divine philosophy of life. And the Princes &amp; great ones of this world amidst scoffs &amp; laughter, replied, Is that all? Nothing great, nothing to dazzle, nothing to captivate! But the disciples of the <hi rend="italic">inward </hi>life recognized the Divine Truth which this doctrine of the Cross contained. The humble of heart and the loving, felt that in this lay the mystery of life, of themselves, and of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>, all revealed and plain. It was <hi rend="smallcaps">God’s</hi> own wisdom, felt &amp; known by those who had the mind of Christ.—</p>
         <p>Now the application of all this is very easy, Love <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>, and He will dwell with you:—obey <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>, and He will reveal the truths of His deepest teaching to your soul. Not <hi rend="underline italic">perhaps</hi>: (away with that word!) for, as surely as the laws of the natural and of the spiritual worlds are true &amp; irreversible, so are these things prepared for obedient love:—an inspiration as true, as real, and as certain as that which ever prophet or apostle reached, is yours,—if you will have it so.—</p>
         <p>—And if obedience were entire &amp; love were perfect, then would the Revelation of the Spirit to the soul of man be perfect too. There would be trust expelling care, and enabling a man to repose on his Father:—there would be a love which would cast out fear—there would be a sympathy with the mighty All of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>:—selfishness would pass, isolation would be felt no longer:—the tide of the universal &amp; eternal life would come with mighty pulsations throbbing through the soul. To such a man it would not matter where he was, nor what: to live or die would be alike. If he lived, he lived unto the <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord</hi>. The bed of down, surrounded by friends,—or the martyr’s stake, girt round with curses,—what matter which? The ward in the hospital,—the union work-house,—the quiet cosy comfortable home, or the lonely friendless couch in a far-off &amp; savage land,—what matter which? It would matter little what he was,—the ruler of a kingdom, or a tailor grimed with the smoke &amp; dust of a work-shop. To a soul filled with <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>, the difference between these two is inappreciable;—as if, from a distant star, you were to look down on a palace &amp; a hovel, both dwindled into distance, &amp; were to smile at the thought of calling one large and the other small.—</p>
         <p>I have touched on “the <hi rend="italic">mind</hi> of Xt.,”—which mind should also be <hi rend="italic">ours</hi>. Just consider His considerate kindness:— “I have compassion on the multitude—bec. they have nothing to eat.” (There was <hi rend="italic">tenderness</hi>!) Again, to the disciples:— “Come ye apart into a desert place and rest awhile” (He did not grudge them relaxation.) Then his dying words (under severe torture of body, &amp; desertion by his own!)— “Behold thy mother!—Behold thy son!” He was too exhausted to say more: but he could think of her desolate state when he was gone, and with delicate thoughtful attention provide for her well-being.—</p>
         <p>Now there are people who would do <hi rend="italic">great acts</hi>,—but, because they wait for great opportunities, life passes, and the acts of love are not done at all. Note, this considerateness of Christ was shown in little things: and such are the parts of human life. Opportunities for doing <hi rend="italic">greatly</hi> seldom occur—life is made up of infinitesimals. If you compute the sum of happiness on any given day, you will find that it was composed of small attentions, kind looks and kind words spoken feelingly,—which made the heart swell, and stirred into health that sour rancid film of pride and misanthropy, which is apt to coagulate on the stream of our inward life, as surely as we live in heart apart from our fellow-creatures!—</p>
         <p>Doubtless, the memory of each one of us will furnish the picture of some member of a family (we have seen or known) whose very presence seemed to shed happiness. A child,—a little daughter, perhaps, whose light step, even in the distance irradiated everyone’s countenance. What was the secret of such an one’s power? what had she done? what doing? Absolutely nothing, but radiant smiles, beaming good humour, the tact of divining what every one felt, &amp; every one wanted, told—that <hi rend="underline italic">she had got out of self and learned to think for others</hi>:—so that, at one time, it showed itself in deprecating the quarrel, which lowering brows &amp; raised tones already showed to be impending, by sweet words:—at another by smoothing an invalid’s pillow;—at another, by soothing a sobbing child;—at another by humouring &amp; softening a father who had returned, worn-out &amp; weary and ill-tempered from the irritating cares of business. None but she saw those things. None but a loving heart <hi rend="italic">could </hi>see them. That was the great secret of her heavenly power.</p>
         <p>Call you those things <hi rend="italic">homely </hi>trifles, too homely for a religious discourse, or a sermon? By reference to the character of Christ, they rise into something quite sublime. For <hi rend="underline italic">that</hi> is loving as He loved. And, remark, too, these trifles prepared for larger deeds. The one who will be found in trial capable of great acts of love, is ever the one who is always doing considerate small ones. The soul which poured itself out to death on the cross—was the spirit of him who affectionately thought of the wants of the people,—contrived for the rest of the disciples,—and was thoughtful, even when in agonies, for his mother!</p>
         <p>Still further:—<hi rend="italic">It was a love never foiled by the unworthiness of those on whom it had been once bestowed</hi>. It was a love which faults desertion, denial, unfaithfulness, could not chill,—even though they wrung His heart. He had chosen: and He trusted. Even in ordinary manhood, that is a finely tempered heart, one of no ordinary mould, which can say,— “It ever was my way, and shall be still, when I do trust a man to trust him wholly.”</p>
         <p>—And yet there was every thing to shake His trust in Humanity. The Pharisees called him Good Master! and were circumventing him all the while! The people shouted Hosannas! and 3 days after were shrieking for his blood! One disciple who had dipped in the same dish, and been trusted with his inmost counsels, deceived &amp; betrayed him:—another was ashamed to own him:—three fell asleep while he was in agony and preparing for death:—<hi rend="italic">all</hi> forsook him. Yet nothing is more surprising than that unshaken, I had well-nigh said, <hi rend="italic">obstinate </hi>trust with which He clung to his hopes of our nature, and believed even in the very face of demonstration.</p>
         <p>As we mix in life there comes especially to sensitive natures,—a temptation to distrust. In young life we throw ourselves with unbounded and glorious confidence on such as we think well of—our error soon corrected: for we soon find out—too soon—that men &amp; women are not what they seem. Then comes disappointment,—and the danger is a re-action of desolating &amp; universal mistrust. For if we look on the doings of man with a merely worldly eye, and pierce below the mere surface of character, we are apt to feel bitter scorn and disgust for our fellow-creatures:—No wonder if we are tempted to think,— “friendship <hi rend="italic">all</hi> a cheat—smiles hypocrisy—words deceit,”—and they who are what is called <hi rend="italic">knowing</hi> in life contract by degrees, as the result of their experience, a hollow distrust of men, and <hi rend="italic">learn </hi>to sneer at apparently good motives.—That demoniacal sneer which we have seen, ay perhaps <hi rend="italic">felt</hi>, curling the lip at times,— “Doth Job serve <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> for nought?”—</p>
         <p>Now the only preservation from this withering of the heart is Love. Love is its own perennial fount of strength.—The strength of affection is a proof not of the worthiness of the object, but of the largeness of the soul which loves.—Love descends, not ascends. The might of a river depends not on the quality of the soil through which it passes, but on the inexhaustibleness and depth of the spring from which it proceeds. The greater mind cleaves to the smaller with more force than the other to it. A parent loves the child more than the child the parent; and partly because the parent’s heart is larger, not because the child is worthier. Jesus loved his disciples infinitely more than they loved him, because his heart was larger, his love stronger and deeper. Love trusts on—ever hopes and expects better things; and this, a trust springing from itself, and out of its own deeps alone (1 Cor. xiii).</p>
         <p>And more than this. It is this <hi rend="italic">trusting</hi> love that makes men what they are trusted to be, so realizing itself. Would you make men <hi rend="underline italic">trustworthy</hi>? Trust them. Would you make them true? Believe them. This was the real force of that sublime battle-cry which no Englishman hears without emotion. When the crews of the fleet of Britain knew that they were <hi rend="italic">expected</hi> to do their duty, they <hi rend="italic">did</hi> their duty. They felt, in that spirit-stirring sentence, that they were trusted;—and the simultaneous cheer that rose from every ship was a forerunner of victory—the battle was half-won already.— They went to serve a country which expected from them great things,—and they <hi rend="italic">did</hi> great things. </p>
         <p>And it is on this principle that Christ wins the hearts of His redeemed. He trusted the doubting Thomas, and Thomas arose with a faith worthy his being trusted by his Master. He would not suffer even the oaths and lies and denials of Peter to shake His conviction, that Peter might love him yet; and Peter answered nobly to that trust, to that sublime forgiveness. (But my Xn. Bishop refused scornfully to <hi rend="italic">trust me </hi>again, even when repeatedly besought to do so,—although he has had ample proof, during 20 years of heavy past faithful services, to which he had also borne witness!) The last prayer of Jesus was in extenuation and hope for the race who had rejected him! He has loved us—<hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> knows why; I do not—and we, all unworthy though we be, respond faintly to that love, and try to be what He taught us, &amp; what He would have us.</p>
         <p>Therefore come what may, my dear Sister, <hi rend="underline italic">Hold fast to Love</hi>. Though the mountains should be removed into the midst of the sea—let us continue to <hi rend="italic">trust </hi>in <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>—our loving Father in heaven: though men should rend our heart, let them not embitter or harden it. We win by tenderness: we conquer by forgiveness. Oh, let us strive to enter into something of that large celestial Charity which is meek, enduring, unretaliating, and which even the overbearing world can not withstand for ever. Learn the new Commandment of Jesus: not to love merely, but to love <hi rend="italic">as He loved</hi>. Let us go forth in this spirit to our life duties: and we shall find that we shall carry every thing before us, and win victories for our <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> by the conquering power of a Love like His.</p>
         <p>May this be our happy lot! Amen.</p>
         <p>Written for my dear sister, on Sunday afternoon, February 7/75:—             Napier, N. Zealand: by W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>