<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0854">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1893 January 10: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1893-01-10">1893 January 10</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1893 January 10: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-627" place="foot" n="627"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Jany. 10/93</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>It is some time (rather longer than usual) since my last to you: but I have been very busy—one way &amp; another, &amp; have often had you in my thoughts. Last week I received your very kind letter written on “N. Yr’s. Day”, &amp; I thank you for it. I believe my last to you was on 19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> Decr.—well, on 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. I went to Dannevirke, and while there I <hi rend="italic">revisited </hi>for<hi rend="italic"> </hi>the<hi rend="italic"> first time in ’92 </hi>[sic] my old distant &amp; loved haunts in the woods,—and that on 3 different days, walking say 6–7–8 miles ea. day—or, thus, occupied 3–4 hours—and of course <hi rend="italic">completely done up ea. time </hi>so that I could scarcely make my lodgings. However, as I had <hi rend="italic">fixed </hi>Ch. work here—I returned to Napier on 28<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., and on my way while halting at ’Pukurau I saw your Uncle John there, &amp; thought (as I told him) he was getting <hi rend="italic">fat</hi>—looking exceedingly well.—</p>
         <p>Now I had closed my letters for England, &amp;c, on the Tuesday night (27<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) and posted <hi rend="italic">there</hi>; and in them I said— “I felt, at last! <hi rend="italic">free from Rheumatism</hi>”. That day the wind was <hi rend="italic">very high</hi>, nearly blew me down on the open plains, and this continued at night, insomuch that I could not sleep from the incessant racket of the <hi rend="italic">upper </hi>open sash in my bedroom; at 1 a.m. I arose &amp; tried hard to shut it, but could not reacch up sufficiently, dressing table lg. glass &amp;c. in the way: well in my trouble &amp; struggles I strained my back and <hi rend="italic">brought on </hi>(or back) <hi rend="italic">Lumbago</hi>!! I could scarcely move next day, yet I was determined to come on—<hi rend="italic">if possible</hi>: so I sat during 80 miles of transit in pain, &amp; then here had to climb this hill! I was not long before I got Anderson to rub me with ac. acid,—spent a sad night, a <hi rend="italic">little </hi>easier next day—but oh! the terrible thoughts of the <hi rend="italic">promised </hi>Sunday work, and no one to help.—</p>
         <p>A little better on Sy. mg.—a <hi rend="italic">rainy </hi>day (with 3 following!)—I got through my S. at Cathedral but the Evg. S. was <hi rend="italic">the trial</hi>—to walk thither (Augustine’s) in pouring rain, &amp; then back and to climb this wet &amp; slippery hill!!! However, <hi rend="italic">I was </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">enabled</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> to do it</hi>: &amp; I trust w. a <hi rend="italic">thankful heart</hi>: when, at ix p.m. I re-entered here. On Sunday last I was at Taradale for both services, day fine—but I felt <hi rend="italic">relieved </hi>(you will I think understand me) when that work also was <hi rend="italic">done</hi>.—–</p>
         <p>I had early written to White Hon. Secy. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>my plant papers, &amp; he consented to withhold sending (all) in to Wgn. <hi rend="italic">until 15</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi>, and so I have been hard at work on them, &amp; have this night finished copying! Hurrah! and <hi rend="italic">these</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">may be my last in Botany: </hi>I cannot afford time for it. So my good friend you may see <hi rend="italic">I have been engaged</hi>: – – – –</p>
         <p>I have received several kind remembrances from various quarters, among them an <hi rend="italic">annual </hi>letter from Peacock, which I shall send to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>—that you may see <hi rend="italic">headings, </hi>&amp;c. this please <hi rend="italic">return</hi>. I also send a <hi rend="italic">curiously printed </hi>Invitation from R. Sy.—that you may see it! O.S. the best of it is, that it was only posted in London, add. to me in N.Z. about the time of the meeting!—<hi rend="italic">Don’t return this</hi>. Also, a circular, which cost me 8d.!!! (was I not wild!) Bob. took it out of P.O. in my absence. <hi rend="italic">Destroy this</hi>. Also, <hi rend="italic">Howes’ </hi>Circular—that you may see it. And a copy of some verses made by a young Maori at Xt.Ch., which has made me &amp; others to laugh: I have had this by me for some time for you, but I always forgot it: <hi rend="italic">Don’t return</hi>. I also send a couple or more of scraps in an envelope, that were brought here by your brother (so Mrs Anderson says)—these are of <hi rend="italic">no use </hi>to me.—–</p>
         <p>I shall send you this day’s “Herald” as some parts of it may interest you. I suppose you heard of the death of Halkett Lord? &amp; now today of Seffern. Pallot has <hi rend="italic">been obliged</hi> to leave “D.T.”, &amp; is now in “Evg. News” estab.!—–</p>
         <p>I thank you for “Evg. Post” containing Tregear’s letter: I should like to talk <hi rend="italic">w. you </hi>on <hi rend="italic">that subject</hi>. I notice what Atkinson has said concern. T.,—there may be <hi rend="italic">some </hi>truth in it: I have always thought so—but I have <hi rend="italic">never yet </hi>opened his book (though I have 2 copies!) since that first &amp; <hi rend="italic">only </hi>brief peep at recg. as I told you &amp; him.—</p>
         <p>In the “Press”, XtCh. of Decr. 19, is an excellent (&amp; long) paper by that same young Maori, who wrote those lines—<hi rend="underline italic">see it if you can</hi>: on his own people.—</p>
         <p>I have recd. a strange letter (in French) from Madrid—my Spanish Don,—who complains of my ansg. <hi rend="italic">in Eng</hi>.! &amp; <hi rend="italic">not </hi>saying anything about his <hi rend="italic">booklet </hi>(Spanish)!!! when I said enough—at least I thought so: it is a queer ep.—but <hi rend="italic">I won’t write again to him</hi>.<hi rend="italic">—–</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Mr. and Mrs. Hill are at Taupo—or Tongariro “awa!” went in his buggy.</p>
         <p>Should you—or Tregear—have anything more to say at your mtgs. re the Moa—first look at what I have said—in “<hi rend="italic">Trans</hi>.” vol. XXI, p.205.</p>
         <p>I hope my papers (being the last!) may pass <hi rend="italic">the ordeal</hi>: I see Tregear is now one of the Governors (examining body?)—and I hope he will not allow mine to lie “rejected” again:—I am led to this—bec. of <hi rend="italic">Maskell</hi>, for in my “Bush Jottings” I have <hi rend="italic">ventured </hi>to say something of the <hi rend="italic">unorthodox </hi>kind <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Constantine’s cross in the sky!!—at which, I fancy, M. would flare!—–</p>
         <p>I scarcely believe those stories of the Rev. R.S. Hawker, sent by you; I have read other similar. Your “Big fish” is matched by this Blue Shark of today, down Otago way; how that story agrees—<hi rend="italic">in part</hi>—with mine (Maori) of the Mako!—past X! and here I “<hi rend="italic">lay up</hi>”.</p>
         <p>11<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. I had hoped last night to finish my letter to you &amp; forward—but I could not—I post however the “Herald”. I have just read over the <hi rend="italic">long </hi>story I wrote to you last night, and I am (or have been) “in two minds” <hi rend="italic">re </hi>same—to burn it, or to send it! <hi rend="italic">Laziness </hi>w. me, has prevailed.—</p>
         <p>At Craig’s on Thursday last (first time for nearly a month) I bought one of Dinwiddie’s <hi rend="italic">wretched </hi>Almanacs! worse than ever—smaller, too, with the horrid advts. on coarse coloured p. interspersed! I bought it for “the Map of the Town” (<hi rend="italic">re </hi>Puffes, in St.!) which is unreadable even with a magng. glass! &amp; <hi rend="italic">so wired</hi>—as not to open freely: but a book recently to hand (from Fielder) printed in your town—by Kirkbride, “Genl. Synod Proceedings,” is worse still in respect of <hi rend="italic">stab</hi>-binding w. narrow back margin.</p>
         <p>This day I have been hard at wk. in my shirt-sleeves only! all day, and so I am now: thermr. <hi rend="italic">in this house </hi>today 90º, yesty. 86º, two very hot days, &amp; yet I have had fire until now. Well: I have been engaged in packing pretty securely all my plants of this yrs. &amp; of last (from Sep ’91!) with Hill’s &amp; others—all of these 8–9 bundles, sorting, changing sheets, &amp;c—these have <hi rend="italic">all </hi>been in this parlour throughout ’92, (to the grief of the house-keeper!) also—any amount of books of ref.—now <hi rend="italic">all cleared out</hi>! &amp; next wk. I hope to begin on the scores (? hundreds!) of Fungi for Kew—also, all <hi rend="italic">here </hi>in parlour on floor under table &amp; in big boxes—I long to <hi rend="italic">finish</hi> this job also.</p>
         <p>I was very pleased to find in your letter such a <hi rend="italic">good account </hi>of Victor, &amp; of you all—&amp; that you endeavoured to look on the brighter side of things secular to begin the yr. with. We have entered on this New Year together—God only knows if we may see its end—but <hi rend="italic">our hope </hi>shall be <hi rend="italic">in Him: </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">He</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">, </hi>my friend, <hi rend="underline italic">He is faithful</hi>. And now with every good wish &amp; kindest regards</p>
         <p>Believe me yours truly</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>All family &amp; friends letters from Home urge my <hi rend="italic">return</hi>!!!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
