<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0783">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 May 28: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-05-28">1891 May 28</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 May 28: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-530" place="foot" n="530"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier<lb/>Thursday Night<lb/>May 28, 1891.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Yours of 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. is to hand, and I thank you for it. I wrote to you on the same day, so that again our letters have crossed in transit.—I am very tired with my work of this day—looking out spns. of plants for Kirk—a most irksome job &amp; most <hi rend="italic">unwillingly</hi> entered on—in fulfilment of my promise to aid him in his editing the new issue of the Handbook: he wants spns. of <hi rend="italic">all my newly-desd.-plants</hi>! which (if I have them, which is doubtful, as I only cared to have spns. to send to Hooker, Kew,)—will cause me to go through all <hi rend="italic">my bundles of plants</hi>, &amp; really would occupy a week or 10 days—close at it!!! I would rather put back into cases <hi rend="italic">a whole lower-c. of pie</hi>!—</p>
         <p>I think I must endeavour to take it up <hi rend="italic">leisurely</hi>—say, <hi rend="italic">every mg</hi>. for 3 hours—<hi rend="italic">or</hi>, every afternoon. I (again) note—in the printed programme, &amp;c. you have sent me of the “Home Rig. Assn.”—that K. is again dubbed <hi rend="italic">“Profr.”</hi>! You will find such is <hi rend="italic">not</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">allowed in the Govt. books, </hi>&amp;c, and it <hi rend="italic">does not</hi> belong to him.</p>
         <p>I went to town on Tuesday &amp; called early on yr brother—in the <hi rend="italic">old</hi> office (I was going to write—“<hi rend="italic">dear</hi> old off.”) I told him of you &amp; yours, &amp;c—asked after, Dad, &amp;c—when, lo! your F. came in, &amp; I never saw him looking so very well—rosy-cheeked, too! We talked for some time, but I was <hi rend="italic">obliged</hi> to cut short, having so much to do in town, after such a long absence (7 weeks): but weather permitting I go again tomorrow—I want some “Jubilee” books, if there are any: I went also to your <hi rend="italic">front</hi> shop in quest of Maori B., &amp; P.Bk.—but none, had some talk w. elderly gent. in charge, calling on Jago to pay him the <hi rend="italic">fees</hi> for re-addressing—he showed me <hi rend="italic">my</hi> L. to P.M. Genl—<hi rend="italic">re</hi> same: sent to J., to enq., if I could furnish the copy of my <hi rend="italic">former</hi> one (alluded to in it) written to Secy. G.P.O., &amp; also of his reply: as both were burnt!! I sd. I could—little thinking what <hi rend="italic">that</hi> involved! All that afternoon did I ransack &amp; search for them, &amp; had—2–3—times nearly abandoned search, but kept on, &amp; at last found <hi rend="italic">both</hi>: but, in copying mine to Secy., it occupied 6 pages <hi rend="italic">large</hi> 4to., closely ruled!</p>
         <p>Calling on Craig I found he had a copy of “The World’s Religions,” by Bettany—a ponderous <hi rend="italic">800</hi> fully illustd. well got up (over 900 pp.) well printed, w. hundreds of engs, <hi rend="italic">some</hi> full page, &amp; <hi rend="italic">good</hi>, price only 7/6. (It was pubd. end of ’90, by Ward, Lock &amp; Co. &amp; I had ordered it.) I looked at N.Z.—“the Maoris”—just 1 page, &amp; that <hi rend="italic">incorrect</hi>! with a well-executed cut, from Cook, but <hi rend="italic">wrongly placed there</hi>—“A N.Z. corpse priest &amp; the dead,” &amp;c—as it belongs to the Friendly (or other) Islands, w. the big plantain trees, &amp;c.—I much fear that Tregear’s Dy. may also fail in this way—by his embracing <hi rend="italic">every</hi> “authority”; the Bp. was here w. me again today, &amp; enqd. <hi rend="italic">re</hi> T’s. Dy: I said I had it, in bk. room, but had not yet looked into it: he sd. Archd. W. had (like me) got 2 copies: one ordered, &amp; one from T.<note xml:id="ftn3-531" place="foot" n="531"> The following “portion of a letter to R.C. Harding” is from ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-1, but fits here.</note>
         </p>
         <p>The Bp came for me to take Ch. duty on Sy. mg. next at Taradale—and also, to go with him thither on the following Sy.—duty divided between us, Tuke going far away inland; of course, to <hi rend="italic">both</hi> I consented.</p>
         <p>Did your eye catch in Collier, p.141 “Gera1d Massey, Book of the Beginnings”,—comp. vocabulary of <hi rend="italic">Maori</hi> &amp; Egyptn. words—<hi rend="italic">nearly 1000 Maori words</hi> w. as many similar Egypt. words in parall. cols.—1881: what a feast for Tregear!!!</p>
         <p>I note your clipping—re the war canoe purchd. by Buller as being that “in wh. the chiefs of Povy. Bay visited Cook’s ship”—another “fad”—<hi rend="italic">they never did go there</hi>! In the D.T. of last wk. a notice of the death of Hemi Taka (a quiet old chief, well-known to me, from <hi rend="italic">the earliest</hi>)—he is <hi rend="italic">said</hi> to have seen Cook and, as a clincher that when Cook’s boat landed <hi rend="italic">here</hi> in H.B. to get water for the ship, H. Taka, then a boy, was frightened &amp; ran off into the flax swamp!!! Now <hi rend="italic">I know</hi> all about that landing; of course it was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> Cook’s ship. R.P. calls him (H.T.) “<hi rend="italic">the Old Cannibal</hi>”!—I had nearly written a letter about it. [Good night].<note xml:id="ftn3-532" place="foot" n="532"> Harding reported this in his <hi rend="italic">Typo</hi> of June 1891.</note>
         </p>
         <p>29th (night) in town this mg. (day fine) I called to see your brother re copies of “Jubilee” Book &amp; was sorry to find him <hi rend="italic">so unwell</hi>—in great pain from indigestion. I spent some time with him &amp; advised on several points; he had been so before &amp; was going to see Hitchings. Kiwi (we believe) arrived last night. The name of the elderly person I saw in your <hi rend="italic">front</hi> shop—is Mayer or Mather. Saw Mr. Sidey—<hi rend="italic">quite well</hi>; ditto Craig, who was vexed at only <hi rend="italic">such a few</hi> at Hill’s Inaugural paper.—</p>
         <p>Fannin, from Dunedin is expected tonight; both Hill &amp; F. away, the <hi rend="italic">young</hi> Mr. Ferguson is “boss”!!</p>
         <p>In putting up the Col. Secy’s reply to my letter for J.W.’s books (<hi rend="underline italic">3</hi> vols) he, <hi rend="italic">twice</hi> says, I am to have <hi rend="underline italic">two</hi> granted me—on paying for them.</p>
         <p>A <hi rend="italic">red </hi>printed sheet almanac for ’89—stuck on my partition upstairs &amp; in sun’s evening rays a few hours each sunny day in summer has become faded, &amp; in some places wholly obliterated!—–</p>
         <p>I have been looking into (i.e. going over every par.) my copy of “Monty’s. Omnip. Deity”—&amp; <hi rend="italic">do not</hi> find those lines quoted by you; yet mine is a <hi rend="italic">10</hi>th Ed. dedd. by permission to Abp. of Canterbury—w. a <hi rend="italic">long</hi> and highly praising art. from the London Times; it is printed, 1830 &amp; publd. by Maunder, Newgate St.</p>
         <p>I have found the line—the “pride that apes humility”—in my edn. of Coleridge, &amp; will copy 2 stanzas;—will also copy the whole for you if you wish it.—</p>
         <p>Very pleased to hear of Victor being better. Rev. Mr. Cornford told me today he was going <hi rend="italic">to Wgn.</hi> (not willingly!) to supply place of some Minr. there.</p>
         <p rend="center">————</p>
         <p rend="center">“The Devil’s Thoughts”</p>
         <p rend="center">v.</p>
         <p rend="center">“He saw an Apothecary on a white horse</p>
         <p rend="center">Ride by on his vocations;</p>
         <p rend="center">And the Devil thought of his old friend</p>
         <p rend="center">Death in the Revelations.”</p>
         <p rend="center">vi</p>
         <p rend="center">“He saw a cottage with a double coach-house,</p>
         <p rend="center">A cottage of gentility;</p>
         <p rend="center">And the Devil did grin, for his darling sin</p>
         <p rend="center">Is pride that apes humility.”</p>
         <p>(xvii stanzas in all.)</p>
         <p>             Ever yours sincy.,                              W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
