<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0308">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1876 January 9: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1876-01-09">1876 January 9</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1876 January 9: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-243" place="foot" n="243"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N.Z.<lb/>Jany. 9, 1876.</p>
         <p>My dear Sir</p>
         <p>I wrote you a long letter on the 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. December, since which I have not had anything from you: our Eng. M. arrived at Auckland more than a week ago, but it is not yet to hand (although St. left with it 5 days back: we may get it tomorrow. The weather has been extraordinary (Grubb says, “dreadful”) from New Yr’s. Day inclusive). The sun has been shining a <hi rend="italic">little </hi>today, &amp; the tree locusts, poor things! have been also chirruping a <hi rend="italic">little</hi> this mg., their first song for the year!—rain every day, so that, while not cold in-doors, I have been obliged to have fire &amp; to again put on worsted socks for the damp. Water everywhere below, &amp; <hi rend="italic">mud</hi> too! Hay &amp; Grass seed <hi rend="italic">lost</hi>, to a large amount, &amp; lots of sheep unshorn: the <hi rend="italic">whole </hi>Spring &amp; summer has been very wet, &amp; I have no ripe gooseberries yet. Wilson’s &amp; Tuxford’s gardens, however, are benefitted &amp; looking splendid! the whole island, back country, hills are still green.</p>
         <p>My last letter will have told you of the elections, then nearly coming off. Well, <hi rend="italic">I am beaten</hi>: (all to rags as the boys say) &amp; no mistake; &amp; certainly most <hi rend="italic">unexpectedly</hi> so. I must refer you to Papers (I send a lot) for particulars. Had I known I was to have <hi rend="italic">2</hi> Governments (or 3, with Municipality) against me, I would not have stood. You never saw <hi rend="italic">here</hi> such an excitement!—It commenced on Monday,—when Sir D. &amp; self had a show of hands in our favour,—this made the Mayor’s party <hi rend="italic">mad</hi>!—And they <hi rend="italic">did </hi>work! and at <hi rend="underline italic">last</hi>, several of my best supporters (Robjohns &amp; others) fearing Stuart would get ahead of Russell, (&amp; seeing that McL. &amp; O. were working hard for R.—) they voted for Russell (in this, I agreeing) &amp; the Maoris led by H.R &amp; Sheehan, voted for Stuart so did the <hi rend="italic">Catholics</hi>. More, it is <hi rend="italic">said</hi> that R. promised to join their Ch. if returned! At Pakowhai, a few days before the poll, Karaitiana &amp; his relations <hi rend="italic">assured</hi> me they would vote for me!! You will see much of me in the Papers, but more than once, allowing that I was the proper person. But I now <hi rend="italic">know </hi>that McL. &amp; O. did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> wish me returned.)—you will see Hawes’ letter! and the Johnny Gilpin parody, was done by the writer,—I suppose <hi rend="italic">you </hi>will <hi rend="italic">guess</hi> all the allusions readily. Buchanan has since had a <hi rend="italic">worse</hi> defeat at Clive, where there were only 2 candidates: and as to R. Pharazyn at Whanganui: and old Cracroft Wilson too, at Heathcote! the election must have cost Stuart a <hi rend="italic">heavy </hi>sum! money was <hi rend="italic">lavishly used</hi>.</p>
         <p>Helen Denny—our 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi> w. ship sailed, about Xmas, with nearly 20 passengers—among them Doyle &amp; family: “British Empire” also left last week: J. Wood is dead—at Noumea, N. Caledonia. Mrs Tanner’s son is going to England, with Mrs St. Hills—Mr. H.H. going also. <hi rend="italic">I would go this </hi>month if I <hi rend="italic">could</hi>: I am hedged in, &amp; cannot see my way—unless I <hi rend="italic">sell all</hi>. If <hi rend="italic">you</hi> were still here &amp; in business, I could manage it, but I do not like to give <hi rend="italic">full &amp; ample powers </hi>to anyone here in business—besides, w. several of them I am <hi rend="italic">not over</hi> friendly. Topping is insolvent,—so I went there yesterday in rain, &amp; got from <hi rend="italic">Mrs</hi>. T. the lease—losing the rent! I was to have seen O. &amp; <hi rend="italic">resigned</hi> Inspectorship but the very wet weather has prevented me: I may go out tomorrow A Govt. sale of Land last week netted over £10,000! Ormond bought largely at Woodville: (see the Paper I send), notice also what is said of Mackay’s shop &amp; N. &amp; Close’s shops.—I have sold “Silinine” to Mr. Morice for £10. not yet taken. Aldridge, is <hi rend="italic">honest</hi>, (just as I expected). Considering the weather—the work Inspg. schools—the bustle &amp; bother of Auctions for I even went to Clive yesterday in the pouring rain to vote for O.—(&amp; so keep <hi rend="italic">my </hi>word,)—and the <hi rend="italic">defeat</hi>—I have enjoyed pretty good health: far better than I had anticipated: I have been often thinking of <hi rend="italic">you </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">yours</hi> how you bear the Eng. winter. Brandon told me, yesterday, that <hi rend="italic">Gollan</hi> now enjoys good health, &amp; will very likely <hi rend="italic">not </hi>return.</p>
         <p>Martin Hamlin’s Land (50 ac. W. Clive) is in the market: I enqd. price, £35. pr. ac! The land at Meanee which you let to Martin, and he let, &amp; I let to a person named Read: well he threw it up as I would not allow him to <hi rend="italic">sublet</hi>, &amp; I have since let to to a Nursery Gardener here, named Gillice. P. Dolbel had a wedding in his house on Xmas day, a nice young niece of his, whom he brought w. him, to a young man thereaway named <hi rend="italic">Hollis</hi>. (Perhaps<hi rend="italic"> </hi>you may know him,)—P.D. was <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, for an hour last evening—<hi rend="italic">quite an event</hi>! W.Thomas <hi rend="italic">never</hi> calls now: why, I do not know. I saw Mr Sidey the other day, he was on horseback. I gave him your messages; he sd. he had heard from you: I <hi rend="italic">think</hi> he, too, had greatly altered towards <hi rend="italic">me</hi>: reason why, I don’t know. It is loudly <hi rend="underline italic">talked</hi> of that Stuart, (Mayor,) became Insolvent at Otago, only paying 5/- in ₤1. &amp; managed to make over property to wife, &amp; run to bror.-in-law! I did not hear of it, until <hi rend="italic">after </hi>the Hustings Scene.—I suppose, he will never forgive <hi rend="italic">me</hi>!</p>
         <p>Mr Redstone, they say, is about to be removed; I am sorry for this, for he is an active &amp; useful little fellow, &amp; came out <hi rend="italic">well</hi> in the trying time of sickness last autumn. Poor Martin Hamlin is still lingering! Grubb is about going in to new P.O. at last!! I had almost forgotten to say, Capt. Read has been returned Member H.R. for East Coast!! (if “<hi rend="italic">These be thy Gods</hi>! O Israel!!) Sorry am I at this. Just the “Herald” rejoices, because such (I suppose) suits McL. &amp; O.!</p>
         <p>Now for a joke. Yesterday in going to Spit, in trap, Kinross entered; &amp; so in after Whitmore &amp; Kirch (Patea). K. &amp; Wh. talked about Read. Wh. didnt like the idea of such a low fellow, &amp;c. K. said, He was as good as many in the House! I asked of K., “<hi rend="italic">Which</hi> Ho.?”—&amp; there was a scene! K. got red, &amp; hesitated; Wh. pulled his pipe from his mouth &amp; looked daggers at me: B. coloured up! I said, to Wh., “You have no need to look so fiercely; there was no harm in my qu. which I repeat.”—Again, asking K., who declined to answer, when B. &amp; self <hi rend="italic">laughed out</hi>,—&amp; so did the other 2.—(My <hi rend="italic">only </hi>joke, or merriment, for New Year.) A large house is being erected here on the hill, in a line from my <hi rend="italic">end</hi> parlour window &amp; Barrack-hill, (looking from my room). Very conspicuous.</p>
         <p>Two only items of scandal:—Robjohns (bachelor) has gone off, <hi rend="italic">very ugly</hi> stories about him &amp; niece. Silas Palin brought up a Mrs Roadknight (or some such name) for a <hi rend="italic">scandal </hi>in <hi rend="underline italic">Sup.</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">Court</hi>!! &amp; lost her case!—I think she was <hi rend="italic">hardly </hi>used.—Terribly slashing articles in the Maori Paper against H. Bay “ring”! I don’t think Ormond, Williams &amp; Co. have <hi rend="italic">really</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">strengthened themselves</hi> by putting in Capt. Russell; he, &amp; his bror. being also deeply involved in same mire: and so, I fancy, the Ho. will think.</p>
         <p rend="end"> (10<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., night.)</p>
         <p>This mg. I got your letter of Novr. 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. and all the many papers you have so very kindly sent, including a huge “<hi rend="italic">Graphic,</hi>” also medicine in packet. I can only just thank you now for all these good things. Your opening remark about arrival of S.F. Mail &amp; <hi rend="italic">your not</hi> yet getting any letters—(bearing in mind you were <hi rend="italic">in London </hi>&amp; wrote <hi rend="italic">on 18</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>.) amused me much; for my eldest son writing from <hi rend="italic">near Durham</hi>, <hi rend="italic">on 17</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>., acknowledges receipt that mg. of mine to him by that mail, so that Durham got their letter before London!! I expect <hi rend="italic">this </hi>will go by <hi rend="italic">Suez</hi>: I saw Grubb, to-day, who was very busy, &amp; who read me a telegram from Wgn., <hi rend="italic">both</hi> Suez &amp; S.F. Mails are to go <hi rend="italic">overland</hi> by <hi rend="italic">Peters’</hi>: Suez will be <hi rend="italic">in time</hi> (leaving there 16<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.), but S.F. <hi rend="italic">may </hi>not; so I shall, I think, make sure. I went to town to day, in great measure, to see Ormond, but he &amp; family are at Wallingford, for holidays, not having had any holiday, owing to elections, and weather: this caused another put off.</p>
         <p>I thought on you again today, “D.Teleg.” sent in their Bill for advertising, election matters, ₤10.19.6!—I went to Herald, got theirs, <hi rend="italic">same </hi>work ₤<hi rend="italic">5.3.6</hi>: so I posted over the way—and, after calling <hi rend="italic">twice</hi>, &amp; a long altercation, I paid them ₤5.10. taking a receipt in <hi rend="italic">full</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">they </hi>deducting, “<hi rend="italic">overcharge</hi>; ₤5.9.6”!! I knew that amount (₤5.10.0) down, I said, I wod. pay <hi rend="italic">no more</hi>. Stuart, I hear, is kicking dreadfully at what he has to pay: and no marvel!—</p>
         <p>I shall send you tomorrow, the “Herald” w. Hawthorne letter (whatever that may be): Buchanan, poor fellow! did dreadfully bad at <hi rend="italic">his </hi>election: it is now known, that out of the 31 or 32 for him were 10 Maoris, 5 or 6 of H.R’s. people &amp; servants, &amp; B. &amp; his sons (B. voted at Kaikoura) —so that he only got some 6 or 7 Europeans.</p>
         <p>The Natives everywhere are going to <hi rend="italic">Register</hi> &amp; boast what they will do!—and they <hi rend="italic">may</hi>—if the Europeans continue supine!–</p>
         <p>I told you that Mrs Carter was married to Margoliouth. I have heard from the <hi rend="italic">best </hi>authority, that she refused <hi rend="italic">Maney</hi>. (It is said, &amp; is, perhaps, true,—that neither Tuke nor Maney, really intended to stand, but they had, <hi rend="italic">each</hi>, a point to carry w. the Govt. &amp; by <hi rend="italic">this means</hi> &amp; they have both succeeded!!)—</p>
         <p>Quite common talk,— “Newton, <hi rend="italic">now </hi>will be J.P.!” Poor young Northe, after suffering a deal from Rheumatism, is just gone to Waiwera Springs.—J. Rhodes is <hi rend="italic">not </hi>yet back in N.Z.; Coleman is. Dolbel says, I am sure to die in Eng. climate; he &amp; his brother suffered. Well, I hope you &amp; <hi rend="italic">yours </hi>will not. <hi rend="italic">You</hi>, I think, are <hi rend="italic">hardy</hi>, more so than your flock. And now, my very dear sir (whose absence I mourn continuously!) Good bye.</p>
         <p>And w. best wishes believe me <hi rend="italic">Yours, </hi>         W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S.                                                                         (Jany. 11<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.<lb/>                                                                            closing.)</p>
         <p>Your old acquaintance Brown of Clive—called this mg. he is just from Pov. Bay, where he has been looking about for 3 months. And, on the very day of his leaving (yesterday) agreed there for 100 ac. at ₤8.—paying down (at Capt. Read’s remark!) ₤200. cash—to secure the Land. The Conditions are, B. is to pay ₤800. in <hi rend="italic">cash</hi> before end of Feby. (He has ₤450. of his own—but, of course, he requires money for stock.) I pity the man’s acting!—if he cannot borrow <hi rend="italic">largely</hi> he will lose his ₤200.—<hi rend="italic">&amp; he sees it now</hi>!! I have promised to go to Town tomorrow, &amp; try to get him help. </p>
         <p>Br. says, that M. Hamlin’s Land, 50 ac. at West Clive, has some (reported) flaw in the title! something between Sutton &amp; him.—</p>
         <p>“Hudson” not yet arrived; perhaps not far off.</p>
         <p>Again good bye.—Be sure to let me know how you have <hi rend="italic">endured </hi>the winter.        And now</p>
         <p>             Believe me</p>
         <p>             Yours truly</p>
         <p>                     W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>3 weeks ago I recd. a notice fm. Govt. about your Premium; I spoke then to Grubb about it; G. said, I could hold on a while: yesterday I found it had been paid by you w. Chq. But, while I <hi rend="italic">am </hi>here, I will always <hi rend="italic">look out</hi>. W.C.</p>
         <p>Swan has engaged <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the Cabs, before hand—<hi rend="italic">one </hi>however was left which Capt. R. got for £2.2. On the polling day <hi rend="italic">this </hi>was also plastered with <hi rend="italic">Stuart’s</hi> papers, 4 colours!! Swan had given Cabby £5.5. to leave Russell!! —We got one new one, brand <hi rend="italic">new</hi>——</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>