<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1066">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1898 November 27: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1898-11-27">1898 November 27</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1898 November 27: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-924" place="foot" n="924"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Novr. 27<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. 1898.<lb/>(Sunday afternoon).</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Yours of 16<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. &amp; 20<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. reached me on 22<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>, &amp; I was <hi rend="italic">then</hi> inclined to reply at once—but delayed—reason, <hi rend="italic">anon</hi>. I thank you for it, a good long interesting &amp; <hi rend="italic">free</hi> letter—best I’ve had from you for many a day—shall I say? owing to your <hi rend="underline italic">heavy</hi> reader’s duty being <hi rend="italic">over</hi>?</p>
         <p>Several items in it, I will notice: first: I trust Hudson’s <hi rend="italic">foolish </hi>paper will <hi rend="italic">not </hi>become embalmed in “<hi rend="italic">Trans.</hi>” As you truly observe—he should stick to his <hi rend="italic">Lepidoptera</hi>—though <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, in published vol., a <hi rend="underline italic">great</hi> plagiarist (like <hi rend="italic">Tregear, the Smiths</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="italic">others</hi>) even to the <hi rend="italic">figures</hi>—pubd. in Engd. before H. was born, &amp; <hi rend="italic">copied </hi>by him: you have had a <hi rend="italic">great loss </hi>in Maskell.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Much pleased </hi>in finding you take so readily to alteration (<hi rend="italic">pro tem</hi>) in <hi rend="italic">situation</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">loss</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I think you will never see any more “copy” of my Dicty. in Govt. Office: time, I fear, is <hi rend="italic">past </hi>with me for that work. And, from yr. remarks as to the <hi rend="italic">rough </hi>Ms. in their <hi rend="italic">present </hi>state, you, <hi rend="italic">too</hi>, seem to be in ignorance concerning them. I like your mention of alphabetical arrangement: mine has always run, A, E, I, O, U, H, &amp;c—<hi rend="italic">our</hi> old Missiony. plan: and should I be able to copy &amp;c another &amp; following portion for press, I should follow it—from E–H., <hi rend="underline italic">incl</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Re</hi>. distribn. of “A” by Seddon: I think I told you, that Hill, travelling with J.D. O. in train, heard from O., that <hi rend="italic">he had recd. a copy</hi>. I have since seen H., I asked him <hi rend="italic">re </hi>same: H. says, “No mistake about it”. Still it seems strange, &amp; yet, not <hi rend="italic">more</hi> so, than the silence with <hi rend="italic">all </hi>Inst. Branches, Colleges, &amp; Pub. Libraries <hi rend="underline italic">in N.Z.</hi>: not one thanked, or ackngd., <hi rend="italic">save Gore</hi>!!—–</p>
         <p>Again, with you, I do not like part III “Maori Art”—I have just had my 3 copies (I subscribe for 4!) &amp; sent them off. You say, you were expecting Hamilton: I shall enclose a clipping, you can show him if he visits Wgn., <hi rend="italic">if not, return to me</hi>.—This (with others like it, I have seen, &amp; <hi rend="italic">more </hi>to come, hereafter,) I set down to H.—in his careless thoughtless, amassing of <hi rend="italic">all kinds</hi> &amp; conditions of (so-called) “Bibliography”:—a common vice, however, nowadays.</p>
         <p>Now to your Botany:—<lb/>1) “little creeping &amp; climbing plant”:—a sp. of<hi rend="italic">Muhlenbeckia</hi>: several sps. in N.Z., may be <hi rend="italic">M. complexa </hi>(?)—I have added a few—in <hi rend="italic">Trans.</hi> from time to time—espy. in vol.XXI.<lb/>2.) “Hemlock”:<hi rend="italic">very likely</hi>: but in <hi rend="italic">all </hi>plants of this order, <hi rend="underline italic">ripe fruit</hi> is absolutely <hi rend="italic">necessary</hi> to decide,—but H. may be pretty surely known by its main stem (2–3 ft. high) being <hi rend="italic">spotted</hi>: hence its trivial name of “<hi rend="italic">maculatum</hi>”.—<lb/>3.) “another<hi rend="italic">weed </hi>(?) w. minute yellow florets”:—is, I think, a sp. of <hi rend="italic">Melilotus</hi>, (closely allied generically to our <hi rend="italic">Trefoils</hi>): there are several species;—but <hi rend="italic">fruit</hi> required to be sure. (Vastly too much fuss, made there at Wgn. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>“weeds” by ignoramuses—experts (!!!) <hi rend="italic">wanting billets</hi>.)</p>
         <p>I sent <hi rend="italic">quickly </hi>your “Eng. Mechan. P.” to your Father—having no time to go into it: I noticed however (marked) the foolish (<hi rend="underline italic">ancient</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> not modern</hi>) Cornish tale: all globe-trotters—parsons, Doctors, &amp; blue-stockings—revel in such things! A-la-<hi rend="italic">3 crows</hi>! When at Woodville last, a lady called at Vicarage to see me, &amp; told me of a fine &amp; large portrait Lindauer was then painting for Auckland Exhibition— “of a <hi rend="underline italic">great</hi> Chief who had died there, &amp; whom the Govr. went to see while dying, &amp; on asking him, If he could get him anything in particular as food—the Chief replied “I should only like to have a few babies to eat”.!!! I told her, ’twas <hi rend="italic">a lie</hi>: I had heard a similar story (<hi rend="italic">read </hi>it, perhaps,) when a boy, of a Carib. <hi rend="italic">lady</hi> to a Governor.—this, &amp; <hi rend="italic">suchlike</hi>, suits Tregear, and the Smiths, John Wh., &amp; Hamilton, &amp; Manning, &amp; others of that ilk!</p>
         <p>The “Dr. Colenso” you mention, in connexion with Sir G. Grey, is a son of Bp. Natal: with whom G. was friendly, &amp;c. Natal left <hi rend="italic">two </hi>sons, one, <hi rend="italic">med. </hi>one <hi rend="italic">law</hi>, from this latter I heard, while laid up at Woodville.—–</p>
         <p>You are in a bit of error as to “Aust. Typg. Journal”—being “<hi rend="italic">dead</hi>”:—I have recd. a <hi rend="italic">second </hi>number from some unknown in Melbourne (?? Peacock)—<hi rend="italic">this</hi>, “October”, former “Sept.” monthly 3d—“Vol.XXIX. 340; containing <hi rend="italic">continuation </hi>of<hi rend="italic"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">my</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>Biography, being <hi rend="italic">yours</hi> (in Chicago) condensed a little, &amp; added to—w. several errors! clerical &amp; printer’s (?)—–</p>
         <p>Dr. H. has <hi rend="italic">refused </hi>me copies of Kirk’s ptd. sheets: saying, only <hi rend="italic">one</hi> was w. diffy. obtd. for Hooker.—I could wish <hi rend="italic">you</hi> had seen two letters I had late last year received <hi rend="italic">from K</hi>.—full of thanks, &amp;c, &amp;c, for <hi rend="italic">spns. then sent</hi>.—Dr. H. returned them—as I had asked him to do.</p>
         <p>Why not the play of “Potipher’s W.”?—after the wretched Ammergan one! &amp; still more wretched &amp; mendacious travesties of the fatuous Rituality! I have <hi rend="italic">several </hi>terrible accounts of these miscreants! I am much afraid, the Bps. are going to work too-late, &amp; half-heartedly. As I <hi rend="italic">said, </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">many</hi> years ago— “the Church” (like all other <hi rend="italic">true </hi>reforms) “must be reformed from <hi rend="italic">without</hi>” and <hi rend="italic">so </hi>of State reforms.—–</p>
         <p>Seeking (by note) some neat Xmas pictures for Home: Crerar sent me <hi rend="italic">two</hi>—1 by Craig, &amp; 1 from Xt.Ch. “with mountain, city &amp; forest”: this <hi rend="italic">latter </hi>small &amp; presentable—but, alas! w. <hi rend="italic">lies</hi> in type! “Our Wgn. city &amp;c “<hi rend="italic">founded </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">1836</hi>”. Craig’s is, <hi rend="underline italic">in part</hi>, good, but not well executed, &amp; too much of “<hi rend="italic">Browning </hi>St”, &amp; Hastings St. (2 views—full, &amp; more): one lot by Howie Brothers of N. is still worse:—and the (belauded!) Otago Xmas. Illusd.—is dreadful (to me!) filled w. atrocious lying reading &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">cuts</hi>. I shall (tho’ late) send 2–3 of the <hi rend="italic">Xt.Ch. ones</hi>: handy size, <hi rend="italic">striking out </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">’36</hi>. But I am <hi rend="italic">tired</hi> of all such— “<hi rend="underline italic">vanity</hi>”.</p>
         <p>And now for my <hi rend="italic">reason</hi>—deferring writing: I think I told you, I had received a memo. (Bill <hi rend="italic">only</hi>, 3 lines) from “Ptg. &amp; Staty. Deptmt.—ptg. “A”—₤82. Govt. adv. ₤20—₤<hi rend="italic">62</hi>—(heoi ano) I wrote at once (on 14<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>) to Mackay—<hi rend="italic">short</hi>—merely making <hi rend="italic">3 </hi>enquiries: viz. Does ₤82. <hi rend="italic">include</hi> Binding? Is ₤82 for <hi rend="italic">500 </hi>copies (as I had ordered) <hi rend="italic">or </hi>for <hi rend="italic">300</hi>, as “allocated” to me by Premier”:—and I fully expected an <hi rend="italic">early</hi> reply: none yet come! I know S. <hi rend="italic">has been </hi>absent from Wgn: I shall wait this week out, &amp; then jog M. If no reply:—I <hi rend="italic">greatly wish to have that settled</hi>, for, until it is, my hands are tied as to the <hi rend="italic">remaining</hi> copies—here w. me.</p>
         <p>A friend in London has sent me a copy of “Nature”, no 1503, Augt 1898, containing <hi rend="italic">Editors review</hi> (?) of “A.”—(? written by some one with a smattering of Maori, &amp; <hi rend="italic">no friend</hi>.) Yet, I should not forget,—<hi rend="italic">not knowing </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">all</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> the circumstances</hi>, neither the <hi rend="italic">later ones w. Seddon</hi>: but some amount of <hi rend="italic">blame</hi> is to my account, as “some scholars are fastidious, &amp;c, &amp;c”. Hill has long been desirous (so he says) of writing a letter, or paper, or something, re “A.”, but hitherto I have kept him back, wishing, <hi rend="italic">first</hi>, to have this old matter between S. &amp; self settled—that is, <hi rend="italic">my payment of the sum required</hi>. If you were here, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">free</hi>, I would much rather <hi rend="italic">you</hi> should write <hi rend="italic">some such </hi>paper. I have recd. a very nice &amp; full letter from a <hi rend="italic">literary</hi> man in London—who had <hi rend="italic">read</hi> “Preface” &amp; “Addendum”—and bemoaned such a <hi rend="italic">state</hi> of things—comparing w. America—which he evidently knows a deal.</p>
         <p>In replying by last Mail, I said, (referring to “Preface”—my saying, “Mr. S. had <hi rend="italic">consented</hi> to printing”) Yes: but ½ not told!—not till after <hi rend="italic">long</hi> solicitation by men of note, Sir R. Stout, Capt. Russell, and then, <hi rend="italic">only ₤20</hi>, towards it while I am now chgd. ₤62.—moreover, <hi rend="italic">that copy was ordered by Ballance &amp; Co—</hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">never paid for</hi>, not even my <hi rend="underline italic">sanctioned</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> outlay</hi>! Ed. “Nature”, says—such is or may be “<hi rend="underline italic">supplementary</hi> to Wms’, &amp; to Tregear’s”.—fortunately my <hi rend="italic">Ms</hi>. was in the Govt. <hi rend="italic">prison</hi> years <hi rend="underline italic">before</hi> their books were issued: but even <hi rend="italic">that</hi> seems to have been overlooked!—</p>
         <p>I have a fine flg. plant in garden—yesty. I wrote a <hi rend="italic">short</hi> note respg. it to <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>—If in H. tomorrow I will send you a copy.<note xml:id="ftn3-925" place="foot" n="925"> A rare plant. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi>, 28 November 1898.</note>—</p>
         <p>By last Mail I have a letter from Mr. Welsh—unexpected! he is scarcely any better—is <hi rend="italic">now</hi> in the hands of a “specialist”, a Dr. Burnett London, who says, “he <hi rend="italic">can cure</hi>, but requires, <hi rend="italic">12 mths. strict med. treatment no worry, </hi>and to <hi rend="italic">live well</hi>” W. is at, or near, Worcester, &amp; goes up to L. every month to see Dr.—–</p>
         <p>Have not seen any of our Clerics. (save Eccles, a <hi rend="italic">few</hi> minutes on Friday, who had come from Woodville w. the <hi rend="italic">schools</hi> to see the sea! &amp; return thither yesterday! too long, too dangerous, for little ones; &amp; <hi rend="italic">not</hi> absolutely required,)—have not been in town of late: few calling (<hi rend="italic">ka pai</hi>!) A Mr. Asher at Gore, nr. Invercargill, has had (or will have) a “<hi rend="italic">call</hi>” to St. Paul’s. Close is <hi rend="italic">said</hi> to be very ill.—Fannin is well, able to go daily to office. I have had a copy of the “Report of Comee. on Prohibn. Question to Bp. Xt.Ch.” sent to me: it is well worthy <hi rend="italic">your </hi>attention: I sent mine to Mr. Hill. Sutton &amp; “H.H.” (alias <hi rend="italic">Hill</hi>?) are fighting over the Woburn estate case: McDougall (of course) joining—in a slashing article—which <hi rend="italic">Hill </hi>can <hi rend="italic">not</hi> like.</p>
         <p>I have not yet attempted to walk to town: I still entertain hopes of doing so <hi rend="italic">before</hi> ’99 commences. This day is “<hi rend="italic">Advent Sy</hi>.”—the <hi rend="italic">beginning</hi> eccl. year with us—Ch. of Engd. Hitherto, of <hi rend="italic">late years</hi>, always <hi rend="italic">occupied</hi> at this season <hi rend="italic">in Ch: now</hi>—Sundays <hi rend="italic">here, alone, </hi>at house, and I think it will be much the same if I go inland—unless went 100 m. to Wdv., too <hi rend="italic">long</hi> a jy., and <hi rend="italic">too expensive</hi>. I see, Leslie, a Teacher in our school, is leaving for a <hi rend="italic">higher</hi> situation in Nelson prov. Do you know him? and, Did you know “<hi rend="italic">Myers</hi>”?—–</p>
         <p>I have lately had here 2 Visitors who reminded me of <hi rend="italic">olden times</hi>: 1 Ben. Warnes, who came to get some Acacia bark, wherewith to <hi rend="italic">tan </hi>a sail. Fortunately, for <hi rend="underline italic">him</hi>, my biggest old acacia had been blown down a short time ago, &amp; so Ben. went to work: it was a very hot day, and after a half-hour I went out again, to see how he was getting on, (Bob being down in town.) To my surprise I found him weilding the axe, coat off &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">hat off</hi>! &amp; his head without a single hair (like a bladder of lard)—fearing consequences, I got him with difficulty, to put on his hat: he observing he never wore a hat in the sun!—–<lb/>2, the other; Mrs Henry Nairn (wife of the<hi rend="italic">deaf</hi> brother N. who formerly lived at Wairoa), she had come to see me, &amp; left card (name only) when I was last inland &amp; <hi rend="italic">wanted much</hi> my opinion as to some curious <hi rend="italic">ancient </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">stone</hi> dykes (or defensive fortifications) near their Home close to Cape Colville: her <hi rend="italic">clear </hi>statement, took with me, &amp; pleased me much: I told her of some I had seen, particularly of that great dyke on the W. outlying flank of Ruahine (as given in my “Ruahine” Journey book, which I send to her—and <hi rend="italic">like</hi> that—in an out-of-the-way place, &amp;c, &amp;c.—–She sd. many had been to see it—Capt. Mair, &amp; others, but none to give any reason, or account for it—up &amp; down almost inaccessible cliffs &amp; the <hi rend="italic">work </hi>of men’s hands; I showed her several Maori things—plates, &amp;c—in all which she seemed <hi rend="italic">very deeply </hi>interested, &amp; knew somewhat, more, I think, than any Eng. lady before.</p>
         <p>On Friday I received from M. Lascelles a Fijian fruit—a <hi rend="italic">Granadilla</hi>—large fruit of a passion flower, weighing 3¼lb: first I had ever seen: I cut it this day (sending ⅓rd. to Mrs. Anderson’s <hi rend="italic">regular</hi> Sunday party) but have <hi rend="italic">not yet </hi>tasted it myself: 60–70 years ago it was cultivated in England in <hi rend="italic">hot houses</hi>.</p>
         <p>“Herald” has donned <hi rend="italic">new</hi> suit!—<hi rend="italic">new type</hi>—but <hi rend="italic">2 sizes too small</hi>—injurious to eyes, &amp; so I shall tell <hi rend="italic">Peter</hi>.</p>
         <p>Now I think I have given you <hi rend="italic">enow</hi>. I am keeping well—but <hi rend="underline italic">feeling age</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">at times </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">weak</hi>. I heartily wish you &amp; yours all good. I think I shall (D.V.) write to <hi rend="italic">you</hi> again—before <hi rend="italic">end</hi> of year—</p>
         <p>         and am always yours.                    W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">P.S. </hi>Monday, I send “Herald” of today—a good <hi rend="italic">finely written </hi>letter from <hi rend="italic">Sutton</hi>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
