<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0491">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1882 March 16: to Drummond</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL 88-103-1/13.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73880/">Drummond</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1882-03-16">1882 March 16</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1882 March 16: to Drummond<note xml:id="ftn3-131" place="foot" n="131"> ATL 88-103-1/13.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier Thursday March 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1882</p>
         <p>Mr John Drummond</p>
         <p>Dear Sir</p>
         <p>Late last night I received your latter of the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, also the little accompanying box of Spiders &amp;c.—As I should like to write you a letter by next mail to your place, I am obliged to do so <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, for I expect to have a visitor this evening, &amp; tomorrow our Council meets on various matters affecting us—when I hope Mr Macfarlane (with others) will be elected, and if so I shall try to write to him tomorrow evening—when I purpose, also, closing this letter.</p>
         <p>There is much in your letter that I like;—we agree, in the main, as to the too common evils attendant on Races. (I am happy to say that I never saw one in all my younger days;—never heard of one in the Whole County; and now, in populous West Cornwall, with its 10000’s of farmers, and in my native town, Penzance, in Mounts Bay, a flourishing sea-port with some 12, to 15,000 inhabitants—<hi rend="italic">Races</hi> are wholly unknown). Last night I had just finished going over the “D.T.” when your letter was brought in, and as I was struck with some of the <hi rend="italic">attendant belongings</hi> to the Races held <hi rend="italic">in the Courts</hi> in Australia, I send, you herewith the paper containing the same—and I also send a copy of the Dunedin “Echo” (which came to me with your letter)—as it contains come appropriate re­marks on a subject we corresponded about, a short time ago. And here I would just observe, 1, that I do <hi rend="italic">not</hi> agree in <hi rend="italic">all</hi> the “Echo” has in its columns,—very far from it;—2, that I have <hi rend="italic">not read</hi> Ingersolls works, (not one of them), and when portions have been given in the “Echo” <hi rend="italic">I have always passed them by.</hi> I do not like the spirit and tone in which he writes; but I much fear that such will increase—indeed it must (as I view things),—seeing the Churches, <hi rend="italic">will not</hi> (can not) reform themselves and put away <hi rend="italic">known &amp; proved</hi> error.</p>
         <p>Thanks, again, for the insects. A few among these <hi rend="italic">are desirable</hi> though none (perhaps) wholly new. Those I prize are, 1, the one with large wings. <hi rend="italic">I think you may get me more of this kind,</hi> do if possible, it may make a short paper. It mostly rests in the day, on shrubs &amp; herbage near marshes and water; unfortunately its horns are broken (it has but left one). I believe I have its <hi rend="italic">curious larva</hi> from Hardy (Hampden) and I hope to gain more of both;—2, next are the 2 <hi rend="italic">longlegged</hi> blackish spiders. <hi rend="italic">I should like also more of these</hi>; 3, the long horned Beetle is a fine fel­low, beautiful too, but described. By and by I hope closely to examine them all. The reason why your many legged little fellow was so long in dying, was (I think) owing to his hard coat—almost armour—of thick scales. And, here let me remind you, never put insects into <hi rend="italic">wool</hi> or <hi rend="italic">cotton</hi>;­—I have been some hours this morning endeavouring to <hi rend="italic">clear</hi> these few, &amp; have all but given it up;—the wool (&amp; cotton too) sticks to the hundreds of <hi rend="italic">hooks</hi> &amp; holds, of their horns, legs, toes, &amp;c, &amp;c,—so that, with the most careful handling, off comes a leg or two &amp;c, and I always think them by far the more brittle after having been in spirits &amp; <hi rend="italic">dried</hi>. Mr Tiffin sent me a rare lot, mostly too in pairs (m &amp; f), packed in wool; Oh! what a job! day after day. I wrote to <hi rend="italic">him</hi> about it directly, &amp; I thought I had you also.—Put wool, or cotton, a <hi rend="italic">very thin</hi> layer, below, but put a <hi rend="italic">thin</hi> bit of paper over the wool, or a <hi rend="italic">bit of old thin rag,</hi> and, also, <hi rend="italic">above</hi>; &amp;, if <hi rend="italic">many,</hi> also a bit of thin old rag <hi rend="italic">between</hi> the layers of insects, as their own horns and legs also catch, &amp; are liable to be broken off. I sent last week two <hi rend="italic">large</hi> match boxes of moths, to a clever Entomologist at Christchurch, who has described many in our Trans, and I assure you it was a job to pack them; in fine flannel, &amp; <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to touch each other!! I was glad when it was done;—</p>
         <p>I note your remarks concerning Vol XIII &amp; Miss Smith; No doubt you are correct,—but I had thought, or hoped otherwise.—</p>
         <p>I find I cannot yet go inland,—owing to a letter from the Govt last week to hand—I shall have to stay here a little longer to receive another, and reply, before I steer S.—</p>
         <p>Friday morning. Last night, or this morning, in bed, thinking on you &amp; your letter,—I decided to say a few more words to you, re what you have termed (from Ingersoll) “Moses mistakes”. I do not suppose Ingersoll to be much of a <hi rend="italic">Scholar</hi>—though, no doubt, a fluent popular writer or speaker, or both. But I wish to tell you—that <hi rend="italic">many learned</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">men</hi> have great doubts whether “Moses” ever wrote those books commonly called his. It is certain, I think, and now beyond dispute, that Leviticus &amp; Deuteronomy are of very <hi rend="italic">late date</hi>—written after the Jewish Captivity; and so the books of Chronicles (which are no true history at all); the creation (as in Genesis), the Deluge &amp;c., are wholly abandoned as Myths pertaining to an early age; Geological Palæontological, &amp; Ethnological Science, and modern discoveries have <hi rend="italic">wholly overthrown</hi> these. I have lately been reading a very learned work on Hebrew Mythology,—in which it is doubted if any such persons as Abm, Isaac, Jacob, &amp;c, <hi rend="italic">ever lived</hi> their names <hi rend="italic">meaning</hi> the several ancient Gods &amp;c. I tell you all this,—as there, where you are you are not likely to hear of these things. The <hi rend="italic">true</hi> ancient story of the Israelites leaving Egypt is (as I take it) a widely different one from this of their embellishing. But, be all these as they may, <hi rend="italic">Truth has nothing to fear</hi>.</p>
         <p>Two other works (among many) I have also lately been reading on the subject; one, Brughsch Beys History of Ancient Egypt, <hi rend="italic">derived from Ancient Monuments &amp; writings</hi> alone, (and all of these 3, &amp; 4,000 years old;) the other, portions of the <hi rend="italic">Great</hi> Jewish book called the <hi rend="italic">Talmud</hi>, now translated from the Hebrew (no doubt Jesus himself read that Book) as it was in use in the Jewish Schools before his time, &amp; also during his life; &amp; there are many <hi rend="italic">sayings therein</hi> which he (Jesus) made use of, (as stated in the N.T.) &amp; which have been set down to him as their author.—The Talmud is a kind of Commentary or opposition of the O.T., &amp; has ever been in the greatest request among the Jews; it contains several good things, but also, an unlimited lot of awful rubbish. I lent my book to Dr. Levy; &amp; we have had our talk over it. But I must stop this. I put too much confidence in <hi rend="italic">Cook</hi>, or in anyone; read, &amp; consider, &amp; follow what you believe to be the light—hoping, seeking, expecting, <hi rend="italic">more</hi> Light; be as the Pearl Diver, or the Diamond Seeker, or the Gold Digger,—ever seeking until <hi rend="italic">you find</hi>.</p>
         <p>Friday night. I now proceed to close my <hi rend="italic">long</hi> letter (you owe me one I think, something for letter writing? at all events I am <hi rend="italic">not</hi> in your debt on this head). We held our Council this afternoon—after long <hi rend="italic">waiting</hi> to make up four!! &amp; we elected Mr Macfarlane with others; I have just written to him. I am <hi rend="italic">tired</hi>; weather delightful these 2 days—too <hi rend="italic">good</hi> for “Races”; Town <hi rend="italic">wholly shut up</hi> looking rediculous (what would they say in England)? Glad you were <hi rend="italic">all well</hi>—may this find you so. Let me hear from you again; and with kind regards I am</p>
         <p>             Yours truly</p>
         <p>                     Wm Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>