<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0917">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1894 November 14: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1894-11-14">1894 November 14</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1894 November 14: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-709" place="foot" n="709"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Novr. 14/94</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I hope you have been so busy in your ptg. of.—of late, that you have had <hi rend="italic">no time</hi> to think of me—or, of my owing you letters. I have <hi rend="italic">been very busy</hi>, (am I yet out of the wood?) my last to you was on 24<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. ult.—from Dannevirke on my way back from Wdv. The next day I was attacked <hi rend="italic">suddenly </hi>w. severe cold in chest &amp; sore throat, both <hi rend="italic">very prevalent </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">there</hi> then: I was indeed very bad, I returned to Napier by degrees, reaching N. by Saty. nt.—then laid up 4–5 days (scarcely able to write by S.F. Mail), &amp; could not go out to see Lyndon, &amp; so that week passed: then I knew I had to prepare for Society Meetg. (promised), when lo! on Wednesday night, <hi rend="italic">late</hi> (7<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.), a visit from Chardn. of St. Andrew’s, for <hi rend="italic">me </hi>to take Mg. S. at St. Augustine’s on Sunday (11<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) &amp; Evg. S. at St. Andrew’s:—and <hi rend="italic">all this unexpected extra</hi>, owing to O. Dean rushing off to Xt.Ch. as a Teetotal Delegate!!! and I not yet recovd. from my cold (as <hi rend="italic">to voice</hi>). However, I consented, &amp; have been able to perform that duty—a pleasing time at the Port, large Congn., &amp; Bp’s. sister and daughter (Mrs Clarke) among them—who, after S., informed me, of their having on that same day recd. wire from Bp. of his save arrival in Persia.—</p>
         <p>Then, Monday night, our <hi rend="italic">last </hi>Meeting, audience <hi rend="italic">large, good, </hi>Dean, wife &amp; fy, Mr. Paterson, Hill wife &amp; daughter, Dr. Moore, Craig, Crerar, Jr., Fraser (Banker), <hi rend="italic">Sturm</hi> &amp; many others: I read my 2 p., &amp; showed spns. (Botanl.) mounted, &amp; showed my rough draft of paper no. 3—Botany, to be copied forthwith; then came the inevil. Tea, Coffee &amp; Cake; I (having before <hi rend="italic">endured</hi> the Stock’s supper—given by the Fox) this time brought a little <hi rend="italic">Wine</hi> &amp; took my glass before them all—who <hi rend="underline italic">looked</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> pleased</hi> (I told them jokingly of their former Fox’s supper, and of my pangs, &amp;c &amp;c—&amp; they <hi rend="italic">did laugh</hi>).—</p>
         <p>Then came the big portrait (only recd. on Saty. nt.) which they, <hi rend="italic">all hands</hi>, praised to the skies: I could not <hi rend="italic">well </hi>join—for <hi rend="underline italic">I don’t excatly like it</hi>: I said, in ansr. to many enquiries, “I cannot see my own face.” Hill made a splendid speech! the best I have ever heard from him: one fault only, laying the sweet <hi rend="italic">on me </hi>too <hi rend="underline italic">much</hi>. It is <hi rend="italic">fairly reported</hi> (say, ¼th.) in “D.T.”, and I send you a copy:<note xml:id="ftn3-710" place="foot" n="710">
               <hi rend="italic">Daily Telegraph</hi> 14 November 1894 p.3: “The portrait in oils of the Rev. W. Colenso F.R.S., executed to the order of the H.B. Philosophical Society by Herr Lindauer, is on view in Mr. Craig’s window, and during the day has attracted a great deal of public attention.”</note> I said a good deal more than there is given there—all ended well: only <hi rend="italic">President </hi>(&amp; Chn.) Humphries was in too <hi rend="italic">great a hurry</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">so </hi>cut it short, &amp; prevented Dean &amp; others from speaking, which they had <hi rend="italic">intended</hi>, &amp; since lamented. H. had told me <hi rend="italic">early</hi>—he did not like waiting after viii, and that he would not be out after x!!—The said portrait is now in Craig’s w. Yesterday I <hi rend="italic">worked hard </hi>to send my Direct Mail (omitted last S.F. one,) and last nt. &amp; this nt. I am on <hi rend="italic">local </hi>letters, answering, and am pretty well again—<hi rend="italic">Laus Deo</hi>.</p>
         <p>The advd. T.Sns. all sold a little above upset price (wh. I had purposely made very low.) and now I have <hi rend="italic">no</hi> T.Sns. left—&amp; am for ever, I trust, free from those atrociously high valuations &amp; payt. of Rates &amp; Taxes.—2 Sns., valued by Govt. @ ₤100. <hi rend="italic">each</hi>, I got after hard fighting reduced to ₤75. each, sold for ₤22. and ₤26:—of course the <hi rend="italic">low </hi>upset, &amp; <hi rend="italic">easy </hi>terms, brought a large attendance, &amp; it was a good sale, but I lost considy. on Wellesley Rd. Sections, which (to please Waterworth) cost me last yr. ₤<hi rend="italic">110</hi>. to fill in.—And now came Act II. of the play! letter on letter for <hi rend="italic">aid</hi>, also personal applicns.—some <hi rend="italic">refused</hi>, point blank”. One, &amp; the <hi rend="underline italic">first</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> personal</hi>, I will give—it was <hi rend="italic">early </hi>after sale, &amp; it was <hi rend="underline italic">yr</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. sister</hi>!! w. a book, ms. heading by McCully, for a Presbytn. Sy. Sch. house at Meeanee,—how much she reminded me of <hi rend="italic">you</hi>! we talked a little of <hi rend="italic">you</hi>:—F. &amp; M. all well, &amp; yr. sister in appy. <hi rend="underline italic">good spirits</hi>. Here it is still fine weather, &amp; fields &amp; gardens very dry; wind high yesterday mg., but <hi rend="italic">not </hi>like it was further S.—Eugene’s day is past—<hi rend="italic">where is he</hi>? I would like to put him in the stocks!!! </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Re</hi>, the sad “Wairarapa” affair, I say nothing: only I am grieved at the line taken by the Auckland lawyers, &amp; others, in <hi rend="italic">endeavouring </hi>to blacken the conduct of the Captain—poor fellow!</p>
         <p>I don’t know if you knew Fannin’s eldest daughter—she was married yesterday to J.D. Canning’s youngest son.—</p>
         <p>Our good friend Hill, had a <hi rend="italic">severe</hi> accident—it might have proved fatal;—he was riding by night along the public road, N. of Tolaga Bay, when he came <hi rend="italic">suddenly </hi>across wire from tel. post to the <hi rend="italic">other side </hi>of the road (acting as guys) wh. caught H. by neck, &amp; unhorsed over rump! &amp; he lay insensible some time! 10 m. from nearest house: horse, too, severely injured, obliged to leave it at Tolaga. He returned to N. last wk., &amp; has kept quiet at home: <hi rend="underline italic">he is much shaken</hi>. What a fool of an Engineer, or Linesman!!! I have promised to go to Bluff Hill on Friday evg. next;—shall (I hope) <hi rend="italic">walk </hi>back late.</p>
         <p>I noticed what you said in your last, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>your thoughts of <hi rend="italic">removing</hi> Pg.O.—I <hi rend="italic">cannot advise you in this matter</hi>—but, from this distance, &amp; bearing in mind the situations of Pg. Offices I have <hi rend="italic">known </hi>at Home—London &amp; Country—I should be <hi rend="italic">against it</hi> &amp; further think you should be in <hi rend="italic">cheaper </hi>houses—<hi rend="italic">wholly irrespective of situation</hi>. You <hi rend="italic">do not require</hi> a fine <hi rend="italic">front </hi>shop site.</p>
         <p>I hope this may find you &amp; yours all well. Mr. Paterson is to be at Waipawa on Sunday next; &amp; I have to take duty at Cathedral, &amp; at Augustine’s, on 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. Sy. in Decr.</p>
         <p>           And w. very kind regards, Believe me</p>
         <p>                                           Yours truly,    W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
