<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0319">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1876 May 2: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1876-05-02">1876 May 2</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1876 May 2: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-263" place="foot" n="263"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand,<lb/>May 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. 1876.</p>
         <p>A. Luff, Esq.,</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir</p>
         <p>At length I am writing to you again, having been obliged to omit the doing so last month (and so to all others in Engd.!)—I merely gave you a scrap then—just to let you know I was alive! Yours of Feby. 9<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. I duly received, &amp; was glad to know you were tiding over (or through) the Winter pretty well: I hope this may find you &amp; yours <hi rend="italic">very </hi>well.—I have a plenty to tell you—if I had but time,—but I have not just now. I have been out a-visiting all the far-off Cy. Schools in March &amp;April,—returning on 29<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> April to town, on purpose to write by this outgoing Mail,—on Saty. 6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. D.V. I return again to my work, which is (&amp; has been) heavy—&amp; winter is rapidly advancing. Mid. of March I went to Wairoa, by steamboat, &amp; was there bar-bound a <hi rend="italic">whole week</hi>!! we tried it, but sea was too high so returned; &amp;, when we did come out, – – – it <hi rend="italic">was no joke</hi>. Nevertheless it <hi rend="italic">was </hi>grand, and (to me) soul elevating, to see the little thing fighting her way. I would not go below to be battened down. Returning to N. at V p.m. I was <hi rend="italic">obliged</hi> to be off next morning &amp; go right awa’ to Danneverk, as the Teacher was resigning &amp; leaving next day: there, in the evening, after school, I had to walk in rain &amp; Sy. gale to Tamaki Hotel,—and, at last, return all the way to N. to make out Teacher’s Qty. vouchers—which done, off again to Porangahau, &amp; then (again) to <hi rend="italic">Norsewood</hi>, &amp;c &amp;c—I have yet to go to Hampden, Patangata, Tamumu, &amp;c—<hi rend="italic">inland</hi>: have been much hindered by wet &amp; gales, but have had pretty good health so far. I carry your <hi rend="italic">Neuraline </hi>w. me, but have <hi rend="italic">not yet </hi>used it.—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">First</hi>, however, to business.—I send you, enclosed, the Regd. Letter you sent me addd. to yourself (I still have <hi rend="italic">another </hi>letter of yours, so addressed,—perhaps the duplicate.) I also send a letter I recd. from Wgn., addd. to you,—on getting it (it was placed in my P.O. box) I wrote to Stevenson &amp; H., a few words, &amp; recd. their memo. to me, which I also enclose, w. my reply of yesterday on it.—</p>
         <p>On my return on Saty. last, I found a lot of letters awaiting me,—among them a P.S. note from Tabuteau, infg. me, of a small box per Capt. of “<hi rend="italic">Madeline</hi>,” contg. a <hi rend="italic">Watch</hi>—&amp; to appear, to pay duties, &amp;c. Well, I did so, yesty., &amp; opened it before him—of course it was your (2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>.) box of “<hi rend="italic">Neuraline</hi>”: stamped value “from 1/- to 2/6” &amp; now, Mr. T., how much duty? the proper Fraction of 1d. he cod. not assess—so I escaped! full thanks to <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">, </hi>nevertheless.)</p>
         <p>We have still more of sickness &amp; death than we could wish—young Butler (who was in Tel. off.) died of Diphtheria, 4 days ago; &amp; poor Mrs Locke is very dangy. ill with it, &amp; has been so for more than a month; Tylee is still holding out, but his legs are paralysed! Bp. Williams too, has been struck in paralysis of right hand &amp; side. Wm. Hunter is dead. <hi rend="italic">Two more </hi>of the Northe’s (unfortunate family (one being Mrs Taylor) are dead. Sim, the tailor, had a son drowned—bathing in the surf! Brandon has another son. Rechab Harding is marrd. to a Miss Miller (daur. of <hi rend="italic">M.J. </hi>Miller—who became, <hi rend="italic">they say</hi>, a Rechabite to catch Rechab.) John Harding &amp; wife are gone home. Margoliouth (&amp; Banner) is riding the <hi rend="italic">high</hi> horse: a splendid building made out of <hi rend="italic">old P.O. </hi>&amp; next to “Dy. Tel.” buildings,—now a large store, <hi rend="italic">Auction</hi> Mart, &amp;c &amp;c. Many new Houses are building all around—on hills,—White Road opp. Swan’s By., on beach near to Kelly’s <hi rend="italic">old house</hi>, Carlyle St, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.—Waipukurau is also going ahead. Trestrail is there w. a large <hi rend="italic">shop</hi>, but <hi rend="italic">what </hi>to do I don’t know. They (at W.) are going in for a Hall, a Hospital, and a <hi rend="italic">Ch.</hi> of Engld. (for this <hi rend="italic">latter</hi> all the money (about £1000.) has been sub.—I <hi rend="italic">refused</hi>. Drower gives £100.—(he has <hi rend="italic">not</hi> yet pd. for Taddy.—another paltry renewal!) Waipawa is also going a-head, in buildings—a new <hi rend="italic">Ch.</hi> of England—I have <hi rend="italic">refused</hi>, <hi rend="italic">until</hi> S.W. does me justice <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Ch. Res. boundaries. At my <hi rend="italic">great </hi>sale there (March 23)—a <hi rend="italic">large </hi>attendance, but <hi rend="italic">no one bid </hi>for <hi rend="italic">a single </hi>lot, &amp; Turley submitted <hi rend="italic">all</hi>. T. played a better part, as Auctr., than I thought he could: that affair has cost me (again) over <hi rend="italic">£30</hi>.! The paddock (wh. was Parkin’s) is let for 5 yrs. to Bennett @ £<hi rend="italic">30</hi>. Parkin’s old Hotel is greatly enlarged. <hi rend="italic">Fletcher</hi> is going to have one built near the Railway Station. Collins Land there, was cut up &amp; sold <hi rend="italic">very well.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>During my absence inland, my man, James, caught my <hi rend="italic">old </hi>servant Aldridge in the garden stealing figs! James had watched him, slinking along, &amp; climbing over the fence, near the big gate. No doubt A went for apples, w. his kit, but they were gathered the day before! poor wretch (he has been completely <hi rend="italic">done up</hi>, some time ago, &amp; self &amp; <hi rend="italic">wife</hi> taken to drinking heavily!)—he was very abject about it—<hi rend="italic">his being caught</hi>,—hope he will not come this way again. Young Torre is leaving us—his goods are to be sold this week; I delivd. your kind remembrance. They (Weber, &amp; Neal &amp; Close!) are still going on w. more ruinous excavation below me,—&amp; yesty. I saw Lascelles about it, who is to write to Blythe a L. letter.—Lascelles’ new offices are fine ones—<hi rend="italic">next to yours</hi>. Rees Watkins, &amp; Jarman, bought cash a <hi rend="italic">sound</hi> ¼ ac. near Grindell, &amp; Rees has put up a decent house at £250. Nice curbing, &amp;c, in <hi rend="italic">some </hi>streets and in <hi rend="italic">some</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">parts</hi>—as Neal &amp; Close’s &amp; McKay’s but <hi rend="italic">not</hi> Morrison’s! also Tuxford’s!! You must look into Papers for Harbour Works, &amp;c, &amp;c.—N.B. one advt. for 1,500,000 ft. of heart of totara!!—&amp; nearly 100,000 cubic yards of stone wall!—money to be borrowed on <hi rend="italic">future </hi>rates!! Turton is about leaving us for Dunedin: he went as far as Woodville thinking about investing there—but <hi rend="italic">does not like it</hi>: it costs too much to clear the Bush. I have had <hi rend="italic">anor. </hi>wall built—the <hi rend="italic">front</hi> of my T.S. 108 (66 feet)—from corner on Cl. Sq. up to the little “Bluff,” so that the gate is now blocked in, &amp; old Bridge taken away. This is just finished. Another house has been built <hi rend="italic">below</hi>—near C. Dolbel’s, on Weber’s Leasehold: in going down the little winding pathway you see lots of <hi rend="italic">little </hi>houses!! Did I tell you, in my last, that yg. Irvine, after returning home, had gained the Armed Constabulary? The “Graphics” you mention as having sent (includg. Xmas. one) never came, I suppose you only put on the 1d. stamp—my son also sent me some, but <hi rend="italic">non est</hi>. H.R.R. &amp; natives are having terrible long &amp; large meetings: <hi rend="italic">he </hi>has been residing in “Arihi’s house” on the hill at Te Aute. <hi rend="italic">They say</hi>, H.R.R. wants to have as much as he can of <hi rend="italic">that </hi>property secured to him (to raise money!)—and <hi rend="italic">Karaitiana</hi> I am told, has really signed a mortgage for £3000!! We had a <hi rend="italic">good lot </hi>of apples on our 2 small trees—the wet season (summer) suiting them. The old Masonic Hotel &amp; Billiard Room are <hi rend="italic">no more</hi>! the frame-work of new one is up, &amp; covers that ground.</p>
         <p>I am still thinking of visiting Engd.—&amp; that by C. Horn—to follow in your wake. My pair are going to have a young ’un in a few weeks—which won’t <hi rend="italic">add </hi>to <hi rend="italic">my </hi>comfort! The “Lady Bird” is now coming-in, &amp; she has the S.F. Mail,—so, I <hi rend="italic">may</hi> have to add to this. Tye (HRR’s old clerk) is out as Auctr. McGreevy has built a <hi rend="italic">large </hi>Horse (&amp; goods) Repository at Waipawa. P. Dolbel is just as ever—full of <hi rend="italic">promises</hi>! (<hi rend="italic">no realty</hi>).</p>
         <p rend="end">May 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>., (night)</p>
         <p>I now continue my letter. Yesterday night I recd. yours of March 8, &amp; was glad to see your well known hand writing, and to find, that you &amp; yours were getting through the winter <hi rend="italic">well</hi>. I went to town today &amp; saw Grubb (who is also writing to you), G. recommended me to send you the 2 receipts (L. Insurance) also the Govt. note—which I now do, enclosed. I noticed, today, that they were carrying the <hi rend="italic">curb</hi> along <hi rend="italic">past </hi>T. Morrison’s, I was glad of it. A large Brick Building, 40 x 20 within, &amp; raised upon a 2 ft. concrete plinth, is building for Oddfellows <hi rend="italic">behind</hi> present Hall,—contract (I believe) £450. It is a pity it is entirely hidden—<hi rend="italic">I never saw it before</hi>,—but then I have been absent. I shall send you <hi rend="italic">this day’s </hi>paper (among others) that you may see the <hi rend="italic">last </hi>bit of our M. Council; note, F. Sutton’s Bill; &amp; nearly £100. for the use of the Oddfellows’ Hall for 1 night to give a Pub. Ball to Governor &amp; this money (less a watch) went into Sutton’s pocket. You will also note the <hi rend="italic">row </hi>about price of gas. That “Herald” should complain I marvel at—they keep up the <hi rend="italic">extra </hi>charge for their paper. I fear Ellison getting the valuation will be a raising of Rates on <hi rend="italic">me</hi>—as well as others. Gollan is going to reside <hi rend="italic">in town</hi>. Sealy (it is said) is shortly “going home on his <hi rend="italic">pension,</hi>” <hi rend="italic">&amp;c. </hi>I dare say my letter to you of Jany. <hi rend="italic">per Suez</hi> M. will have turned up in due course. I am sorry for your sake, that you say,— “I have not yet settled down to anything”: I wish you had comfortably &amp; with <hi rend="italic">good prospects</hi>. You say, “You cod. not advise <hi rend="italic">me</hi> to come to Engd.—but you don’t give the <hi rend="italic">reasons</hi>. I do believe, that if you were here (or some one <hi rend="italic">like </hi>you, whom I could safely trust) I would go to England by end of this year: but, as <hi rend="italic">you know</hi>, my matters are so many, so scattered, &amp; <hi rend="italic">so small </hi>(singly) that I fear I must e’en remain to look after them. It is sd. that old Fitzherbert is to be the Speaker (a sop!)—&amp; Rolleston (no friend of mine) Minister of <hi rend="italic">Education</hi>! <hi rend="italic">under whom </hi>I would not be. I <hi rend="italic">cannot </hi>tell you about Pakowhai Estate—what it is. Tylee was got out, &amp; to town, today, in a trap; he may get round: I did not see him. Mrs Locke is worse: I fear, small hopes. I send you <hi rend="italic">in today’s </hi>paper, a photo. overlooking <hi rend="italic">the Bakery</hi>, &amp;c. &amp;c. below; the building appearing to right—is the Wesleyn. Ch. It was taken somewhere on my (<hi rend="italic">our</hi>) hill. The <hi rend="italic">old </hi>Masonic Hotel (Bar, &amp;c) looked so funny today: the new Bdg. is erected <hi rend="italic">over </hi>it, &amp; the lower room in this new one is higher than the roof of the old one!—it looks like a big Bird Cage! Money is getting scarce,—&amp; is rising in market. P. Dolbel has lately borrowed £<hi rend="italic">600.</hi>, on a mortg. from Bee to him of some 300 ac. of Mohaka land,—he has given £350. for the <hi rend="italic">mere goodwill </hi>of 3 yrs. lease, to run, of a small p. of land nr. him which was Gill’s (Masonic), &amp; on which there is a fair rent to be paid by P.D., &amp; a good purchg. cl. at end of 3 years! I fear he is getting crazy: he (of course) has not <hi rend="italic">got</hi> a 1d. for <hi rend="italic">me</hi>!! the remr. of his £600. goes in fencing &amp;c. on his Petane (Maori) Run. There is a nice piazza like verandah now from Mandy’s <hi rend="underline italic">old</hi> corner right up to Cobb’s Coach corner—save the one interval of Hague’s shop—the adjg. 2 small Bank premises—I have never heard a word since <hi rend="italic">re </hi>our old Clive friend Brown. We have plenty of <hi rend="italic">apples</hi> (kitchen sorts) this year in the garden, &amp; some pumpkins. Frost began early—at Wairoa &amp; inland, in March, &amp; several times since: the weather is very fine <hi rend="italic">just now</hi>. I forgot to say the Govr. was <hi rend="italic">here</hi>—overland from Auckland—I was <hi rend="italic">absent</hi> all his stay. Mr. O. &amp; Col. Whitm. took him about—inland as far as Kaikoura, by rail. He is a <hi rend="italic">very plain </hi>dressed man, &amp; is sd. to resemble (in app.) Dr English.—</p>
         <p>And now my dear Sir once more Farewell. I am sure I write <hi rend="italic">you</hi> a <hi rend="italic">terrible lot</hi>! Please remember me kindly to your family. I am glad to hear of your sons getting-on at school. Believe me, with much affection, to be yours truly, W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>No 3!) (supplement)                  May 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. 1876</p>
         <p>Although I have written so largely to <hi rend="italic">you</hi> I must give you more! In bed last night I thought on a few matters which you would like to hear. 1. McLean sold his Akitio run to a Mr J.Armstrong—“25,000 acres freehold, 1,200 sheep, some cattle, &amp;c—for ₤35,000.” It was announced in papers <hi rend="italic">as if </hi>done by Miller,—then a tel. from Wgn. that D. had himself sold it. 2. Col. Russell has sold Mangakuri, “21,000 ac. freehold, 18,000 sheep” to J.Williams, Karamu, for ₤50,750.” J.W. had <hi rend="italic">recently</hi> sold his Kereru property. 3. I did not tell you <hi rend="italic">all </hi>of P.Dolb’s. troubles. P. had given Miller 200 sheep for sale, &amp; M. sold them to Bridge; P. came for money, “call again tomorrow;” P. did so, grumbling at loss of time: on the morrow P. found that M. had deducted ₤25. (or 20)—being <hi rend="italic">overplus</hi> Run fee M. had lately paid to Sealy, on behalf of Gammel, who had taken P.D’s. Mohaka run). P. would not allow it, but was obliged to give in. Sealy <hi rend="italic">now </hi>says that such is the Law of all those Runs over there let on a kind of Lease—viz. to rise in rental every 4 years, or so. P. allows that he had told Gammell, that the Rent was only so much, as he had hitherto been assessed, throughout the whole term; and M. tells P. (<hi rend="italic">now</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">as Gammell’s </hi>agent) that poor P. will have to pay that heavy &amp; <hi rend="italic">increasing</hi> overplus every year of the term!! If so, then better P. had given it away. Bee, Kinross &amp; others there (5 or 6 in all) have paid the increase but under <hi rend="italic">protest</hi>. Sealy told them, If they did not he would immy. relet them! I suppose there will be a lawsuit about it. 4. I sent you a “D.Tel.,” which (some how,—conscience-struck, it <hi rend="italic">may </hi>be,) had suddenly taken my part—in 2 successive arts. <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Mao. Lexn.—Sir D. did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> like it, I know: Carlile wod. not (? could not) defend his Patrons. But <hi rend="italic">suddenly</hi> the “Evg. Post” (Wgn.) comes out with a most atrociously twisted article about <hi rend="italic">me </hi>&amp; it:—&amp; curiously enough <hi rend="italic">this appeared 2 days after Sir D’s. return to the City</hi>!! A friend there sent me a copy: I send this to my eldest son, I would I had another—but I think the “Evg.Post” is filed somewhere in London—if so, try &amp; see the number of March 6/76. The Parly. Paper contg. my offl. Letter was printed in Jany. &amp; known in Wellgn. early in Feby., the “Dy.Tel.” (&amp; “Weekly Mercury,” too,) commented on it <hi rend="italic">fully</hi>,—so that there is no <hi rend="italic">apparent </hi>reason why the “Post” should have been so long silent—&amp; at last, &amp; at <hi rend="italic">that</hi> peculiar time, break out: it seems to me as if manufactured, &amp; <hi rend="italic">made to order.</hi>—I have not since heard from D. although he promised to write to me <hi rend="italic">about it</hi> (in reply to mine to him, Official, of Feby. 16)—I don’t think he (or they) <hi rend="italic">can </hi>reply. The publicn. of that Parly. Paper has done me (or my cause) a world of good. I don’t think I shall ever again have that Lexn. matter hurled (or hinted) at me. I got copies of the Parly. Paper (buying them at 3d. ea.) &amp; sent them round to <hi rend="italic">several</hi>—in N.Z. Judge Johnston, Sir G. Grey, Sir D. Bell, Dr. Haast, Macandrew, &amp; many others;—some old settlers here—have said to me, “How could you remain so quiet?”—only by <hi rend="italic">knowing</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">feeling</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">I was </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">right</hi>: <hi rend="underline italic">that</hi> sustained me.—</p>
         <p>And now, let me add, to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, that I have always thought you were somehow <hi rend="italic">against </hi>me in this matter (I mean, did not think or agree with me,—or the Work)—at all events, I have fought my battle single handed, &amp; <hi rend="italic">no help</hi> from friends and acquaintances. <hi rend="italic">To </hi>
            <hi rend="smallcaps italic">God</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> be alone the praise</hi>! Farewell,</p>
         <p>             Yours faithfully</p>
         <p>                             W. Colenso</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>