<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0915">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1894 November 4: to William Colenso</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL Ms-papers-10535-1.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1894-11-04">1894 November 4</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1894 November 4: to William Colenso<note xml:id="ftn3-705" place="foot" n="705"> ATL Ms-papers-10535-1.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand,<lb/>November 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>./94.</p>
         <p>My dear Nephew William,</p>
         <p>I cannot tell you how glad I was yesterday on receiving your letter of Septr. 16<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.―in prompt reply to mine; and this feeling of pleasure was increased when I read it and noted all your manly &amp; good expressions. Of course, had I known that you were so carefully economizing that £5. I sent you for poor Ellen, I should have been easier in mind during this last year of time.―Now, then to business: (1.) partly owing to my <hi rend="italic">not</hi> hearing from you, and to the exigencies of the case―want on <hi rend="italic">her</hi> side, and extreme old age on <hi rend="italic">mine</hi>, and your <hi rend="italic">own </hi>constant and pressing business engagements―I had already mentioned the matter to Sarah (and I think also to Rd.), and Sarah agreed to act: and as I have to remit <hi rend="italic">her </hi>money (once more for that everlasting drain Glen Trewithen) by this outgoing Mail, I shall just make <hi rend="italic">one </hi>draft serve. (2.) I shall send £<hi rend="underline italic">100</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. For Ellen</hi>, but how <hi rend="italic">the better </hi>to use it for her benefit, <hi rend="italic">I leave entirely to you and to your sister</hi>. I do not know Ellen’s <hi rend="italic">state </hi>of health, or, if she could well be <hi rend="italic">trusted</hi> with money to keep, or, her <hi rend="italic">habits</hi>: but one thing I do know (from you), that she, poor soul! Has only £16. a year―on which to exist―or starve. Now you there on the spot, knowing her and her peculiar ways and requirements, must so use this sum as most conducive to her wants: either (say) by placing it in the Bank (that is the remainder) after deducting £10. For a year for her use,―or by investing this £<hi rend="italic">100</hi>. As you kindly did her £<hi rend="italic">200</hi>. Moreover, I would also send Home another £<hi rend="italic">100</hi>. If <hi rend="underline italic">needed</hi>, to make her last days a little more tranquil &amp; comfortable. So do you &amp; your sister Sarah put your two heads to work, and <hi rend="italic">act quickly, in this matter</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">settle it</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="italic">let me know</hi>. Fortunately, I have the money at command just now! For only 3 days ago I sold at Auction my Town Sections (of which I think, I wrote to you in my last,) as these were eating themselves up in <hi rend="italic">heavy</hi> Rates &amp; Taxes ever increasing!! I shall send you a Paper containing their sale;<note xml:id="ftn3-706" place="foot" n="706"> WC: 13th. Not <hi rend="italic">now</hi>―none handy, and I a long way from shops in town.</note> and, as you may readily suppose, I have already <hi rend="italic">lots</hi> of applications for aid! Another fortunate circumstance, (seeing our monthly S.F. Mail only left us 3 days ago,) is, this of a Direct Mail leaving next week, which is timed to reach England on Xmas. Day.</p>
         <p>I am much pleased, my dear nephew, in knowing again &amp; from <hi rend="italic">you</hi> (as I have often heard from others) of your doing so well in your business, also your brother Rd. in connection with you: and of your being again elected to your Borough Council; of your being an active member of the two Libraries of <hi rend="italic">our </hi>old town, and of your bringing up <hi rend="italic">one </hi>of your sons to your own trade &amp; calling; <hi rend="italic">this</hi> is as it should be, though I never approved of my brother (your Father) bringing up so <hi rend="italic">many</hi> of his sons to his own trade.―</p>
         <p>I really pity Preby. Hedgeland, (we corresponded for a short time a few years ago,)―but, I fear, he has to thank himself for much that has taken place,―he should have shown more firmness, more consistency, <hi rend="underline italic">early</hi>, and kept that wretched Jew curate in his proper place, and not allowed the innovation of “Cassocks”. There is vastly too much of High Church and Ritualism among us here, (though far worse in some other places,) and I set myself resolutely against it, now, as I <hi rend="italic">ever did</hi>, and against all “fads”―especially in matters of Religion—Mormons, Adventists, Spiritualists, Christadelphians, Salvation-Army Mole, &amp; Theosophists,—of this <hi rend="italic">last </hi>we have at the present time their Johanna-Southcote-like prophetess, <hi rend="italic">Mother Besant</hi>, who arrived in Napier yesterday and held forth last night in the theatre. No doubt, your Bishop is <hi rend="italic">too High</hi> Church, (I have long seen that in the papers,) such fantastic dreams are more than ever out of place in <hi rend="italic">Cornwall</hi>; when will our Church of England awake to her duty!—I was much pleased 2 months back, in reading in the “Rock” Newspaper a letter from the Bishop of Worcester, <hi rend="italic">against</hi> that miserable Hymn Book (“Ancient &amp; Modern,”)—stating, it was the cause of Romanism going ahead in England. I lectured against its use, a few years ago, here, saying, it should be pub licly <hi rend="italic">burnt</hi> here in Clive Square. There are a few good Hymns in it, just enough to deceive the unwary—jam and sugar for the enemy’s false teaching. This century has indeed been the prolific age of novel Religious sects &amp; parties! How many do I recollect springing!! from the sad Puseyite &amp; Tractarian movement at Oxford, before I left England, (which I, <hi rend="italic">then</hi>, called, “the Blight,” &amp; “the curse” of our dear old Church of England,)—the great apostate movement of Rome, with her false additions to the old creeds,—and the low upstart lying delusions of the Mormons, Adventists, and miserable (and <hi rend="underline italic">falsely</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> called</hi>) “Salvation” Army. I have preached against them all; but the wonder with me, is, that the several Christian Churches do <hi rend="italic">not</hi> (apparently) <hi rend="italic">see </hi>this—that their <hi rend="italic">errors </hi>and <hi rend="italic">false </hi>teachings are clearly truly and frequently shown in the N. Test. by Jesus himself from the very beginninmg of his teaching (<hi rend="italic">Matt</hi>. VII. 13–23), and by his Apostles; and the Church <hi rend="italic">in particular</hi> is informed, that such would surely come to pass, and be as signs of the end! (1 Tim. IV. 1–5: 2 Tim. III. 1–6.)</p>
         <p>I am pleased in hearing of your “Sailor-boy” having just passed his Mate’s Examination and gained his Certificate: may he succeed in his onward progress, &amp; gain the top of the tree: and <hi rend="italic">may our Heavenly Father ever preserve him!—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Here</hi>, only a few days ago, we have been awfuly excited—and, also, the whole Colony of N.Z. together with the neighbouring ones,—at a dreadful shipwreck, in fine weather too!! by which more than 100 miserably perished! one of the worst (if not the very worst) N.Z. has yet known: I send you a paper containing it.<note xml:id="ftn3-707" place="foot" n="707"> The steamer <hi rend="italic">Wairarapa</hi> struck a reef off Great Barrier Island with the loss of 134 lives.</note>—</p>
         <p>I am keeping fairly well, though lately for a whole week I was suffering much from a very severe cold). Sometimes I take service in one of our Churches—always ready, as an “emergency man.” On the 14<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. ult., in the absence of the Dean, I took Mg.S. in the Cathedral—a very large Congregation: same day, Evg.S. in St. Augustine’s, in this town: on 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. at Woodville—100 miles S.,—and on Advent Sunday I have to take duty again in the Cathedral: May <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> enable me for it! <hi rend="italic">Such work, is, </hi>as ever, <hi rend="underline italic">my</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">chief joy</hi>. I am still able to take 2 full Ch. Services<hi rend="italic"> </hi>in the day, and I <hi rend="italic">cannot </hi>preach <hi rend="underline italic">short</hi> Sermons.</p>
         <p>One short sentence in your letter I don’t understand: you say,— “If I dare to give you any advice I would say, by all means keep that buggy, horse and boy, it would save your legs &amp; feet much, so have them &amp; enjoy them as you deserve.” Wherever did you pick up that? I <hi rend="italic">never</hi> had a buggy, nor for 20 years a horse. I should like well enough to have such as you mention, but I cannot afford it—too much outlay for my poor <hi rend="underline italic">self</hi>! Besides my residence here is on a high craggy hill, not easily accessible to a buggy: Willie can explain the locality.—–</p>
         <p rend="end">(Novr. 10<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>I now proceed to close—as I have to be very busy tomorrow &amp; next day. Since writing above I am unexpectedly called to take 2 full Church Services <hi rend="italic">tomorrow</hi>, 11<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst., the Minister of St Andrew’s (the port Ch.) having gone suddenly to Christchurch: so I shall be there in the evening, &amp; at St. Augustine’s here in town, in the morning.—And on Monday night, 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., I have to read 3 papers and exhibit specimens.—–</p>
         <p>Looking over what I have rather loosely written about Churches and Sects and parties,—I think I should add (to prevent any misconception) that I do not “hail” as belonging to the so-called <hi rend="italic">Low </hi>Church or evangelical party), neither indeed to the <hi rend="italic">High</hi> Church (as it is commonly understood): and if I must name <hi rend="italic">one</hi>, as in some measure agreeing with me, it would be the <hi rend="italic">Broad</hi>, or Reasonable Church party—which I believe to be <hi rend="italic">the Church</hi> of the future:—as it certainly was originally <hi rend="italic">the true </hi>one, before the sad increase of human traditions, superstitution, &amp; man’s garnish. the word of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>—of Jesus—and of the Apostles, in <hi rend="italic">all their plainness</hi>, are my joy, my treasure, my <hi rend="italic">all</hi>: and so I preach, <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> helping me.—–</p>
         <p>The weather is still very fine, and I am keeping well. <hi rend="italic">I do not wish </hi>for Ellen to <hi rend="italic">know</hi> who succours her—at the same time, I leave it to you &amp; S. to let her know—or not.—</p>
         <p>And with an old man’s Love to you, my dear nephew, &amp; to your wife &amp; family, Believe me, Yours Affecty.</p>
         <p>                                                                   W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>