<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0816">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 February 10: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-02-10">1892 February 10</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 February 10: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-567" place="foot" n="567"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke<lb/>Wednesday<lb/>10/II/92</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>Being (almost) <hi rend="italic">idle</hi>, and having <hi rend="italic">you </hi>much—<hi rend="italic">very much</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">increasingly</hi> in mind: I will <hi rend="italic">begin</hi> a letter to you, to be closed &amp; posted at end of week.</p>
         <p>First: I hardly know how to express myself fully &amp; clearly <hi rend="italic">re </hi>my apparent running away from you! When, too, I had myself proposed to you what you so kindly &amp; readily accepted. And, then, too, my wretched scrawl! to let you know of the vitication!! That memo. came about in this way. I did not hear fully, nor agree to go to Woodv. until <hi rend="italic">late </hi>on Thursday night, when Robertshawe here w. me we talked over the vitication, &amp; he waited to take notes to P.O. (at that late hour XI) so as they should go, both N. &amp; S., by early mg. <hi rend="italic">mails</hi>.—The notes to Woodville to Ch. officers, &amp; to Haggen <hi rend="italic">re </hi>advtg., were written at <hi rend="italic">last </hi>hour, having <hi rend="italic">left</hi> &amp; gone N.—&amp; <hi rend="italic">we</hi> only knew of that from <hi rend="italic">3 lines </hi>in the “Wdv. Exr.” of Wednesday (to hand on Thursday) and R. had been expecting to hear from, or see C. (if he should leave), &amp; also to hear from the Bishop, who was <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, at Wdv, on Friday aftn. &amp; nt., but R. did not hear from either, &amp; so, as a last <hi rend="italic">resource </hi>(rather than to shut up the Eng. Ch. there) this old m. agreed to go &amp; to do his best—<hi rend="underline italic">looking up</hi>.—Your thoughtful note of 5<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>change in your movements, which I recd. <hi rend="italic">here</hi> before I left (the rainy mg. keeping me until afternoon) eased my mind consy., my only fear being that possibly (owing to weather, &amp;c.) your good cousin R.—might not get my letter, to be of any service.—I may mention, that I wished R. to go to Wdv., and I to take (say) 1 S. <hi rend="italic">here </hi>in his Ch. (1 only, owing to weakness) but he would not; he too is still unwell from that horrid Infl.—weak like myself, but <hi rend="italic">stronger </hi>far than I am.——</p>
         <p>I had also to send off instanter to Napier, to my man—for a decent Sunday coat &amp; for Ch. garments, as, when I came away, I never intended doing any Ch. work.—I went to Wdv. &amp; was enabled to get thro’ the <hi rend="italic">2 Ss</hi>., the <hi rend="italic">Evg</hi>. one trying my powers, much. Congns. however good &amp; glad to see me again, after 15 months, from last visit. And now I (<hi rend="italic">we</hi>) don’t know who will be there Ministering <hi rend="italic">next</hi> Sy:—probably this o. m. will have to go again!——</p>
         <p>I thank God, my dear friend, that I <hi rend="italic">am</hi> able to say, <hi rend="italic">I am better than I was</hi>, tho’ the sad <hi rend="italic">remains</hi> of this weakness <hi rend="italic">continues</hi>, &amp; cough (<hi rend="italic">at times</hi>) is strong.—Some, whom I have seen, here &amp; there, quite despair of ever shaking off the distressing weakness!——</p>
         <p>Thanks for your so kindly remembering me (in the midst, too, of your heavy constant labours) with a copy of your old “Times” of Nov/73!—nearly 20 years ago!—&amp; now, last night in “D.T.”, Tom T. has thrown down the gauntlet, in his letter re coming election. May he be bitterly defeated!</p>
         <p>On my return hither, on Monday night, I was surprised &amp; pleased to find 3 letters from N. One, &amp; a <hi rend="italic">long </hi>one, being from Hill—for which (as I take it) I am, in the main, indebted to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>. H. tells me of your visit, &amp; <hi rend="italic">re </hi>“poetical” scrap, (which, please, <hi rend="underline italic">do not</hi> pub. in “Typo,” &amp;c.) and then H. goes on to say (<hi rend="italic">I quote verbatim</hi>),</p>
         <p>“Mr. H. &amp; I had a <hi rend="italic">serious </hi>talk on a certain matter concerning yourself: and it was arranged, that I should speak to you on the subject should an opportunity offer itself.”—</p>
         <p>Of course, ths strange &amp; strong (?) matter has quite stirred me up: and I must beg of <hi rend="italic">you</hi> (as my most intimate &amp; confidential friend) <hi rend="italic">to let me know </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">early</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">fully</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> all about it</hi>. You can write me (if you should wish to do so) a <hi rend="italic">priv</hi>. &amp; <hi rend="italic">confidential</hi> note <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the same. <hi rend="italic">Do not disappoint me</hi>. I have already written to H., but then I am not sure of finding him at N. &amp; <hi rend="italic">not </hi>busy, and <hi rend="italic">willing </hi>to <hi rend="italic">write same</hi>: I cannot appeal to him, as I <hi rend="italic">can </hi>&amp; do to <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>.——</p>
         <p>Among many papers &amp; circulars &amp; catalogues from Engd. by last week’s mail, is one from an unknown Bookseller named Arnold, which I shall post to you w. this. He has marked the p. referring to <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, tho’ mainly to Tregear’s Dy., I shall send to A., on my arrival at N., a copy of that Py. Paper you reprinted for me, which may serve to open his eyes to <hi rend="italic">that date</hi>. And I may <hi rend="italic">tell </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>, that I have been thinking of drawing up a kind of <hi rend="italic">No 2 </hi>statement, showing, briefly, how I have <hi rend="italic">since </hi>been “served-out” by Ballance &amp; Co. No doubt I should do this had <hi rend="italic">you remained</hi>. Tell me—when you next write—<hi rend="italic">what you think of it</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I shall also return your “Morris,” with <hi rend="italic">many thanks</hi>: I have ventured to note (on 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi> blank p.) 2 bits that caught my eye. Also, at p.98, bottom—<lb/>    “Strange whispers, rise from the surrounding deep,<lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Like that weird ocean sound<lb/>      Borne in still summer night</hi>on weary watching ears.”<lb/>as quite agreeing to what I wrote, &amp; you published<hi rend="italic">re </hi>our H. Bay seas!—You can <hi rend="italic">easily</hi> rub out my venturesome wee comments. But why should I have only selected 2–3 bits? There is <hi rend="italic">much </hi>in the vol. I <hi rend="italic">like</hi>—as “The Wanderer”—“the flight of Lady Birds,” &amp;c, &amp;c.</p>
         <p>Since writing p.5 I have drafted a letter to Arnold, which I enclose for your information, &amp; <hi rend="italic">correction wherever you deem such to be necessary</hi>: as, no doubt, in days to come, <hi rend="italic">you</hi> may have something <hi rend="italic">more </hi>to say in defence of this O. M. after he is gone—as you have already done: <hi rend="italic">do not </hi>send back the catalogue.—</p>
         <p>I suppose you are once more safe &amp; <hi rend="italic">well</hi> w. your dear family in Boulcott St., I hope so,—and got over your heavy job—viz. this side of it, &amp; your brother assiduously helping you: I hope to hear of your little son Victor being much better. How glad the dear boy must have been to <hi rend="italic">hear </hi>your voice &amp; to <hi rend="italic">see </hi>your face &amp; <hi rend="italic">gain </hi>the father’s <hi rend="italic">kiss</hi>.</p>
         <p>I hope you are quite in time to be at the meetg. of the “Philosophical”, &amp; that you may be able to attend it, &amp; to tell me all about it—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> my paper. And, should you have the opportunity to enq. of Didsbury <hi rend="italic">re </hi>vols. VI &amp; VII of Jno. Whites work—please do so: also, if I can get them from D.</p>
         <p>An earthq. seems to have been pretty generally felt yesty. mg., but not by me nor by anyone <hi rend="italic">here</hi> in Dvk. that I know. The rain this afternoon for nearly an hour was prodigious! thick &amp; heavy, such drops! I have scarcely ever witnessed such—the street was soon a river from kerb to kerb: old Dvk. residents say, they had never seen such rain here before, wind W.</p>
         <p>Strange! no advt. in H.B.p. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>annual Mtg. of “Institute”—which should have been held on 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi> inst, &amp; now 2 Mondays have passed: Hill, too, tho’ he writes of the Inst. (<hi rend="italic">past</hi>), does not allude to it.—I sent Gore my subsn. 10 days ago, but no rect. yet to hand: perhaps he is waiting for his Mtg. to come off. Bp. Stuart, I find, had to return to N. on Monday on account of his siter’s <hi rend="italic">serious </hi>illness; I fear for her, as she is aged &amp; not strong, &amp; she was laid up w. Influenza before Xmas. Another saddening letter from my eldest son <hi rend="italic">re </hi>his little daughter. I am still keeping my room—in slippers!—No “Whitakers Almk.” yet from Craig!!</p>
         <p>12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. I now conclude my long letter.—Weather this mg. delightful—blue sky &amp; a refreshing coolness after the late heavy rains! Creation keeping Jubilee!—–Yesty. a letter from Bp. requesting me to take Ch. duty at Wdv. for the remaining 3 Sundays of this mo., or the Ch. must be closed: I have consented to do so—tho’ my return T. expires on 20<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. &amp; by it I must lose 16/6!—I suppose you will have seen in p., ere this reaches you, the <hi rend="italic">sudden </hi>death of Dr. de Lisle’s wife—it is a sad blow &amp; loss too to him: I never knew her, but Dr. McAllum, now here, speaks very highly of her.<note xml:id="ftn3-568" place="foot" n="568"> In December 1896 Dr de Lisle asked Colenso to stand godfather to his and his new wife’s baby son (see below).</note> Younghusband (Robjohns partner) now here, tells me of his having seen my name lately quoted as an authority <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the stinging powers of our big NZ nettle—<hi rend="italic">Urtica ferox</hi>! some persons exploring in the Midland Railway line had also made its acquaintance. I am, of course, here for <hi rend="italic">all Feby. </hi>so if you write address <hi rend="italic">here</hi>. I am improving in health, but <hi rend="italic">still weak</hi> w. anomalous shifting light pains in the thorax. Good bye. Kindest regards &amp; <hi rend="italic">Best wishes </hi>Yours affy. W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
