<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0753">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1890 November 15: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0495.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1890-11-15">1890 November 15</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1890 November 15: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-494" place="foot" n="494"> ATL qMS-0495.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier<lb/>Saturday night<lb/>Novr. 15/90.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Although I have written to you so recently (on 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.), &amp; although I have several letters unanswered, I feel greatly inclined to <hi rend="italic">commence </hi>a letter to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>—because <hi rend="italic">I have you so much in mind.—–</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Last night I went to our adjd. Inst. meeting, &amp; although it was VIII when I got there—no others in the room but Dr. Sp., &amp; the <hi rend="italic">new </hi>Secy. (I have <hi rend="italic">since </hi>learnt his n. is Geo. White), and a bald-headed m., who was also there on My. night, &amp; who <hi rend="italic">may </hi>be Ringland. (I should mention that Dr. Sp. called here on me in the aftn., and told me the reason of his not turning-up on last My. nt. was, that he had a patient in his house—that Mrs. Sp. was away at the Birch’s (Patea), &amp; his daughter at the concert.) Well, we waited uneasily until VIII.10, when 4 ladies came in, (this day, on enqy., I found they were Mrs Begg, Miss Weber, Miss Browning (who was also there on Monday nt.) and ? Miss Begg; and a few min. later, Carlile, also Mrs Hill: and so the play commenced: G.W. read the Minutes of last meetg. <hi rend="italic">(very scanty!)</hi> then I began Paper No 1—“Bush Jottings”—it took some time &amp; was (I think) pleasing to the audience: while reading, Dr &amp; Mrs Moore, Craig &amp; wife, &amp; 2 others, unknown came in; that ended (&amp; <hi rend="italic">nothing said</hi>—no-one cared to speak),—I took up No 2—but <hi rend="italic">not to read</hi>—merely say a few words—it was “Enum. of Fungi”, I had sent to Kew in March last, of which <hi rend="italic">a portion</hi> had been determined, &amp;c, by Dr Cooke—Contg. 132 species <hi rend="italic">new to N.Z.Flora.</hi> That over, G.W. commenced Taylor White’s interminable Ms. (—paper <hi rend="italic">folio</hi> flp.!!!) on Rats &amp; mice! Dr. M. &amp; Lady left at once and I think I am right in saying, we all wished the said Ms. to———. Never did I sit for ½ hour or 40 m. to hear such stuff! about Rats &amp; M. <hi rend="italic">at Home</hi>—in <hi rend="italic">old</hi> times—their species then depredations there, &amp; here,—&amp; then about his so-called <hi rend="italic">Maori</hi> rats, 3 mounted on table (which Large <hi rend="italic">this mg.</hi> told me had cost us <hi rend="italic">£1</hi>.) However, it <hi rend="italic">ended</hi>! (I am sure that G.W. inwardly rejoiced.) Dr. S.—who never spoke the whole evening,—looked at me to say something, &amp; I did so—prefacing, “I wished T.W. was present, that <hi rend="sup">6</hi>/<hi rend="sub">8</hi>ths. of the <hi rend="italic">said</hi> paper was copied, &amp;c, &amp; that the papers <hi rend="italic">required </hi>were to be<hi rend="italic">original</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>&amp;c &amp;c<hi rend="italic">—</hi>Then I showed several interesting plants—from Mt Cook, S. Island, &amp; from Bush—which relieved our dreariness, &amp; mightily pleased the ladies—only I had myself to do <hi rend="italic">all</hi> the showings &amp;c.—Lawrence (formerly of Homewood) <hi rend="italic">also there</hi>, so Craig told me <hi rend="italic">today</hi>—but I did not know him—hair <hi rend="italic">so white</hi> &amp; wearing specs.!!—Large was absent at Te Aute, on valuation, &amp; could <hi rend="italic">not </hi>“<hi rend="italic">wire</hi>”;<hi rend="italic"> </hi>he was (or seemed to be) vexed, at his being absent: his daughter was also there.—McDougall came in at close.</p>
         <p>On 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I got my looked-for letter from the Bp., written at Wairoa on Monday: he had a sad journey thither: on leaving on Thursday he was overtaken w. rain at Aropawa, had to <hi rend="italic">lead</hi> his horse! owing to slipperiness—&amp; wet through plod his weary way to Mohaka!!—</p>
         <p>I leave here (D.V.) on Thursday next for Dvk. (on Saty. to Wdv. for Ch. S. there on Sunday, &amp; as I have promised to be at the Presbytn. Ch. annual gathg. shall be <hi rend="italic">there</hi> until end of that week—but do you address as before <hi rend="italic">to Dvk.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>And now <hi rend="italic">goodnight</hi>! for it is XI hour.——–</p>
         <p>Wedy. 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> IV.p.m. I now go on with my letter: it would have been finished &amp; posted but I have had a <hi rend="italic">deal to do</hi>, however I have (once more!) finished packing, &amp;c &amp;c, (both for leaving, &amp; for carrying, &amp; also, papers &amp; books for Engd. per mail next wk.!) I went to Parkinson’s Ch. on Sy. Evg., &amp; was surprised to see Rev. <hi rend="italic">O. Dean </hi>take service,—but My. “Herald” gave the reason the Dean, Hovell, having been suddenly taken ill &amp; Dr. called in. Parkinson told me yesty. he was better, but not out of his room yet. At home all day today on My., in town yesty.—saw Sidey, Paterson &amp; others, <hi rend="italic">both</hi> S. &amp; P. will be at Woodville next <hi rend="italic">week</hi>, where I hope to see them. A terrific &amp; <hi rend="italic">grand</hi> surf here on shore today—weather fine, &amp; little wind, &amp; this, from E. I leave (D.V.) by early train tomorrow mg. Someone at Auckland has sent me a late “Herald”—contg. a long acct. of all N.Z. papers from <hi rend="italic">commencement</hi> in Bay of Islands ’40. If you would like to have it, say so, &amp; I’ll send it w. pleasure. “Evg. News” last night came out w. some really good (being <hi rend="italic">condemnatory</hi>) remarks on Parnell. I think I will clip &amp; enclose.—A man, stranger, came up to me in town yesty. &amp; opening a scroll, asked, “If I knew that?” I did laugh! <hi rend="italic">a capital side-likeness</hi> of Swan, in colours, cigar in m. &amp; hands in pockets! underneath—“our coming M.P.” Taken that way S looks <hi rend="underline italic">awfully low</hi>! I can’t say when I may return to N., you will hear.</p>
         <p>I have been thinking <hi rend="italic">re</hi> “E. press” &amp; my letter—pubd. or not.—</p>
         <p>Possibly I may write to you from Woodville—as I see I am a fixture <hi rend="italic">there</hi> until Friday 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Hope you <hi rend="italic">are well</hi>, ditto Mrs Harding &amp; children.</p>
         <p>             With very kind regards.</p>
         <p>                             Yours truly,</p>
         <p>                                             W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
