<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1034">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1898 February 28: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1898-02-28">1898 February 28</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1898 February 28: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-882" place="foot" n="882"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Feby. 28/98<lb/>(<hi rend="italic">late night</hi>)</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>Your kind &amp; interesting letter of yesty. (27<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) is just brought in, and I thank you for it, &amp; will reply <hi rend="italic">at once</hi>. I have been having <hi rend="italic">you </hi>much in mind of late, &amp; should have written to you <hi rend="italic">yesty</hi>. if I had received from P.D. a few copies of my <hi rend="italic">booklet</hi>. published on Saty. last, 26<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. and 50 copies sent to Crerar—<hi rend="italic">these </hi>w. <hi rend="italic">paper</hi> covers, 1/6. ea., 85pp.—but I had arranged w. that “Jew” (P.D.) for a few copies <hi rend="italic">bound</hi> in cloth for presentation, &amp; he only sent me one! &amp; as I had written a note <hi rend="italic">re </hi>same to Bp. W. I sent off both to <hi rend="italic">him</hi> this mg., &amp; a request to P.D. for ½ doz. My man came back saying, I could not have any <hi rend="italic">till Wedy</hi>., &amp; mail by str. to England closes on <hi rend="italic">Tuesday </hi>night. However I sent you this day “Herald” of Saturday, contg. advts. &amp; a <hi rend="italic">local. </hi>I would that <hi rend="italic">our </hi>Ch. E. Ministers wod. or <hi rend="italic">could</hi> (?) move in this matter (some good friends have said, “they ought to do so”)—at all events the Presbys. (<hi rend="underline italic">Sc</hi>.) should—as you will <hi rend="italic">see</hi> when you get your copy, especially in <hi rend="italic">Appendix</hi>—Your (or <hi rend="italic">our</hi>) good friend, Grant, takes ₤1. worth: Stewart, Greymouth also goes in for a lot: it will be the <hi rend="italic">heaviest</hi>, by far, of all <hi rend="italic">my pubs.—</hi>but it is in a <hi rend="italic">good cause</hi>, &amp; done both <hi rend="underline italic">heartily</hi> &amp; with <hi rend="underline italic">love</hi>.——</p>
         <p>Knowles, &amp; manager, sent up <hi rend="italic">two </hi>memo., <hi rend="italic">seeking</hi> advts.—for 1, or 2, wks, &amp; naming fig., I <hi rend="italic">declined</hi>, <hi rend="italic">verbally</hi>, “<hi rend="underline italic">NO</hi>” being <hi rend="italic">doubly busy at time</hi>, &amp; boy waitg. for ansr., at night I wrote—<hi rend="italic">explanation</hi>.</p>
         <p>I was <hi rend="italic">busy</hi> in this way: Hill brought from Ruahine on Wedy. last, a lot of small fine delicate plants <hi rend="italic">stuffed </hi>(as usual!) <hi rend="italic">anyhow</hi> into a coarse canvas sugar-bag! he sent them to me on Thursday mg.—I was <hi rend="italic">glad-sorry</hi>! for I saw it was a desperate job, if done at all: I noticed some novelties, &amp; I determd. to undertake the job!—here in my parlour all <hi rend="italic">that day </hi>till IV.p.m. in much &amp; pretty constant pain from standing &amp; stooping, back, &amp;c,—physical weakness:—on Friday, to town, on business—mainly to see, finally, P.D.—returning at noon <hi rend="italic">too tired</hi> to go on with Hill’s plants, so again re-commenced on Saty. mg. &amp; was so engaged when “Printer’s Devil” came: on <hi rend="italic">both </hi>days Mrs Anderson had strict orders—to admit <hi rend="italic">no-one</hi>, &amp; she is “first-rate” at that! I have omitted to say, on the Thursday I had <hi rend="italic">no dinner </hi>here!—could not allow table to be cleared.—I have all those plants (some very small but little beauties—gems!) all under paper &amp;, if I go in for examg. &amp;c, <hi rend="italic">plenty of work</hi>.</p>
         <p>You amuse &amp; vex me <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Kirk, but <hi rend="italic">that </hi>is just the man! <hi rend="italic">always so as I told him </hi>here! am greatly pleased at Sir J.H. coming-out: he is <hi rend="italic">right</hi>. I had <hi rend="italic">something</hi> to say about the republication of the HandBook with <hi rend="italic">additions</hi>: and you greatly surprised me (in yr.last, <hi rend="italic">re</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Lepidium</hi>) in saying, that it was “<hi rend="italic">in 4to.</hi>” <hi rend="underline italic">disgusting</hi>!! like that monstrous folly Kirk’s compilation— “Forest Flora” in a ponderous <hi rend="italic">folio</hi>, w. <hi rend="italic">wretched plates </hi>as <hi rend="italic">I told him by letter</hi>: most (all of note) of our N.Z. plants were <hi rend="italic">faithfully </hi>and <hi rend="italic">beautifully given </hi>50–60–70 yrs. ago from dried spns. sent to England. Do not trouble yourself <hi rend="italic">re </hi>that <hi rend="italic">Lepidium</hi>: I do not <hi rend="italic">care much </hi>about it, &amp; am pretty sure, from the Family it belongs to, that it only flowers early in the spring.—–</p>
         <p>You mention— “weather <hi rend="italic">cold</hi>”: so here, espy. at nights: I got laid-up for 3 days—10 days ago—through going <hi rend="italic">outside </hi>w. Mr. Welsh—from <hi rend="italic">warm </hi>room into <hi rend="italic">cold strong </hi>wind from sea: I soon beat a retreat, but mischief was done that night &amp; next day miserable: <hi rend="italic">dry</hi> heat, &amp;c, &amp;c—but, thank <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>, on <hi rend="italic">3</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">rd</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.day</hi> it wore off.——–</p>
         <p>Since my last to you I have received <hi rend="italic">fair copies</hi> of <hi rend="italic">last </hi>sheets of “A.”, with preface, title, dedicn., &amp; (<hi rend="italic">your </hi>ptg.) long letter as Appx.—and hope soon to see some of the books—with <hi rend="italic">Bill of Costs</hi>.—I had a <hi rend="italic">visitor</hi> today—to whom I showed <hi rend="italic">above</hi>, as <hi rend="italic">we </hi>were in the House together, and <hi rend="italic">he </hi>knew all about that trouble—Sir Maurice O’Rorke! had not met for nearly 40 years: I was right glad to see him: he merely landed &amp; came up to see me—on his way to Dunedin. Have you seen Part II (<hi rend="italic">double</hi> no.) of “Maori Art”? Hamilton’s work, ptd. at Dunedin: I got 2 copies from Gore (15/- ea.) &amp; sent to Engd. by S.F. Mail. <hi rend="italic">They </hi>held their Annl. Instit. Mtg. (as usual! a week <hi rend="italic">behind </hi>proper fixed time) and Hill managed to get Dinwiddie <hi rend="italic">out </hi>of Hony. Secy., placing Adams in. Hill <hi rend="italic">now </hi>sees, &amp; allows, that <hi rend="italic">I was right</hi>— “No man can serve 2 Masters”.—Craig is made Treasurer.</p>
         <p>I was greatly pleased in finding Dr. Sidey came out—strong (Nasmyth Hammer fashion) at their Assembly in Auckland—some smaller &amp; younger member, wanting to go the whole hog of <hi rend="italic">intemperate </hi>Temp., yclepd “<hi rend="italic">Prohibition</hi>”: Dr. S. remarked, he had been for many years a student of the Bible, &amp; could not find P. in it—and so, the thing <hi rend="italic">collapsed. </hi>I was grieved this mg. in seeing in “Herald”, death of Welsman’s son, 14, caused by internal injuries received at Gymnasium High School: I could not resist writing a word of sympathy this aftn. to the sorrowing parents. May <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> comfort them.—–</p>
         <p>I got 1 doz. copies of “Herald” containing that good &amp; fitting Judgment on that misl. Jesuitical creature in London, &amp; sent 2 to Synod in Xt.Ch. to Eccles, &amp; to the Dean. Was very glad to see John Hall’s folly cast out,—I think John Hall has done <hi rend="italic">enough </hi>mischief in his time.—–</p>
         <p>Old Mrs Heslop’s death took place last week, she was buried on Sunday—like her husband, last year, died very suddenly;!! how well I recollect their arrival here! Last Sunday week I had a kind visit from Fannin. “<hi rend="italic">Joe Rhodes</hi>” was here in town last week with his new wife: he did not stay long. Rev. R. Welsh has taken passages, self &amp; wife, in “Ruahine”, to leave <hi rend="italic">Wgn</hi>. on 17<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. March,—but leave <hi rend="italic">here</hi> by <hi rend="underline italic">str</hi>. on 15<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., &amp; so have their luggage transferred to “<hi rend="italic">R.</hi>” He has had <hi rend="italic">great </hi>difficulty in doing duty for the Dean—who has been <hi rend="italic">long </hi>absent—only returning on 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. Welsh is one of my <hi rend="italic">dearest </hi>friends—if not my <hi rend="italic">only </hi>one <hi rend="italic">in </hi>Napier! <hi rend="italic">toiling </hi>regularly every wk. up this hill, in weakness &amp; pain, &amp; sometimes <hi rend="italic">twice</hi> in the wk.! I shall indeed feel the want of him when he goes.—I think I shall (D.V.) take a run inland <hi rend="italic">soon after </hi>W. leaves.</p>
         <p>I cannot wholly agree w. you <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the finding of the Jury &amp; sentence on the unhappy man P.—no doubt <hi rend="italic">certain circumstances</hi> seem to point that way but—the <hi rend="italic">one link </hi>is <hi rend="italic">wanting</hi>: the Scotch verdict “<hi rend="italic">Not proven</hi>” is more correct, but Wgn. has always been famous (or in-famous) for <hi rend="italic">such verdicts</hi>: as, I think, I told you long ago.—I have agreed to help W. at St. Aug’s. on <hi rend="italic">his last </hi>Sy. there, 13<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. M., preaching Mg. S., possibly <hi rend="italic">my last</hi>, there,—as I do <hi rend="italic">not know</hi> the Minister (Mr. Taylor) who is to reside &amp; do duty: he has been here nearly 2 years, &amp; at 2 Synods, &amp; has <hi rend="italic">never spoken to me</hi>. I am pretty well certainly stronger in legs, &amp;c &amp; begin to think—<hi rend="italic">I may yet walk to town &amp; climb this hill! </hi>Hope this may find Mrs Harding <hi rend="italic">well</hi>—&amp; you, too, &amp; all your family. Good Bye, &amp; with kind regards &amp; best wishes</p>
         <p>Believe me, yours sincerely</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">March </hi>1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. (to bed after xii!)—On referring to your kind &amp; able note a fortnight ago re <hi rend="italic">Lepidium </hi>(<hi rend="underline italic">not handy</hi> last night,—you are <hi rend="italic">right</hi>—in saying K. ought <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to have shut out a sp.—or plant, because only <hi rend="italic">once </hi>found: for many years that was the case with <hi rend="italic">several </hi>(and with <hi rend="italic">some</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">still</hi>!), as <hi rend="italic">he </hi>well knows from his letters to me <hi rend="italic">re </hi>their <hi rend="italic">habitat</hi>. You will find several <hi rend="italic">so mentioned</hi> in HandBook, have not time to look up. e.g. Myosurus: Spiranthes: Gymnogramme rutæfolia: several Ferns—and particularly <hi rend="italic">Seneca perdicioides </hi>(see)—but of <hi rend="italic">late years</hi>, this last found again, &amp; growing in Tiffen’s garden. Cheeseman, in his last years journey to N. Cape, begged me to give him localities where I had found species—<hi rend="italic">not since seen</hi> (just as K. did before him)—and some are still undiscovered: but enough. Who is this K. (from Pitoone) brought out by S.O. Could you tell me if letter A is in binding? or anything about it.—I was much pleased in hearing O’Rourke speak <hi rend="italic">highly</hi> of Mackay.</p>
         <p>Weather fine today—night cold. The Women’s Convention is now in full swing here: better they had stayed at their Homes, &amp; helped <hi rend="italic">their poor neighbours</hi>. Heard lately of a Ladies’ Club at Woodville meeting weekly, making dolls, &amp; small articles for w. &amp; girls, China, India!!!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
