<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0755">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1890 December 1: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0495.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1890-12-01">1890 December 1</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1890 December 1: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-496" place="foot" n="496"> ATL qMS-0495.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke,<lb/>Decemr., 1/90</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>What would I not give to have you here with me this evg.?—for a quiet 2–3 hours “chat”—or rather <hi rend="italic">intellectual</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">treat</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I had determined, on Satuday last, <hi rend="italic">soon</hi> to write to you, again—and now, this afternoon, yours of 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. &amp; 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. arrived, &amp; served to clinch that determination. While at P.O., &amp; on recg. yours &amp; opening it <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, (a thing I <hi rend="italic">rarely ever</hi> do,)—&amp; finding again “the old old story”—<hi rend="italic">re</hi> the copies of “E. Press,”—I invested a 1/- right off to gaily inform you of their <hi rend="italic">non</hi>-appearance.—</p>
         <p>I may truly enough say—I have been troubled beyond measure <hi rend="italic">re</hi> that paper:—written to Woodv.—spoken to Haggen &amp; to Walsh, <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, to Clayton (Ed. “Bush Adv.”) here, and also written to Mrs Weber (although almost <hi rend="italic">a stranger</hi> to me) and <hi rend="italic">last</hi> resource! &amp; hitherto all in vain!! I have much wished you had sent me your copy (sparing it.) especially since I recd. a letter from Sir W. Buller, in which he says, respg. it,—(I copy verbatim,)</p>
         <p>“I was much interested in your letter in the “Evg. Press” re Eb. Baker, and I have cut it out for my Scrap Book. You are quite right in being so jealous of the Early History: such statements as these complained of, left uncontradicted, would in time, form spurious history.”—<note xml:id="ftn3-497" place="foot" n="497"> To the editor, <hi rend="italic">Evening Press</hi>, Wellington, 22 November 1890.</note>
         </p>
         <p>(He also tells me of “Wallace, the author of Brett’s Early Histy. of N.Z. part II, being now on his death-bed”.—And, of his “having lately recd. from the Auckland Islands a very fine pair of <hi rend="italic">Phalacrocorax Colensoi</hi>—which he will exhibit at one of the meetings of Wgn. Phil. Sy.” So look out for them &amp; for opposition (of <hi rend="italic">course</hi>) from Maskell &amp; Co.)</p>
         <p>What, perhaps, may have tended to make me the more “savage,” re those missing copies of “E.P.”—is the fact, that Haggen had (so he says &amp; so his shop-assistants,) sent me in August 6 copies of “Examr.”—containing his report of sermon on Weber’s (&amp; others) lonely death—and these never came to hand, nor could they be traced—Yet I had to pay for them w. postage of course:—&amp; worse still I could not get a copy, anywhere for love nor money!—save, <hi rend="italic">at last</hi> on my return to Napier, from Mrs. Weber.—</p>
         <p>I hope <hi rend="italic">you have recd.</hi> your copy of Vol.XXII. “Trans.”,—you don’t mention it,—<hi rend="italic">be sure to let me know.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to you briefly from Woodville on 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. (?—you say, “<hi rend="italic">25</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>.,) I was hard up for writing materials, and doing so on an extra high table. However, I will just add, that I returned (thus far) with Rev. Mr Paterson &amp; his expected friend (that mg. arrd. at W. by coach) Capt. Hore—whom you <hi rend="italic">may</hi> both see &amp; hear at Wgn. Here on Saturday I saw Rev.—Douglas, who told me they had an <hi rend="italic">excellent meeting</hi> at Woodville on Thursday, notwithstanding the weather. Rev. Mr. Grant, spoke to me at Ry. Station on leaving W., <hi rend="italic">re</hi> naming a lot of mounted ferns for him before 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., (same Bazaar, I suppose,)—and now, that I have determd. to go purposely to Kaikoura on 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. to vote for Capt. R.,—I have written to Mr. G. to let him know, I will be at Waipu. on that day (returning) &amp; will call at Manse &amp; do so:—and then, also, I shall be <hi rend="italic">thinking</hi> on <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>.</p>
         <p>On my return to this place, I found Mr Robertshawe had given out, &amp;c, of his Special Services (“Intercession for Missions”,) here on Saty.—mg. &amp; evg.—proceeds of Collns. between “C.M.S., and “Propgn. Gospel,”—&amp; <hi rend="italic">so </hi>he got me to preach the Sermon in evg.—but, only <hi rend="italic">one</hi> (a wom.) came <hi rend="italic">then</hi>, &amp; there were <hi rend="italic">none</hi> at the mg. S.!! But what could be expd. on such a day, and (must I add?) for such a purpose! So—last night—I gave <hi rend="italic">that Sermon</hi>, which, I fancy, did not, <hi rend="italic">could not</hi> please everyone! (I <hi rend="italic">had</hi> been <hi rend="italic">very</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">unwell</hi>—<hi rend="italic">severe diarrhoea</hi>, Saty. nt. &amp; Sundy. mg., but managed:—&amp; this day, mg. especially, extra Rheumatism, which may be attributed to change of <hi rend="italic">weather</hi>—from dry &amp; warm to wet). Here, folks are “Election mad”—or nearly so; and that kind of talk <hi rend="italic">don’t interest</hi> me.—I thought it strange, to see J.N. Wilson going to Otago, a few days ago; and to find J.D. Ormond among the passgrs. S.—I know <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> of Fannin or of Hill, or of Spencer, or of anyone at <hi rend="italic">Napier</hi>! I have no correspdts. <hi rend="italic">there</hi> now, save to ask for <hi rend="italic">donations</hi>, &amp; to send small driblet bills—which always cost me 2d. extra.—</p>
         <p>And now I will turn to your letter. It was very kind (aye, <hi rend="underline italic">too</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> kind</hi>) of you, to write me such a <hi rend="italic">long</hi> letter at your <hi rend="italic">extra</hi> busy time—<hi rend="italic">Eng. Mail week</hi>.—Your long questn. from “N.Z. Methodist” amuses me: that also contains <hi rend="italic">errors</hi>. I believe I have copies of those 12mo tracts, &amp;c, printed at W.M. Hokianga,—but <hi rend="italic">never</hi> by Hobbs (whom I <hi rend="italic">very well</hi> knew) but by <hi rend="italic">Woon</hi>—a trained <hi rend="italic">Printer</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">Cornishman</hi> too!—We (Woon &amp; self) corresponded <hi rend="italic">often</hi>, I have <hi rend="italic">many</hi> of his letters—I saw the bundle only the other day. Both W. &amp; Hobbs came to N.Z. from the Islands—driven (?) by climate. Surely you (or your Father) must have known Woon at Whanganui? he was a tall fine man: and I know that Mr<hi rend="underline">s</hi>. W. used to preach, there. I also remember seeing Ironsides, &amp; some other of the <hi rend="italic">younger</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">later</hi> Misss., and I <hi rend="italic">think</hi> he arrd. at Waitangi <hi rend="italic">late</hi> on the <hi rend="italic">day of signing</hi>, &amp;, of <hi rend="italic">course</hi>, was at Kororareka that place being a kind of Methodist head-quarters in the Bay, besides the <hi rend="italic">only</hi> township (or nucleus of one) where <hi rend="italic">stores</hi> could then be obtained. (But <hi rend="italic">much</hi> on this head I must leave till we meet.—) I will, however, add, that I never before heard, of the W.M. Society “<hi rend="italic">purchasing</hi>” a 1000 copies:—&amp; this I <hi rend="italic">greatly</hi> doubt. He is right, as to that copy of the N.T. being <hi rend="italic">then</hi> (or 2–3 yrs. after it was printed) so <hi rend="italic">greatly</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">valued</hi>: even of late, up here in the Bush, a copy has been sought <hi rend="italic">from me </hi>by the Mao. Chiefs—a piece of land, or £20. cash, could be obtained for one.)—From yours, I learn—that “S. Ironside is <hi rend="italic">still</hi> at Hobart”—of course, like myself, an aged man <hi rend="italic">past</hi> “threesc. &amp; ten.”—anything of that kind (also, if<hi rend="italic">any</hi> rejoinder, &amp;c, &amp;c, from Eb. Baker) <hi rend="italic">be sure to let me know—send copies—I will repay all outlay.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I scarcely understand you when you say—<hi rend="italic">re</hi> J.B.—“I regard him as the direct cause of my transplantation”: but (&amp; as you further say) “<hi rend="italic">it was for the best</hi>”—which <hi rend="italic">I sincerely hope</hi>:—tho’ <hi rend="italic">I am the great loser.—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>As far as I can see at present, I shall leave here for N. on (say) the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.—not later, and shall <hi rend="italic">not</hi> return again for the summer: but I hope &amp; propose to write <hi rend="italic">to you</hi> again &amp; again, ere I leave the Bush.—</p>
         <p>&amp; w. very kindest regards &amp; best wishes believe me. </p>
         <p>Yours faithy.</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Dec. 2</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">nd</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>In bed last night, w. <hi rend="italic">little</hi> sleep, &amp; thinking on <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, I recalld. I had not ansd. a former qy. of yours—<hi rend="italic">re</hi> witchery, sorcery, &amp;c. among the Maoris: You also adduced Manning &amp; others; I must however be brief. Of <hi rend="italic">M.</hi> I had always the <hi rend="italic">lowest</hi> poss. opinion in <hi rend="italic">every </hi>way. (Much as I have of your McDonnell there, yclepd “Colonel”!!!) But it is nothing new for the greatest sceptics in religious matters to bound to the furthest opposite!—&amp; some Missionaries I have known were <hi rend="italic">very</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">weak</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">minded. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>I forget what <hi rend="italic">yr</hi>. you joined H.B.Ph.Sy.—but I had early commd. a <hi rend="italic">series</hi> of papers on the “Ideality of the Maori”—and was working it out: when oppositions (<hi rend="italic">concealed</hi>) came from Cooke—but <hi rend="italic">egged on by Weber and Holder,</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">that</hi>, &amp;, Dr Hector showing <hi rend="italic">adverse</hi> feelings culminating in the <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Governor’s N.Z.I. address led to my relinquishing my job—<hi rend="italic">with disgust. </hi>Otherwise <hi rend="italic">that</hi> (S <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Maoris—&amp; papers on them, &amp; such—as Maskell &amp;c) would have folld. in course. Is it possible, now, for me to resume?—</p>
         <p>I have lately noticed (somewhere) of <hi rend="italic">several</hi> (6?) vols. of J. White’s work! Is this so? I have only 2—&amp; these <hi rend="italic">uncut</hi>!!</p>
         <p>Should you have any diffy. in getting me a few copies of “Eg. Press”—please purchase at 3d. or 5d. ea.—if to be had.</p>
         <p>I send w. this a copy of “Wdv. Exr.” containing Presbytn. Ch. Mtg.—thinking you would like to see mention <hi rend="italic">of your old friends</hi>: the more I have seen of Douglas the more I like him. In “Herald” &amp; “D.T.” of Saty. last a “<hi rend="italic">Mr Harlock</hi>” took D.S. in Eng. Ch. at Taradale—this man was formerly the Schoolmaster at <hi rend="italic">Hampden</hi>—did you ever know him—or, <hi rend="italic">anything of him</hi>?—</p>
         <p>I am better today but <hi rend="italic">not feeling</hi> right. Weather still dull showery close—this I fancy has much to do with it.—I suppose <hi rend="italic">you</hi> will read &amp; <hi rend="italic">con</hi>. the <hi rend="italic">long</hi> art. in “Herald” of yesty. <hi rend="italic">against</hi> Smith.—I cannot suppress a <hi rend="italic">strong feeling</hi> of dislike against that fellow <hi rend="italic">Stanley</hi>—<hi rend="italic">I have always had it</hi>—&amp; it increases—!</p>
         <p>Ever yrs.</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
