<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0853">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 December 19: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-12-19">1892 December 19</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 December 19: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-626" place="foot" n="626"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Monday night<lb/>19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>, XII, 92</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>I trust you have been far too busy in your proper business to think of me, &amp; the non-appearance of a letter. I have had you, as usual, often in mind, &amp; not unfrequently your name upon my lips—but have been <hi rend="italic">very busy </hi>since my last on 30<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. ult. Your kind reply of the 8<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> inst. I duly received &amp; thank you for: I should have written ere this, only I wished to know—<hi rend="italic">How it would be w. me. </hi>But first, to your letter: again do I agree w. you—when you <hi rend="italic">denounce </hi>that “patronising irreverence” used by some when writing of Christ; you are correct in your estimation of all such writers &amp; their followers.</p>
         <p>Thanks, for the “Mg. Times” containing a full account of Tennyson’s funeral:—I have it also in “Standard” &amp; something more, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Tennyson, which I will send you anon.</p>
         <p>You interested me largely in your graphic account of your late meeting: I think “young Hudson” got off remarkably <hi rend="italic">easy</hi>, he would have heard <hi rend="italic">much more</hi> from me, had I been present. I wonder if he knows—that a large proportion of his Insects (some, too, w. <hi rend="underline italic">new</hi> names!) were published w. <hi rend="italic">figures</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">dissections</hi> (in a proper Sc. way) 50 years ago! It was this that vexed me, when I got his book (sent by Hamilton), and I took it in w. me to Dvk. to write an exposure—but had always plenty to do there, &amp; <hi rend="italic">had not those sc. works there w. me</hi>. He is not the only one who has <hi rend="italic">so</hi> come out—especially in Botany: but enough of this.</p>
         <p>I have seen—a <hi rend="italic">few</hi> times only—the tertiary rainbow you mention. But the fungus <hi rend="italic">story</hi>, caused me to laugh outright—! &amp; yet a louder Guffaw, on reading your remark— “a copy of Taylor’s Book w. a <hi rend="italic">good</hi> (!!) coloured drawing was passed round.” I have (I suppose) the same here in my Taylor’s “Ika-a-Maui”, 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. (&amp; most <hi rend="italic">erroneous</hi>) edn. and the wretched thing—a bit of a goose quill w. small vermilion rays! is no more like the Fungus, than it resembles a peach: the Fungus itself (formerly common) is as large as this page: I have some very fine ones in spirits (a new species) colld. by Winkelmann at Te Aute.—</p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">Private</hi>: be on your guard respecting <hi rend="italic">Kirk </hi>and <hi rend="underline italic">Field</hi>—whenever anything concg. me, or my name crops up: <hi rend="italic">more anon when we meet</hi>]</p>
         <p>For more than 2 years I have been promising to go to Hill’s to tea, &amp; spend evg. so I went last Friday, (but was <hi rend="italic">not quite comfortable</hi>, because my trap came for me at vii.30—<hi rend="italic">too early</hi>.) Of course we had a long chat, your n. kindly mentioned more than once. I don’t know if you correspond w. H.,—but I may tell you, he has got a large no. (40, or more!) of greenstone ear-drops, hei-tiki, &amp;c &amp;c, w. <hi rend="italic">many other </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">ancient</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> valuables</hi>,—I believe from grubbing in old Maori cemetary! He wrote to me from Gisborne, saying he had got the scent of such a place, &amp; had spent a whole Sunday there (away in the back woods) but had only <hi rend="italic">then </hi>gained some scores of <hi rend="italic">beads</hi>! and tresses of human hair, children’s skulls, &amp;c &amp;c (some of these <hi rend="italic">last</hi> he has here!) I <hi rend="underline italic">don’t like</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> that kind of thing</hi>—never did;—besides I think it is <hi rend="underline italic">wrong</hi>. H. &amp; self are pretty friendly again now. I have been also to see old Mrs. McKain &amp; her daughters—one, Mrs <hi rend="italic">Hamilton</hi>,—also Miss Stewart, (Bp’s. <hi rend="italic">sister</hi>) &amp; Mrs. Clarke the widow, at “Ladies College”: Bp. is expected back by middle of Jany. The Dean w. family leave on 26<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. for Kuripapango:—He has been here twice to see me (second time this afternoon), wishes me to take Services at Cathedral and at Augustine’s on New Year’s Day: and Tuke, also, at his Ch. on 8<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> and 15<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. during his absence. I purpose leaving on Wednesday for Dvk.—but only for a <hi rend="italic">few</hi> days, should you write, address <hi rend="italic">here</hi>. Very sorry to see in paper this evg. a prohibition order sought against young <hi rend="italic">Carnell</hi>, Lawyer, &amp; <hi rend="italic">granted</hi>!—I went to Augustine’s Ch. last night, &amp; heard Canon Fox, (I had not seen him before!)—my first visit thither since Parkinson’s funeral, just <hi rend="italic">exactly </hi>12 months! Gardiner of Gisborne has been elected for Waipawa by “Noninators”—there were 4 applicants—G., Oliver Dean, Wills, &amp; a Mr. Clarke from Nelson Diocese,—I hear—that D, &amp; W. were <hi rend="italic">nowhere</hi>.</p>
         <p>Did I ever tell you of Luff’s picture? When I went to Dvk. in Sepr.—I recd. a letter from L., saying he had sent me a picture, drawn in India, of my friend Sir J. Hooker, in the Himalaya gathering Rhododendrons &amp;c—but L. only <hi rend="italic">lent </hi>it—<hi rend="italic">not to be copied</hi>, &amp;c. Now I had taken in w. me Hooker’s “Himalayan Journals” (a 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. ed. &amp; <hi rend="italic">just to hand</hi> by Mail from him) and in reading it there sure enough was a good <hi rend="italic">graphic </hi>description (a-la-<hi rend="italic">Harding</hi>) of the same! How that it (or <hi rend="italic">he</hi>) was drawn in colours on a Buddhist Temple by the Lama’s &amp; Monks—<hi rend="italic">all in good part</hi>. Last wk. I opened the <hi rend="italic">big case</hi>—the picture &amp;frame, glazed, is about 3.6 x 2.0, a monster in size,—it is in water colours, curiously &amp; strongly done, but while it represents him &amp;c. it is <hi rend="italic">not a copy </hi>of what he has described. I have written to L. about it, and I shall <hi rend="italic">return</hi> it ere long: it cost 5/ carriage hither, &amp; will cost <hi rend="italic">me</hi> same to return it. L. wishes me to hang it up here in my room for a season—<hi rend="italic">as a loan</hi>: a strange notion on his part.</p>
         <p>A <hi rend="italic">cart road</hi> has just been finished (that is for the time) from Milton road up to this paddock: it is <hi rend="italic">entirely </hi>of <hi rend="italic">Robert’s contriving</hi>—but it has cost me <hi rend="italic">already</hi> more than £100.—Edser’s bill for a retaining wall, alone, was over £<hi rend="italic">50. </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">I have just seen it once</hi>. I was in town today, and found it <hi rend="italic">very difficult</hi> to climb this hill on my return, and perhaps still more so in going down it, owing to my poor <hi rend="italic">knees </hi>&amp; feet. Rheumatism however is very much less.—</p>
         <p>There is a fine Panoramic View in the “Auckland Graphic”, Xmas. No,—<hi rend="italic">try to see it</hi>. I both wrote to, &amp; spoke with P. Dinwiddie <hi rend="italic">re </hi>their Almanac and strongly recommended him to engage your Father to get the proper astronomical matters done: P. said, they had engaged Saunders: I replied can he do what is really required?</p>
         <p>I find Craig has (again) sold all his <hi rend="italic">Naut. </hi>almks for ’93—if you can get me one there at Wgn. do so.</p>
         <p>You intimate that the present would be “a good time” for printing papers I had been mentioning to you—but you do not specify, and I am far too busy at present, (and, I expect, shall again be shortly,) to touch any.—</p>
         <p>I had a very pleasant talk with my dear Rev. R. Fraser, a few days ago: have recd. also excellent letters from Rev. R. Stewart, Greymouth: such talk and letters are quite refreshing—&amp; “like A’s. visits.”—<hi rend="italic">kindest regards </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the good old wishes of our fathers at these 2 great festive seasons now close at hand.—</p>
         <p>Bel. me yours faithy.</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
