<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0769">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 February 25: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0495.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-02-25">1891 February 25</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 February 25: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-513" place="foot" n="513"> ATL qMS-0495.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, 25, II, 91.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Yesty. my eyes &amp; heart were gladdened by arrival of yours of 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">thanks</hi>: now, I hope we shall proceed <hi rend="italic">more</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">regularly.</hi>—Before however that I take up yours,—a few words <hi rend="italic">re</hi> myself.—</p>
         <p>You will see by <hi rend="italic">enclosed</hi> (lot!) I had been thinking on &amp; wkg. for you.—On 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I went in trap to Clive for D.S. that evg. I stayed at the <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Hotel (kept by Nicholson) &amp; retd. by mid-day train on My. I did not feel very well—but on Tuesday mg. I went down to town intending to leave next day <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> for Dvk. I knocked about a good deal in the sun, &amp; came up this hill <hi rend="italic">fagged</hi>: took dinner <hi rend="italic">without</hi> relish, &amp; was soon taken w. extreme pains in whole abdomen: shirt up and to bed at VII,—no rest there! <hi rend="italic">Torment</hi> without intermission. I was obliged to <hi rend="italic">bear</hi> till daylight, IV., when I crawled down in shirt, &amp; rang big bell, no one replied! I waited till V. when (½ dead) I repeated, &amp; <hi rend="italic">both</hi> soon came: I sent off for H. who (dear old f.!) was out of bed &amp; soon w. me,—sat by bedside till VII.30 to watch, pulse &amp; opn. of meds.—&amp; afterwards climbed <hi rend="italic">this hill 2ce more that same day</hi>!! I was thus shut up (say) till <hi rend="italic">Monday</hi>, on slops, &amp;c. come dawn &amp; lay: Yesty. I was obliged to <hi rend="italic">sit up a little</hi> as Eng. M. was closing. This day am <hi rend="italic">much better</hi> but <hi rend="italic">very weak</hi>: I hope however to be able to move inland (for a <hi rend="italic">very short visit</hi>) next week. During confinet. the Bp. came on 2 days to see me, “no admission”. Again on Monday last, making a very short stay—10m. or so: he is off again to the N.—</p>
         <p>Now for your <hi rend="italic">last</hi> letter. My main reason for wishing regr. replies from <hi rend="italic">you </hi>(&amp;, of course, my also <hi rend="italic">answering regularly</hi>) is, that you <hi rend="italic">omit</hi> replying to many questions—<hi rend="underline italic">never willingly</hi>
            <hi rend="underline"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">I know</hi>. In fut., you write on Sy. (as you geny. have done) &amp; I will reply say, on Wy. or Thy.—</p>
         <p>There is much in yr. theory <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Smith, but, as you <hi rend="italic">don’t</hi> yet know all, it is defective: lay it aside for the time; <hi rend="italic">more anon</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I should much like for <hi rend="italic">you</hi> to see Angas’ N.Z. Bide-a-wee. Thanks for <hi rend="italic">all</hi> yours <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Halkett L.; as before in much of your discrimination I go w. you:—I, too, have noticed “serious blunders in his “Bookmart”.<note xml:id="ftn3-514" place="foot" n="514"> Richard Halkett Lord was the first editor of the Napier <hi rend="italic">Daily Telegraph</hi>, but later lived in the United States, and edited the <hi rend="italic">Bookmart</hi>, a librarians’ magazine.</note>—</p>
         <p>Re <hi rend="italic">Tregear</hi>:<hi rend="italic"> </hi>better tell B. to send me <hi rend="italic">early</hi> a copy of Dy. strongly bound, letting T. <hi rend="italic">at same time</hi> know I have ordered one: thanks for letting me know a little of his circumstances: but <hi rend="italic">how</hi> does he <hi rend="italic">live</hi>?—</p>
         <p>Hill, <hi rend="italic">says,</hi> he did <hi rend="italic">not know</hi> of the rule—to send in P. (but quæ.)—I was infd. of it by Secy.</p>
         <p>You rather surp. me with yr infm. from Dy., <hi rend="italic">re</hi> his ptg., part of my old task!! &amp; I confess I <hi rend="italic">don’t</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">now</hi> like it: I suppose, I shall have proofs sent to me (that was the offl. stipulation), &amp; that will bring me back from Bush to do it: besides, had I <hi rend="italic">known</hi> of such coming on, I should have been able to get ready a few more in A obtained since; which, though coming to hand in ansr. to enquiries, I have never yet attended to—being so <hi rend="italic">heartily</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">sick</hi> of the job! I may tell <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi> that 10 months ago a person high in off. took it up, &amp; (I was infd.) read thro’ <hi rend="italic">the whole</hi> of the Correspce <hi rend="italic">re</hi> same!! &amp; also saw the My. about it, &amp; a promise (I was told) was given, that <hi rend="italic">after election</hi> it should be ptd.</p>
         <p>“Jany. 3/35,—was made memorable by the landing of a printing press in the charge of Mr Colenso <hi rend="underline">&amp; Mr Wade</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>Mr Colenso<hi rend="italic"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline">had a Native assistant by whose help</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">,</hi> 2000 copies of the Epistles to the Ephesians &amp; Philippians were struck off in the form of tracts.</p>
         <p>“In <hi rend="underline">1838</hi>, the whole of the N.T. in the N.Z. language was printed, &amp;c——the Prayer book was also completed, &amp; both printed by Mr Colenso” (“<hi rend="italic">Annals</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> of the Diocese of N.Z</hi>.,” S.P.G.K.1847) p.18.</p>
         <p rend="center">———————————————————–</p>
         <p>N.B. 3 <hi rend="italic">errors</hi> in above: underlined by me.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="sub bold">x</hi>
            <hi rend="sup bold">x</hi>
            <hi rend="sub bold">x</hi> There are some well-executed &amp; truthful wood cuts in the above work: some (if not all) have been reproduced in “Early History of N.Z., but <hi rend="italic">most wretchedly </hi>done!—W.C.</p>
         <p>—“In <hi rend="underline">1836</hi>, Mr W. Williams had <hi rend="underline">ready</hi> for publication <hi rend="underline">complete translations of the N.T. &amp; the Book of Com. Prayer.</hi> The portions previously published, having been sent to Sydney to be printed were, as has been already said, sadly disfigured by errors of the press; but of these new &amp; complete translations Mr. W. was fortunately able to superintend the printing himself, at Paihia, the C.M.S. having opportunely sent out, in 1834, a printing press in charge of Mr. William Colenso”.</p>
         <p>     “Colonial Church Histories: N.Z.” by V.R. Hy. Jacobs, D.D., Dean of XtCh.—p.67. (a very recent work of 500 pp., the last letter in it bearing date of “Octr. 1889”.)</p>
         <p rend="center">———————————————————</p>
         <p>N.B. Two errors in above extract, underlined by me—W.C.</p>
         <p>I should here, make another extract from Dean Jacob’s book.—In the “Introduction,” acknowledging <hi rend="italic">assistance</hi> received—he is bound to mention first &amp; foremost, the name of his friend—the Ven. Archdeacon Williams of Gisborne” (p.v.)—and, in the body of his book (p.45,) he gives in a note:—<lb/>—“In a brief memoir of his father the Bp. of Waiapu—published in the N.Z. Church News, 1878. “The archdeacon himself, as we shall presently see, <hi rend="italic">was not quite an eye witness</hi> of the scenes he describes.” (The <hi rend="italic">Italics</hi> are the Dean’s own.)</p>
         <p>     (Reminding one of Mr E. Baker’s recent <hi rend="italic">descriptions of scenes</hi> pubd. in Wellington papers.)</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
