<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0813">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 January 10: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-01-10">1892 January 10</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 January 10: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-563" place="foot" n="563"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Sunday Jany.<lb/>10<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> 1892: ix.30 a.m.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>Having you <hi rend="italic">much </hi>on my mind (and no Ch. wk. to do—&amp; if I had any assigned me could not perform it!)—I <hi rend="italic">must write</hi>.—</p>
         <p>Yours of 5<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst. came duly to hand &amp; I thank you for it, especially as it contained more favourable tidings of your dear little son: I hope such good signs continue w. large increase.</p>
         <p>But I wish to write to you now respecting <hi rend="italic">your own “</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">worldly</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">” </hi>prospects &amp;c—appertaining thereto.—I know nothing of this ‘Mr. Harcourt’ (whom you mention). I dare believe that you will take in <hi rend="italic">good part</hi> what I write, &amp; that in my <hi rend="italic">plainness </hi>I shall not offend you. You know what is said of a Bystander seeing (knowing) more of the game (how it is likely to go) than the player.—But if <hi rend="italic">not</hi>,—then I would suggest that you should hesitate entering afresh into the toils—wh. might (&amp; probably would) end in your losing all your ptg. material! For, in your opening <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, you do so <hi rend="italic">in opposition </hi>to the already estabd. printers, and from them I fear you would have no help—no consideration.—</p>
         <p>And your 2 <hi rend="italic">young </hi>(&amp; <hi rend="italic">single-men</hi>?) copartners, would cut &amp; run to a better locality—Australia, perhaps.—</p>
         <p>Were you, too, <hi rend="italic">single</hi>, I should write differently.—</p>
         <p>Here you may reasonably ask— “What do I advise?”—</p>
         <p>1. I am <hi rend="underline italic">not</hi> in <hi rend="italic">possession </hi>of <hi rend="italic">all</hi> in your mind—<hi rend="italic">all you know, re </hi>the (<hi rend="italic">recent</hi>) past, w. L. &amp; B.,—the present,—the future—as to <hi rend="italic">what you could do there</hi>, outside your profession, in case of great emergency; &amp; not only what <hi rend="italic">you</hi> could do, but what you could <hi rend="italic">get to do</hi>.—</p>
         <p>2. Here you would certainly get a share (perhaps only a <hi rend="italic">small </hi>share) of printing, but you would escape some of those “absolute” &amp; first heavy charges—as Rents—removal material, &amp;c. &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>3. I would put some printing into your hands (<hi rend="italic">say, extent of </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">£</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">50. for this year, 1892</hi>)—and I think I should be doing <hi rend="italic">justice </hi>to myself if I were to get this (returned) part A. Mao. Lex. printed.—</p>
         <p rend="center">======</p>
         <p>In faithfulness to you, as a well-wisher &amp; a friend, I should not keep back from you what I have <hi rend="italic">lately </hi>heard some of your <hi rend="italic">best </hi>friends here say—viz. that you are <hi rend="italic">not </hi>a man for business (i.e. one to cope w. the men of the world), almost sure to be taken-in: and this arrangement of yours w. L. &amp; B., (which we had supposed to be, at least, a <hi rend="italic">permanent</hi> one,) &amp; this w. D.W. &amp; Co. re <hi rend="italic">“Almanac” </hi>seem to support this view.——</p>
         <p>In your entering into that <hi rend="italic">new </hi>path (of yr. business) there at Wgn. you will be very heavily loaded, &amp; the qu. w. me, is,—Can you climb the hill? <hi rend="italic">very much</hi>, here will depend on the parties you may have to deal with—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> as to your <hi rend="italic">owing </hi>them money—<hi rend="underline italic">would they wait</hi>?</p>
         <p>1. rent (or rent<hi rend="italic">s</hi>)            )<lb/>2. Taxes &amp; Rates              )<hi rend="italic">absolute</hi>
            <lb/>3. Interest on loan                )<lb/>4. Necessaries—living expenses in trade (not always foreseen): medical attendance, &amp;c.!!<lb/>5. Charges attending removal<lb/>6.</p>
         <p>Now if, say, 1 &amp; 3—could stand over for 1–2 years (through your having friends, or mercifully disposed folk, to deal with—who, seeing your industry, &amp;c &amp;c,—would <hi rend="italic">wait</hi>) so far good.—and I must, add, that I think you are wrong in determining to carry on your “Typo”—<hi rend="italic">ever </hi>a <hi rend="underline italic">losing</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> monetary </hi>concern! w. no prospect of it changing: moreover, <hi rend="italic">here </hi>(or partly in connection therewith) the <hi rend="italic">cost</hi> to you in <hi rend="italic">money </hi>as well as time must be <hi rend="italic">great</hi>:—<hi rend="italic">you cannot afford it</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I know, I admire, <hi rend="underline italic">I feel with you</hi>, in your proper &amp; honourable feelings in <hi rend="italic">not </hi>liking to abandon “Typo”—but, my dear friend, you <hi rend="italic">now </hi>have a w. &amp; fy. to care for—<hi rend="underline italic">first</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">chiefly</hi>.—[“take care of <hi rend="italic">pence</hi>”.]</p>
         <p>Is there <hi rend="italic">no</hi> chance of your again entg. into P.O. of L. &amp; Bl.—in any other capacity (even if only for a time)?</p>
         <p>Could you not obtain some kind of fit supervising profl. situation in some other P. estab.? Didsbury—or even in some other city or town, N.Z.,—leaving Mrs H. &amp; fy. <hi rend="italic">there</hi>—this for a time, at least? No doubt I could say, &amp; suggest, more if we were together: but here I stop: merely adding—<hi rend="underline italic">Do nothing rashly</hi>.</p>
         <p rend="center">______</p>
         <p>Of this place I have little to say: I am still a kind of prisoner, but daily getting better—I think, yet <hi rend="italic">very slowly</hi>. I purpose (D.V.) leaving for Bush (Dvk. probably) on 19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. Robertshawe is still unwell &amp; at Clive: Tuke is now ill—the Bp. goes to Taradale today in his stead,—&amp; <hi rend="italic">no </hi>S. at Puketapu. Wills is serving Augustines. Hovell, w. &amp; fy. are at Kurip.—&amp; will stay there this mo. Hamilton is here, &amp; has <hi rend="italic">arranged</hi> w. H.B. Ph. Instit. Council; he will leave for Wn. near end of this week, &amp; will stay there a day or two <hi rend="italic">en route</hi>. I have seen <hi rend="italic">no one, here, </hi>save Hamilton. Am (again) busy on my spns. for Kew. If I hear from you during wk. will write next Sy: but do not write if soon coming this way. With kind regards &amp; best wishes</p>
         <p>Believe me Yours faithy.—</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>Weather, dull, <hi rend="italic">close</hi>, little rain this mg.—more (I hope) coming.</p>
         <p>I think I told you of my eldest son’s daughter (10–11 yrs)—her long suffering from that horrid influenza, of 8–9 months ago: well, he <hi rend="italic">now </hi>writes— “The least extra exertion brings on spasms of the heart. I took her up to Dr. Sanson last wk. (of course, tho’ only 2 hours from London, we two had to go up one day &amp; home the next). His verdict was—‘the heart was in a very bad state, but there was hope, he had had as bad a case before, which had recovered as far as ordinary life was concerned, tho’ the mischief was <hi rend="italic">always there</hi>! at same time he had cases which ended fatally. This La Grippe <hi rend="italic">left such extraordy. weakness behind it </hi>that the victims had not much chance. Still (he said) there was a glimmering of hope’:—and that is something to us, who are low in that commodity, heaven knows.” [I have quoted verbatim, that you &amp; Mrs H. might know of <hi rend="italic">others</hi>].</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
