<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0822">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 March 4: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-03-04">1892 March 4</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 March 4: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-577" place="foot" n="577"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Private &amp; Confidential.</p>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke, March 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., 1892.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>Having spare time I must now “brace up my loins” and reply to that portion respecting myself of your very kind and truly friendly letter of the 14<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. ulto., which (in my replying thereto) was purposely omitted. But I find myself in a similar fix (as you mention in your writing on the subject), <hi rend="italic">we </hi>(<hi rend="underline italic">two</hi>) could <hi rend="italic">talk well </hi>on it, pro &amp; con,—but to write is quite another thing. You say (in conclusion)— “Most of these considerations <hi rend="italic">must </hi>have occurred to you, &amp; doubtless you have <hi rend="italic">not </hi>omitted to make provisions for many of the contingencies referred to.” I regret to say (knowing that this will <hi rend="italic">grieve </hi>you) that <hi rend="italic">such is </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">not</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> the case</hi>; and mainly (of <hi rend="italic">late</hi> years) because I did not know of any one in whom I had that <hi rend="italic">necessary reliance</hi>. My oldest son (an M.A. Cam.,) whom I have always striven to support well, and who will come in for much at my decease (per my Will)—is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> a true and hearty friend of mine: our correspondence has never been open and full, but necessarily reserved &amp; distant (especially on his part), a great &amp; heavy grief <hi rend="italic">to me</hi>! Several years ago, in an <hi rend="italic">old Will </hi>(since cancelled) I left <hi rend="italic">all that </hi>to Dr. Hector: then again, in a subsequent one,—to have <hi rend="italic">all papers </hi>put up securely for (say) 50 years after decease, and placed in custody of Col. Museum: and, again, that was subsequently abandoned—save, as a matter of course &amp; of law, my eldest son would inherit, leaving them to take their chance—to the flames! I have become <hi rend="italic">careless </hi>in those matters, seeing I have not been treated well (<hi rend="italic">in reality</hi>) by both Ch. &amp; State—in so saying, including <hi rend="italic">all Powers</hi>! And my <hi rend="italic">Home friends</hi>, most being of nearly same age as myself—cannot, <hi rend="italic">must not</hi>, be troubled <hi rend="italic">re </hi>these matters.—</p>
         <p>Many thoughts have occurred to me:—1. to engage a young fellow from school as clerk or secretary; but then, probably, just when he should become really useful he would leave me, carrying with him all secrets! 2. to engage an educated man from Home—if a really <hi rend="italic">suitable </hi>one could be found. 3. (<hi rend="italic">Don’t </hi>be offended) Had <hi rend="italic">you </hi>determined to return to Napier, a short time ago, I had thought, <hi rend="underline italic">on your doing so</hi>—with your small amount of Printing Employment, to make you a kind of additional subsidiary offer, of (say) £52. per annum for assistance of 1 or 3 days a week, as Secretary. But I would not dare to mention this to you so as to make it (small though it was) a kind of bait—or a few extra grains to turn to the beam.</p>
         <p>You kindly go on to say:— “Your friends—<hi rend="italic">and you have perhaps more than you know</hi>—would never cease to grieve if, when the time comes that takes you from us, much of your life’s work should be scattered &amp; dissipated”. Thank <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, again, for that: you do tell me <hi rend="italic">news</hi>—and <hi rend="italic">good tidings </hi>too. I fear, however, you are over sanguine in this matter. <hi rend="underline italic">Who are they</hi>?</p>
         <p>Now I much wish to make a <hi rend="italic">fresh</hi> Will; it is highly necessary that I should do so, and so it has been for a year past! and yet I am always noting it down on each month’s Agenda paper, and yet deferring it! Why?—–</p>
         <p>1. Because I cannot fix on 2 resident Executors &amp; Trustees. (In my <hi rend="italic">present </hi>Will, Grubb &amp; Knowles hold that office; but Grubb, in whom I have great confidence, is no longer a resident, and I doubt his being able to give the necessary time and attention (especially under <hi rend="italic">this </hi>Government). Now, can you help me in this matter? Give me 2 or 3 names—in the strictest confidence—<hi rend="italic">practical, honest, active, business men</hi>;—their whole work might be supervised and done within 12 months.</p>
         <p>2. Because, for my younger son &amp; his wife, (always wholly maintained by me,) I wish to purchase a Government Annuity, but I am in a fix—whether to do so <hi rend="italic">here</hi> (our Colonial) or in England: and then it would take such a big sum in cash down for (say) £150. per ann. (what I now allow him), or (say) that sum with £50. separate to his wife, and so caring for <hi rend="italic">both</hi>. </p>
         <p>But this, after all, is of smaller consideration at present,—as I could always instruct my Executors &amp; Trustees to do it immediately after my decease; and <hi rend="italic">while I live it is better as it now is</hi> (my ½-yearly remitting); besides the longer it is left, the less, of course, it would cost. Moreover, I have seen, in the <hi rend="italic">last</hi> quarterly issue of the “Postal Guide,” (last &amp; <hi rend="italic">new </hi>page,) a long statement <hi rend="italic">re </hi>moneys <hi rend="italic">lent </hi>to our Government, such receiving 4 and 5% Interest. This astonished me, it being <hi rend="italic">by</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">far </hi>the better plan for me; only, <hi rend="underline italic">Is it safe</hi>? and, What <hi rend="italic">re </hi>further taxation on <hi rend="italic">absentees</hi>?——</p>
         <p rend="center">_______</p>
         <p>I enclose another clipping from N. Californian Paper, sent me in a letter from my good friend Dr. Yates: please return it. On a former occasion I had asked Dr. Y.— “How did such become known to “D.T.” Napier?” he says, he had sent a copy of the paper containing it, to our H. Bay Institute. If <hi rend="italic">this </hi>becomes known in Napier to Swan, Neale &amp; Co., <hi rend="italic">I shall get it hot</hi>! La Grippe is very prominent there but of milder type.</p>
         <p>I have just finished a long letter to Hill at Gisborne. I have still your Paper to read afresh and report on which will come on next. Have lately recd. from Sir J. Hector 2 packets of proofs of my last 4 Botanl. Papers, &amp; have read &amp; returned them. With kindest affect. regards &amp; best wishes, </p>
         <p>Believe me always yours, </p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
       
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
