<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1053">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1898 June 8: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1898-06-08">1898 June 8</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1898 June 8: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-905" place="foot" n="905"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, June 8<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. 1898</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>“A time of <hi rend="italic">war</hi>, &amp; a time of Peace.” So said (truly) the wise ancient! This is a <hi rend="italic">time of war</hi>! Physical, mental, spiritual!—</p>
         <p>Americans &amp; Spaniards—<lb/>Protestantism &amp; Romanism<lb/>Temperance &amp; Truth &amp; Prohibition,<hi rend="doubleunderline underline italic">&amp;c</hi>
            <hi rend="doubleunderline underline">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="center">
            <hi rend="doubleunderline underline">________</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">1</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">st</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi>) In yours of “May 2” you have these words:—</p>
         <p>“I have sometimes thought you were a little <hi rend="italic">hard</hi> on her” [Mrs Featon] <hi rend="underline italic">and similar amateurs</hi> who do their best.”—</p>
         <p>That sentence of yours (<hi rend="italic">one of the most unjust you ever wrote re </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">me</hi>) has burnt—rankled—in my bosom ever since I read it! <hi rend="italic">being the very opposite of what I have been doing largely &amp; increasingly &amp; regardless of expense &amp; loss of time</hi>—for <hi rend="underline italic">many years</hi>: insomuch that I have been found fault with, by friends &amp; acquaintances (visiting me, early &amp; late, and seeing me so engaged)—in answering numerous letters, &amp; in naming many parcels of spns. sent to me for that purpose—among whom, the Dean, Welsh, Fannin, <hi rend="italic">Hill</hi>, Burnett, Eccles, Florance, Knowles, &amp; others.—And <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> must have pretty well known all this</hi>!—(your friend Kirk took good care to be <hi rend="underline italic">paid</hi> for all he did!) I received that letter of yours in the country, &amp; I determined to put you up the Featon correspondence (with others “<hi rend="italic">similar</hi>” &amp; late, <hi rend="italic">handy,</hi>) on my return to Napier, &amp; forward; that <hi rend="italic">you</hi> might have a <hi rend="italic">little ocular</hi> proof of things as they really are. Mrs. F., poor lady! was <hi rend="italic">vastly too assuming</hi>, too ambitious: her <hi rend="italic">work</hi> (of which <hi rend="italic">since</hi> I wrote my long letter to her I have seen vol.I., brought by Hill) <hi rend="underline italic">shows</hi> it (<hi rend="italic">do see it</hi>): &amp; her own letter to me <hi rend="italic">proves it</hi>. And no doubt, my truthful dealing with her in reply (together w. plates sent) drove her—wild or worse! It is the old story of the frog &amp; the ox!—Hence she could not write me an answer; even after a month I was obliged to ask to have plates returned, (I had enclosed w them 4d. p. stamps to pay return postage) and then a <hi rend="italic">bare </hi>note from <hi rend="italic">her husband</hi>, who had never written to me before! and the little parcel made up slovenly (i.e. <hi rend="italic">loosely</hi>) &amp; I think <hi rend="italic">addressed </hi>by her.—I consider myself <hi rend="italic">ill-served</hi> in that matter.—</p>
         <p>And I (am <hi rend="italic">sorry</hi> to have to say) I am just <hi rend="italic">served out</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">same</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">style</hi> by Miss G.H.<note xml:id="ftn3-906" place="foot" n="906"> Georgina Burne Hetley.</note> (or <hi rend="underline italic">her people</hi>), I don’t know any of them:—and I send you this correspce. also: only the booklets I gave her are not to be seen w. letters:—nothing of late years has pleased me more than to seek to be of some assistance to this Botanl. (N. Histy.) direction: <hi rend="italic">Teste</hi>: Presl. Address. Hill told me at Dannevirke, before Soundy and others—what he had <hi rend="italic">that day </hi>done in closing examin. school, pointing out to youth, what they should <hi rend="italic">severally do, correspond w. me</hi>, &amp;c, &amp;c. (I wish you could see <hi rend="italic">him.</hi>) Then, in addition; <lb/>Miss Buchanan &amp; her sisters—<lb/>Miss (name<hi rend="italic">forgotten</hi>—of the family who painted the <lb/>  Marshalls in Athm.)<lb/>—Howlett (<hi rend="italic">very many </hi>packets)<lb/>Athenius Olsen (<hi rend="italic">son</hi> of <hi rend="underline italic">A</hi>. Olsen) <note xml:id="ftn3-907" place="foot" n="907"> actually <hi rend="underline">Othenius</hi> Olsen: He trained as a pupil teacher in Norsewood and in 1899 moved to Gisborne where he taught until retirement in 1946. It was Colenso who urged Andreas Olsen to support his son into teaching. I am grateful to Mrs Joan Fitzmaurice, Othenius Olsen’s daughter, for this information.</note>
            <lb/>Axel Mortensen<lb/>Andrews, Coll. Sch. Whanganui<lb/>Leydell (an entire stranger! 2 days work naming spns.)<lb/>Ethel &amp; Edgar Florance, frequent <lb/>J. Keir, Rangiora, entire stranger, letter (being my second) sent on Monday last,<hi rend="underline italic">9pp. 4to</hi>, an <hi rend="italic">amateur </hi>re Ferns.,—answers. So much in pp.1–4 in my <hi rend="italic">defence</hi>. Do you examine my witnesses: and, please, <hi rend="underline italic">return all</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> within a fortnight</hi>:<hi rend="italic"> no need </hi>to write a letter with them, if busy, or unwell.—</p>
         <p rend="center">_______</p>
         <p>I also <hi rend="italic">felt </hi>a wee bit grieved at your <hi rend="italic">not replying</hi> to my qu. <hi rend="italic">re</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">Costall</hi>, whose letter I also sent you (<hi rend="italic">please return it</hi>)—as I wished to know about him: and I have since had a <hi rend="italic">2</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">nd</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> letter</hi> (<hi rend="underline italic">very</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> good indeed</hi>) and I have sent him copies of 3 of my pubd. papers: I should, however, have <hi rend="italic">preferred knowing something of him </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">from you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> first</hi>. </p>
         <p>And (I cannot help thinking) you might have given me some useful advice how to act in the matter of the (unfort.!) Mao. Eng. Lex. spn.—things are as they were! when I wrote to you last month,—only I received at <hi rend="italic">Waipukurau </hi>on <hi rend="italic">20</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>May—the missing parcel of <hi rend="italic">6 copies </hi>which no. I had particularly begged of Mackay: and strange to say, it only bore Wpu. post stamp! I saw the P.M. about it, he sd. he had also noticed it being <hi rend="italic">without</hi> P.O. stampg., &amp; had called his assist. to witness it, but could not explain it.—On my return to N. I did what I promised My, overhauled correspdce. &amp; gave point blank denial to Mackay’s— “I had only ordered <hi rend="italic">300</hi> copies, in March/95”!!! In March/96 w. <hi rend="italic">first</hi> proofs I ord. of Costall <hi rend="italic">500</hi> copies, &amp; recommended him to ask Govt. if they reqd. any. (The letter of ’95, to which Mackay referred me, as contg. order for <hi rend="italic">300</hi>—was my <hi rend="italic">first </hi>note to Seddon, on receipt of Capt. Russell’s &amp; Seddon’s <hi rend="italic">w. </hi>R. re <hi rend="italic">that </hi>£20: &amp; did not, <hi rend="italic">could </hi>not, contain any order for number.) As M. was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> in off. <hi rend="italic">then</hi>, could any thing have been <hi rend="italic">added </hi>to it? I have the copy.—I am <hi rend="italic">now</hi> thinking of writing to S. <hi rend="italic">direct</hi>, to have my <hi rend="underline italic">share</hi> sent me.</p>
         <p rend="center">_________</p>
         <p>I sent you 2 “Heralds” (as you said you don’t see our N. papers now) of <hi rend="italic">late</hi>, the Sp. war, &amp; the Prohibitionist War has been the talk, &amp; scribbling of the time. Right glad was I to see such a phalanx of N. <hi rend="underline italic">head</hi> men come out <hi rend="italic">in favour of Emerson</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">against</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> that wretched creature </hi>(w. brow of brass, &amp; heart of hate) <hi rend="underline italic">Taylor</hi>! Such, should be <hi rend="italic">cast in costs</hi>:—I have little doubt of <hi rend="underline italic">Oliver</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>Dean being T’s. <hi rend="italic">secret</hi> informant <hi rend="italic">here</hi>: may he, too, get his <hi rend="italic">deserts</hi>.—</p>
         <p>And, <hi rend="italic">lastly</hi>, to your recent letter of the 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. inst. (long expected!) there is much in it,— “food for thought”, with <hi rend="italic">me</hi>. I am sorry for your skin ailment, wh., causing so much extreme constant pain, irritation, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">must </hi>interfere w. your duty: you mention “<hi rend="italic">Vinolia</hi>” as offering relief: I should recommend the <hi rend="italic">Coal-Tar</hi> soap—A few years ago I had a letter from a friend in Engd., who was suffering in a <hi rend="italic">similar manner</hi>, &amp; was <hi rend="italic">cured</hi> by the com. use of <hi rend="italic">C.T.</hi> soap: moreover <hi rend="italic">this </hi>seems <hi rend="italic">reasonable</hi>: <hi rend="italic">not </hi>so <hi rend="italic">V. </hi>soap!—Further: <hi rend="italic">I don’t like </hi>your thoughts of coming to Meeanee low flats, at <hi rend="italic">this season</hi> of the year, <hi rend="italic">merely to be at “The Golden Wedding</hi>”! You &amp; young may pay dearly for it: it seems to me so <hi rend="italic">unreasonable</hi>: the <hi rend="italic">place</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">time</hi> (you, too, scarcely seated in your saddle!) Parlt. opening!—and the risk—in travelling to &amp; fro, with possible consequences. If such an assembly of the Clan Harding could be held at the <hi rend="underline italic">big</hi> manor house (I go by Report) at Mt. Vernon—saving too ¼ distance then you <hi rend="italic">might </hi>reasonably think of it. I trust you will <hi rend="italic">not </hi>come on—though I should be glad to see you here, under <hi rend="italic">different </hi>circumstances &amp; <hi rend="italic">not</hi> in a merely flying visit.</p>
         <p>Shall I laugh? or shall I weep? over the wretched stupid “Bishop precedence” correspdce. worst of all that from Walters “<hi rend="underline italic">MA</hi>” Ugh! But I do not <hi rend="italic">know</hi> the <hi rend="underline italic">cause</hi>, can only guess it. Am very sorry to see those doubly wretched doings (as sent by you) in Lond. Churches: however, let <hi rend="italic">them</hi> go on! ’twill, I trust, only hasten the <hi rend="italic">denouement</hi>—long deferred, &amp; surely coming. I have seen in a L. Ch. Newspr. the <hi rend="italic">reply</hi> of the 2 Eng. Abps. to Cardl. Vaughan—and I approve of it—in the main. I trust you may see it, it is short &amp; to the point: they <hi rend="italic">fully</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">heartily</hi> agree w. Arts. &amp; Canons Ch. of E.—<hi rend="italic">re</hi> Transubn., Mass, &amp;c &amp;c—–I lent my lot to <hi rend="italic">Grant</hi>, who agrees w. me (or I w. him)—I would I knew more friends <hi rend="italic">like him</hi>: I had a <hi rend="italic">cap</hi>. L. from him last wk. (I preached <hi rend="italic">twice</hi> at Wpu. on 22<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi> good congns., it was an <hi rend="italic">effort</hi>—but I was strengthened (generally so, tho’ I often go w. trembling!)—&amp; had a job to walk back at night—to hotel, it being so <hi rend="italic">very dark</hi>.) Grant wishes me to <hi rend="italic">revisit</hi> Wpu., &amp; so do some others.</p>
         <p>Hill had a terrible time of trial a fortnight ago—he retd. on a Saturday by nt. train, found his young <hi rend="italic">neice</hi> visitor from Xt.Ch. for her health rather unwell, called in Dr. &amp; soon found she was <hi rend="italic">near </hi>death, &amp; indeed died next day! so unexpected: H. wrote to me broken-hearted: poor dear man!</p>
         <p>Gladdened daily in hearing of the Am. successes agt. the Spaniards, may S. be brought <hi rend="italic">very low</hi>—for her old <hi rend="italic">national</hi> sins. I see Queen Christine is about to follow suit of “Empress” (Ugh!) Eugenie, &amp; take care of herself in time—though <hi rend="italic">no other </hi>comparisons ’tween the 2 women. I devoutly hope the war may <hi rend="italic">not</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">spread </hi>among other Europn. (and <hi rend="italic">S. Am.</hi>) states. What a serious time of upheaval &amp; discontent all over the world! I shall enclose a note of yours that you may <hi rend="underline italic">see</hi> your <hi rend="italic">own date</hi>! Homer sometimes “<hi rend="italic">nods</hi>”.</p>
         <p>You say, in your last, that <hi rend="italic">my last </hi>to you was “the <hi rend="italic">brightest</hi> you ever had from me”!!! and I have <hi rend="italic">not</hi> the <hi rend="italic">slightest</hi> recolln. <hi rend="italic">of it</hi>: this is <hi rend="italic">wholly true</hi>, and is a remnant of my hurt at Wdv. last year, latent memories failing <hi rend="italic">fast</hi>: physical health &amp; strength better, though <hi rend="italic">not so good </hi>as when inland; <hi rend="italic">loss </hi>of many <hi rend="italic">small </hi>comforts <hi rend="italic">here</hi>.—–</p>
         <p>Allanson (“<hi rend="underline italic">Missioner</hi>”) is <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, at St. Aug’s. carrying-on, but I have nothing to do w. him: I <hi rend="italic">don’t like</hi> proceedings of that kind: it matters not to me, whether <hi rend="italic">infra</hi> or <hi rend="italic">extra</hi>, from orthodox Ch., or heterodox—Soltan, or Allanson, or – – –. Have seen too much (and read <hi rend="italic">more</hi>), and am doubtful of all <hi rend="italic">false lights</hi>, however plausible &amp; alluring: the <hi rend="italic">warnings</hi> of Xt., and of His Apostles, <hi rend="italic">throughout</hi> N.T., are too little attended to by even professing good Xn. people. A., I heard, <hi rend="italic">pleased </hi>at Waipukuu., in my Evg’s. S. there, I warned them of the seed sown on rocky ground, spg. <hi rend="italic">early &amp; well</hi>—but—the cares, the riches, the pleasures of this O.—if withered away, &amp;c &amp;c. May you &amp; I, my good friend, be <hi rend="italic">kept faithful </hi>to the <hi rend="italic">truth</hi> as known by us, &amp; grow in gr. &amp; the love of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>.—–</p>
         <p>Am <hi rend="italic">rather</hi> too lonely (explain this—in <hi rend="underline italic">seeing</hi> (human beings) as well as in hearing.) here—have only had <hi rend="italic">1</hi> visitor since return, &amp; that Mr. Burnett from Woodville. I saw Mr. Paterson, in town, <hi rend="italic">first </hi>time since Xmas., he <hi rend="italic">seemed </hi>very worn &amp; thin; &amp; said, he would call on me before he left for Gisborne: weather this week (3 days) constant rain, is against his coming hither.</p>
         <p>By the way let me tell you of a <hi rend="italic">nasty </hi>error in my booklet;—found out by <hi rend="italic">me </hi>while inland, at p.17. “<hi rend="underline">ob</hi>taineth” for <hi rend="underline">con</hi>taineth”, near end of p., quotn. too!! I find it was <hi rend="italic">orig. ptd. </hi>correct in<hi rend="italic"> </hi>“<hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>” &amp; of course in ptd. copy: it vexed me considy. I have not said half of my say, but must close.–</p>
         <p>Hope Mrs. Harding &amp; family are all well, &amp; that <hi rend="italic">you will act reasonably </hi>&amp; so take care of yourself—for their sakes—</p>
         <p>And, I am yours, <hi rend="italic">lovingly</hi>
         </p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
