<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0760">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1890 December 25: to Taylor White</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Papers-11282.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/75006/">Taylor White</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1890-12-25">1890 December 25</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1890 December 25: to Taylor White<note xml:id="ftn3-501" place="foot" n="501"> ATL MS-Papers-11282.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>(copy)</p>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Decr. 25, 1890.</p>
         <p>Taylor White, Esq.,<lb/>Wimbledon.</p>
         <p>Dear Sir</p>
         <p>Your note of the 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst. reached me here just as I had returned from Dannevirke, where I had been some time sojourning: writing (as you remark) at this time, I would reciprocate your kind wishes, and sincerely wish you all the compliments of the Season.—</p>
         <p>Re your enquiry as to the meaning of the word, “Mokokuri,”—I have but little to say (in a note)—it means,—an inferior or commoner or courser or less-elaborate kind of face tattoo. <hi rend="italic">Kuri </hi>is added, adjectively, to several words in Maori, generally meaning as above—(having nothing to do with the <hi rend="italic">Kuri </hi>= dog,) much indeed like our English use of the term <hi rend="italic">horse</hi>—as in horse-chestnut, horse-mint, horse mussel, horse-mackeral, horse-laugh, &amp;c.</p>
         <p>From your note I gather, you are going to write <hi rend="italic">again</hi> on the Maori Dog. I fear I shall run the risk of displeasing you in saying,— “think twice before you do so,”—or you will greatly err. At all events <hi rend="italic">first </hi>read my exhaustive paper on that subject, in vol. x. Trans.N.Z. Inst.—</p>
         <p>Sir G. Grey, and Dr. (now Sir James) Hector made, years ago, similar mistakes, as, I believe, you have done.</p>
         <p>I hope you are keeping well. I am not very well just now, and so am solitary at home, and thus writing <hi rend="italic">this night </hi>to you, to be in time for your mail leaving here on 29<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. I expect to leave again for the Bush about the 10<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. of Jany.</p>
         <p>I am, yours truly</p>
         <p>(signed) W. Colenso</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>