<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0892">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1894 January 18: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1894-01-18">1894 January 18</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1894 January 18: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-672" place="foot" n="672"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">(finally closed, 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>.)<lb/>Napier, Jany. 18/94</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>I think I will <hi rend="italic">begin </hi>(at all events) my letter to <hi rend="italic">you </hi>this night—as I don’t <hi rend="italic">feel able</hi> for anything requiring exertion—physical or mental. – – –</p>
         <p>And, <hi rend="underline italic">first</hi>, to thank you heartily for your last good long &amp; most interesting letter of the 10<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst., which I have read 3 times, &amp; shall again!—also, to acknowledge receipt (this day) of L. Brassey’s <hi rend="italic">gilded </hi>cuts (pamphlet) &amp; your addl. clippings, for which I thank you—the big one, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Xanth. &amp; Soc. caused me to laugh outright! a rare thing nowadays for this old Hermit to do!—</p>
         <p>The little plant spn. you enclosed is <hi rend="italic">not </hi>“Churlock”, though much like it, (there are several of these <hi rend="italic">small </hi>closely allied Cruciferous plants that <hi rend="italic">prima facie </hi>are much alike;) this one sent is “Common Hedge Mustard” = <hi rend="italic">Sisymbrium officianale</hi>—but <hi rend="italic">not </hi>belonging to the same genus as our <hi rend="italic">Mustards</hi> (3): “Churlock = Wild Mustard = <hi rend="italic">Sinapis arvensis</hi>”—is a <hi rend="italic">larger </hi>flowered plant, flrs. also darker yellow, with swollen pads bearing a long 2-edged beak: it is <hi rend="italic">very plentiful </hi>here among wheat, &amp;c—fields quite brilliant with it nr. Hastings.—This spn. you have sent is also <hi rend="italic">common </hi>here.—–</p>
         <p>I like to read of your noticing <hi rend="italic">our Brit. plants </hi>(“weeds”—if you like the term better): I often do the same, every yr. as the seasons come round; I dare say you know the <hi rend="italic">Pimpernel </hi>it is now well-established here in my paddock, and with it 2–3–4 British <hi rend="italic">Geraniums</hi>: <hi rend="italic">G. molle </hi>a great favourite of mine. For several years a low trailing plant of the Mallow family throwing out <hi rend="underline italic">long</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>rooting stems has been firmly fixed here—rather too common: at first (4–5 yrs. back) I worked <hi rend="italic">hard &amp; long</hi> in my cloak in the winter-spring days, digging it up w. a trowel wishing to extirpate it—and feared the horses would not touch it—but I have since found they will eat it w. others;—but it has small red <hi rend="italic">pretty </hi>flowers—reminding me (<hi rend="italic">prim. fac.</hi>) ’mong herbiage, of <hi rend="italic">pimpernel</hi>: it is curious, too, in its seed vessels, &amp;c., it may be a Madiola—a S. Am. genus, w. which I am unacqd.—I shall enclose a bit. Ere I drop Botany—I may <hi rend="italic">tell you</hi>—this aftn. I opened the big parcel contg. “Index Kewensis,” <hi rend="italic">I Fascic. </hi>(“A.–Dend.”) 730 p.p., an astonishing amount of labour—mentl. &amp; physl., I shall have to cut it (top-edge); I don’t like the <hi rend="italic">very thin </hi>p. it is ptd. on; it is scarcely 1½in. thick: I have looked in, here &amp; there, &amp; I am pleased in finding <hi rend="italic">many </hi>of my early described N.Z. plants have stood the test—and are <hi rend="italic">therein as bona fid. </hi>species. The wk. however does not come down later than <hi rend="italic">1885</hi>—and does <hi rend="italic">not </hi>include any crypts., not even Ferns!—Have you any <hi rend="italic">garden</hi> ground attached to your house? my <hi rend="italic">Clianthus puniceus </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">vera</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>(the N. form, or <hi rend="underline italic">species</hi>, both described by me fully in vol. XVIII, Trans. p.291) has just ripened seed, &amp; I could send you a pod; it differs from our (&amp; your) S. one; I had the seeds of this from Judge Gillies.</p>
         <p>I suppose you will have recd. a copy “Herald” I sent you cntg my <hi rend="italic">long</hi> letter re <hi rend="italic">floods</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">
               <note xml:id="ftn3-673" place="foot" n="673"> Floods. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> 16 January 1894. </note>
            </hi>—&amp; I hope you were interested in it. Nearly a fort. ago I asked Ed. if he wod. insert, <hi rend="underline italic">or</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>“return, unused”: a very kind reply— “<hi rend="italic">insert</hi>”; but I had never intended it to be so long—&amp; when I exhumed my old Jl. (rough draft copy)—I was surprised to see I had scribbled so much!—and then I was 8–10 days over it—owing to <hi rend="italic">this </hi>lumbago—writing much of it in pain &amp; misery!—and when I sent it in (Monday 15<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. IV. p.m.) I apologized, &amp; asked—to pub. in 2–3 parts in Daily—but as <hi rend="italic">one </hi>in Wkly., &amp; for 1 doz. copies, <hi rend="italic">gratis</hi>. I assure you I was surprised on Tuesday mg. to <hi rend="italic">see it all there—plus</hi>, few errors <hi rend="italic">of course</hi>: in yestys. “Herald,” the Ed. noticed that <hi rend="italic">one </hi>glaring error—“<hi rend="italic">patent</hi>” for “<hi rend="italic">potent</hi>”:—it is not often in our Eng. l. that the alteration of a <hi rend="italic">single </hi>letter causes the <hi rend="italic">opposite</hi>; tho com. enough in Maori.—I sent a copy to Dr. H., &amp; would have sent one to A. Luff, but I <hi rend="italic">think </hi>he takes in the “<hi rend="italic">Hd</hi>.”</p>
         <p>A few <hi rend="italic">old </hi>documents came up from the Mummy Vault w. that portion of Jl., some of them I should like <hi rend="italic">you </hi>to see. <hi rend="italic">e.g. </hi>a curious letter written by <hi rend="italic">Hapuku </hi>himself, chg. me with murder planned—of him! &amp; declg. war—on me; &amp; my ansr. thereto, denying &amp; then we duly met, &amp; had 4 hours!—a true-scene: the copy of my offl. letter to Col. Secy. in ’62, in reply to an <hi rend="italic">abom. </hi>letter from Bp. Williams to the Govt., against my remaining at Waitangi!! w. <hi rend="italic">enclosures</hi>—I fancy if he (the Bp.) saw it—he would – – – However, to cut it short, I gained the day! I had <hi rend="italic">wholly forgotten </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">this</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>matter, &amp; also others allied thereto—in conn. w. Archd. Sam.—[some day <hi rend="italic">you may </hi>see them—If, as you say, <hi rend="italic">you are coming </hi>this way, &amp; the O.M. still alive.]—I wished to let the <hi rend="italic">Clivites</hi> see, that they were not the <hi rend="italic">only sufferers </hi>by floods;—that there had been <hi rend="italic">far</hi> severer ones; that, <hi rend="italic">in my case, </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">no</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> aid—</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">no</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> subscripn. </hi>&amp; my pay then <hi rend="italic">very small</hi>! I had to “grin &amp; bear”: &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">out of all</hi>—<hi rend="doubleunderline underline italic">Delivered</hi>!!</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Re </hi>“Tidal Lore”—I sent you ½ dz. <hi rend="italic">for yourself, </hi>&amp; to sell, if appln. made. I have 100’ds here on the groaning shelf, also, of “Jubilee P.” &amp;c.—By the way I should much like to place 2–3 copies of each of those printed here in the 2 Libs. there w. you, &amp; will send them <hi rend="italic">to you</hi> for that purpose if you are agreeable.</p>
         <p>One item you <hi rend="italic">omitted</hi>—I wished to get from you yr. opin., <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Malcolm’s &amp; Steele’s letter and my reply (1.) Bec. my <hi rend="italic">reply </hi>to S., much like that in yr. Wgn. P. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Ebenezer Baker: (2.) Did <hi rend="italic">you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">know </hi>Malcolm—kpg. sch. at Port? (3) <hi rend="italic">Strange </hi>conduct—no ackngt. of 2 photos.—It seemed <hi rend="italic">strange</hi> you never even alluded to them! <hi rend="italic">Why </hi>did I send them to you? <hi rend="italic">Ditto</hi>:—<hi rend="italic">re </hi>Circular from <hi rend="italic">R. </hi>Sy.—–</p>
         <p>I agree w. you—<hi rend="italic">re </hi>editls. “D.T.” Hospital Drs., <hi rend="underline italic">&amp;c</hi>—<hi rend="italic">too much of it</hi>. In “D.T.” this evg. the death of Mrs. Grubb—did you or Mrs. Harding know the lady? Dr. Reed, Waipukurau, is coming to reside in Cl. Sq., F. Tiffin’s ho., having purchased it.</p>
         <p>I am <hi rend="italic">still</hi> a prisoner from my old foe! only been 3 times to town since my last,—&amp; of them <hi rend="italic">twice </hi>to Augustine’s: Sy. nt., 7<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., <hi rend="italic">obliged </hi>to go to take Service, driven in trap—climbed hill <hi rend="underline italic">w. gt. diffy</hi>. Sy. nt., 14<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., being fine, &amp; I easier, I went again to hear new Mr. (first time)—sat in misery—returned w. diffy.!</p>
         <p>19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. (night.) I now proceed: this day a day of steady rain, no wind, doing great good, to dried soil, &amp; bringing down temp, which was <hi rend="italic">very high. </hi>Late last nt., 2 letters!! one from Can. St. Hill,—Clerical Meeting at Havelock on 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. wish me to attend—I fear <hi rend="italic">not</hi>, &amp; so have replied: one from Fielder—meetg. in St. John’s School-room My. nt., 29<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—to make “<hi rend="italic">presentation</hi>” to Bp., am asked to be present: “<hi rend="italic">Yes</hi>”: reply, but what is this “<hi rend="italic">presentation</hi>”?—–</p>
         <p>This mg. closely engd. in repairing old broken books, worked steadily till near noon—in constant back pain! but <hi rend="italic">did </hi>my fixed job: am easier this evg. Last nt. I met w. a passage in “Standard”, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>your (<hi rend="italic">or our</hi>) late friend Blades, which I thought would interest you, so have posted the p. I have also to thank you for your “<hi rend="italic">Calendar</hi>, ’94”—but I wished you had <hi rend="italic">not</hi> troubled yourself to send it as I have <hi rend="italic">more than a dozen</hi> already, all sorts &amp; sizes! From <hi rend="italic">Whitelaw</hi>, I<hi rend="italic"> </hi>think, 7! (sizes)—wrote to him, asking, “If I should return ½ doz.?” a neat reply— “NO”. There must be an enormous number of these things wasted! Do you know of any Almanac (<hi rend="italic">Colonial</hi>), contg. <hi rend="italic">planetary movements</hi>, &amp;c. like yours of old? I had <hi rend="italic">again </hi>spoken to P. Dinn. about it, and to employ your F.—but to no effect: I much wish I were <hi rend="italic">nearer</hi> to yr. F., or he to me. I have got hold of an excellent story! to cap our Maori saurian legends:—I found it in Vertot’s “Knights of Malta”, (2 <hi rend="italic">fol</hi>. vols. w. engravings (<hi rend="italic">good</hi>) of <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the Grand Masters, ptd. 1728: Lond.)—a <hi rend="italic">full </hi>account of the slaying of a <hi rend="italic">Dragon</hi> (or Serpent) by one of the G.M., a strange story—but <hi rend="italic">fully authenticated</hi>! it has pleased me much. I intend to make a <hi rend="italic">Paper </hi>of it—just to supplement <hi rend="italic">those</hi>. There is some excellent reading in these vols.—Popes, Kings, Emperors, Grand Masters are <hi rend="italic">not </hi>spared! Vertot, too, being one of the fraternity,—I should think—a <hi rend="italic">Chaplain</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I like the clipping <hi rend="italic">re </hi>“Dying in Harness”; much therein I agree with. I have had some <hi rend="italic">extra </hi>trouble here! Do you recollect a nice plot of ground, just beyond &amp; under my little gate on the <hi rend="italic">brow</hi>—w. 2 stone steps? well, a fortnight ago, down went a frightful lot—w., of course fence &amp; all! hundreds of tons! <hi rend="italic">smashing</hi> outhouses below &amp; a chimney, &amp;c, &amp;c., (late W. Thomas’)—of course owing to <hi rend="italic">his</hi>—or <hi rend="italic">their</hi>—former rash excavating: this is 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. or 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. slip <hi rend="italic">there</hi>—losing more than ¼ ac. of ground, and now obliged to erect a new fence not far (in front) from the old seat!!</p>
         <p rend="end">
            <hi rend="italic">Good Night..</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">20</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi> again! I have read yr. letter <hi rend="italic">twice </hi>more! it contains such a <hi rend="italic">fund</hi> of “<hi rend="italic">news</hi>”. <hi rend="italic">Re </hi>your remark on Smales correcting my erroneous Maori (as S. says), I never knew <hi rend="italic">of it—never heard of it</hi>: I recollect, when at Auckland and, hearing of a <hi rend="italic">Gideon </hi>Smales living <hi rend="italic">retired </hi>there in the suburbs—I suppose, the same person.—–</p>
         <p>Your account of yr. ptg. off. staff has interested me greatly: of course you will print my little order <hi rend="italic">at yr. leisure. </hi>You surprise me w. your remarks re Morris &amp; <hi rend="italic">our art.</hi>—a centy. hence!! I can hardly venture to write about your dear afflicted son—Victor: May <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>—<hi rend="italic">our Father</hi>—give <hi rend="italic">you </hi>(<hi rend="underline italic">all</hi>) whatever you may <hi rend="italic">require</hi>—“G. moves in mysterious way,” &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>     “Behind a frowning providence<lb/>              He hides a smiling face.”</p>
         <p>Last nt. I recd. a letter from a gent. down S. who had read <hi rend="italic">your</hi> report<hi rend="italic"> </hi>of our Paper in Wgn. P.—he thanks me for the <hi rend="italic">Paper</hi> (you read) &amp; will look ford. to see it in “Trans”.—he naïvely asks (or says) “Why was 2. p. published in last vol? <hi rend="italic">only </hi>bec. it was transld. by <hi rend="italic">Miss. B. </hi>&amp; introd. by <hi rend="underline italic">Sir</hi> W.B.!! &amp; seems to indicate—much had <hi rend="italic">therefore </hi>been said about it. And <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, this aftn., in looking into a no. “Proceedings Linn. Socy.” Octr./93, (to hand last night) I find the <hi rend="italic">death </hi>of “Jean Louis Armand de Q.” in Jany./92—I <hi rend="italic">suppose </hi>the same person! I, in my ignorance! had hoped Q. would <hi rend="italic">see </hi>my p.—if pubd. (Just as it was in the case w. Owen!) I sent you, <hi rend="italic">this mg</hi>., a “Herald”, contg. a mare’s-nest—re<hi rend="italic"> </hi>a Volcano—another story, nicely met. And I shall send you a long clipping (lately sent to me) re <hi rend="italic">Mr. Aldred </hi>wh. also has on its back, obsns. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the Libel case: Aldred I knew a little of.—And I shall put up w. it H. Jones’ <hi rend="italic">lot</hi>!—</p>
         <p>Another <hi rend="italic">item </hi>I had enqd. after—is “<hi rend="underline italic">Grongar Hill</hi>”, an old poem, learned by me in childhood—<hi rend="italic">do you know the author</hi>?<note xml:id="ftn3-674" place="foot" n="674"> John Dyer 1726: <hi rend="italic">Grongar Hill</hi>.</note>
         </p>
         <p>I am pleased w. yr. remark on Taylor Wh’s. letter in connex. w. my p. in vol. XII:—but I felt surprised at what follows, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Tregear&amp; <hi rend="italic">his </hi>p. in vol XXV.—you <hi rend="underline italic">truly</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> say </hi>, “T. made use of the whole store of phill. informn. I had collected on the subject:”—but, in yr. adding, “and <hi rend="italic">named me as his authority</hi>”—you <hi rend="underline italic">greatly err</hi>! T took <hi rend="italic">good care </hi>(as in his former papers) to do <hi rend="italic">nothing </hi>of the kind! If you look &amp; comp. carefully you will find it to be so: true, he mentions me specially in 2–3 places, but not as he should have done; and in <hi rend="italic">one </hi>place in partr. quotes <hi rend="italic">a bit </hi>of a sentence (somewhat like Q.!) to suit his own views, &amp; so makes me there to say what I had never intended (see p. 425). “Mr. C. says—that the Moa in genl. appearance somewhat resembled an immense dom. cock.” I sd. <hi rend="italic">that</hi>—&amp; a great <hi rend="italic">deal more</hi> (see XII/64). I have often of late years (40–50) wished I had never written <hi rend="italic">that </hi>about <hi rend="italic">the Cock</hi>, or (better perhaps) had <hi rend="italic">explained </hi>it.—Dr. H. early tackled me w. it. Now, it came out in this way: at E. Cape, in Jany. ’38,—in getting all the informn. I could over the few bones, <hi rend="italic">and </hi>Moa bone fishooks—<hi rend="italic">then in use, my own 2 Mao. lads w. me from the Bay, </hi>put in a word, “me he tikaokao, pea?—to help out the ½ doz. (or more) local ideas of it—but “a Cock <hi rend="italic">w. face like a man</hi>,” &amp;c &amp;c. N.B. the term “Cock” came from <hi rend="italic">those 2</hi>, who <hi rend="italic">alone</hi>, of all the 100d’s. of M. present had <hi rend="italic">ever </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">seen</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> a “Cock”</hi>: and <hi rend="underline italic">then</hi>, I, on the other hand, <hi rend="underline italic">believed</hi> in their immigration myth, &amp; so used the term, w. “Cassowary”, &amp; the further Polynesians: moreover, my knowledge of Maori was small (just 3 yrs. in the land, &amp; wkg. <hi rend="italic">hard </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">daily</hi>!) and, further, the N. Maoris had <hi rend="italic">never even </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">heard</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> of the Moa—no </hi>bones found <hi rend="italic">there</hi>: Polack, who had lived yrs. in <hi rend="italic">the Bay</hi>, <hi rend="italic">first </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">only </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">heard</hi> of such <hi rend="italic">when at Tolaga</hi>—obliged to stay there as his Vessel was lost; and (as I lately told Hamilton) P. <hi rend="italic">never brought away a single bone </hi>(if indeed he ever <hi rend="italic">saw </hi>any!) which I am sure (<hi rend="italic">knowing him</hi>) he would have done for sale,—as a Jew collector of curios, &amp;c.—Tregear (unwittingly, perhaps?) has too often come out in <hi rend="italic">that way—</hi>just like that “Brain-sucker” (Seth Smith) to use yr. old friend’s term (Sir W. Fox),—as I had pointed out to you <hi rend="italic">re </hi>my paper on M. <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi>—&amp; sent you at the time an author’s copy—but <hi rend="underline italic">no reply</hi>! I have <hi rend="italic">since</hi> seen Seth S. <hi rend="italic">at it </hi>again, in a paper in vol. XXV, and even in the item of Rangitoto (vid. “3 Lity. Papers”) where I had exposed <hi rend="italic">Dr. </hi>Purchase’s notion <hi rend="italic">re </hi>same (&amp; so silenced <hi rend="italic">him</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Seth </hi>comes out <hi rend="italic">again</hi>, endeavouring to rehabilitate the old story (of the Colonists!) saying, an old Maori had told him &amp;c &amp;c of a bloody fight there, &amp;c &amp;c. And <hi rend="italic">such </hi>(as Tregear shows,) is received! &amp; <hi rend="italic">goes down w. them</hi>—that party, Travers, McDonnell, Field, &amp; Co. Try to make out my meaning—I am a little vexed, more tired, careless, &amp; in pain.</p>
         <p>As there are a <hi rend="italic">few</hi> items in this letter I should like to have noticed, (just as if we were conversing)—I will go over this long letter &amp; touch each of them w. <hi rend="underline italic">red</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> ink</hi>. This is Saty nt., and I have not been out for this wk—save just in front of door, but I am much better today—<hi rend="italic">can </hi>walk about house <hi rend="italic">without </hi>my <hi rend="italic">trusty </hi>stick!—but don’t intend to go to Ch. tomorrow.</p>
         <p>Do not you think, either of ansg. <hi rend="italic">quickly</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">largely</hi> (as in yr. last)—no need of <hi rend="italic">that</hi>. You cannot afford to come out in <hi rend="italic">that </hi>way. Your <hi rend="italic">time</hi> is too precious, too useful.—I <hi rend="italic">may </hi>say—I have nothing to do, and so may scribble away to you—though I cannot <hi rend="italic">now </hi>write fast. S.F. Mail <hi rend="italic">time</hi>, too, is “<hi rend="italic">close </hi>aboard”! once more, “<hi rend="italic">Goodnight</hi>”.</p>
         <p>21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Sunday night</hi>. I now proceed to close my already <hi rend="italic">too long </hi>letter.—This day has been a very fine one—&amp; not too warm. I am still mending, &amp; I hope to go to town on Tuesday. Last evg. Hill sent me, by his daughter, a bag of specimens from our Alpine Dist.—I was in part sorry to rec. them, as I knew I <hi rend="italic">must wk. </hi>at them <hi rend="italic">this mg.</hi>, however I rose early, began viii.15 &amp; finished (unpacking &amp; roughly laying out) by x.15—some good things there—a week’s work! but, alas! &amp; <hi rend="italic">as usual </hi>w. H. in a ½ rotten state.—</p>
         <p>Good bye, kindest regards &amp; best wishes,</p>
         <p>Yours ever,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. Did you personally know this Mr. Morrison, who has been filling Mr. P’s. place here at St. Paul’s?</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
