<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0320">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1876 May 31: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1876-05-31">1876 May 31</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1876 May 31: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn2-264" place="foot" n="264"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand<lb/>May 31/76.</p>
         <p>A. Luff, Esq.</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir</p>
         <p>I have already written to you on 2 &amp; 3 of this mo., &amp; now I am again scribbling! &amp; no letter <hi rend="italic">yet</hi> to hand from you but I hope to get one in the mg. The Mail via S.F. arrived on <hi rend="italic">time</hi>—but the fine new steamer “Australian” passed on without landing <hi rend="italic">our </hi>mail, and <hi rend="italic">I </hi>venture to think her Capt. acted rightly, for the night was both dark &amp; tempestuous, &amp; raining too! &amp; I feared, as I lay in bed, something might happen to her—to the mails or passengers, (going or coming in) if she anchored near us. I think it very wrong to make those large <hi rend="italic">ocean</hi> steamers run down our stormy broken coasts,—and I hope that ere long, that arrangement will be set aside—if only on accounts of its <hi rend="italic">extra </hi>expense.—“Rangatira” left Wgn. with our Eng. Mail last evening @ 5 o’clock, &amp; should have been here I think. This is to leave Napier on 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi> June, so I am obliged to begin writing now. The “Australian” grounded at Port Chalmers in going up the channel, &amp; lay aground until next tide, fortunately without damage. The “Kiwi” also got on “Rangatira” <hi rend="italic">bank</hi> here last week in going out, but after 2 days lightening her (taking-out cargo, &amp;c.) she was got off without injury, &amp; left yesterday for Wgn.—</p>
         <p>Visiting Country Schools, on 8<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst. returning here on night of 28<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., (the next day being Queen’s B.D. &amp; holiday)—found things <hi rend="italic">queer</hi>—the man’s wife being laid up (from the day before!) expecting delivery—&amp; I feared it might prove a serious case, your old Dr. was up &amp; down (weather <hi rend="italic">then</hi> bad too) however on Quns B.D. the stranger came! a girl, &amp; she has not yet been seen by me,—I doing <hi rend="italic">all</hi> the household work within my dwelling, &amp;c. This event <hi rend="italic">may</hi> bring about others in its train: small things often cause larger ones.—But I have wished myself, at <hi rend="italic">Waipukurau </hi>hotel again! This week I should have been at Meeanee Puketapu, &amp;c., but the Sy. weather has kept me at home—we have had a glorious autumn down to 28<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst. inclusive, and though I had some rough adventures in travelling, &amp;c, yet I came <hi rend="italic">through all well</hi> &amp; in good health &amp; spirits,—though I have plenty yet <hi rend="italic">to do</hi> ere Vacation day.—</p>
         <p>At Waipukurau I recd, an Offl. telegram—then to await arrival of the Govt. Commissrs.—Gisborne Seed. Knowles, (Weber, also, who was then inland,)—that interview took place on night of 19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—they had <hi rend="italic">lots </hi>of questions to put &amp; I hope I satisfied them: we shall see by-&amp;-bye what the upshot will be. Speaking of Weber—I may tell you, he is in part provided for—as Engr. of Harbour Works w. his old saly. £600.—the building my 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. wall! E. side of Sn. 108. I am completely moated in now! You will see in “Herald” of 29<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. my letter about a new road<note xml:id="ftn2-265" place="foot" n="265"> This newspaper is not available.</note>—a <hi rend="italic">short </hi>one to Barrack Hill, &amp;c, which should have been done years ago.—There has been some commotion in our town during my absence—a Mrs Wright murdered her little baby (a <hi rend="italic">strange case</hi>)—they built a house adjoining your old office (<hi rend="italic">now</hi> Lascelles’ office &amp; a good one, too,)—and a desperate burglar named Symonds in gaol for <hi rend="italic">10 yrs</hi>! broke away from Miller’s hard labour gang, &amp;, after having been <hi rend="italic">in the town</hi> a whole week! was captured at night in Tiffen’s garden! J. Chambers the good peace-loving Quaker jumping out of bed &amp; out of the window too in his nt. shirt to aid the gardener in his capture: he, or they, may gain the Victorian  for such deeds of daring &amp; valour! From the papers the 2 yg. Sealys at Canterbury have been taking a kind of lesson from H.B.S. the elder, in the Ld. Off. <hi rend="italic">there</hi>: <hi rend="italic">our </hi>Sy. does not like the remarks made, &amp; has come out w. a letter in “Herald”—but it won’t do. P. Dolbel is in more trouble; his nephew (Rd’s. son) had Diptheria &amp; P. in endeavouring to save him, caught the disorder! he has had a time of it for 2–3 wks. both are better, &amp; now his sheep have the “staggers” <hi rend="italic">dreadfully</hi>—2 of his <hi rend="italic">imported</hi> ones dead! Poor P. was here today, looking worn &amp; very sad.—Fannin, too, has more trouble,—2 now of his young children very ill (perhaps same disorder!)—he is wearing out—no rest by night at home. Several children have died of it, &amp; of Fever, <hi rend="italic">not </hi>noticed in papers. Mrs Locke is bettering slowly (going, tomorrow, w. father &amp; mother to hot springs near Auckland); Tylee <hi rend="italic">is </hi>able to come to office. Routledge has resigned the Hon. Secretaryship of H.B. Agl. Society. Donald McL. <hi rend="italic">has </hi>had a <hi rend="italic">long</hi> interview w. his Maori Majesty which (it is said) is likely to be productive of <hi rend="italic">good</hi>. New Buildings going on in town, notably—Masonic Hotel, &amp; <hi rend="italic">2 new shops</hi> where your “L.Ho.” stood &amp; the ground betw. it &amp; Morrison’s—<hi rend="italic">these would surprise you</hi>! McLay’s is a handsome buildg., so is N. &amp; C’s.—with a <hi rend="italic">fine </hi>smooth concrete pavement <hi rend="italic">all round it</hi>—having N. &amp; Close in large black letters in pavement before all entrances! There are to be 4 new hotels in town—McMurray’s nr. Railway Station, one—where Sebley’s old one was—one on reclaimed land at wharf—one by a Scandinavian on Wh. Road; the Empire hotel at Waipawa is to be greatly enlarged, &amp; the old “pound” removed.—The Taradale Road is again put to rights, &amp; to be thrown open tomorrow (1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. June.) Our Parlt. is to meet on 15<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. O. is going <hi rend="italic">early</hi>, no Council now. It is said, in this evg’s. “D.Telegraph” that the Chf. Justice had ruled several pleas in <hi rend="italic">plaintiff’s </hi>favour (Arihi Hiraka <hi rend="italic">v. </hi>Gordon)—what they are, or whether true, I know not (see <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> of June 1). An old settler named Jeremiah Fitzgerald was drowned near Waipawa on Saty. evg. last; I fear he was <hi rend="italic">not sober</hi>. I had a <hi rend="italic">very plentiful </hi>crop of apples from my 2–3 trees this yr., enough for self &amp; for neighbours.—— I have not seen Grubb for some time, he is at Pov. Bay,—the P.M. there having been dismissed.</p>
         <p>                                                                             June 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. I have <lb/>recd. your letter of April 5 &amp; 6—glad to find you were all well. I cannot reply to it fully by this mail—but hope to do so by next. I send you some Papers as usual, which will interest you, I know.—I am tolerably well—obliged to keep a sharp lookout for the enemy, &amp; feeling shaky—no doubt owing (in part) to the large lot of English letters just to hand &amp; which I must answer.</p>
         <p>Good bye &amp; kind regards, Yours truly,</p>
         <p>                             W. Colenso</p>
         <p>P.S. (June 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>.) You know well my situation here <hi rend="italic">as to property</hi>;—what would you <hi rend="italic">advise</hi> me to do, with reference to my returning to England, at (say) end of this year? Give Lyndon power of attorney to receive Rents, &amp;c. (&amp; <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to sell?)—or <hi rend="italic">how</hi>. If <hi rend="italic">Wilson </hi>were here I would ask him. I am thinking of trying Brandon,—<hi rend="italic">viz</hi>. to get his opinion. I would sell all I could,—but there is no market just now—either for Town or Country properties, save <hi rend="italic">picked </hi>ones. Don’t fail to give me your honest <hi rend="italic">valued</hi> opinion. P. Dolbel’s is (I am sorry to say) one of my <hi rend="italic">worst </hi>ones (as to paymts.)—next, Sladen’s, owing to late floods, &amp;c &amp;c; &amp; these two are ½ of my income—leaving out pay as Inspector, which will soon now cease.—W.C.</p>
         <p>P.S. <hi rend="italic">No.2. </hi>Again have I opened my letter. I am thinking of offering <hi rend="italic">all </hi>this hill property in one lot; or, all excepting house <hi rend="underline italic">party</hi> of <hi rend="italic">front</hi> paddock,—I will see Brandon <hi rend="italic">quietly</hi>, &amp; try. It would well suit any <hi rend="italic">capitalist</hi> as an Investment.</p>
         <p>I forgot to say—that Ferard came to Waipukurau with 3 Commissn.—&amp; with him I had a <hi rend="italic">nice</hi> talk,—I never had such w. Ferard before. He &amp; his are going to England, Miss Wilson also:—he has let his house to Gollan for one year certain. J.A.Smith, Cable &amp; Burton (Wairoa) came on to Waipukurau &amp; on to Woodville; they sent a telegram to host P. Gow to prepare for them!!! at table (in com. room) J.A.S. did not like a remark of Cable’s; John put down his K. &amp; f. &amp; sd. vary gravely, to C.,—that “it was consd. a very impertinent thing to contradict in company.” I expected an explosion, but it passed without carnage.——</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>