<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0771">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 March 11: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0495.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-03-11">1891 March 11</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 March 11: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-516" place="foot" n="516"> ATL qMS-0495.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke, March 11/91:<lb/>3 p.m.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Thank you for your long &amp; full letter of the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. inst., recd. by me on the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.—much that you have so kindly written therein I have read w. more than comn. interest, &amp; (in fact) have gone through it <hi rend="italic">3 times</hi>! There is just one drawback to my pleasure &amp; that is, my having been the cause of giving you so much <hi rend="italic">extra</hi> confinement &amp; <hi rend="italic">writing</hi>, and (I fear) keeping you from attending to other &amp; more useful correspondents. As usual, I go with you in so much that you have said, particularly in your truthful yet saddening remarks on the <hi rend="italic">Newspr. Lit.</hi> of the present day! I have <hi rend="italic">often</hi>, of late, ½-determd. to give up taking in both H. &amp; D.T., I may yet do so.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Re</hi> your clipping respg. <hi rend="italic">name</hi> of Port Jackson—I think I may be able to throw some light on that, when I <hi rend="italic">return to N</hi>. Then, w. ref. to Mr Webb &amp; his Library—I regret to say, we are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> on friendly terms <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, and I fear may not again become so—<hi rend="italic">this</hi> being the <hi rend="italic">second</hi> severe falling-out (entirely occasioned by himself), and only 2–3 days after the first (also <hi rend="italic">made by him</hi>) was condoned!</p>
         <p>Your mention of that old &amp; once popular work, the “Arminian Mag”.—aroused a number of <hi rend="italic">old</hi> feelings within me,—for I knew it <hi rend="italic">well—</hi>when a boy &amp; living with my maternal Grandfr.—he had all the vols. &amp;c., indeed, in the still earlier time, (as I had often heard), J. Wy’s. Ministers stayed at his house.</p>
         <p>I left N. on Thursday mg. 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>—for Waipawa: stayed there that day, expecting to see some from the Country—but was disappd. Johnston (Coroner, &amp; “O.C.”) came up rushing on platform to mention his “apology”—in “D.T.” of last mo., re self &amp; Messs. R. Stewart &amp; Wallace; &amp; again I gave him a bit of my mind, as it was <hi rend="italic">erroneous</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">no </hi>“<hi rend="italic">apy</hi>” at all! (I think I sent you a copy <hi rend="italic">at the time</hi>: let me know, if not.) On Friday I came on to this place—in pretty good health—weather too very fine (but only just commenced <hi rend="italic">here</hi>) which has continued ever since:—indeed, it is <hi rend="italic">too hot</hi> for me to venture out, and I <hi rend="italic">dislike</hi> hotel <hi rend="italic">food</hi>, and so I am not so well as I was when I came, and having nothing to employ me, <hi rend="italic">I feel it.—</hi>I could not go out yesty.—too<hi rend="italic">weak </hi>(in knees) &amp; <hi rend="italic">listless</hi>: but early this mg. (IX) I walked to Mr Wallace’s new House, ¾ mile or so, &amp; felt done up! After resting an hour or so I returned, &amp; have been lying down ever since! On Monday I was surprised &amp; sorry to see in “Herald”, that Dean H. Was again taken severely ill on Saty. &amp; so his Doctors prohibited his taking any Ch. duty on Sunday: Parkinson managed, having <hi rend="italic">Arthur</hi> Williams (from Te Aute) there: and I wrote yesty. (or rather on My. night) offg. my aid—if <hi rend="italic">the D. Should remain ill</hi>:—but to hear in reply <hi rend="italic">tomorrow</hi> nt. at furthest, &amp; if wanted I return to N. on Friday: but <hi rend="italic">since</hi> I wrote I feel weaker than ever—indeed, at present <hi rend="italic">unable.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>It is a very true ex. “<hi rend="italic">Spt. willing, flesh</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">weak</hi>”. In leaving N. I did not intend to stay long in the Bush Dist., so I took a <hi rend="italic">Return</hi> ticket.—A kind of Influenza is prevalent here, &amp; I caught it (I think) at Parsonage, during a <hi rend="italic">short</hi> visit—all hands there having got it, but of a very mild form.</p>
         <p>You <hi rend="italic">at Wgn</hi>. will be sure to know a good deal of the opg. Gorge Line, so I say nothing about it. There are 3 Mails <hi rend="italic">now</hi> daily from N. to Dvk.! &amp; yet we are worse off than before! &amp; get no <hi rend="italic">Eng. P.</hi> In “H.”of this mg. is an acct. of meeting of Edn. Bd., &amp; some “lively” talk (not howr. given—being in Comee.) over a letter from Waipk. Sch. Com; unfortunately O. was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> there, &amp; S—y as Chn. ruled, &amp;c. &amp;c. adversely. Sutton (as ever!) coarse &amp; bumptious: (I wish <hi rend="italic">he</hi> were away!) &amp; your good cousin <hi rend="italic">left</hi>—but returned again. Their mtg. was a long one—&amp; report <hi rend="italic">condensed</hi>. Again, on coming hither this time, I had some <hi rend="italic">pleasant</hi> talk w. your cousin Rechab<hi rend="sup"> </hi>(on Waipukurau platform)—his father had gone to hot spgs. for Lumbago.—</p>
         <p>I have recd. “Typo”, also 2 copies of “Review” from Lyon &amp; B., w. memo. of cost—this I will remit when I pay for J. Wh’s &amp; T’s. Dicty.—&amp; so make <hi rend="italic">1 job</hi> of it. From what you <hi rend="italic">now</hi> say I have hopes of getting the <hi rend="italic">wanting</hi> vols. from Didsy—or Govt.—I will ere long, write about ’em. Guide me in this matter—to write to Didsbury?—</p>
         <p>Now that the heavy &amp; continuous rains are over, the Bush burning on <hi rend="italic">large</hi> scale will be carried out (begun already) and I <hi rend="italic">don’t like it</hi>—such a smoky atmosphere, w. always more or less of <hi rend="italic">fears</hi>—on change of wind, &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>I have <hi rend="italic">not</hi> seen Frith’s “Moa” story referred to by you: have <hi rend="italic">always</hi> had a <hi rend="italic">very low</hi> opinion of Fr.—from my being <hi rend="italic">constrained</hi> to sit next to him at the one sm. table allotted us, 2, at Parlt. held in Ad.,—<hi rend="italic">not</hi> lessened by his <hi rend="italic">subsequent</hi> conduct including <hi rend="italic">his</hi> talk w. <hi rend="italic">Froude</hi>:—!! and his <hi rend="underline italic">draw</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>from Bk. N.Z.—to my loss. The worst is that “in days to come”, all such rubbish will (I fear) become<hi rend="italic">one </hi>with more truthful relations. By the way there is a <hi rend="italic">good</hi> paper on the Moa in vol. XXII. “Trans”, by Mair: <hi rend="italic">read it</hi>: it is an <hi rend="italic">antidote</hi> to his bror-in-law’s (Buller) say on the Moa in his big book on N.Z. Birds:—my attention has been drawn to it from a correspdt. in Engd., and I am <hi rend="italic">disgusted</hi>.—I must look you up a copy of my paper on the <hi rend="italic">Moa</hi> (which I consid. exhaustive) on my return to N.—</p>
         <p>I note <hi rend="italic">particularly</hi> what you have told me <hi rend="italic">re</hi> your present &amp; near future employ: &amp; I have my thoughts: all I can venture to say is, I hope you may not <hi rend="italic">overtax your health</hi> &amp;c, &amp;c.—Your remarks, together w. those of Librarian (G.A.L.), are of a melancholy nature, and serve to make me <hi rend="underline italic">more</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> sad</hi>! – – – – – – – –</p>
         <p>I am much pleased w. this <hi rend="italic">last “Typo”</hi>, (probably I should also have been with the late former nos., but I could never find time to read them!) I thank you for your kind honest remarks on <hi rend="italic">Bradaugh</hi>—a great man; one of Nature’s true types of m. Would there were more like him—barring some angularities, which, <hi rend="italic">in some form or other</hi>, pertain to <hi rend="italic">us all</hi>! I am astonished with the wonderful &amp; continued stream of improvement in our printing-presses &amp; their 1000 &amp; 1 helps &amp; aids!—I, who can look back on <hi rend="italic">the toil and bother of the old wooden pg. press &amp; halls!</hi> Here I will copy a sentence from a new book I bought at Craig’s, (“A popular story of the Ch. of Engd.”)—speaking of the Bible,—“It took Wycliffe &amp; his copyists 10 months to prepare 1 copy—wh. cost a sum equal to £40. of our money. Now an ordy. Ptr. of Bible can produce 120 copies an hour—2 a minute”. (Is this <hi rend="italic">quite</hi> true?—mind, <hi rend="italic">not</hi> Printer<hi rend="underline italic">s</hi>.)</p>
         <p>In “Herald” of this mg.—“Xt.Ch. Tuesday: at RM court this day, Bowerman &amp; Co., proprs. of <hi rend="italic">Picturesque Atlas</hi> sued H.Munweek for £10.10. Deft. sd—he had agreed to take 1pt. only for wh. he pd. 40/- the R.M. gave <hi rend="italic">agt. him</hi>, w. costs. So, I suppose, more &amp; similar suits will follow:</p>
         <p>Your critical eye detected those 2 ۥ  in my <hi rend="italic">little</hi> book—in Aۥwerika (for Africa) &amp; in <hi rend="italic">kowۥa</hi> (to distinguish it from <hi rend="italic">kowa</hi>). I had wholly forgotten them! &amp; on reading your letter turned to a copy I brought on w. me—but you have <hi rend="italic">kindly</hi> passed over my ugly-looking lower c. italic <hi rend="italic">t’s</hi>—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">IX.p.m.</hi>) I must now go on w. my letter, though I have little more to add. I have been readg. “<hi rend="italic">Lux Mundi</hi>”: a few passages are <hi rend="italic">good</hi>: am pleased to see them from <hi rend="italic">such</hi> writers. <hi rend="italic">Many</hi> are too High Ch. &amp; far fetched for me. <hi rend="italic">Too much of the “Fathers”.</hi> I believe, the m. tomorrow <hi rend="italic">from</hi> Wgn. will reach here at 1.30 p.m., and the M. thither close <hi rend="italic">about</hi> 2.30, I don’t know at present; but shall keep this open until tomorrow—S. Mail closing.—</p>
         <p>If Tregears Dy. should be bound <hi rend="italic">in difft. ways</hi> send me one of the strongest—best: I feel better this evg. &amp; night, than I did in the mg. I am told that “Evg. N.” will send its copies this way by a special conveyance! Do invest <hi rend="italic">1d..</hi> in a “Timetable” book, just to see the strange timing of trains to &amp; from N.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">12</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>. 2 p.m. Just retd. from P.O.—nothing fresh from you. Letter from Parkinson full of thanks but Dean <hi rend="italic">better</hi>—so I am saved that jy.—at wh. I am glad, for I feel <hi rend="italic">very weak</hi>—not myself<hi rend="italic">. </hi>Fairchild retd. no tidings of “Kakanui” <hi rend="italic">quite as I expected</hi>. Glad to find great &amp; many reductions C. Service.—Good bye,</p>
         <p>Yours truly &amp; affy., W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
