<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0490">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1882 March 8: to Balfour</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73378/">Balfour</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1882-03-08">1882 March 8</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1882 March 8: to Balfour<note xml:id="ftn3-130" place="foot" n="130"> ATL 88-103-1/07. Original at MTG HB 67861.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier Wednesday March 8/82</p>
         <p>Mr D.P. Balfour</p>
         <p>Dear Sir</p>
         <p>Last night I received your truly interesting letter of the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, with accompanying match-box packet, &amp; thank you for all; particularly for all your kind &amp; zealous pains in the good cause of Nat Science, &amp; most particu­larly for your valued closing expression—that you “consider it to be a pleasure to do anything I ask”. Well, I would there were a few more like you ­in good truthful wishes, &amp; honest zeal—and we would soon know a little more of Natures Stores, hidden, yet awaiting in the rich, and prolific fields around us. Believe me, your letter is a treat, &amp; real pleasure.</p>
         <p>I should not however be now replying at once, were it not that your <hi rend="italic">weekly</hi> mail to G reached you <hi rend="italic">tomorrow</hi>, hence I am obliged to write early. I have other work in hand, &amp; I expect Dr Spencer &amp; Mr Weber here today (we being a sub committee to select books, &amp; lay same before the Council)—&amp; so I write at once.</p>
         <p>First—our insects. I am pleased w your full account, &amp; drawing of plan of their <hi rend="italic">homes</hi>; of this more anon; also, of your having Figniers work,—I sought it on Monday at Athenm. Liby. but it was not there. The work passed through my hands, when Inspector of Schools, as I had selected it (&amp; that more than once) as a prize book. Should you note anything re the insects­ habits, &amp;c, &amp;c, let me know, by-and-bye; my pair still <hi rend="italic">keep below</hi> the water, they are remarkably quiet, &amp; have eaten nothing (save water?)—. I have chan­ged the water daily, giving them clear clean water, &amp; yet <hi rend="italic">every time</hi> I find small fine sands in the bottle; this puzzles me, as their bodies with fine hairs are quite clean. Have you <hi rend="italic">good</hi> grounds for supposing them to use their mouths (or “mask” apparatus) in excavating? At the bases of 4 (out of 5) holes, or chambers, you have this mark—I suppose you stopped <hi rend="italic">there</hi>? you did not <hi rend="italic">bottom</hi> them?. I presume they live on water insects, or worms. The 2 small plants, with a single leaf to each, are 2 Orchideous ones, (<hi rend="italic">very similar</hi>, in leaf &amp; size, to those of W,) but flowering spns are needed; which won’t be until next summer. I fancy they have also been described in Ws. The specimen of “Liverworts”in the box, being all destitute of fructification, I cannot say much about them!. I believe they are all known &amp; described, the biggest large lobed one <hi rend="italic">may</hi> be <hi rend="italic">Marchantia foliacea</hi>; but they vary much from soil &amp; situation, &amp; all depends on their <hi rend="italic">fruit</hi>—or flowers, who m &amp; f. are on different plants. One of the lot, the <hi rend="italic">tallest</hi>, is a moss. I have put them all on a plate &amp; in water.</p>
         <p>Enclosed I send you a few dried specimens of that <hi rend="italic">order</hi>—such as I have handy. Soak them in <hi rend="italic">hot</hi> water for a day, or so, if you wish to examine them. Some of them are <hi rend="italic">rare</hi> in fruit, or rarely found by me; though I suspect that the winter–spring months is the <hi rend="italic">proper</hi> time, for hunting them up in their shaded, damp &amp; wet homes,—which my Rheumatism does <hi rend="italic">not</hi> like, &amp; won’t hear of.</p>
         <p>Memo of a few spns of Liverworts (Hepaticæ) of six Genera.—(Just to know how much they vary in leaf &amp;c).</p>
         <p>No 1 Plagiochila (my new one of ’79–80, lately described &amp; <hi rend="italic">may</hi> be in Vol XIV.</p>
         <p>No 2 Another large species,—long known</p>
         <p>No 3 Ditto, Ditto, lovely objects under glass</p>
         <p>No 4 A small &amp; <hi rend="italic">thick</hi> fronded spn,—spn sent, nearly full size of plant, fru­iting spns needed (though I have seen them).</p>
         <p>No 5 A frondose spn.—Plant sent nearly full size.</p>
         <p>No 6 An elegant spn.—grows in tufts,—fruit <hi rend="italic">very curious</hi>, but scarce; this, too, lately described by me, with No 1.­</p>
         <p>N.B.         1–3, mostly found on trees, &amp; prostrate <hi rend="italic">wet</hi> logs in forest.<lb/>             4–6, on wet clayey banks, shaded sides of watercourses.</p>
         <p>P.D. has been here, and I find “Dickey” is getting all right again—which I was glad to hear. The others at Springfield were all well. Goodbye, &amp; with kind regards, believe me to be</p>
         <p>             Yours truly</p>
         <p>                             W.Colenso</p>
         <p>P.S. I use so <hi rend="italic">heavy</hi> a label, a bit of card will do; parchment better. W.C.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>