<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0891">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1894 January 4: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1894-01-04">1894 January 4</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1894 January 4: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-671" place="foot" n="671"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Jany. 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>/94</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>Late last night your long looked-for missive arrived <hi rend="italic">here </hi>&amp; I was really glad to see (once more) your well-known hd. wtg. in address. I have termed it “long-looked-for,” and perhaps I have better explain this at the commencement of my note: I have been nearly 3 wks. laid-up with Lumbago &amp; am not yet well—tho’ <hi rend="italic">much</hi> easier. Hence it was that I had allowed myself to be too much on the <hi rend="italic">watch-tower</hi>—straining my eyes for a messgr.; besides, as I had reason to believe you were back in office, I got fidgetty for Victor.—I thank you for your letter—but I ama little disappd. in it, as you have again <hi rend="italic">not </hi>ansd. mine—at all events not to expectn. I note your ending, w.—“I <hi rend="italic">could </hi>write more but hour is late.” (Just as in the former one— “written in office—letter at home—hence some things unanswered,”) I think <hi rend="italic">we </hi>agree in this, that letter-wtg. should be as <hi rend="italic">near </hi>conversation as possible, but, my good friend, you sadly fail here. I sent you Steele’s, &amp; Malcolm’s letters, &amp; my reply to St., &amp;c. [Strange! soon <hi rend="italic">after </hi>sent them 2 photos, 1 ea., asked for—<hi rend="underline italic">no acknt</hi>! I wonder if Smales is mixed up in that matter?]—&amp;, of course I looked for your remark: I mentioned <hi rend="italic">my Jubilee here</hi>: also of Hoben &amp; Lasse—also, sent, that <hi rend="italic">neatly </hi>got-up plan &amp; book from Adelaide: circular from R. Sy. &amp;c—enqd. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Mair, Mantell, &amp;c. at your Phil. meeting: all <hi rend="italic">unnoticed</hi>.—Yet <hi rend="italic">all </hi>would have been right &amp; proper were you (<hi rend="italic">as in </hi>Novr.) <hi rend="italic">hard at wk. in Pg.O.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This day I sent you a Paper “Herald” of this mg.—contg. some <hi rend="italic">stuffing</hi>! 1.) an abusive art. in <hi rend="italic">“D. T.” </hi>of yesty. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Drs. M. &amp; Sp., &amp; in <hi rend="italic">H. </hi>2 letters <hi rend="italic">re </hi>same, also, report of the meeting held here yesty. to <hi rend="italic">prevent </hi>future mischief from f. w. floods: (2.) a long tirade from some Metht. Minister named <hi rend="italic">Smale </hi>arising (in part) from your report—printers <hi rend="italic">errors included</hi>—of our Paper; read it carefully: you will discern the <hi rend="italic">animus </hi>of the writer. Unforty. for <hi rend="italic">him </hi>(&amp; all <hi rend="italic">his brethren</hi>) I never knew a single Mt. Minister who was even <hi rend="italic">slightly </hi>acqd. w. <hi rend="italic">Science</hi>: indeed, the <hi rend="italic">old ones </hi>steadfastly set their faces <hi rend="italic">against </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">all such</hi>—and Smales, evidently, wishes to pose as one of the <hi rend="italic">old</hi> lot (whose shoes he was not worthy to carry!)—but <hi rend="italic">Brett’s </hi>work <hi rend="italic">won’t allow</hi> of it. One thing I could—I might (?) remind him of—viz. that when he came to N.Z. he had <hi rend="italic">a N.T. in Maori </hi>ready for him, &amp; also his connexion 1000 copies of the same painfully worked by <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, &amp; for which <hi rend="underline italic">extra</hi> wk. I never had a 1d. But “<hi rend="italic">Heoi ano</hi>.” I don’t know who at <hi rend="italic">Auckland</hi> sent me the copy of the Paper. (3.) a clipping from Herald of 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. contg. a letter from the inexpressible Taylor White again on Maori <hi rend="italic">words</hi>—&amp; the Moa!! Now, <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, (as in former case of my p. on the <hi rend="italic">kuri</hi>)—if he had only cared to look into our “<hi rend="italic">Trans</hi>.” he would have found all he wanted to his hand in my paper vol. XII:—Capt. Hutton, in his long &amp; A.1. paper on the <hi rend="italic">Moa</hi>—in only 2 vols. back—had T. Wh. but looked into it, would have helped him.) T. Wh. forcibly brings to mind a remark of yr. own worthy Father to me, in a note—(<hi rend="italic">re </hi>the stupidity of Ed. “D.T.” or his enquirer concg. the diffce. ’tween Venus &amp; Mars—if <hi rend="italic">any</hi>!!!)—that “same, if <hi rend="italic">brayed in a mortar</hi> would still be just the same,” &amp;c.—only in better and more fit language. I would have briefly replied to T. Wh. just (again) showing him <hi rend="italic">where </hi>to get the informn. he sought—but I remembered how he had flouted my former reminder <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the <hi rend="italic">kuri </hi>and so remained quiet. You will also see in <hi rend="italic">Herald </hi>a letter from Howlett which may amuse you.—I duly recd. from you the copy of “<hi rend="italic">Evg. Post</hi>” contg. yr. letter on Moa Paper, &amp; thank you for it (Smales should have seen <hi rend="italic">that</hi>—perhaps he did!)—&amp; noticed an error of yours: I also recd. the Paper contg. letter signed “<hi rend="italic">Dinornis,</hi>” attacking yours—and my <hi rend="italic">first </hi>impression (seeing <hi rend="italic">errors </hi>in it) was, to write a <hi rend="italic">short </hi>letter to the same Paper, to say— “If Dinornis would give his <hi rend="italic">name</hi>—I would ansr. it.” I was rather grieved to see the name of <hi rend="italic">Travers </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">again</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>stereotyped as a Govr. of our Inst.—I hope however, t’other <hi rend="italic">T. </hi>will be <hi rend="italic">there </hi>and manfully do duty!——</p>
         <p>I have put aside a lot of scraps, &amp;c—for you—some I shall send w. this. One on “<hi rend="italic">the Printing of Books</hi>” will surprise even you unless you have already met with it. I shall also send you Sass’ letter w. memo re Ferns—to show, how <hi rend="italic">much better </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">some</hi> of the theatrical fraternity are than we suppose them to be. I have recently recd. 2 long letters from a Mr. Herbert Jones, sent from Atiamuri, informing me of his going to call on me for lots of informn.—and begs me to write (&amp; get ready!!) at least, 2–3, chaps. for his wk. on N.Z.—on Maori lang., Maori History, &amp; Maori Flora: <hi rend="italic">not one </hi>shall I do, I shall refer him to vols. <hi rend="italic">Trans. </hi>He gives me a long string of names of S. &amp; N. helpers—including (of <hi rend="italic">course</hi>) Travers,—Hill told me he also had got a letter from him—asking H. to write a Geologl. &amp; a Volcanic-action paper for sd. work: H. sent him an “author’s copy” of his papers re same—but reply—“<hi rend="italic">more &amp; new</hi> required!”—for my part, <hi rend="italic">I have not the most distant desire </hi>to be brought out in any of those popular Handbooks; I run away from it.—Besides I have neither <hi rend="italic">time </hi>nor patience for those tourists and globetrotters: Hill told me of a <hi rend="italic">Dr. Thomas</hi>, recently here, who wished H. to bring him up to me wh. H. declined: at the same time <hi rend="italic">there ought to be someone down in town handy to show our Museum.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In “Cook’s Journal” I notice the cutting off the tips (? lobes) of Orton’s ears—Cook’s clerk—is stated (we had it in <hi rend="italic">Parkinson</hi>);—and, also, Cook’s <hi rend="italic">own entry</hi> in margin of Journal <hi rend="italic">re</hi> same.—this item, howr., is taken from Paul Marcoy’s long adventurous Journey across the Andes, &amp;c—from Pacific to Atlantic ocean, &amp;c &amp;c 4 vols. folio (peculiar size, 14 x 10½), w. 500 engravings, a handsome beautifully printed &amp; got-up work, all engs. good—it is on very stout hot-pressed paper &amp; in large type, quite a treat to read it, or to go through it: and I have had these books in my back <hi rend="italic">lumber </hi>room some 12–14 years! sleeping—under boxes of Mosses, &amp; Lichens!!! the work is <hi rend="italic">most interesting</hi>; Marcoy, a Frenchman, is a Catholic, but he deals <hi rend="underline italic">openly</hi> with the R.C. &amp; Jesuit Missions in Brazil, &amp;c, &amp;c.—How I should like for <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi> to see &amp; go through this work! You may some day. It is an Eng. transln. &amp; ptd. in Edinbr.</p>
         <p>I suppose I told you of my engagement (made a month, or more, ago) with the Dean—that, on his taking his fortnight’s holiday, I would assist at the Cathl. Well, the Dean left on the 26<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. Decr.—and (woes me!) <hi rend="italic">the </hi>Sunday drew near! and I <hi rend="italic">hors de combat</hi>! Mr. Bradbury came to see me, &amp; further to arrange with me—as the work for Cathl. &amp; for Augustine’s lay upon us—and at last, we were obliged to write to the Dean, who was then at Petane, &amp; he had to return to Ahuriri for the <hi rend="italic">Sy. Evg. </hi>S. <hi rend="underline italic">there</hi>—Mr. B. having met w. a travelling Minister in town at the last moment—who helped;—&amp; now next Sunday is drawing nigh, and I <hi rend="italic">must decide </hi>tomorrow—<hi rend="italic">this matter, </hi>from the first, has tended to <hi rend="italic">increase </hi>my indisposition, &amp; make me very uncomfortable—yet, it should not be so— “the spt. <hi rend="italic">is willing</hi>, but the fl. <hi rend="italic">is wk.</hi>” However, I will hope for the best: I find Mr. Bradbury a nice kind of man—but, I fancy—very High Ch.—–</p>
         <p>The Bp., whom I have not seen since my last to you, &amp; who with all his family left N. last Wedy. mg. 27<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> for Tarawera, there quietly to remain for a week,—wrote to me a nice letter from T., giving me also an outline of his Journey—on to Auckland, Thames, Waikato, N. Plym., Whanganui, Woodville, &amp; to be at Kaikoura for 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. inst., to consecrate new church there, &amp; <hi rend="italic">here </hi>on 22<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. to be a neighbour (old Gr. school) for a week—<hi rend="italic">leaving </hi>on Feby. 1. His furniture, &amp;c, were sold at the house on Thursday 28<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., and his Books, at Lascelles’ Mart Yesty. M. Lascelles wrote me a note, wishing me to attend—but I could not. Besides, weather wretched! <hi rend="italic">Every day of this year Rain</hi>! &amp; I fear the same tomorrow. It is a curious fact, that last year <hi rend="italic">it was precisely the same, the first 5 days were pouring rain</hi>—as entered in my Diary. I fear, many of our sheep farmers, <hi rend="italic">late </hi>shearers are great losers. Hill, who kindly came to see me last wk., &amp; who told me that he and Walker were going off on Monday last to Kaweka, &amp;c—if they went, must be having a time of it!—of course it is this weather that is keeping me back, everything so <hi rend="italic">damp </hi>in house, &amp; atmosphere close, heavy, some days <hi rend="italic">hot</hi>, but <hi rend="italic">today</hi> cold, wind Sy.—–</p>
         <p>I had forgotten to mention <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the drowning of your assistant. I <hi rend="italic">first</hi> saw this in <hi rend="italic">our papers</hi>—as an “employe <hi rend="italic">w. Harding &amp; Co.</hi>”—and then, for the <hi rend="italic">first time</hi>, I <hi rend="italic">knew </hi>of yr. having had aid! Now I had <hi rend="italic">party. asked</hi> you that qu. <hi rend="underline italic">twice</hi>, but you <hi rend="italic">did not ansr.</hi> it!!</p>
         <p>You, again, speak of “<hi rend="italic">this month</hi> being <hi rend="italic">a slack one</hi> in Pg. off.” <hi rend="italic">If so</hi>, &amp; you will print me 100 copies of that Py. Paper <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Lex. that you printed before,—i.e. <hi rend="italic">reasonable</hi>, do so. You gave me, some time ago, a memo. of cost, but I thought it astonishingly <hi rend="italic">high</hi> (I believe it was ₤5. or thereabouts): I should think ½ that sum sufficient—perhaps I am wrong; that amount, however, is what I consider “<hi rend="underline italic">reasonable</hi>”.</p>
         <p>                                                     —Good Night!—–</p>
         <p>5th. still showery &amp; cold—wind S.—so I am obliged to keep within doors, though I much wish to go down to town.—The <hi rend="italic">spns.</hi> of your plant, mentioned, have not come to hand: send them, flr. &amp; seed vessels.</p>
         <p>I have often thought of asking you if you have met (in yr. ygr. days) w. a poem called “Grongar Hill”? and, if you know the author? I knew it when a school-boy.—–</p>
         <p>I must now close—over ½oz! thick paper, your note paper is suitable. Hope to get better news of Victor. w. kind regards</p>
         <p>Yours ever</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. I send D.T. of 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. contg. de Lisle’s letter <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Hospital &amp;c, concluded 3 wks. ago—not to go inland until <hi rend="italic">after</hi> the Bishops leaving.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
