<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0788">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 July 14: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-07-14">1891 July 14</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 July 14: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-537" place="foot" n="537"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Tuesday.<lb/>14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> July: VII, p.m.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding—</p>
         <p>I have only just got rid of my outg. Eng. M.—a <hi rend="italic">heavy</hi> job this time, and I should like <hi rend="italic">rest</hi>—or, to hear <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">talk here</hi> by my side: but I must again act, &amp; for the 1000<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. time, “<hi rend="italic">bring my mind down to my situation</hi> seeing I <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi> raise this to my mind.”—</p>
         <p>Your welcome letter of the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I got last nt. from P. Box, on retg. from Sy’s. Meetg., &amp; thank you for it:—written, too, under such saddening circumstances. I trust your poor dear &amp; aged Aunt has been <hi rend="italic">released</hi> from her pain, &amp; weakness long ere this reaches you. You have had a full share of deaths to relate during the last 2 months, or so. I am pleased to find you bearing these afflictions so reasonably—aye, may I not also say, religiously?</p>
         <p>Your letter of the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. inst—(which I ansd. on receipt), apprised me, of your having posted my letter to Capt. R., and so all last week I was on the <hi rend="italic">qui vive</hi>. Day after day passed, nothing arrived, but on Friday night a note of 5 lines from Capt. R. That he “<hi rend="italic">had posted</hi> to me No. XC. Q.R.,” this was consolatory, next mg. sent Robert for the parcel: <hi rend="italic">None</hi> had arrived! but <hi rend="italic">at night I got it</hi>: &amp; was I not <hi rend="italic">glad</hi>!!! A big sq. heavy parcel: 1/- postage: I put it aside until I should have <hi rend="italic">finished</hi> for Eng. M., &amp; also Sy’s. Meeting:—well <hi rend="italic">this evening</hi>, I opened it, and guess my disappointment—my horror! at finding that Collier’s quotn. <hi rend="italic">is not in it</hi>!! I have gone thro’ it carefully; <hi rend="italic">not there</hi>: the no. is “XC”, right enough; but it is the Vol. for July 1831,—so that it is impossible for anything <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Owen’s work, or Moa, to have been in it; a grave error this of Collier, especially, too, as he <hi rend="italic">repeats</hi> it, 2–3 times, both XC. &amp; pp.—</p>
         <p>And now I am at a loss! I know not how to act: I cannot trouble Capt. R. again, seeing I <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi> fix the no. or the vol.</p>
         <p>I am thinking:—</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">Of asking you</hi>—if you can somehow manage it for me, through being in Wgn. Either gain admission, &amp; look into Genl. Index, if any, (or no. CX, or CIX, or CXIX,)—or, hire someone to do so, I will pay.—</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">Of my asking Dr Newman</hi>:—to undertake the job for me (that is, to get the <hi rend="italic">vol</hi>. required,) <hi rend="italic">he</hi> may be able to do so through the Librarian, or some suitable person known to him: (I may tell you, that <hi rend="italic">I helped him</hi> in former years, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> enquiries after Maoris—persons, &amp; things.)</item>
            <item>I shall also briefly tell Capt. R. the <hi rend="italic">position</hi>—&amp; ask him to look into Collier, p.134: but I will await your answer, before I write to Dr. N. I shall return the vol. tomorrow, to Capt. R.—</item>
         </list>
         <p>Last week, Thursday, I sent Kirk my <hi rend="italic">first</hi> big package of spm. plants (60–70)—&amp; was I not glad!! (I would that finished the ugly job, but NO, scarcely half!) However, I put my parlour to rights (it was a scene before!) &amp; so far, pleased the auld wifie.</p>
         <p>I had taken care last week to know from Hony. Secy. White all I could get from him re last night’s Meeting: subsequently he came out big with advts. <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>. in our papers—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Bp., Hill, Westall, were to read Papers.—</p>
         <p>I went thither last evg. at VIII. found a <hi rend="italic">large</hi> attendance (say 50, or <hi rend="italic">more</hi>!) Canon Webb, &amp; others among them. Bp. with a huge bundle of books, (one being very large, say Royal 4to.) how he managed to bring them down I don’t know. Hill, Prest., Chn., looking <hi rend="italic">well</hi> with his specs, &amp; blk. Coat. He commenced, <hi rend="italic">no paper</hi> to hand from Westall: <hi rend="italic">no paper</hi> from himself,—not ready, (quite as I had supposed from what White had told me!) Then Hill asked <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, “If I had anything?”—nothing of <hi rend="italic">importance</hi>”<hi rend="italic">. </hi>Then he called on the Bp.—The Bp. said, he had not been able to get his p. ready—but with the <hi rend="italic">books</hi>, &amp; his notes, he wod. do his best &amp;c! And certy. he gave a <hi rend="italic">most interesting account</hi> of the origin, rise &amp; progress of the <hi rend="italic">Press</hi> in India. How often I thought on <hi rend="italic">you</hi>!—You would have been delighted, both in hearing, &amp; in <hi rend="italic">seeing</hi> the books—in <hi rend="italic">var. Oriental languages</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">written</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">, lithd.</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">printed</hi>.—The big book was a <hi rend="italic">marvel</hi>, <hi rend="italic">all written</hi>, &amp; so beautifully, so <hi rend="italic">regularly</hi>, done: the Koran in 3 languages: 1.) Arabic; 2) Hindostance (interlinear transln., &amp; in <hi rend="italic">red</hi>); 3.) Persian translation all around on the wide margin. I suppose the Bp. was ¾ hour; at close, H. rose <hi rend="italic">quickly</hi>, &amp; said “Has anyone any <hi rend="italic">Questions</hi> to put to the Bp.”—and on his sitting, the Bp. immy. rose, &amp; added (to what he had sd.) speaking (say) 5–8 min. longer.—And on his resuming his seat, Dr Moore arose to give his remarks on the “Humble Bee”, reading from “Jl. of Science” for Jany (?)—as <hi rend="italic">he</hi> had brought the H. Bee out from Home; well, when Dr M. ceased I sd. a few wds., &amp; so did Hill, on the <hi rend="italic">same</hi> subject. <hi rend="italic">But</hi>, I, on my rising walked into Hill, for his manner &amp; <hi rend="italic">words</hi>, at close of Bps. address:—i.e. “Questions”: <hi rend="italic">instead</hi> of remarks or observations; saying <hi rend="italic">I had been going to speak</hi>, &amp;c. &amp;c. (this caused approbation general!) But <hi rend="italic">now</hi> I should pass on. So I took your clipping <hi rend="italic">re</hi> that “strange fish”—<hi rend="italic">Regalecus pacificus</hi>, &amp; with Haast’s acct. in vol. X, “Trans”., &amp; the <hi rend="italic">large 4to</hi> Paper of <hi rend="italic">R. argenteus</hi>, with colored drawings, by Prof. Parker in the <hi rend="italic">Zoologl. Socys. </hi>papers, (a copy of it the Profr. had kindly given me a few years ago): this over, Hill put the qu. “Whether to <hi rend="italic">begin</hi> his unfind. Geologl. Paper?” No-one said, Yea, &amp; as it was <hi rend="italic">late</hi>—&amp; a Council yet to be held—we dispersed.—</p>
         <p>See in “D.T.” of this evg. a pretty fair acct. of meeting—that in the “Herald” of this mg. is wretched!—</p>
         <p>Went yesty. to pay Peter D. for ¼s Subtn. “Hd”.—P. says, <hi rend="italic">all the papers are being pubd. at a loss</hi>!</p>
         <p>I enclose a clipping wh. may interest you: I had read of it before.</p>
         <p>Craig told me, at close of Mtg., how vexed he, too, was, at Hill coming out in <hi rend="italic">that way</hi>—as he (C.) wished to speak, &amp; was waiting for me to commence, &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>I recd. from Secy. Wh. my “author’s copies,” (vols. not yet issued), and I shall send you a copy of the “<hi rend="italic">Jottings</hi>”—which I did not write for <hi rend="italic">publication</hi>: indeed, I had never supposed that such would pass the grand ordeal! But, after Taylor White’s, Rat, Dog, &amp;c—anything <hi rend="underline italic">may</hi> go down!!—. I noticed in the Auckland “<hi rend="italic">Report”</hi> (which Cheeseman sent me), it is stated, “– – – papers recd. &amp; read, of which <hi rend="italic">a selection will be made for Wgn.</hi>”—</p>
         <p>Weather is still fine: though we had rain this mg. until XII., but <hi rend="italic">mild</hi> temp.; wind N.—</p>
         <p>I expect I shall have to go to Waipawa on Thursday next, <hi rend="italic">on business</hi>,—absent, 2 days, or so.</p>
         <p>Was <hi rend="italic">very glad</hi> to hear of the little folks being <hi rend="italic">well</hi>, &amp; dear boy “<hi rend="italic">improving</hi>”—may such continue!</p>
         <p>Thanks to Mrs Harding for her clipping <hi rend="italic">re</hi> “Insomnia”—I wld. try it, forthwith, had I any one to heat water in mid. night, the requisite articles; but I will try wet cloth;—Better still If I could <hi rend="italic">command &amp; retain</hi> sleep <hi rend="italic">as you can do</hi>!</p>
         <p>White was at me (at close) for a p. for next Mtg., but I would not promise. He says, Pinckney will have one—<hi rend="italic">on Ferns</hi>.</p>
         <p>Sir J. Hector very kindly gave me a copy of a Paper in <hi rend="italic">this</hi> vol. on our Fossil Boty., w. plates of their leaves, by some foreign <hi rend="italic">savant</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="underline italic">Thanks</hi> for yr. kind &amp; timely remarks <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Mrs. M.G. Pearse: <hi rend="italic">we may meet.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I purpose <hi rend="italic">tomorrow</hi> opening your <hi rend="italic">big</hi> parcel, of those 2 books! &amp; expect a treat.</p>
         <p>I visited Mr Brandon last wk. he is a <hi rend="italic">confirmed</hi> “Spiritualist” (but that <hi rend="italic">word</hi> has many other meanings).</p>
         <p>And now, good bye: I am tired</p>
         <p>Kindest regards to <hi rend="italic">you</hi> &amp; yours</p>
         <p>From your friend </p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
