<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0948">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1895 November 15: to Hill</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Rex Nan Kivell collection, NK4168: Australian National Library Ms 4246. p118.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/74331/">Hill</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1895-11-15">1895 November 15</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1895 November 15: to Hill<note xml:id="ftn3-762" place="foot" n="762"> Rex Nan Kivell collection, NK4168: Australian National Library Ms 4246. p118.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Novr. 15<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>./95</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Hill</p>
         <p>Thanks, many &amp; big, for your very kind remembrances of me—in your long &amp; friendly letter of 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> &amp; 13<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>—to hand <hi rend="italic">late</hi> last night. I was truly glad to hear from you (which I had partly expected—seeing, <hi rend="italic">unfortunately</hi> we had <hi rend="italic">not met</hi>, ere you again left Napier on duty,) you have expressed a wish to hear from me—in reply, and this I will now essay, so as to meet you at Gow’s.—</p>
         <p>I had <hi rend="italic">much feared</hi>, that both yourself &amp; Mrs Hill were a little put out (or, downright vexed!) with me—at my <hi rend="italic">not keeping </hi>my appointment with you at your hospitable home at Bluff Hill—but so it was! and only <hi rend="italic">dire necessity</hi>—Fate!—prevented me; and I had been looking forward to it with joy! but enough, in note: more <hi rend="italic">re</hi> same, I may tell you when we next meet.—I regret your not having had fine weather when at Norsewood: your remark <hi rend="italic">re </hi>non-appearance of <hi rend="italic">Clematis</hi> (maxima) may, I think, be fairly met, with my reminding you of its being our <hi rend="underline italic">early</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> Spring </hi>flower—and so its season proper was <hi rend="italic">past</hi>. Am glad you saw <hi rend="italic">Eccles</hi>—poor dear! I fear he was “<hi rend="italic">sold</hi>” <hi rend="underline italic">again</hi>! He was with me on Tuesday, 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—II p.m., left me to go by train, as <hi rend="italic">he thought</hi>, to Dannevirke that aftn. &amp; thence to Woodville by early train on Wednesday—but he must have found out, to his grief, that he could only get to Waipukurau—&amp; not to his Home until the next evening!!—Am sorry to hear <hi rend="italic">your</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">account</hi> of Willie Jones. confirming the poor dear lad’s melancholy letter to me of the week before; which I answered. I have my fears for him. I had (in my heart &amp; mind) messages for him, &amp; others, in the Bush, which I had vainly hoped <hi rend="italic">to send by you</hi>! I much doubt my visiting Bush this year (’95), or this summer &amp; autumn season—as I have already told some of them—there, &amp; Eccles himself, lately,—<hi rend="underline italic">I have nothing to do</hi>—either in Ch. or State (? No—rather, <hi rend="italic">in </hi>Ch. or <hi rend="italic">out</hi> of it!)—and <hi rend="italic">I cannot remain idle</hi> in a country pub. &amp; without friendly compans.—</p>
         <p>Eccles’ remark, quoted by you,— “he had not been treated as he should have been”—may be quite correct, and full of meaning— “food for thought”—but neither fattening nor satisfactory!—(more anon). I have been working <hi rend="italic">hard</hi>, <hi rend="italic">here</hi> for some consid. time, and I enjoy it: only I cannot get on fast enough—time, too, rushing by on albatross wings! soon, very soon perhaps, to terminate with me. I have been engaged on many of your plants (not yet even come to the last one!)—and Olsen’s, and Andrews’—more than 20 in all that have had to pass the ordeals of severe examn., and now I am copying—slowly—their respective descriptions, &amp;c—for Dinwiddie Hon. Sy.—At our last meeting I showed (at a distance!) my rough drafts of the same—togr. with mounted specimens of some of them. Then I have been engaged on 2 <hi rend="italic">extra</hi> long letters (“papers”—I may properly call them,) one to Buller, &amp; one to Dr. Hocken. B. had early, in May (while I was at Baddeley’s) sent me an “Author’s copy” of all his papers—in vol. xxvii, “Trans.”, with a request—that I would read his <hi rend="italic">long one</hi> on “Darwinism” (<hi rend="underline italic">&amp;c</hi>.) &amp; report: this I had then promised to do: then followed the <hi rend="italic">thumb</hi> disaster! and I had forgotten it—but in Octr., B. reminded me—<hi rend="underline italic">gently</hi>! and so I took up the oar—it was rather a tough job (partly for want of time—so <hi rend="italic">many things</hi> coming together;) however, it was <hi rend="italic">done</hi>. Then Dr. Hocken’s (1–2–3 papers!) this <hi rend="italic">last</hi> pubd. <hi rend="italic">in extenso</hi> lately in the Otago Papers, &amp; sent by Dr. H. for considn.—subject, Tasman’s Voyage or rather Tasman’s adventures in, or off, N.Z. And for that purpose H. had got <hi rend="italic">Tasman’s </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">log</hi>, in original and ancient (!) Dutch, from Amsterdam and <hi rend="italic">transcribed it</hi>!! with all other rare &amp; old Spanish &amp; Portuguese Navigators’ voyages &amp; logs, &amp;c, &amp;c, (and the Dr. is very fond of spinning theories—some, reminding me, of Swift’s Professors of Laputa, extracting Sunbeams from Cucumbers!)—Well, I have tackled this also—and replied: and have told H. (as I had told B.) that the sooner he pitches overboard the Maori <hi rend="underline italic">myth</hi> of voyages from Hawaiki, <hi rend="italic">as being a veritable </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">fact</hi>, the better—that, (always assumed as <hi rend="underline italic">their</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> base</hi> line) ensures &amp; entails any amount of error!—then, comes Howlett—with many long letters—6–8 pages (&amp; some <hi rend="italic">good</hi> things in them): ditto Hamilton, with his <hi rend="italic">folio</hi> paper &amp; minute <hi rend="italic">graphy</hi>! which I cannot read <hi rend="italic">by night</hi>: Harding, too; excellent! graphical &amp; full details of <hi rend="italic">their</hi> “Instit.” meetings—which are well worthy of their name: (Alas! for <hi rend="italic">our abortions</hi>!!)—&amp;, lastly, letters to boys—Bush—Victoria (Australia), and N. of Auckland:—there are several <hi rend="italic">now</hi> bearing <hi rend="italic">my name</hi> (W.C.—as their <hi rend="italic">Xn.</hi> names) their fathers <hi rend="underline italic">old</hi> acqs., (tho’ some I have never seen) and now <hi rend="italic">these</hi> their offspring write to me—one very recently from interior authentic. All this by the way—that <hi rend="italic">you</hi> may not suppose you are the <hi rend="italic">only</hi> hard worked man among us—true—mine is of <hi rend="italic">small value</hi>, and will <hi rend="underline italic">not bear</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> comparison.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Re </hi>the Dean’s visit to Gisborne:—I knew it was to come off some time in Nov. (he having promised Webb) but not of his going—till he was gone. I found from <hi rend="italic">Heron</hi>, that St. Hill, and a <hi rend="italic">newly</hi> arrived married man named Taylor (residing at Havelock, where he has purchd. 30 acres) were to officiate in Cathl.—subsequently <hi rend="italic">confirmed </hi>by Welsh. (I had my thoughts, in spite of “guardian angels.”) So I went to Cathl. on Sy. mg., expecting to hear St.H. <hi rend="italic">once more </hi>(“for auld land sy.”) when lo! the little man Taylor with his dark <hi rend="italic">biretta</hi>: service over I came back, &amp; got my man to <hi rend="italic">remain</hi> at Home in evg., making sure, this time, of St.H., when, lo! the little m. again—with his ominous <hi rend="italic">black </hi>biretta <hi rend="italic">in relievo </hi>among the <hi rend="italic">white</hi> surplices! I was vexed, &amp; nearly came away: &amp; did <hi rend="italic">not like </hi>S.—(perhaps, <hi rend="italic">increased</hi> by disappt.) <hi rend="italic">This mg </hi>I went to town, mainly to see Dean, (who retd. yesty., well, happy, &amp; enjoyed—there) and from him I learned—that he had spoken to <hi rend="italic">Canon</hi> St.H. (&amp; to <hi rend="italic">Canon </hi>Archd. Sam) <hi rend="italic">re</hi> their taking their <hi rend="italic">fair share</hi> of duty in Cathl. Services, <hi rend="italic">as Canons of the Chapter</hi>, &amp; this St.H. had agreed to do—on this Sy.—or send substitute: that seems, all <hi rend="italic">square</hi>. Still, I <hi rend="italic">fancy</hi>, that <hi rend="underline italic">I</hi> shall <hi rend="italic">not</hi> appear there again—neither at Augustine’s, &amp; <hi rend="italic">certy. not </hi>at <hi rend="italic">Dvk</hi>:—as a <hi rend="italic">preacher</hi>: “Coming events cast their shadows before” and <hi rend="italic">our new</hi> Bp. is at bottom of this. I <hi rend="italic">could</hi> have sd. to the Dean—today—make <hi rend="italic">me</hi> a Canon, (fills up the vacancy,) as it appears, Jordan will never get it—and then you have help—such as it is! <hi rend="italic">ready</hi> &amp; near. I did remark how <hi rend="italic">badly</hi> he &amp; Chapter were off, in this matter of Canons—2 at Gisborne, and 2 <hi rend="italic">unwilling </hi>(?). The D. told me a queer story <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Gisborne, &amp; the Bp. The Bp. has been laid up with Lumbago (severely), on the day of Dean’s leaving Bp. still unwell &amp; <hi rend="italic">looking bad</hi> left on horseback for Opotiki—a Maori on h. &amp; w. a pack-h. with him. But the packh. would not travel! curvetting, &amp; performg. in all manner of ways. When the Dean who had seen that, mentd. it to Herbert W.—H. said, “Oh! yes, it is always so with that horse, it <hi rend="italic">must </hi>go <hi rend="italic">next to the </hi>Bp. then all right.”</p>
         <p>Here—this town all alive! with the flaring theatrical painted Calico devices of the Baptists! <hi rend="italic">to me</hi>, sickening: add to that, yr. <hi rend="italic">noisy</hi> pseudo-Temperance orators—races—holidays—pic-nics, children’s outings, &amp;c, &amp;c, &amp;c, and the world’s <hi rend="italic">Comedy</hi> [of errors] is complete! then the <hi rend="italic">Tragedy</hi>—suicide—at Hastings: man killed yesty. here on line—and robbery <hi rend="italic">Mrs Robertshawe’s </hi>Jewels!!—of this <hi rend="italic">last</hi> I know nothing, at present.</p>
         <p>I am keeping pretty well—though daily <hi rend="italic">grunting</hi>, <hi rend="underline italic">&amp;c</hi>. from pains in bones &amp; muscles—rather peculiar <hi rend="italic">if</hi> Rheumm. but, as I told P. Dinwiddie this mg., “only the sure sapping &amp; mining of Old Age &amp; his party of Engineers.”——</p>
         <p>Of <hi rend="italic">visitors</hi>, <hi rend="italic">none</hi>, save Welsh: and Mrs Leach a-begging—as usual.—I manage to keep up—somehow—until nearly midnight; then to bed: sleep <hi rend="italic">pretty</hi> well:—of late, much pleased with watching, on clear skies, of approach of Luna to Jupiter, &amp; to Venus: of late, V., as mg. star, is truly lovely—resplendent about IV. a.m.—Oh! how truly <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> is <hi rend="italic">seen </hi>in <hi rend="italic">all His works</hi>! whether in the cells of a minute <hi rend="italic">Hepatica</hi>, or in the mg. star! Would that more of our fellow colonists (or <hi rend="italic">townsmen</hi>) had eyes opened to see them!</p>
         <p>I suppose you have heard of the jolly row—in the House! between Mackenzie Minister of Lands and Sir Walter Buller—I have a pretty full account of it here in Wellington Papers (at <hi rend="italic">your service</hi>). From Harding I have a <hi rend="italic">nice</hi> &amp; full account of <hi rend="italic">scena</hi> at their meeting: (not very unusual!) A yg. Member, called Hudson—rather forward—introduced a Paper to <hi rend="italic">alter time</hi>! so as to make people rise 2 hours earlier &amp; to be done by <hi rend="italic">law</hi>! Hudson got<hi rend="italic"> </hi>it, hot &amp; heavy! but the pachyderm could not, would not, take it! asseverating—we (they) were old Tories, &amp; that <hi rend="italic">his</hi> scheme would by-&amp;-by be adopted by the wiser generation of young N.Z.!!! How this stiltified talk serves to remind me of the Teetotallers &amp; prohibitionists——Further: Kirk (<hi rend="underline italic">somehow</hi>! President this yr.!!) came out strong <hi rend="italic">in his way</hi> on <hi rend="italic">Dactylanthus</hi>, as being <hi rend="italic">common</hi>, and still <hi rend="italic">unknown</hi> as to growth, &amp;c, &amp;c,—viz. that Solander’s plants, &amp;c. of Cook’s Voyage, were <hi rend="italic">now</hi> about to be made known through <hi rend="italic">KIRK</hi>—and <hi rend="italic">here</hi> Hdg. got him again. It has been said (or surmised) that Kirk got his supplies of D. from you, or from Hamilton; but more of this when we meet. It is a <hi rend="italic">fact</hi>, (is it a curiosity?) that <hi rend="italic">all</hi> my prized Sc. correspondents possess names beginning with H. Hamilton, Hocken, Hdg., Hector, Hutton, (Howlett), Hooker, Hill.</p>
         <p>I have here a new curiosity in your particular line—<hi rend="italic">Geology</hi>: Three days ago a man from inland brought me a stone, (which the wise ones below of the “<hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>” had pronounced “an <hi rend="italic">aerolite</hi>”) it is a globular stone, 6½ inches diamr., 19½ in. circumf., &amp; weighs 11 lbs—a fine grained sandstone, without shells, &amp; evidently never imbedded in earth, almost a <hi rend="italic">perfect </hi>globe! he found it on the rugged peaks of Chambers’ Run: I bought it, and have written to Hector about it; the <hi rend="italic">peculiar </hi>feature is, its <hi rend="italic">roundness</hi>.</p>
         <p>I dare say you remember the <hi rend="italic">former</hi> Presbytn. Mr. of Woodville R. Stewart? well, a few days ago I recd. a <hi rend="italic">long</hi> letter from him (on folio fcp.) and a family photo. containing himself and wife and <hi rend="underline italic">6</hi> fine children! His <hi rend="italic">last</hi> to me was Xmas. ’93—&amp; he now fully apologizes for long silence! seems however to be doing well in (<hi rend="italic">their</hi>) Ch. matters. A letter, also, from Rl. Sy., asking me to allow myself to be nominated (or rather <hi rend="italic">added</hi>) to the Comee. for raising memorial to Huxley:—I have assented—but enquired, what can this <hi rend="italic">old</hi> m. do, at this <hi rend="italic">great</hi> distance?—</p>
         <p>I go with you in your remarks on Baddeley’s <hi rend="italic">cuisine</hi>—always low, <hi rend="italic">bad</hi>! <hi rend="italic">many</hi> have been my remarks to <hi rend="italic">her</hi> (it being her own doings): and I had long ago determined that, If I resided there again for a lengthened period, as before, I would order my own butcher’s meat. Hence, too, it was, that I managed, now &amp; then, to have a fowl to <hi rend="italic">myself</hi>—which, however, was always to last <hi rend="italic">six</hi> meals! to the———of Robertshawe. I was <hi rend="italic">against</hi> Scrimgeour going thither: B. can<hi rend="italic">not</hi> afford to <hi rend="italic">lose</hi> customers in these times, and I doubt if Dvk. <hi rend="italic">can maintain </hi>these 2 hotels.—</p>
         <p>A “clerical meetg.” is summoned to take place at Tuke’s W.p.rau on 28<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—<hi rend="italic">commencing </hi>at X.30:—I shall <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be there (“Express” arriving at midday): <hi rend="italic">ditto</hi> Welsh: <hi rend="italic">ditto </hi>Eccles: <hi rend="italic">ditto </hi>Archdn. S., who will then be at Wgn. and I <hi rend="italic">doubt</hi> the Dean going. <hi rend="italic">Cui bono</hi>?</p>
         <p>I shall hope <hi rend="italic">to see you </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">fairly</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> here</hi>, soon after your return: Let your conscience speak, and remind you, what you will owe me for this <hi rend="italic">long</hi> letter.</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely</p>
         <p>W. Colenso</p>
         <p>P.S. To be addressed to you at <hi rend="italic">Gow’s</hi> (&amp; <hi rend="italic">not</hi> Wallingford) as the safest &amp; surest.——</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>