<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0792">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 July 24: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-07-24">1891 July 24</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 July 24: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-541" place="foot" n="541"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Friday night,<lb/>July 24/91.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I think I must write to you tonight, and in doing so, first, ackn. rect. of yours of the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. inst. Regret reading no better account of your dear little boy: poor little fellow! I yet hope he will live to thank you &amp; his Mother for all your extra care and many fears, &amp; prove a good &amp; useful man in his day.—<hi rend="underline">Amen.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Since my last to you I have had some “ups &amp; downs” of var. kinds—both physical &amp; mental. I told you in my last of my letter to Capt. R. <hi rend="italic">re</hi> vol. XC., and I have been patiently (?) waiting: this day, however, I recd. <hi rend="italic">the vol</hi>—so long reqd. &amp; find it (the Note) much as Collier gives it, (and a great deal more—taking on the 2 pps. nearly a <hi rend="italic">whole</hi> p. of small type—nonpl. perhaps,) but the <hi rend="italic">main</hi> aim of the Qly. Revr. is—to pitch in to Dr Mantell. At the close, the Reviewer says,—“The statement of these facts detracts nothing from the merit of Mr C’s. observations—but what becomes of Dr M’s. affirmation “that Mr C. was the <hi rend="italic">first</hi> observer that investigated the nature of the fossil remains w. due care &amp; the requisite scientific knowledge?”—But, if what the Revr. strives hard to show is correct, (<hi rend="italic">e.g</hi>.—“In Dec./39, Prof. O. <hi rend="italic">despatched to N.Z.</hi> copies of his first Memoir—&amp; <hi rend="italic">they were recd. before the close of 1840. – – </hi>Mr C’s. paper is dated May 1/42<hi rend="italic">. – – – </hi>Dr M. takes no account<hi rend="italic">of the influence of the dispersion of the first memoir in N.Z. between 1839 and 1842.</hi>”<hi rend="italic"> </hi>&amp;c<hi rend="italic">.</hi>)<hi rend="italic">—</hi>I should say, such must<hi rend="italic">detract </hi>a jolly lot from my obsns. He goes in largely for the bones sent home by Rev. W. Williams<hi rend="italic"> </hi>(<hi rend="underline italic">in Nov. 1843</hi>), who sent them (including mine) <hi rend="italic">to Dr</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Buckland</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> at Oxford</hi>; and who, <hi rend="italic">very clearly, had never heard of P.O’s. paper</hi>! However, I shall work up my paper, &amp; very likely shall send the Ms. to you ere I send it. I purpose also writing to Mantell, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> charge against his f.—perhaps he can help me.—</p>
         <p>A bit more <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the Moa, before I quit the subject.—(this, however, <hi rend="italic">may</hi> be in Owen’s work).</p>
         <p>Did you ever hear of the skeleton of an old Maori having been found down S. buried w. a Moa’s Egg in its hands? I did; &amp; I should like to find its place—if recorded—in any paper or Serial.</p>
         <p>Among my collected scraps, I find this:— “The Maoris found the Moas there when they landed in the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. centy., and the Maoris of today describe them as a heavy stupid bird, which their forefathers killed &amp; ate, <hi rend="italic">as being the easiest way of procuring a livelihood.</hi>” <hi rend="italic">Signed</hi>, “Charles Hind, Midland Hotel, Liverpool.” In “<hi rend="italic">Country Gentleman’s Newspaper</hi>,” April 15/76.—</p>
         <p>Last Saty. nt. (18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>) I recd. an off. L. from G.S. Cooper <hi rend="italic">re</hi> Mao. Lex. I will enclose a copy: I have not yet sent my reply, I am incubating! <hi rend="italic">I may tell you, </hi>that I had heard from<hi rend="italic">good authority, </hi>that the late Govt. gave directions to have it printed before they left Office, this, indeed, is pretty nearly the same as D–y. told you.—</p>
         <p>Last Friday night I recd. a letter from Loughnan, infg. me—I was reqd. at Waipawa on Monday (20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>), but if I <hi rend="italic">could not</hi> come, to wire to him early &amp; to see (or write to) Sy. &amp; Logan: however I went. My. was a <hi rend="italic">delightful</hi> day! (the Sunday 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. was <hi rend="italic">not</hi>—I remd. at Home all day!). Tuesday was fair for a winter’s day, tho <hi rend="italic">very cold</hi>, in the mg. I returned by the night train on Tuesday,—Rev. R. Fraser being my companion from W. to Hastings, &amp; <hi rend="italic">I did enjoy our conversn.</hi> (which made me again to think of <hi rend="italic">you</hi> &amp; my loss!!) He had been supplyg. ’Pukurau, &amp; Gt. at Havelock, &amp;c. On Wednesday I went to town on business long deferred: mg. threatening, but I hoped to return before rain: <hi rend="italic">not so</hi>, however, &amp; after waiting under Newton’s verandah till I was nearly ½-frozen,—I started &amp; got here <hi rend="underline italic">drenched</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">much worn</hi>! The climbing this slippy. hill in pouring rain, w. my <hi rend="italic">thick</hi> storm &amp; Ry. cloak &amp; <hi rend="italic">no</hi> umbrella nearly did for me.—And here I have been since, working away, but <hi rend="italic">doing nothing satisfactorily</hi>.</p>
         <p>Returning late on Tuesday, I did not go to hear Guy Pearse; and it is well I did not! <hi rend="italic">Such a Lecture</hi>! and to travel 400 m. to deliver <hi rend="italic">it</hi>!!! I suppose you saw it (as reported) in one, at least, of our papers.—</p>
         <p>I saw yr. cousin, Mr Rechab Hg. in town on Wedy., he was looking well, he told me of his F. having been to Wgn. &amp; of the death of his Sister.—I am (again) <hi rend="italic">pleased</hi> at your Cousin’s coming out strongly &amp; <hi rend="italic">fairly</hi> aft. Sidey &amp; his ape Sutton at E. Board; &amp; I am really sorry, at Mr Sidey <hi rend="italic">so</hi> acting: and to t’other S. – – – – I wish, sometimes, he was further from <hi rend="italic">N</hi>.,—&amp; would stay more at his home.—</p>
         <p>Good night: shall not close this till tomorrow.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Sunday 26</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">., noon. </hi>I am again at Home this S. morning: the sun <hi rend="italic">rose</hi> in a lovely manner, &amp; so contind. till IX, then cloudy &amp; cold, &amp; now rain:—I resume, to post this evg.—</p>
         <p>I have written to Col. Secy. &amp; enclose copy for your considn. I do not suppose that you there are likely to hear anything, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the Mss.—will they return them?</p>
         <p>I shall also write to Mr. Mantell by this post, re what Collier &amp; Qy. Revr. say: hoping that M. may be able to throw any light on the <hi rend="italic">said</hi> distribution of Owen’s first p. in N.Z.—</p>
         <p>Since I commenced this letter I have been deeply rummaging among old letters and Mss. (heaps from Maoris, &amp; others) seeking what I cannot find—information for my paper for our Instit., Yet I know I have it <hi rend="italic">somewhere</hi>! In my search I have found some <hi rend="italic">old</hi> Type-founders spn. sheets, which I send to you—hope such may prove of some little service, or be welcomed.</p>
         <p>On my return from Waipawa I found a note from Dean H. &amp; his lady, inviting me to tea at St. John’s Schoolroom yesterday 4 p.m.; in replying, I said, <hi rend="italic">I would be there</hi> (D.V.) However, I did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> go, but sent early in the mg. a note of apology, &amp;c. the fact is, that every day &amp; <hi rend="italic">pretty regularly too</hi>, from 3.45 to V.30<hi rend="italic">, </hi>I am feeling miserable! fagged, worn, &amp; in an ill-humour or very near it! It <hi rend="italic">beats me: no use</hi> resisting—a cup of tea always refreshes me, &amp;c. So, <hi rend="italic">knowing this</hi>—I was sure I should be anything but fit for such a sociable mtg. Another peculiarity of mine—of <hi rend="italic">late</hi>, is sneezing—<hi rend="italic">severely</hi>, 2–3 times together—and <hi rend="italic">several</hi> times in the day. This is certainly <hi rend="italic">indicative of something</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Thanks</hi> for your kind note re the little spirit stove for hot w. at night.—</p>
         <p>Know nothing of the so-called discovery of the ancient version of N.T., <hi rend="italic">older</hi> than those known to R.V. correctors—Don’t believe it.—Lots of such things turning up now—all being forgeries.—</p>
         <p>Eng. Ch. about being erected at Kaikoura. Another <hi rend="underline italic">sad</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> Sunday</hi> shootg. case at Dvk. Were I there, &amp; had oppy. I should again preach agt. that Sy. exercise—not <hi rend="italic">caring</hi> for the father’s feelings. A yg. man called Martyn has been adopted by Rev. Tuke as a Lay reader at Taradale, &amp;c. M. was shepherding at Kereru &amp; had been some time residing there.—<hi rend="italic">Jas</hi>. Irvine’s Goods &amp;c at Green Meadows, to be sold, auction, order Registrar, suit <hi rend="italic">Herman</hi> Carruth (“Herald”) gone to Australia “£4. <hi rend="italic">pr. wk, &amp;c.</hi>” His sister Mary, also gone thither to be marrd. to a yg. plumber <hi rend="italic">hence</hi> named Paul. Agnes is slightly better. (from Mrs Anderson.) Dawson (Akaroa) wrote to Craig for “3 Lity. Papers”, &amp; 2 copies “Tidal Lore”. Gifford has had to apologize, &amp;c, publicly, in “D.T.” of 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. to Guiness &amp; Co. for using forged brands! I have long known this!! You joy w. me in getting ½-thro (ugly) job for Kirk—t’other half is <hi rend="italic">the worst</hi>. Would t’was done! Here this aftn it is wet &amp; cold, w. Bar. at “Set Fair.”</p>
         <p>And now goodbye—I have given you a <hi rend="italic">lot</hi>—of all sorts. With kindest regards, Yours sincerely. W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
