<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0435">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1880 December 20: to Hector</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Museum of New Zealand—Te Papa Tongarewa MU000094/005/0082</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/33221/">Hector</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1880-12-20">1880 December 20</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1880 December 20: to Hector<note xml:id="ftn3-68" place="foot" n="68"> Museum of New Zealand—Te Papa Tongarewa MU000094/005/0082</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Decr. 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1880.</p>
         <p>My dear Sir,</p>
         <p>I was much pleased in getting your letter of the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., which reached me on the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, and I should have again written to you, last week, only I thought you would be doubly occupied on the arrival of the Eng. Mail.—</p>
         <p>I have several things to say, but how to compress (and yet to write fully), and how to write so as to get an early answer from you—are, I fear, beyond my skill.—</p>
         <p>But here goes!—<lb/>1. To begin at the beginning, or<hi rend="italic">Public </hi>work.—<lb/>The old question has again cropped up (on their seeing Cheeseman’s visit to Pirongia in vol. xii.)— “Why do you not publish my visit to Ruahine?”—for which there are many good (or better?) reasons assignable:—<hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> (1) the large number of interesting species found <hi rend="italic">only there</hi> in this N. Island; (2) many of the drawings in the Fl. N.Z. are of plants obtained from Ruahine, and which are more particularly described by me in my paper: (3) no other European has ever crossed that range, or even visited its summits:—&amp;c.</p>
         <p>Of course, we all know of your wish to publish an <hi rend="italic">Abstract</hi> of that paper. And we here should long ago have published the said paper in its entirety, but for a kind &amp; proper remark of our President the Bishop,—viz. “that to do so, as a mere pamphlet, would be to lose it, whereas it should be a record,” &amp;c &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>And now, to cut the matter short, I would ask,—If you will take the said Ms. back and just publish in your forthcoming vol. what you (?) have marked for the said abstract,—including those two <hi rend="italic">small</hi> semi-geological portions,—one, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the bases of the Ruahine, and one, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> that most peculiar rock formation on its summit,—which, I see, are market <hi rend="italic">out</hi>, (though why these should have been struck out I cannot divine).—</p>
         <p>If you will agree to this, and also place the said Ms. in reliable hands, (I mean, as to the many cuttings-in-and-out; you, I suppose, being again soon to be absent from N.Z.,)—then I will forward to you.</p>
         <p>2. Now as to “plates” for “Transactions”.—You (again) kindly tell me,— “Of course any plates required for papers will be done.— —Have you sent the drawings?”—</p>
         <p>To the latter, first:—No, I have not sent them, for I cannot <hi rend="italic">now</hi> trust my hand to make them, &amp; I know of no one here whom I could employ. Some time ago (in ’79 perhaps), I understood you to say, that if I sent the <hi rend="italic">specimens</hi> to you, such would be (even) better than drawings. I wrote to Botanl. draughtsmen in London, (Fitch &amp; others,) and have their replies; and I could get what I want executed there (at rather a high figure though!),—but then would the letter-press be <hi rend="italic">certainly</hi> published by you? and, if so, could I <hi rend="italic">depend </hi>on those plates being here <hi rend="italic">in time</hi> for your Binder? I fear not.</p>
         <p>I noticed remarks in some of our N.Z. Papers (particularly the “Auckland Wkly. News”,) on the fewness of plates in vol. xii. Others have also remarked on <hi rend="italic">such plates</hi>—as Knight’s Lichen-spores, and Maskell’s Coccidæ (see end), as being but of very little general interest, or (as to the Lichen-spores) of any real scientific utility, this being also the <hi rend="italic">second </hi>time,—while, on the other hand, such things as new plants, especially new <hi rend="italic">ferns</hi>, are omitted. And here I would venture to observe, (1.) that it is almost impossible (as our oldest and best European Pteridologists know &amp; have repeatedly said,) to describe fully &amp; clearly in words the specific differences of closely-allied Ferns,—while a faithful drawing shows them at once: and (2) that last year I had offered to you to pay the whole expense of drawing &amp; printing my specimens. No doubt Mr. Buchanan having had so much to do in the getting out those plates of the “Grasses” must have taken up his time <hi rend="italic">last</hi> year—and even now he may have his hands full.—</p>
         <p>3. I have much regretted your not having been able to get for me those few specimens of common Australian Ferns while in Sydney. I have during the last 2 years expended a good deal of money in a Fern Library of reference,—having obtained from Madras, London, Paris, Berlin, &amp;c., some <hi rend="italic">expensive</hi> works by the <hi rend="italic">first </hi>authorities. I have, also, endeavoured to secure dried specimens from various parts, particularly in these Seas, at no small expense, and yet to little purpose!! Take an example: after much trouble I found out a Fern-Collector in Sydney: got a visitor there to see him: heard from him, &amp; then wrote for some Australian and Tasm. Ferns, dried anyhow (<hi rend="italic">not</hi> laid out) but perfect:—particularly marking the species I wished to have, and that such were to be sent to me by Bookpost. He sent the little package (<hi rend="italic">under</hi> 3 lbs.) by various steamer<hi rend="underline italic">s</hi>! (it was for some time lost at Auckland,) and with a polite (?) note (I being a stranger, &amp;c. &amp;c.) for damages, £5. (they were all unnamed),—and, that those ferns I had particularly wanted were <hi rend="italic">not then in stock</hi>! but he should be leaving directly on receipt of my remittance to look them up, &amp;c. I sent the P.O.O. &amp; would have nothing more to do with the fellow: and what with Custom-House Agents, Freight, storage, &amp;c, &amp;c,—nearly another £ was consumed!—</p>
         <p>I begin to despair now of ever seeing <hi rend="italic">Lomaria Patersonii</hi>, <hi rend="italic">vera</hi>, from Australia: but all that I have read about it, including the study of its <hi rend="italic">plates</hi>, have only confirmed me in my old original belief, that it has <hi rend="italic">nothing to do </hi>with <hi rend="italic">our</hi> N.Z. <hi rend="italic">Lomaria </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">at present</hi> lumped with it under that name,—and so of others.—</p>
         <p>—But I must draw to a close.</p>
         <p>I have to thank you—much and heartily—for the concluding part of the large Work on <hi rend="italic">Grasses</hi>.</p>
         <p>One thing in it (and in the smaller work also) in the <hi rend="italic">Index</hi> pleased me much,—and seemed as if some seasons were returning to their right senses!—<hi rend="italic">i.e. </hi>the proper placing of a capital letter to the specific, or trivial, name of a Grass when called after any one. Why that good old rule of ancient days and of universal acceptance throughout the scientific world should ever have been broken here in N.Z. (of late years) has astonished me.—I am sorry to see it <hi rend="italic">again</hi> so in the Index (and nomenclature) of Broun’s <hi rend="italic">Coleoptera</hi>: and I am still more sorry to see that work issued <hi rend="italic">without</hi> an Alphabetical Index!! as it now is, it takes a precious time to hunt up anything required.</p>
         <p>Now my dear Sir I have given you a lot to read: don’t be over irate at any of my free and open sayings. For I must either write freely (especially to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>), or not at all. Please bear in mind, that I shall not much longer bother you.—And try &amp; find a few minutes to reply to one or two matters.</p>
         <p>Ever sincerely yours,</p>
         <p>Wm. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. Since writing the above it has occurred to me to add (as this <hi rend="italic">may </hi>be read by you when in a <hi rend="italic">generous</hi> mood!)—If you agree to my request <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the Ruahine Ms., would you also allow me to mark, say, <hi rend="italic">2p. in all</hi> of the Ms., for <hi rend="italic">your consideration</hi>, to be <hi rend="italic">added </hi>to the portion you had selected to be published?   W.C.</p>
         <p>Decr. 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. I have been conversing with Mr. Ormond, &amp; other of our Members <hi rend="italic">re</hi> what I have herein said to you about the Ruahine Ms.,—and now I have another proposition to submit:—viz. Would you consent to our printing it here at our expense, pretty nearly in its entirety, and furnishing you with the required no. of copies for your volumes of “Trans.”,—you binding it up with vol. xiii.—much as those “Essays” were in vol. I.?</p>
         <p rend="center">___</p>
         <p>Further, and to prevent misunderstanding, I should also say,—that <hi rend="underline italic">I</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> am not </hi>against your publishing those plates of Maskell’s Coccidæ,—very far from it. Indeed I have a few <hi rend="italic">novel ones</hi> (to me, at least,) which I collected for him in the Bush last summer,—and am about sending them to him.</p>
         <p>I again going over your letter, I find you saying (in remarking on Broun’s Beetles),— “There is still a lot more to print, about another vol. like the first: however, we can’t afford it at present.”—May I ask, If this “lot more” is about <hi rend="italic">Beetles</hi> (proper)?—or, rather, the Orders of our N.Z. Insects—exclusive, perhaps, of Lepidoptera?—How pleased I should be to see such printed! I would subscribe £5.—or even £10. towards it. How sadly disappointed I was with those <hi rend="italic">few</hi> in “Zoology of Erebus &amp; Terror”; after my having given <hi rend="italic">them</hi> so many, &amp; sent, also, such a lot to England!! I have been told, that, in all likelihood those I sent are still in their original bottles, &amp;c., in the “stores” of the Linnæan S.!!!</p>
         <p>Farewell.    W.C.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
