<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0528">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1883 March 26: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1883-03-26">1883 March 26</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1883 March 26: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn3-175" place="foot" n="175"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier Monday March 26<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.<lb/>1883.</p>
         <p>A.Luff, Esq.</p>
         <p>Dear Sir</p>
         <p>Your kind note of 16<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. I duly received &amp; thank you for it. Ever since I have been thinking how best to meet your wish—of meeting you at some fixed place in the Bush, on the Coach road between Ry. terminus &amp; Wgn., but I scarcely see my way clear to do so, &amp; this for several reasons:—1. I now find (at last, from Sperrey), that my <hi rend="italic">main</hi> objection against Arrow’s Exclusive Valuation at Waipawa is not allowed, and so, if I prosecute it, I must be there at the Court on the 6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., and as there seem to be a large number of cases, I <hi rend="italic">may</hi> be here also on 7<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., 9<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., &amp; so on!! at all events that being the Coach day I could not leave before Monday. I should be quite inclined <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to appeal (as, indeed, I have <hi rend="italic">decided </hi>in the matter of my sections here, at W. Spit, &amp; Havelock)—although the difference is something, only I fear the W.Co.C. <hi rend="italic">may</hi> accept the said valuation for themselves, &amp; then it would be considerable. Such being the case, although I leave here on Friday next (<hi rend="italic">if </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">fine</hi>), I shall not go into the Bush proper until I am free from W.</p>
         <p>2. The weather generally in the Bush is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to be depended on—and as a rule I never travel in <hi rend="italic">wet</hi>: further, sometimes the <hi rend="italic">one </hi>coach is crowded, &amp; so <hi rend="italic">I am obliged to wait</hi>! therefore I cannot well fix, at all events, just now: I may perhaps in 10 days or a fortnight hence. I wish to go on to Woodville (where I have never yet been) indeed I have partly promised to do so; and, in the Bush, my main halting-place will be at Towers’ Roadside Hotel at Matamau (close to Mrs. Crosse’s house), halfways between Norsewood &amp; Dannevirke. The most feasible plan that I can see at present, is, for me to drop you a line from Towers’, telling you my days for being at Woodville, where I should stay <hi rend="italic">2 clear days</hi>, of course allowing full time for my note to reach you, &amp;c. There is no teleg. <hi rend="italic">thereabouts</hi> so that I could not well send a telegram. You may expect a note from me (D.V.) about <hi rend="italic">the mid. of April</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I am very vexed about this over-charge on my small properties, through it I have already lost much val. time, and I shall yet lose more besides delaying my Bush visiting—carrying that on so far into the season &amp; hindering my return.</p>
         <p>With this I send you a small parcel of seeds,—I got it ready on Saturday last, but not in time for the S. Mail, being <hi rend="italic">late</hi> w. my Eng. letters, &amp;c.—My time has been much frittered away &amp; taken up of late w. <hi rend="italic">other </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">foreign</hi> matters.—</p>
         <p>The few seeds will speak for themselves. Ngaio berries are very scarce <hi rend="italic">this year</hi> (I have not seen one!) my man cold. these. The <hi rend="italic">Coprosma</hi> is a pretty thick growing evergreen shrub, or sm. tree, one of the ornaments of Tiffen’s garden.—</p>
         <p>Hope this may find you quite well, w. all yr. family, and w. kind regards, I am, Yours truly </p>
         <p>                                                                     W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. But be sure you do not think of travelling N., if the weather is rough or unsettled.                                            W.C.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>