<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0967">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1896 May 19: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1896-05-19">1896 May 19</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1896 May 19: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-786" place="foot" n="786"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke, May 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.<lb/>1896.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I must no longer put off writing to you: your excellent full long &amp; friendly letter of 22 April, I have <hi rend="italic">here </hi>before me. I think it is one of the best (if not <hi rend="italic">the </hi>best) you ever wrote to me: I <hi rend="italic">have</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="italic">do</hi>, humbly thank you for it: <hi rend="italic">on it</hi>, at <hi rend="italic">first </hi>reading, I wrote:—<lb/>“From the fullness of the heart the mouth speaketh &amp; the hand writeth.”<lb/>Since the receipt of it I have had so very much <hi rend="italic">extra </hi>to employ my time, that really I could not take on me to answer: one particular “<hi rend="italic">extra</hi>” I may tell you: my eldest son suddenly arrived in N. the week of your letter, staid 10 days, &amp; left for Engd. via Wgn. &amp; Sydney—28 years since last at N., &amp; I should not have known him! He left Engd. for health (Doctors’ advice)—hoping sea-voyage would be of service, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">so it proved</hi>: hence <hi rend="italic">no </hi>warning to me. However, I was, &amp; am, very pleased at his coming: <hi rend="italic">we met, lived, &amp; parted </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">in peace &amp; love</hi>.</p>
         <p>I think I must have told you of my consenting to help—Waipukurau Sy. Ch. Ed. Services, during Tuke’s <hi rend="italic">absence</hi>: he, &amp; wife, left for Sydney on 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. inst., Arthur Williams took duty on 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., Williamson of Waipawa on 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>: <hi rend="italic">W.C.</hi> next Sy. 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., Williamson again, on 31<hi rend="sup">st</hi>., and (if reqd., W.C. on June 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.) Tomorrow (Wedy.) I go to Wdv., should have gone <hi rend="italic">this day</hi> but rain came on: I go thither merely to see a friend or two.—</p>
         <p>2 p.m. “Herald” just to hand. I see Buckley’s death! I wonder if that <hi rend="italic">severe </hi>J. thought on his undue severity here at his <hi rend="italic">opening </hi>assize? &amp; now he is <hi rend="underline italic">gone</hi>. Pollen, too! (well, well, well!!!) You will see (in clipping—no, paper sent—enclosed, mine, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>your Uncle J.,<note xml:id="ftn3-787" place="foot" n="787"> The proposed museum. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi>, 19 May 1896.</note> &amp; may guess the rest.—I sent you 2 papers, contg. report of “Address”, &amp;c.—“Evg. News” also good—but all <hi rend="italic">alike</hi> defective as to amount promised by me, viz. <hi rend="underline italic">saying</hi> £2000 instead of £1500—I suppose from 2 evg. ones <hi rend="underline italic">copying</hi> from “Herald”: I early wrote a note to Herald about it—in explanation: adding, not worth while my writing to p. about it. As I have <hi rend="italic">since </hi>noticed in vol. XXVII “Trans. N.Z.I.”, that you had Schaw’s address inserted w. “Proceedings”, I wrote to Hector re this of mine—not that I expect an affirmative reply. Our Hony. Secy. is so utterly careless of proceedings, Report, &amp;c., &amp;c.—If H. declines, &amp; a few will subscribe, say 2/. ea. it shall be printed—? here, <hi rend="italic">or </hi>by you??—I have recd. one <hi rend="underline italic">slashing</hi> letter, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>address (the part pubd. in “D.T.”, <hi rend="italic">highly eulogized by writer</hi>!) in wh. I am told I am in corruption &amp; carnality, an old m. near the grave, blinded &amp; led by Satan, letter signed, “<hi rend="italic">A Believer</hi>”; the writing good &amp; peculiar. Now I had carefully said, at close—I <hi rend="italic">abstained</hi> from theological dogmas out of place, but I hoped they cod. see a kind of silver thread of pure Religion burning through it. The night was dark, wet, rainy! I had Robert &amp; Son, striking matches going down the hill for me to see the path, &amp;c.! Rev. <hi rend="italic">Mr. Paterson </hi>&amp; wife were there: the Dean &amp; Son: Dr. Spencer &amp; other medicos: Rev. W. Welsh &amp; wife, Carlile, Andrews (Whanganui), Craig, Crerar, &amp; many others—about 60 altogether, in <hi rend="italic">big </hi>room Athenm. Buildg.—Museum goods &amp; gods not yet put to rights!!</p>
         <p>What of Govt. Printer? I see he has <hi rend="italic">resigned</hi>. Ten days ago, or so, I recd. a packet from him first 3 pp., &amp; 3 very long Galley slips of my poor old Mao. Lex. part A., with a letter from him (another “<hi rend="underline italic">extra</hi>”) hard put, to go over it, twice, &amp; <hi rend="italic">read w. copy</hi>! I returned proof as quickly as I could, w. a letter to <hi rend="italic">him</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">now</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">resignation</hi>! another obstacle—I suppose. Proofs were <hi rend="italic">good</hi>, w. very few errors.</p>
         <p>It blew furiously at N. on Thursday night 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. My biggest &amp; oldest Acacia tree (35 yrs old) uprooted, &amp; in its fall smashed fence.—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Warm</hi> letters in papers betn. Buller &amp; Fraser Pakeha-Maori Interpr. (&amp; general <hi rend="italic">fleecer</hi> of the poor Maoris—I <hi rend="italic">don’t like </hi>him—never did!) I think B. has the best of it—see p. <hi rend="italic">of this day </hi>w. this.</p>
         <p>Hamilton is Prest., Otago Auxiliary Inst., he has just sent me an amazing Catalogue (<hi rend="underline italic">100</hi>ds Maori curios) printed at Patea: collection of many years by a Pawnbroker at Taranaki to be sold <hi rend="italic">without Reserve</hi> at Dunedin tomorrow. I am pretty well <hi rend="italic">here</hi>: weather fine until this mg.—now again clearing—night, frosty. Hope you <hi rend="italic">all </hi>are well. Kind regards, yours ever, W. Colenso.</p>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke, May 19/96</p>
         <p>Will write shortly. W.C.</p>
         <p>Woodville——–20–22 (D.V.)<lb/>Waipukurau      23–<hi rend="underline italic">24</hi>—<hi rend="underline italic">Ch.S</hi>.<lb/>Waipawa———25<lb/>Makotuku——–27<lb/>Dannevk———28–30th</p>
         <p rend="end">(19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi rend="italic">evening</hi>.)</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">P.S. </hi>Have just read your capital letter <hi rend="italic">again</hi>! Since writing to you &amp; putting up paper (no.2). Thanks for it—<hi rend="italic">I go w. you heartily </hi>in <hi rend="italic">many things</hi>. I have been here 4–5 days,—have seen <hi rend="italic">little </hi>of Robertshawe (High Ch!) who has been absent in Weber District: he told me on Saty. in street, leaving (our <hi rend="italic">first </hi>interview) he had arranged w. his Lay Reader for Sunday Services (he lives 6–7 miles distant) but wishes me to share w. him—I said, <hi rend="italic">No</hi>. At Ch. on Sy. mg. Lay R. went thro the S. in less than 1 hour! Sermon read from a book occupying 9 minutes! his name is <hi rend="italic">Costall</hi>—any relation to Gt. Pr.?—rather a yg. man without reverence for Book—possibly for postures, &amp;c.</p>
         <p>Slip in yr. L. re “Davidson on Canon”—just seen, will send on my return to N.—</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
