<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0806">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 November 18: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-11-18">1891 November 18</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 November 18: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-556" place="foot" n="556"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, November 18, 1891.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Although I wrote to you so recently only 3 days ago I am going to begin another letter, just to notice a few items in your last 2 letters which I could not well take up in my last. At the same time, I must preface by saying, that my chest is painful when I lean forward to write—this horrid influenza still holding sway! <hi rend="italic">increased</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">returned w. power</hi>) I regret to say, through my sitting in the R.M. Court last Monday from X.30 to XII.30, in a <hi rend="italic">strong cold draft</hi>! So that, at last, I left it <hi rend="italic">shivering</hi>. I had been summoned by C. &amp; McL. to give evidence in a trumpery squabble between Blom &amp; Petersen &amp; P. &amp; Blom, (3–4 witnesses on each side, &amp; had to be <hi rend="italic">re-heard</hi>! in the <hi rend="italic">2 cases</hi>!) and after all <hi rend="italic">my</hi> evidence was <hi rend="underline italic">not</hi> required, &amp; both wretched cases were <hi rend="underline italic">Dismissed</hi>, &amp; rightly too.—</p>
         <p>Now to yours: you say, “It was perhaps well that I was not at Renata’s feast.” &amp; no doubt, you are right—from your point of view: but what I meant (in my remarking (?) that I could throw light on Renata’s last words re his will) was of a different nature altogether: it is grounded on what took place at Waitangi (H.B.) in ’45—which became proverbial among the Maoris—but the story is <hi rend="italic">too long</hi> to write in a letter.—S.W. never knew of it; and he was (or <hi rend="italic">is</hi>) <hi rend="italic">not</hi> friendly enough w. <hi rend="italic">me </hi>for me to volunteer the narration. Again you are right, in thinking, that it is pretty nearly alike as to Donnelly or Broughton <hi rend="italic">caring </hi>for “the Trust”:—though perhaps the odds are in B’s. favour, through his <hi rend="italic">closer</hi> connection w. the Maoris. But (as I have often said, publicly, too,) <hi rend="italic">Mrs</hi>. D. would never have dared, or ventured, to act as she has done—from the <hi rend="italic">beginning</hi>—had she not been set on by D., &amp; the Lawyers, &amp; the Creditors!!! A rather note-worthy incident <hi rend="italic">re</hi> this matter took place at Dannevirke in the N. L. Court, <hi rend="italic">while I was under examination, &amp;c., on oath</hi>: that fellow Fraser (a regular out-&amp;-out swell pakeha-maori!) must for sooth to please his party (or himself—to show his mightiness!) put some questions to me, irrelevant &amp; nasty, as concerning <hi rend="italic">one</hi> of my old M. Teachers (Matthew) now blind, and present; winding-up by saying—<hi rend="italic">re</hi> Mrs. Donelly’s grandmother, Renata’s sister, that “she was the <hi rend="italic">married</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">wife</hi> of the great Chief Tiakitai”, (this, of course, to be <hi rend="italic">taken down</hi>)—I rejoined: “<hi rend="italic">No: not so, the slave-concubine</hi>” <hi rend="italic">this, </hi>F. &amp; others (pakehas &amp; judges) had had before from me when in a similar position at Hastings, 3–4 yrs ago: Mrs D. also present. I could write a good (?)—rather a curious &amp; peculiar—memoir of Tiakitai, &amp; of other big chiefs of H. Bay.—</p>
         <p>(This is Wedy. night, &amp; my clock has just struck VIII, so <hi rend="italic">I am</hi> thinking—<hi rend="italic">you</hi> may be in your Philosoph. Conclave, with my tedious paper on the <hi rend="italic">lapis.</hi>)</p>
         <p>You also remark, re the <hi rend="italic">proof</hi> I sent you, that it “was interesting, &amp; appears to be a very full &amp; exhaustive botanl. dicty.”—It is a wonderful work! It originated w. <hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, &amp; on his death Hooker took it up, but <hi rend="italic">thousands</hi> of £s. were <hi rend="italic">wanted</hi>! much money has been collected, &amp; the Uy. Of Oxford has agreed to publish it,—at their own cost, &amp; <hi rend="italic">certain immediate loss</hi>. 2 vols. of some 1200 pp. each. Mr Daydon Jackson (one of the Secys. Linn. Socy.) has been workg. at it (Tregear fash—<hi rend="italic">as to zeal</hi>) ever since ’82: “the Darwin family have already expended nearly £3000, &amp; will pay Jackson £150. a yr. while engd. on it. – – – – I have to revise the whole of the work myself, before going to press, &amp; when I tell you that there are 500– to 600,000 notices,—you may guess what that means. – – – It is the heaviest job I have ever undertaken, &amp;c, &amp;c. I fear there will be a heavy bill for <hi rend="italic">correction</hi> of the press, towards which the Clarendon Press makes a handsome allowance”. <hi rend="italic">You</hi> may see I have <hi rend="italic">quoted</hi> largely from Hooker’s last letter, that came w. “proof.,”—as I knew it <hi rend="italic">would interest </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>: and now, last week, I recd a case (24in by 22) per “Doric”, contg. Sir J.D.H’s. <hi rend="italic">portrait</hi>—long promised,—but <hi rend="italic">not yet seen by me</hi>—(like Tregrs. Dicty.!) Ellison &amp; D. had some trouble (as usual) in passing it at Customs—so that I was obliged to see Patten—though (between us) I don’t think Carter cares too much for P.—</p>
         <p>I should like for you to see Hooker’s writing! I have <hi rend="italic">often</hi> wondered how any comp. could decypher it, seeing, too, pretty much of it is in <hi rend="italic">foreign</hi> language. I have been engd. of late (at times) in putting up small crypts. for Kew—<hi rend="italic">my last</hi>!———Hope to finish by Jan.1892.</p>
         <p>I think I told you I had recd. a letter from Sir W. Buller, written 2 days <hi rend="italic">bef.</hi> his wife’s death,—but <hi rend="italic">not</hi> its purport.—It was to get from <hi rend="italic">me</hi> a short Memoir of myself for a Lond. gent. travelling &amp; collecting inform. for a large Lond. printing firm. &amp;c, who had recently left Wgn. for Engd. Evidently <hi rend="italic">B</hi>. had not seen your “Typo”—so I sent him <hi rend="italic">one</hi>—<hi rend="italic">last week</hi>. I see, in “Typo” you have John Bassett, Ed. &amp; prop. of “Printing World”; he got from me, on application, a long time back, copies of nearly all my papers, but I have never since heard from him, <hi rend="italic">neither do I know if he recd. them</hi>! I shall post this days “Herald” to you, that you may see <hi rend="italic">re V. Bedingfield</hi>; and art. on Governor. There is little <hi rend="italic">new</hi> in C. Philips “Moth-trap” (so nicely sketched by you),—save in the dish of oil, &amp;c below: the plan is an <hi rend="italic">old</hi> one for taking Moths; though sugared, or molasses, on paper, was used—to capture specimens for preserving.</p>
         <p>I am much vexed w. the way in which <hi rend="italic">our val</hi>. Books are kept in the Library—on their shelves thus <hi rend="bold">////.</hi> I have several times put them to rights, &amp; told <hi rend="italic">folks</hi> (offls. &amp; others) of it: I note, also, that some vols. are <hi rend="italic">out</hi> from Jany. last!</p>
         <p>Last wk. I had a <hi rend="italic">visit</hi> from Wimdram &amp; his associate (a big burly fellow, name unknown,) <hi rend="italic">re</hi> valuation as Property Assessors, &amp;c—they staid ½ hour,—I did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> relish the remarks of “the big ’un” trouble, I suppose, ahead!—</p>
         <p>When I go to town I shall <hi rend="italic">seek</hi> a “Naut. Almc.”—&amp;, if reasonable, buy; but if <hi rend="italic">not</hi>—shall send to you.</p>
         <p>Here I stop for the time—<hi rend="underline italic">tired</hi>.—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">20</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th.</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> night.—</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Weather being fine I ventured to town this mg. as I wished to see Mr. Parkinson; I went thither in “trap” but could not see him, the Dr. was engaged w. him, and would be for some time, so his sister told me,—and that, he was much worse: I had heard this from the Dean who had been sent for by P. yesty. mg. at daybreak, after passing a wretched night; I left w. her your kind message: afterwards in town, talking briefly w. Mr Sidey, he (again) mentioned his great concern for him, &amp; that he believed he would not recover. Dr. Allen is his med. man; but yesty. mg. other Doctors were called in for a consultation. We must still <hi rend="italic">hope</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">look</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">up</hi>. I am far from well myself, this influenza with me seems to have taken quite <hi rend="italic">another </hi>phase, head-ache, eyes burning &amp; hot, &amp; <hi rend="italic">coughing</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">incessantly</hi>, w. gt. pain in chest: so I hasten to close this that it may be posted in the mg. Unforty. I am <hi rend="italic">fixed</hi> for duty at Augs. on Sunday, both mg. &amp; evg.—&amp; there is no one else—not even a lay reader there! Of course I shall <hi rend="italic">try hard</hi> to do my best &amp; if I fail—or fall—I do so in faith: in this, as in other matters, <hi rend="italic">past</hi> &amp; present, I endeavour to say &amp; to act—Thy will be done.—</p>
         <p>With kindest regards Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours very sincerely, W. Colenso.—</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
