<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0956">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1896 January 15: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-1.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1896-01-15">1896 January 15</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1896 January 15: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-772" place="foot" n="772"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-1.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Jany. l5th. 1896.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding,</p>
         <p>Your kind letter of 13th. to hand last night: I had been talking to you a few hours before (IV.p.m.) w. your sister Mrs Wilkie, who had kindly come to see me bringing your <hi rend="italic">eldest</hi>. I was much pleased w. both, your daughter seems very well—the <hi rend="italic">picture</hi> of health. I should mention the curious adventure of the day before. (You <hi rend="italic">know</hi> how I <hi rend="italic">dress</hi>!! here in my cell—and also perhaps my old <hi rend="italic">Rule</hi>—“Open to the public, from II to IV. p.m.” Well at <hi rend="italic">V. sharp</hi>, I take my cup of tea, still in “dress”, shirt sleeves &amp; loose shawl, &amp; just as I had sat to tea, evg. before, a card was brought in (Robert having told the bearer “I was engaged”—<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> at tea) <hi rend="italic">Mrs Wilkie</hi> on card: “Who is this Mrs W?” no one knew—but she would call again tomorrow. I set it down, to some f. of one of the numerous “Churches” out on her <hi rend="italic">usual </hi>rounds of begging! However it turned out to be <hi rend="italic">your own</hi> sister! And <hi rend="italic">full</hi> explan. being given, <hi rend="italic">all right</hi>. Our convn. lasted nearly an hour, and was animated, cheering: you, &amp; your Father came in for a good share: I much wish to see <hi rend="italic">him</hi>, &amp; will (D.V.) ere long, by fixing a day &amp; hour, &amp;c.—–</p>
         <p>I have a few items to give you: I think I sent you a p. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Pinkney (another <hi rend="italic">long</hi> prosy L. from him <hi rend="italic">since</hi> wh. I send now): a p. contg. <hi rend="italic">lg. letter</hi> from Allom, Tasmania, re <hi rend="italic">Bees</hi> a terribly <hi rend="italic">fussy </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">family</hi> affair: I believe I sent you <hi rend="italic">this</hi>. Then Hill was out—2–3 times, re his <hi rend="italic">new</hi> Club, &amp; his Hon. Secy. sent me (a 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. time) a <hi rend="italic">begging</hi> ep.—said (by him) to have been instigated by <hi rend="italic">Hill</hi>—I ansd. it—enclosing (unwillingly) £2—for <hi rend="italic">Hill’s sake</hi>—but, at same time, conscientiously telling him, I could not see where the true education lay—in their noisy programme, &amp;c. and (as Hill was leaving for Australia) I wrote similarly but more at length to Hill, &amp; <hi rend="italic">very plainly</hi>, adding I could gladly aid any one—a journeyman shoemaker, carpenter, plumber, &amp;c., w. advice, books, &amp; even money, who went out w. a heart to seek after nature’s beauties in Geology, Zoology, Botany, &amp;c.—but <hi rend="italic">not</hi> that singing &amp; music &amp; picnicing, &amp; mutual admiration &amp; animal enjoyment.—I kept <hi rend="italic">no </hi>copy of mine to H., but I send you <hi rend="italic">his </hi>reply. Of course H. is wholly gone w. this new fad: his wife w. him in it, also eldest son (who is their chief) &amp; eldest daughter too!—I have spent the aftn. of 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>. with him at his house. I had (<hi rend="underline italic">long</hi> ago) begged of him for “Institute’s” sake to so arrange his visits for ’96, that he might be <hi rend="italic">in Napier</hi> during the <hi rend="underline italic">six</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> nights </hi>but he would <hi rend="italic">not</hi> consent! And, again, to defer going to A. until <hi rend="italic">after </hi>annual Mtg.— “NO”. So, at last, I devised a plan that the meeting (1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. My. in Feb) to be called, &amp; as a quorum is 11, to have <hi rend="italic">no</hi> 9 m. &amp; so ppone it until <hi rend="italic">March</hi>—when he will be here (D.V.) It is very clear to me, that unless H. (and 1, or 2, more?) acts warily &amp; zealously the H.B. Ph. Inst., will become a thing of the <hi rend="italic">past</hi>! (<hi rend="italic">absit omen</hi>.) I could <hi rend="italic">tell </hi>you more.</p>
         <p>Dinwiddie (Hon. Secy). has lately seen Gore at Wgn., re missing paper of mine: and <hi rend="italic">now</hi> (<hi rend="underline italic">yesty</hi>!) that I turned-to, to <hi rend="italic">work</hi>—I have <hi rend="italic">discovered</hi> that “Paper” was <hi rend="italic">never sent to Wgn</hi>. <hi rend="italic">&amp; that Gore was right</hi>!! (Keep this <hi rend="italic">private,</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">pro tem</hi>., till I write to Gore next week—on this &amp; other matters). I had a latter from G. last week; in it he says, “Sir J.H. is at the N. beyond Auckld.”</p>
         <p>On Monday I was engaged in putting up—in a case—one of the big Greenstone slabs for Buller, who wished to have one and this mg. in putting up—6 ea. of pubs. for Crerar—including “Kereopa”. Working every day (hour) in <hi rend="italic">pain</hi> from all joints; very heavy &amp; constant in me of late, save when <hi rend="italic">quiescent</hi>: but <hi rend="italic">much less</hi> this evening: the weather has been <hi rend="italic">very hot</hi>, &amp; dry, &amp; for the last 3 days <hi rend="underline italic">windy</hi>—wind W.—–</p>
         <p>I took mg. S. in Cathedral on 5<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—&amp; evg. S. at St. Augustine’s—but <hi rend="italic">two whole </hi>Ch. of E. Services in <hi rend="italic">one day</hi> is too much for me: I <hi rend="italic">felt it</hi>. Bp. W. is again back—preached last Sy. evg. in Cathl. from Rom. xii. 1: a <hi rend="italic">long</hi> S. <hi rend="italic">Re</hi> your clippings: I agree w. you, “somewhat barbaric”—this latest luxury of entombing of flowers &amp; animals. And I go <hi rend="italic">wholly</hi> w. Monsr. Lageau <hi rend="italic">re</hi> “over study in schools”—as sent &amp; <hi rend="italic">underlined</hi> by you: I have ever held that belief—and would it were carried out in its integrity <hi rend="italic">here</hi>—&amp; don’t believe such will be—in days to come. </p>
         <p>I note (w. interest) what you say, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> “hell”—reinga, hades, &amp;c—but must not take it up—tonight. I believe I have <hi rend="italic">Hone</hi> (far away in a corner shelf)—but I have also far better than <hi rend="italic">his</hi> compilations &amp; translations. It is astonishing, the no. &amp; variations of those <hi rend="italic">early</hi> (<hi rend="italic">earliest</hi>) writings—espy. when we consider <hi rend="italic">all </hi>M.S.S.! and such <hi rend="italic">poor </hi>materials, &amp; scanty too, for writing; and it is well (on the <hi rend="italic">whole</hi>) that such a good discrimination was exercised, in sorting out their “<hi rend="underline italic">pie</hi>”. The Churches erred greatly in <hi rend="italic">not</hi> keeping <hi rend="italic">closer</hi> to those words at <hi rend="italic">end</hi> of Matt. (recg. them as genuine)—i.e. <hi rend="italic">teaching them to obs. whatsoever </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">I have commanded you</hi>”—But, ’tis the teachings &amp; commands, &amp; catechisms of churches <hi rend="italic">put in the place of those of Jesus</hi>: exactly the same kind of error as he found fault w. the Jews of his day for their doing— “teaching for doctrines the commndts. of man.</p>
         <p>I note what you say <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the <hi rend="italic">Veronica </hi>(a mistake, I ween.) I <hi rend="italic">did</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">not</hi>, <hi rend="italic">do not</hi>, wish <hi rend="italic">you to see the wh.</hi> plant <hi rend="italic">again</hi>, neither trouble the owner about it,—but merely (in a <hi rend="italic">few words</hi>) tell me—<hi rend="italic">height</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="italic">general appce.</hi> of shrub—loose, or compact, spreading, or not:—not of much consequence; I suppose <hi rend="italic">you plucked</hi> that specimen you sent.</p>
         <p>Robert Anderson’s wife returned hither on Thursday 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>. <hi rend="underline italic">Most unexpectedly</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> she rushed in to see me</hi>!! I had previously told <hi rend="italic">him</hi>—that she was to be as a mere visitor to them (<hi rend="italic">as far as I was concerned</hi>) until the Monday evg. 6th when we would have <hi rend="italic">our talk</hi>. This accordgly. took place, <hi rend="italic">all</hi> present, and as she <hi rend="italic">promised</hi> to obey &amp;c. and so things have gone on—&amp; <hi rend="italic">much better</hi> than before (on a sep. bit of p. I will give you <hi rend="italic">my terms</hi>—which her son had also sent to her in Scotland).——–I scarcely need tell you—that on the whole I was pleased with this.</p>
         <p>And now for another <hi rend="italic">new</hi> arrangement! In Decr. P.S. McLean, &amp; Sir Donald’s son, &amp; several others (<hi rend="underline italic">Sc</hi>. of course,) made overtures to me, to have the use of the <hi rend="italic">3 outer</hi> paddocks for golf play—&amp; yesty. I agreed, &amp; a lease is to be drawn for 3 yrs. Then I proceed to stop the public from going through my grounds—by advt. &amp;c. 100 d’s daily—<hi rend="underline italic">more</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> than by M. Rd</hi>! to S. end of Scinde Island; but, had I <hi rend="italic">not</hi> entered into this agt. such <hi rend="italic">must be done</hi> as <hi rend="italic">it is unbearable</hi>! grass destroyed, fences &amp; banks broken down, trees broken up, gates left open, horses straying &amp; impounded, &amp;c, &amp;c, &amp;c.—fowls, ducks &amp;c, all killed by dogs; fruit stolen, &amp;c.—continual terror from <hi rend="italic">fire—smokers’ matches</hi>.                                           (<hi rend="italic">Good</hi> night, X p.m.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">16</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">.</hi> You err, Hamilton is <hi rend="italic">not </hi>here, only Mr<hi rend="underline">s</hi> H. &amp; children: he <hi rend="italic">may</hi> visit New Plymouth.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Re</hi> Min. Lands &amp; Buller, and your just remark—“I can think of no graver kind of misdemeanour on the part of public men, than to use their official power to gratify a personal grudge.”—How this applies to <hi rend="italic">me </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">D.</hi> McLean &amp; the Mao. Lexicon! A few days ago in conversing w. Sir. G. Whitmore down in town I happd. in speaking of the <hi rend="italic">past</hi> to call Sir. D. <hi rend="italic">his</hi> “<hi rend="italic">friend</hi>”. Heigho! You should have heard Sir G.!! (I suppose I told you, years ago about the Mao. Lex. &amp; McL) Whitmore (as far as I knew) was the only other person cognisant of it. If I have <hi rend="italic">not</hi> told you—<hi rend="italic">let me know</hi>.</p>
         <p>Again: your remarks are excellent, because truthful natural, <hi rend="italic">re</hi> my sticking to my “home” and “fitting <hi rend="italic">all surroundings</hi> to me”, &amp;c. (as you too, are enabled to do) but now and for 2–3 years I have another <hi rend="italic">important</hi> factor to deal with—<hi rend="italic">loss of teeth</hi>, so that I am driven to <hi rend="italic">soft</hi> foods—a bit of stewed mutton or its soup, every day, w. sardines &amp;c. (not liking eggs), and my appetite, though <hi rend="underline italic">good</hi>, dislikes the sameness, &amp;c. I have been to Wilson several times <hi rend="italic">re</hi> set of teeth, he has <hi rend="italic">thrown it</hi> up! unless I consent to extraction of several <hi rend="italic">low</hi> stumps in both jaws, which are <hi rend="italic">firmly</hi> set. I could not endure the pain; W. proposes “Chloroform”,—“<hi rend="underline italic">NO</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">, not at my age</hi>”: and so it <hi rend="italic">ends</hi>. Were I at hotel, or <hi rend="italic">good</hi> kind <hi rend="italic">thoughtful</hi> Housekpr. all would be well enough—Tapioca, Rice, A-Root, C-flour puddings &amp;c, &amp;c. would suit me <hi rend="italic">well</hi>—but <hi rend="italic">I</hi> must <hi rend="italic">not think</hi> of such things. While Mary A. makes such commonly <hi rend="italic">for her son John</hi>. But I must stop <hi rend="italic">this</hi>: you cannot form a correct notion of what I have, <hi rend="italic">in such simple </hi>matters! <hi rend="italic">submitted to</hi>. Hence it was, that I formerly made such <hi rend="italic">long stays</hi> in Country Hotels (change in diet), and <hi rend="italic">never called this house–</hi>“<hi rend="underline italic">Home</hi>”!!! (It <hi rend="italic">may</hi> however, alter yet for the better.)</p>
         <p>Have read—again &amp; again! your sad relation <hi rend="italic">re</hi> your being so <hi rend="italic">fettered</hi> in your movements owing to <hi rend="italic">financial difficulties</hi>. If things (<hi rend="italic">finance</hi>) were now with me as they <hi rend="italic">were</hi> 2–3 years ago, I could help you; my difficulties (self &amp; <hi rend="italic">others depend. on me</hi>) are these (1) <hi rend="italic">No rents</hi> &amp;c. from Octr. /94 – Dec. /95 (2) Income—when <hi rend="italic">all pd</hi>. £200 a yr. <hi rend="underline italic">less</hi> for ’96 &amp; fut. (3) “Call” Bk. N.Z. a millstone! (4) To all that, I think I should also add that in my late will, I have bound my executors to sq. up everything <hi rend="italic">within 2yrs</hi> and this keeps me from entering on anything <hi rend="italic">new</hi>—not wishing to cause <hi rend="italic">embarrassment to anyone</hi> hereafter. I have had several applications for <hi rend="italic">aid</hi> which I <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi> give. Only last night replied to one from a <hi rend="italic">very respect. old</hi> resident in N. (known to you) wanting a loan of £10 to save his furniture &amp;c. being taken &amp; sold; very sorry, <hi rend="italic">cannot aid. </hi>Of course I have this large block of land here, but I am <hi rend="italic">hampered</hi>, obstructed, in selling portions; a gentm. (<hi rend="italic">married man from S</hi>.) called on me a short time ago, re purchg. part of the big S. hill, but when he found I had no other entrance from Carlyle St., than the <hi rend="italic">narrow</hi> Govt. lane (yclep’d “Faraday St”) <hi rend="underline italic">22 feet</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">wide</hi>! that sufficed. Many years ago I offered to give Borough 15 feet wide all the way up to make street—<hi rend="italic">NO</hi>.—and then, <hi rend="italic">add thereto</hi> (1) natl. love of <hi rend="italic">quiet</hi>, increasing w. age: (2) The certainty of my quitting all ere long. I intend, however, <hi rend="underline italic">shortly</hi>, once more making a <hi rend="italic">public</hi> move in 3 papers <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the old projected road from N. Terrace through my grounds to Milton Road: <hi rend="italic">now</hi> there is a very large no. of folks living S. end Scinde Island on hill—and these should move in the matter, &amp; I think they will. I <hi rend="italic">give</hi> the land (¾ths of what will be required) and<hi rend="italic"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">if the</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>Ch<hi rend="italic">. </hi>(Saml. W.) will give the ¼th all may be done; but <hi rend="italic">all Chs</hi>. are greedy! </p>
         <p>The Dean, w. &amp; fy., are back from the Coast, (Mangakuri—S. of Waimarama), &amp; seem to have enjoyed themselves.There is a little Ch. building there belg. to Station, where D.S. is regularly held: the D. took mg. &amp; <hi rend="italic">sad to hear</hi> Layman (Manager of Station) in evg., &amp; the D. says, “he preached a very nice Sermon”. I note how you are wkg. <hi rend="italic">on Sundays</hi>, and it pleases me—yet in <hi rend="italic">drawbacks</hi>: your <hi rend="italic">need of rest</hi>, seeing, too, you wk. <hi rend="italic">late</hi>. Dont overtask. God does <hi rend="italic">not </hi>req. <hi rend="italic">that</hi>.—–</p>
         <p>                   Kindest regards</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>                   W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
