<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1049">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1898 May 19: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1898-05-19">1898 May 19</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1898 May 19: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-899" place="foot" n="899"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Gow’s Hotel<lb/>Waipukurau<lb/>May 19 1898</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I have <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> so much in mind</hi> that I must need to be scribbling to you again:—not, however, to cause you to be writing to me. Yesterday was a red-letter day to me—<hi rend="italic">here</hi>.</p>
         <p>I wrote to you on 12<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., came hither on 14<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>—weather unpleasant wet &amp; cold, but travelling <hi rend="italic">all the better for </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">me</hi>—few passengers indeed, from Takapau I <hi rend="italic">alone</hi>! Sunday, cold, &amp;c, remained incog. Monday, visited Vicarage &amp; Manse our friend Grant well &amp; hearty. Tuke wished me to take Ch. S. on Sy. next, as he was going on Friday to Ashley Clinton, &amp;c, and would not return until Sunday 5, p.m., but, having been so long absent from N., &amp; hotels expensive &amp;c—I did not consent: on returning to hotel, &amp; thinking over it, &amp; seeing in the Hd. <hi rend="underline italic">ill</hi>ness of Dean on Sunday 8<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., I wrote to the D., offerg. small partial help if <hi rend="italic">needed</hi>, or would remain &amp; help Tuke—wire came “he had already arranged”, &amp;c., so, I <hi rend="italic">have agreed to stay over next Sy</hi>.—but, nolens volens, <hi rend="italic">must </hi>go <hi rend="underline italic">on My.</hi> to escape Q.Bth.D. &amp; races, Tuesday, &amp;c.—</p>
         <p>Yesty. <hi rend="italic">a gala day here</hi>! Gow’s eldest nephew (a yg. m. long with Jones) to “a nice yg. woman”, a teacher in Tuke’s Sy. Sch., the match <hi rend="italic">very popular</hi>: and (strange to say) this old m., <hi rend="italic">asked</hi>, by bride &amp; b.groom, and family &amp; friends and Tuke, to help in tying the knot! at first wod. <hi rend="italic">not </hi>consent, but gave way &amp; took share in mge. ceremony. Day gloriously fine! all ’Pukurau out! Catholics &amp; prots. Jews &amp; Gentiles! such a motley crowd: Ch. crammed, with lots outside, all went off <hi rend="italic">well</hi>: Mr. Grant at Ch. <hi rend="italic">Gow</hi> gave her away: folks came from Dvk., &amp; Waipawa, &amp;c, &amp;c,—and adjourned to f-in-law’s house there <hi rend="italic">ample </hi>refreshments for all hands—&amp; on tables in <hi rend="italic">open</hi>! (though nights <hi rend="italic">cold &amp; frosty</hi>) Heigh ho! My <hi rend="italic">last </hi>mge in ’52! (food for thought!)—–</p>
         <p>Yesterday, also, the <hi rend="italic">missing </hi>parcel ½ dz. copies of “A.” sent by Mackay came to hand: strange to say <hi rend="italic">only bearing postmark.</hi> “Waipukurau 18.” A nicely got up vol.; you will recollect seeing me at wk. on it in 1884! (also Grubb, Fannin, Hill, &amp;c.)—more <hi rend="italic">food again for thought</hi>! I could have <hi rend="italic">cried</hi>—pardon weakness! <hi rend="italic">strange lonely </hi>thoughts—too solemn even to jot down to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Ebenezer</hi>!—what a host of memories! resuscitations, &amp;c, &amp;c.—–</p>
         <p>Further: letters from S. &amp; N. (particularly from Brunnerton, and Hokianga)—encouraging <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the pamphlet, “Errors of R.”, &amp; wanting copies, &amp;c. And, also, a letter (which I shall enclose) <hi rend="italic">I have consented</hi>, adding, I would send him a copy of “50 yrs. in N.Z.”, if required.—<hi rend="underline italic">Return</hi> letter anon:—who is the writer?</p>
         <p>I uppose you may have seen Hd. of Monday, 16<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.? If not, look <hi rend="italic">it </hi>up: mine is gone North. Some person or person<hi rend="underline">s</hi> have been writing, too much, of <hi rend="italic">me</hi>! I should like very much to <hi rend="italic">see </hi>Seddon, <hi rend="italic">soon</hi>: if not, shall write, but I want to have “A.” fully <hi rend="italic">settled</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> as to any payment to Govt. I am very well, getting stronger daily: think I shall soon (D.V.) go up &amp; down my hill in Napier! Another <hi rend="italic">capital </hi>letter from Home—Sir J. Hooker: now all <hi rend="italic">these good </hi>things coming <hi rend="italic">together</hi>, should make me <hi rend="italic">wary</hi>—a <hi rend="italic">squall may be at Hand</hi>! but never mind, “Deus noster refugium”.</p>
         <p> Kindest regards to you &amp; all—</p>
         <p>                         Yours ever                              W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>Rev. J. Patterson removing to Gisborne: Library 850 vols. to be sold at auction on 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. at night.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
