<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0750">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1890 October 21: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0495.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1890-10-21">1890 October 21</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1890 October 21: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-484" place="foot" n="484"> ATL qMS-0495.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke, Octr. 21/ 90</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Your welcome Birth-day (19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) souvenir reached me yesterday, and I thank you for it. I had been some time wondering what might have happened—son’s illness, or <hi rend="italic">your </hi>over exertions &amp; grief at the <hi rend="italic">great </hi>Printing office fire, or your <hi rend="italic">own </hi>illness, or your <hi rend="italic">overworking</hi> at office:—and now, my dear friend, I am <hi rend="italic">right glad to hear </hi>from you, to<hi rend="italic"> see </hi>your well-known hand writing again, to <hi rend="italic">know </hi>that <hi rend="italic">you </hi>are <hi rend="italic">well </hi>in physical health, to <hi rend="italic">congratulate </hi>you &amp; rejoice <hi rend="italic">with </hi>you on your Birth day, and, <hi rend="italic">best of all</hi>, to join you, heartily, I hope, in using those <hi rend="italic">precious </hi>texts of scripture you have brought forward in your letter—they have long been among my own choice &amp; peculiar ones; may they (w. others like them) be your &amp; my solace &amp; comfort in our journey through life—increasingly so as the years pass-by: for there is little here—as things now are and (I fear) are yet likely to become—to deserve our attention.—</p>
         <p>You are right—in saying—“the past is my warrant for the fullest trust in Divine Providence for all the days to come”: Yes: I have preached that pretty often of late, but I want to realize it more—to have it always ever-present w. me.—</p>
         <p>You however say:—“I have not had a reply to my last letter.”—This is strange (&amp; yet, to a certain degree, you are right,) my last to you was on 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. Sept.—written from Woodville—&amp; at that time you were <hi rend="italic">2 </hi>letters in my debt! In yours to me of the 28<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. Sept. (though I think this date erroneous on your part, because the Wgn. P.O. stamp on it is “<hi rend="italic">27 </hi>Septr.”) in that letter—written <hi rend="italic">before </hi>you had received mine of 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—you begin by saying— “I think it must be 3 weeks since I wrote, &amp; now I have <hi rend="italic">2 </hi>long &amp; kind letters of yours to answer.” Further, I may add, that when I went to the Wdv. P.O. <hi rend="italic">on 26</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. Friday</hi>, to post my letter of 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. I enquired, If there were a Mail going that day to Wgn., as the Ry. train &amp; Palmn. coach were <hi rend="italic">not </hi>running. And so I have been waiting to hear from you. Before I drop this—I would ask you to kindly give date (or dates) of the <hi rend="italic">last </hi>recd. by you: <hi rend="italic">as a rule </hi>I always do so, to every one at beg. of letter: and, 2ndly (should you at any time not answer directly,) just <hi rend="italic">look into</hi> the last to hand, &amp; see if there be not something to be noticed, or answered. The <hi rend="italic">not </hi>doing this is a very common error—at <hi rend="italic">Home</hi>! &amp; often serves to vex me: my <hi rend="italic">eldest </hi>son in particular errs in that way. But I must stop this.—</p>
         <p>My last was from Wdv. directly after Lect. aid of Presbytn. Ch. there:—I remained till 27<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.—returning hither that day: and I may tell <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>, that I <hi rend="italic">fully</hi> expected to have heard from Wdv. <hi rend="italic">soon after</hi>—which <hi rend="italic">might, perhaps, have caused me to visit again &amp; again</hi>: but to the present I have heard nothing from that quarter. Unfortunately Mr. Burnett (Minister’s Churchwarden there) had to go to Nelson soon after (Mrs. B. having preceded him) to the funeral of his m-in-law, Dr. Boor’s wife, &amp; he is not yet returned to Wdv. As you see the N. papers, you will have known what is said in them <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the Synod! (I want to know—<hi rend="italic">the real good of the meeting</hi>.) I staid here, (as an old Maori woman in a <hi rend="italic">pa</hi>) to look after leavings: all the other Ch. of E. Bush Ministers having gone to N. But <hi rend="italic">I am </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">idle</hi>—as to Church work; <hi rend="italic">discontentedly so! </hi>and I should not now be here were it not for 2 things (or promises of mine)—1. to see Capt. Deeble <hi rend="italic">once more at Wdv. </hi>before he finally leaves N.Z.: and, 2, to be at the ordination of my good friend R. Stewart, which is to take place there; and <hi rend="italic">perhaps </hi>at the Presbytn. public meeting on the following day. (as <hi rend="italic">our </hi>good friend Rev. J.G. Paterson, <hi rend="italic">wished </hi>this.)—but I shall not be very willing to stay <hi rend="italic">here </hi>much longer—<hi rend="italic">idle</hi>. Of course, <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, who know me so well, will understand what I mean by <hi rend="italic">idle</hi>: last week I have managed to write a paper for our next Instit. Meeting the <hi rend="italic">last </hi>for this season: but though I hope to read it myself, (or failing to do so, shall send it,) I <hi rend="italic">do not write it for publication</hi>—merely for the audience of that evening. I am sick at seeing such stuff—as Taylor White’s, &amp; Smith’s <hi rend="italic">stolen </hi>mess, &amp;c., &amp;c.—pubd. in Trans. The question has again &amp; again been put to me (since my Lect at Wdv., &amp; also by letter, from S.) Why I don’t <hi rend="italic">go on </hi>w. my papers on <hi rend="italic">Anct. </hi>Maori matters? &amp; perhaps Sir J.H. may <hi rend="italic">not like </hi>my answer, should he hear of it.—By the way, I recd. yesterday a copy of a little “Handbook of XtCh.—for <hi rend="italic">use </hi>of<hi rend="italic"> Members </hi>Australn. Assn. Science”—edited by Prof. Hutton, &amp; in first page they are told “the Ty. of Waitgi. was signed on <hi rend="italic">5</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>Feby.”! I have written a note to H. <hi rend="italic">re</hi> same.—also, a letter from “Jos. Churches, Hokitika,” for a copy Mao. Dicty., as he had heard I had some for sale. Hill tells me, he has (at last!) recd. a long letter from Hamilton, who was well &amp; wrote in <hi rend="italic">good spirits</hi>. I wish he would ansr. my letters. I suppose you saw in “Herald” <hi rend="italic">re</hi> the noisy folks in <hi rend="italic">adjg. room </hi>at Athenæum, night of last Instit. Mtg.! I have had a <hi rend="italic">sad </hi>account from Hill &amp; others: it was really <hi rend="italic">too bad</hi>: one writer speaks of them as “<hi rend="italic">un</hi>-christian,” &amp; perhaps he is right. I intend writing to Hon. Secy. to <hi rend="italic">timely </hi>move in matter for the next. I was <hi rend="italic">very glad </hi>to hear of your brother T. having done so well at the Port, &amp; note (w. a sigh!) your remark thereon: I hope the foolish <hi rend="italic">criminal</hi> “strikes” are now pretty nearly at an end—but, I fear, the snake is merely scotch’d <hi rend="italic">not killed</hi>.—I think I can guess your thoughts <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Reardon, &amp; Gannon!! aye, &amp; S. too! N. seems to have sunk pretty low! There is a <hi rend="italic">good </hi>art. in “Herald” of yesty. re Racing &amp;c. Would they had come <hi rend="italic">out earlier</hi>; it is just what I have repeatedly preached, &amp; set forth as I have but <hi rend="italic">one </hi>vote, <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, I shall give that to Capt. R.—–</p>
         <p>Younghusband of this place, (who had married Robjohns’ unfort. daughter,) has lately married J. Wood’s daughter.—of “Herald”; perhaps you knew her, Mr. Rudman’s niece. We had <hi rend="italic">very fine </hi>weather down to 13<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. almost too hot, summer come on us!—but on 13<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. it changed—&amp; since <hi rend="italic">very windy </hi>cold &amp; wet: <hi rend="italic">worse at N. </hi>Hill’s trees<hi rend="italic"> </hi>torn up by roots, &amp;c, &amp;c. That sudden &amp; great change in temp. &amp; w. affected me pretty consy., but I have again rallied and am pretty well, having been several days confined to house, thro’ wh. I hope you have got your vol. “Trans.”—I shall mention it to Hon. Secy., also, others that I know have not been issued.—Howlett has got an Eln. address out—for Masterton! He <hi rend="italic">is mad</hi>, &amp; no mistake, and should follow Harker to asylum: if I can get you a copy (Bush. Adv. <hi rend="italic">reprint</hi>) I will send it. Now I must close.—</p>
         <p>Kindest regards &amp; best wishes for you <hi rend="italic">all</hi>—from yr. old friend, W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. I shall not write again till I hear from you, and <hi rend="italic">so on</hi> as I will (D.V.) write immy. on receipt.</p>
         <p>24<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.<note xml:id="ftn3-485" place="foot" n="485"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-1; pages dated “24th” and “28th” appear to belong here.</note> (Hard frost last night, &amp; cold this mg. yet a <hi rend="italic">fine </hi>winter’s day.)</p>
         <p>I omitted to ask (tho’ at N. I had made a note of it!) Why on earth! did you send back those 2 papers? “H.” &amp; “D.T.”, (w. scraps too, cut from them!) utterly useless to me &amp; cast out; By so doing you <hi rend="italic">wasted</hi> 2 x ½ d. = 1d. The W. Guardian <hi rend="underline italic">I had asked for</hi>, when <hi rend="underline italic">done w. by you</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I enclose a clipping from a Penzance paper—which <hi rend="italic">amuses</hi> me: you, there, at seat of Govt. may know more of it.—</p>
         <p>I regret my being <hi rend="underline italic">idle</hi> here, and shall be glad (for <hi rend="italic">once</hi>!) to leave &amp; return: woods too wet <hi rend="italic">dark</hi> &amp; cold for me to penetrate into their recesses: hope to find a letter from you at N.—</p>
         <p>Once more good bye</p>
         <p>                                                     W.C.</p>
         <p>28<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. x a.m.</p>
         <p>After an awful night of weather! wind, rain, thunder &amp; lightning—such a night as I have but rarely known here at N.—I scrawl this P.S., to let <hi rend="italic">you</hi> know I am going forth—storm allayed a little but very cold, &amp; I w. Rheum. in back &amp;c.</p>
         <p>By leaving today I can halt at Waipawa—tomorrow (D.V.) Dvk., Saty Wdv. <hi rend="italic">Think on me on Sunday</hi>—I shall need it.</p>
         <p>Once more adieu!</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely</p>
         <p>W. Colenso</p>
         <p>Nothing but my old stern view of “sense of duty” impels me to go forward in this weather.</p>
         <p>W.C.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
