<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0553">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1883 December 13: to Luff</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4. Letter addressed to “A. Luff Esq., Post Office, Wellington.” Endorsed “Rec’d Dec. 20”.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73426/">Luff</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1883-12-13">1883 December 13</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1883 December 13: to Luff<note xml:id="ftn3-216" place="foot" n="216"> ATL MS-Copy-Micro-0485-4. Letter addressed to “A. Luff Esq., Post Office, Wellington.” Endorsed “Rec’d Dec. 20”.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Norsewood, Decr. 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>., 1883.</p>
         <p>Mr. A. Luff, <lb/>  Wellington.</p>
         <p>My dear Sir, </p>
         <p>I don’t think <hi rend="italic">you</hi> will be greatly surprised at finding me sojourning <hi rend="italic">here</hi>. I left Napier on Friday last, &amp; stayed a day or two at Gow’s, as I had not been to that township for some time: I brought away some old letters w. me, intending to ansr. them on some <hi rend="italic">rainy</hi> day, shut up in “the Bush”—and yours of Nov. 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. among them. As I generally reply quickly to your (&amp; to most) letters, I trust that you have not thought that <hi rend="italic">I had forgotten you.</hi> At Napier, every day and night too brought their writing work—of late I had been overwhelmed,—though, by close application, keep­ing much at home, &amp; cutting short visits from the <hi rend="italic">few</hi>,—I managed to get on, but I really needed a little relaxation, and so I have left N. for at least a fort­night. I would that you were <hi rend="italic">nearer</hi>, that we might once more have a good long “chat” as in days of old. The rain today keeps me indoors, so I commence my letter-writing; and <hi rend="italic">first </hi>to you.</p>
         <p>I have scarcely remembered such a wet season, so long, so continuous. Gow said on Sunday last, that it was the first dry Sunday, for 17 successive ones were wet. Shearing has not commenced yet in that locality: <hi rend="italic">outside</hi> the plains are <hi rend="italic">very wet</hi>, plantations of trees standing wholly in water, hay, cut, rotting. On the <hi rend="italic">hill</hi>, in my old garden, it is well: my man says he never saw the y. Laburnum nor the Lilac flower there before, &amp; this is his 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. year,—they did, however, formerly; and I had same fine strawberries from the garden. w. plenty of peas &amp;c., &amp;c.—Of course, the whole country is <hi rend="italic">green</hi>, &amp; vegetation generally flourishing.</p>
         <p>I have seen but little of Grubb of late, save in passing him, occasionally, in the street. Several new houses are building in N.,—one (2-story) on the flat, in a line w. Barry’s, where formerly water! one, a large &amp; fine one, where L. &amp; Townley’s shop was—for the Insce. Co.,—one, a monster! high &amp; showy on the hill behind <hi rend="italic">old </hi>U. Bk., for a “High” Girls’ School: this completely commands my porch &amp; front grounds! another for J.D.O.—what <hi rend="italic">was </hi>G. Richardson’s, being enlarged and raised to a 2-story; this too overlooks me, on t’other side. Lucas &amp; Humphreys, Builders, have large steam-mill work-shop on (what was) my Tn. Sec. 325—&amp; there are others—both E. &amp; W. Tylee’s Ho., that was Col. McGregor’s, is to let: Tylee &amp; wife are leaving. Sealy was here lately: I saw him &amp; thought he was looking <hi rend="italic">miserable</hi>!—He will reside, I believe, at Auckland. As you take in the “Herald” you will have seen there report of my case (which I had thought at the time would interest <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, as you know the locality so well,) and, <hi rend="italic">since I left</hi>, I find by the papers that the Judge has given his decision wholly in my favour—leaving<hi rend="italic">me to pay my costs. </hi>I could not see how he could well do otherwise, seeing that the 2 Assessors (one of them too, being the imported Govt. one from Nelson!) had <hi rend="italic">early</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">quickly</hi> done so, though not to the extent of my claim. I <hi rend="italic">was surprised</hi> (though I <hi rend="italic">well knew</hi> the 2 men) to hear Margoliouth’s and Rd. Williams’ statements on<hi rend="italic">oath re</hi> that property. <hi rend="italic">Part</hi> of Margoliouth’s (a rich bit! that caused the <hi rend="italic">walls </hi>of the Court Ho. to smile,) was omitted by his Brother “<hi rend="italic">Councillor</hi>” McDougall, who was the reporter:—Mr. Pat. McLean had been questioning M. pretty sharply as to his <hi rend="italic">employ</hi> (!) knowledge of the value of property, &amp;c. M. said he was a Land &amp; Estate Agent: had been in the profession 12 years: and, after a good deal of fencing, &amp; McLean keeping him to the point, M. said he had disposed of 100 estates during <hi rend="italic">that </hi>period: “but how many during the last 12 months?” M. was <hi rend="italic">obliged</hi> to say (at <hi rend="italic">last</hi>) “<hi rend="italic">Not one</hi>”. His name is on a door in town—but he is never there. Again: M. had valued my corner Sn. 331 in ’79–’80 for Govt. at £400: but <hi rend="italic">this year</hi> at £300. (M. was brought forward by Cottrell, together w. Dick W., to show that my property there had recently increased in value thro’ the railway works adjoining,)—after a deal of twisting on part of M., he actually said that he did it to <hi rend="italic">please </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">me</hi>! who had asked him to strike off £100 from that Sn.!!! <hi rend="italic">I ask him</hi>? to save me 4/2 tax! when we were anything but friendly on account of the <hi rend="italic">old scores </hi>in Reviewers Courts. At the conclusion of M’s. statement, the Court adjd. to lunch, and I was asked by McLean to re-enter the box to give the most flat denial to that statement of M.,—but when I returned to the Court, McL. was addressing the Judge. “It did not matter in the least,” observed McL. to me, “for you see the 2 Assessors did not believe him”: (they had just returned to Court, from their private room, w. the <hi rend="italic">conditional award</hi>). Cottrell from the <hi rend="italic">first—</hi>only stood out on a legal (or <hi rend="italic">ill</hi>egal) quibble.—But eno. of this. All the <hi rend="italic">great </hi>cases—from which we had been expecting so <hi rend="italic">much</hi>! such displays of forensic talent!—<hi rend="italic">or </hi>cunning—came to nought! either settled out of Court, or postponed. Keep out of law, especially<hi rend="italic">the lawyers’ hands</hi>, my good friend; the more I see of it, the more I dislike it.</p>
         <p>I have not time nor space to touch on the <hi rend="italic">great </hi>pol. questions of the day:—France going to war (or <hi rend="italic">at it</hi>) in both Asia &amp; Africa, and claiming such a number of <hi rend="italic">groups </hi>of Polynesian Isles for the worst of purposes! If she goes to war w. China, I do not see how a general war is to be avoided: but we must look <hi rend="italic">Above</hi>. Then there is this Annexn. Q.,—which <hi rend="italic">may</hi> be a very good, or a very bad thing—<hi rend="italic">for us</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Extra </hi>steam service: <hi rend="italic">extra </hi>electric cable commn., &amp;c., all means, <hi rend="italic">extra taxation</hi>. And last, <hi rend="italic">not least</hi>, to H.B. is the Harbour. If ever <hi rend="italic">our</hi> Colony needed good, long-headed, practical, far-seeing men, it is now: May she find them in her need!</p>
         <p>And now (once more) to <hi rend="italic">your letter</hi>. I was <hi rend="italic">gladdened</hi> to get such a budget from you. 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. as to <hi rend="italic">Ruahine</hi> papers: I fear these may <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be published: I have received but <hi rend="italic">few</hi> responses to my “Yellow” Circular. Some of them, however, I <hi rend="italic">value</hi>, as they came <hi rend="italic">quickly</hi> from those <hi rend="italic">old </hi>settlers who had read &amp; highly approved of my recent pamphlet: as Gollan, T.Tanner 3, Oliver (Puketapu), Newton, Vautier, H. Nairn, Trestrail 3, D. McLean, Hill 6 (Inspr. Schools), John Stewart 3, H. Baker 4, D.P. Balfour, Hamilton 3, Sturm 3, &amp;c., &amp;c.—and, of course, yourself 2. (The figs. <hi rend="italic">over </hi>are the no. of copies they wish to have). I was up <hi rend="italic">here</hi> (as you say) “early in Novr.”—1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> to 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. inclusive, working <hi rend="underline italic">hard</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>for our <hi rend="italic">last </hi>meeting on the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.—but the rain spoiled our meeting. I sent you a D.T. containing a report of the Mg. In my opinion the “D.T.” is far ahead of the “H.” &amp; has double the circulation now. Walker is <hi rend="italic">said</hi> to have done <hi rend="italic">D. &amp; Co</hi>. much injury—<hi rend="italic">I am sorry for Peter D</hi>. Thanks for the C. Isld. “Lily” seeds—hope they may do well; you are right as to <hi rend="italic">proper</hi> soil, situation, &amp;c. Your lot of specimens of <hi rend="italic">Crypts</hi>. pleased me much! they reminded me of my old travelling days: they are all known, &amp;, I believe, published; they are <hi rend="italic">all without fruit</hi>, which is always desirable. 2 are Ferns: 5 are Mosses; the rest “Liverworts” (<hi rend="italic">Hepaticæ</hi>): so there are 3 orders here.—They are all pretty, elegant, even while barren:—showing that your son has a good taste for natural beauty. I hope he is <hi rend="italic">well</hi>.</p>
         <p>Write as early &amp; as often as you please &amp; have time. I hope you &amp; yours are all well; I am so. I don’t know if <hi rend="italic">you </hi>keep Xmas: but I will wish you a cheerful one &amp; a “Happy New Year” w. <hi rend="italic">many</hi> returns. Bel. me,</p>
         <p>Yours truly, W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>In a late no. of the “Illustrated N.Z. Times” was a large &amp; faithful drawing of Pakowhai by Sam. Begg: I sent 2 copies to England.</p>
         <p>P.S. (last) The seeds sent, were (of course<hi rend="underline">)</hi> stamped upon!! I have sometimes thought the P.O. <hi rend="italic">underlings</hi> do so out of mere devilry! Consequently I always attach a loose hanging label &amp; put the stamp on that: or, if a <hi rend="italic">few</hi>, or narrow, secure them in the, <hi rend="italic">lower</hi> part of the envelope. W.C.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>