<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0836">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 July 12: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-07-12">1892 July 12</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 July 12: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-597" place="foot" n="597"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke<lb/>July 12, 1892 (night).</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>My last to you was on 28 June, since then 2 kind notes w. enclosures from you, one of the 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi> &amp; one of the 10<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> inst., this last to hand this day.—I thank you much for both, and regret seeing in this last your metion of <hi rend="italic">state of your health</hi>, I trust however that such is only temporary, &amp; will be quite gone ere this reaches you.</p>
         <p>You know the old saw,— “It is an ill wind that blows nobody good;” and so you may thank my unlovely unwelcome visitant <hi rend="italic">Lumbago </hi>that I am here &amp; now writing to you. This day I had <hi rend="italic">fixed </hi>for being at Napier, but on Saturday last I was attacked rather severely on rising, &amp; for some hours feared to attempt Woodville; but getting better I went,–&amp;, as usual, got there in <hi rend="italic">rain</hi>! heavy r. all that night, less r. on Sunday mg., heavy again afternoon &amp; evening &amp; night: <hi rend="italic">very small </hi>Congns. that day; indeed I would not have held Service in the evening, could I have timely informed the folks: moreover, I was now (<hi rend="italic">forced</hi>) in new lodgings, very distant from Ch., the newly built hotel close to Ry. line &amp; Station, kept by Jones—Peters’ old Coach driver;—and the weather being so bad, &amp; new roads so miry, I engaged Peters to drive me to &amp; from Ch. 4 times: Lumbago also having returned early on Sunday mg. very severely;—only my strong sense of “<hi rend="underline italic">Duty</hi>” carried me through. And this affection continuing yesterday also the rain! (and so again today) I put off going to N. until next week: and as I had supposed I should be leaving Dvk. this week, I <hi rend="italic">last Friday </hi>finished my lot of letters Papers &amp; book-packets (author’s copies) for England—&amp; now am tolerably free!—–</p>
         <p>With this I purpose returning my old letter to you: I had taken it <hi rend="italic">twice </hi>w. me to Wdv. to copy a portion of it, but could not manage it,—always some hindrance, and in returning this one of yours I am reminded to ask you to return to me those Wesleyn. Missy. ones I lent you—which I think you have had “a yr, &amp; a day”!!</p>
         <p>I hardly know where to begin, in replying to yours, there are so <hi rend="italic">many </hi>things we should <hi rend="italic">talk </hi>on. if together: 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. <hi rend="italic">I much like </hi>your poetical “Exercitation,” “The richest men in Rome”: alike, I may say, in metre, rhythm &amp; idea—but particularly this <hi rend="italic">last</hi>”: Ka pai, <hi rend="italic">bien bon</hi>! I exclaimed: one line only I should like to see you alter (I dare not offer a suggestion)—viz.—</p>
         <p>“Is wide as ocean’s foam.”——</p>
         <p>I thank you for your clipping <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Easter Island! how much! how frequently! has that island &amp; its poor injured inhabitants occupied my thoughts—30–40 yrs. ago. I fear however that in <hi rend="italic">that account</hi> there is much of exaggeration—<hi rend="italic">American</hi>! As to “the seals head for that of<hi rend="italic">a Moa</hi>”! Well, an exactly similar game was played out at Poverty Bay, just at the time of my visit there—mentioned in “<hi rend="italic">Status quo</hi>.” The story is too long for a note. Nothing new in the Katipo bite, &amp;c. Thanks for your kind labours re Spanish: Fannin kindly<hi rend="italic">obtained</hi> a Sp. Dicty. <hi rend="italic">by </hi>Wessely &amp; Girone’s (publd. by Routledge)—a miserably printed thing—which throws no light on the <hi rend="italic">word</hi> required: and <hi rend="italic">so</hi> I have not yet ansd. that letter—though I have to Genoa, Santa Cruz, California, &amp;c.—am almost <hi rend="italic">tired </hi>w. so much letter-writing! I sent you <hi rend="italic">this mg. </hi>a Woodville paper. I had been keeping it for you, &amp; in it 2 clippings,—one re <hi rend="italic">your favourite </hi>R. Kg. which, I thought, would interest you.—</p>
         <p>I must tell you a <hi rend="italic">bit </hi>about that ₤50.—it came about in this way: I found out, the debt of ₤100 (or so) was <hi rend="italic">still </hi>owing on the Ch., &amp; that from erection, &amp; incumbent on 3 guarantors (one an aged &amp; <hi rend="italic">poor Xn</hi>.!) &amp; paying 9%, &amp; Congn. &amp; members apathetic &amp; careless. Remembering the Presbytn. Ch. <hi rend="underline italic">here</hi>, &amp; what we did to pay off its debt on erection; also, afterwards, at Makotuku—in which I largely assisted clearing; I was <hi rend="italic">determined </hi>that this stigma of debt should be removed from this house of prayer: Bazaars were wished for! I denounced them with all their coaxing semi-swindling inchoate-gambling belongings: “What then?” “Subscribe boldly lovingly cheerfully—‘all hands to the pumps’:” and seeing they still hung back, (and bearing in mind that many of our Congn. were poor,) I came out to set an example, (the more so, as I was only a <hi rend="italic">visitor</hi>, there today &amp; gone tomorrow, and should <hi rend="italic">not</hi> for long even as their Minister be benefitted thereby; besides, <hi rend="italic">I may tell you</hi>, I never recd. a 1d. from them, &amp; <hi rend="italic">have always paid all my expenses of every kind</hi>,) and so offered to pay half, or ₤50. <hi rend="italic">if the remr. was raised within a given time. </hi>I wish them to <hi rend="italic">see</hi>, I want to do them a benefit <hi rend="italic">re </hi>their souls: “freely ye have recd., freely give,” &amp;c, &amp;c. <hi rend="underline italic">You know</hi>!—Besides, I must not omit, they had lately (last autumn) subscribed ₤150. as their <hi rend="italic">share </hi>towards building a parsonage now nearly finished; and also engaged to raise ₤100 per ann. instead of ₤75. (as heretofore) as <hi rend="italic">their share </hi>of future Minister’s stipend. One word more: my heart &amp; spirit exulted within me, when I could enter the house of <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">knowing it was at last free.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Yesty. on my return, I found a <hi rend="italic">long </hi>letter from Hill: Buller had been <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, demanding <hi rend="italic">all </hi>Locke’s deposits in Museum! which Hill handed over. A site for a museum is talked of, on Survey Res. opp. Cathedral, &amp;c.—H. is strong on me for a Paper for Sy.—but, I fear, <hi rend="italic">in vain</hi>. Last night they had 4. I enclose notice. Taylor Wh. again!! I have not yet recd. <hi rend="italic">the </hi>vol., have written to Gore <hi rend="italic">re </hi>same. I was somewhat amused, in findingh, Hill following in <hi rend="italic">your </hi>&amp; <hi rend="italic">Hamilton’s </hi>groove,!!saying <hi rend="italic">much re </hi>my p. on Curious old Maori matters, but taking <hi rend="italic">no notice </hi>of my <hi rend="underline italic">chief</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> one</hi>—of research time &amp; labour—my defence of Dr. Mantell! To be sure <hi rend="italic">you </hi>heard it <hi rend="italic">read</hi>, &amp;c, &amp;c, which makes the difference. I notice in some of the “author’s copies” that have reached me from the authors, that <hi rend="italic">those </hi>have <hi rend="underline italic">half-title</hi> pages on opening the cover (looking very neat &amp; finished), which mine have <hi rend="italic">not</hi>. Chapman (I suppose–<hi rend="italic">no name </hi>written on it) has sen me a copy of his <hi rend="italic">Greenstone </hi>Paper: a <hi rend="italic">very long </hi>&amp; very tedious affair, <hi rend="underline italic">all</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> he could gather</hi>! <hi rend="italic">E. W. N. &amp; South</hi>, and in his <hi rend="italic">so </hi>doing has spoiled it, (in my estimation,) and <hi rend="underline italic">may</hi> keep me from going on w. mine—<hi rend="underline italic">long</hi> on stocks! I have not read it, only looked into it here &amp; there; he has (I think) <hi rend="italic">something of mine </hi>from old papers, but he has <hi rend="italic">carefully abstained </hi>from mentioning <hi rend="italic">me</hi>: this I had been led to expect.—Unfortunately (if sent me by him) I <hi rend="italic">cannot </hi>send <hi rend="italic">him </hi>a copy of my papers, for I want <hi rend="italic">more </hi>than I am allowed! what, then, ought I to do?——can you suggest?</p>
         <p>I fully intended to say a few words to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">this time </hi>on this new Insect book &amp; your Review of it, but must again defer.—</p>
         <p>Very likely you are right as to sulphur being used for <hi rend="italic">bleaching</hi> Ferns: but then those I saw &amp; admired were not only bleached but <hi rend="italic">reduced in thickness </hi>to that of tissue paper! Even such a thick <hi rend="italic">leaved</hi> Fern as <hi rend="italic">Asplenium lucidum</hi>: it was this that particularly astonished me.</p>
         <p>Do not for a moment think of copying Kipling’s “Tomlinson”: <hi rend="italic">I shall be vexed w. you</hi>, if you do. I have, at last, read the “Little Minister,” &amp; don’t think <hi rend="italic">very highly </hi>of it; (I prefer D. McLeod’s “<hi rend="italic">Starling</hi>”); no doubt there are some good parts, some levers for thought <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Sc. Presbyterianism, &amp; some extraordinary &amp; <hi rend="italic">unnatural </hi>things,—besides, for <hi rend="italic">me</hi> a glossary of some phrases is required! I marvel, <hi rend="underline italic">more than ever</hi>, at <hi rend="italic">your </hi>upholding <hi rend="italic">fem. </hi>suffrage! I could never have believed it, had <hi rend="italic">you </hi>not told me: a great great <hi rend="italic">evil</hi>—a curse on the people: <hi rend="italic">N.B. </hi>my words, <hi rend="italic">hereafter.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I thought I had written enough for this time; but I have more to say. I noticed in your last “Typo” a postage stamp: are you obliged to use stamps? I am much surprised by Dr. L. Yates’ letters—he says, that <hi rend="italic">no</hi> Eng. pubs. are allowed to be sent through Am. P.O., his &amp; others (more than 2000 vols.) seized &amp;c at S.F., and that spns. of shells to him from Australia for the museum, also siezed under pretence of being val. <hi rend="italic">commercial </hi>articles. I don’t know how to send him his vol.; in sending my “author’s c.” obliged to post as a big letter &amp; letter postage of course!</p>
         <p>I see in last night’s “D.T.” death of Mrs Hobbs, Minister’s wife, at Hastings from Influenza—<hi rend="italic">relapse</hi>! (What a narrow escape mine was!) she leaves 5 children. Dean Hovell, too, is very ill from it, confined to bed!! Bp. now has <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the Services at Cathedral! Could you by any means ascertain from Gore re my “Memoir on Pope”? could I get it back?</p>
         <p>This aftn. I gave 3 hours to my letter to Hill, &amp; this to you has taken 3½ hours! So you may see, how <hi rend="italic">slowly</hi> I write <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, aye, &amp; badly, too!—</p>
         <p>I have <hi rend="italic">again </hi>read, &amp; <hi rend="italic">have notes</hi>, of my <hi rend="italic">priv. </hi>letter to you of March 4<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>:—I cannot but think (repeat?) you have <hi rend="italic">not </hi>answered the questions I put therein—save in the matter of Executors: you mentioned Craig &amp; 2 others: of <hi rend="italic">C. </hi>I have the highest opinion but I fear his being so immersed in his own business (&amp; in Ch. matters &amp;c.) would hinder him: the other 2 I don’t know.—Will you kindly go <hi rend="italic">closely </hi>over my letter again, &amp; reply thereto? I have done nothing yet: but daily <hi rend="italic">feel </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">I ought to do</hi>,—<hi rend="italic">Who are my friends </hi>in Napier?—</p>
         <p>Hamilton has written me a terrifically long letter! small hand &amp; on 2 sides folio flp.—I dread to tackle it! From others, unknown to me, I have enquiries <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Maori words &amp; phrases!—Heigho.</p>
         <p>“Shut, shut the door, good John!” fatigued I said;</p>
         <p>“Tye up the knocker, say, I’m sick, I’m dead.”</p>
         <p>Among several others, Mr John Chambers, senior, is very ill, doubtful if he may recover. Lyndon has got a <hi rend="italic">nephew </hi>out from Engd. in partnership w. him. Rev. C. Penny met with <hi rend="italic">another trouble </hi>on Sunday last, at Pahiatua his horse fell w. him crushing bones of arm, &amp;c—whole country in a deplorable state from continual rains! water every where: train yesty. 2½ hours late, and again today—slip at Gorge <hi rend="italic">this time</hi>,—</p>
         <p>Should you notice anything political <hi rend="italic">worth sending </hi>in your Wgn. Papers, send copies <hi rend="italic">&amp; charge to me</hi>. I hope to hear of <hi rend="italic">better “luck”</hi> in your business.—</p>
         <p>I do not know how Anderson &amp; wife (at my place) are at present, have not heard since the 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi>, and wrote yesty. <hi rend="italic">blaming </hi>them: for, had I gone on today to N., I should have been obliged to go to the “Masonic.” I suppose, “no news is good news,” and they are taking it <hi rend="underline italic">easy</hi>!—</p>
         <p>                                                                     X, p.m. Good night.</p>
         <p>(13<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. X, a.m.)</p>
         <p>Among several other matters <hi rend="italic">omitted </hi>by you—was “Holloways Almc.” its cuts.—–</p>
         <p>I enclose, “Prospectus of Bibles from Oxford” arrived <hi rend="italic">last night</hi>, while writing to you.</p>
         <p>Mentioning (<hi rend="italic">partly</hi>) what I have confided to you re Will &amp; Executor to an old acquaintance at N.—he, after<hi rend="italic"> </hi>thinking over the matter, recommended Cotterill &amp; Bennet, Chm. Cy. Council formerly: I have always had a high opinion of Cotterill, &amp; perhaps he would consent to act, but then C. &amp; McLean are <hi rend="italic">my </hi>solicitors! This matter is the <hi rend="italic">only thing </hi>on my mind—I would it were settled! There was <hi rend="italic">another </hi>stoppage at the Gorge yesty.—the night train here, due 7.30, did not arrive until XII.15 a.m. but you there will hear. Hill says, Maoris went to Craig’s to get copies of my Ty. Waitangi—but he had <hi rend="italic">none</hi>! Some time ago I begged C. to get some. I must be sure (now!) to get Hamilton’s “book of plates J.Wh’s. work,” &amp; will report.</p>
         <p>Goodbye: kindest regards: best wishes—you &amp; yours. Ever &amp; always,</p>
         <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
