<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0421">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1880 August 11: to Cheeseman</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Auckland Museum MS 58, Box 5, Folder 3.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/73513/">Cheeseman</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1880-08-11">1880 August 11</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1880 August 11: to Cheeseman<note xml:id="ftn3-50" place="foot" n="50"> Auckland Museum MS 58, Box 5, Folder 3.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier<lb/>Augt. 11, 1880</p>
         <p>T.F. Cheeseman, Esq</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir,</p>
         <p>At length I have done a <hi rend="italic">little</hi> this day towards fulfilling my promise to you some time ago. I have just put up a few specimens of ferns, which, with this, will go by Saturday’s Mail hence to Auckland. I should have greatly preferred sending you larger and copious specimens of the 2 large Ferns,—but that cannot be at present,—I have so many demands. You will see that the portion of a pinna of <hi rend="italic">Cyathea polyneuron</hi>, is not from one of the largest (or mid-frond) size; such would be much too large, unless folded, to go by the Mail: the spns of <hi rend="italic">Hymenophyllum erecto-alatum </hi>are not so good as I could wish; I have a few better, I know, somewhere!—some younger &amp; fruiting specimens,—but for the life of me I cannot tell where! I have spent some hours this day searching for them. In the summer I hope to have more spare time, and then I purpose going through my Ferns, &amp;c., (now in <hi rend="italic">more </hi>than 40 parcels &amp; packages! Just as collected &amp; dried during the past 10 years). I think you will be pleased with the <hi rend="italic">smaller </hi>ferns: the little <hi rend="italic">Hymenophm</hi>. I first made acquaintance with many years ago at the far N., but I only lately found it in fruit,—its fruiting specimens are scarce.</p>
         <p>I thought on you often of late, (knowing from Dr. Hector that my last 3 ferns were in this vol.—xii.,) and so determined to send you spns. Of all—the former 2 and these 3 = 5. And as I supposed you had received a copy of this vol., I just sent you a brief telegram last week, to let you know I had <hi rend="italic">not </hi>forgotten you—fearing you <hi rend="italic">might </hi>be thinking the contrary.</p>
         <p>One of the prettiest fairy-like scenes I ever saw in our N.Z. forests I witnessed last summer:—I had found a fine plant of <hi rend="italic">Cyathea polyn. </hi>Growing freely in an open glade, and I reclined on the grass under its ample and lovely fronds; the sun was high, and the view on looking-up <hi rend="italic">through </hi>the foliage softly waving in the wind was truly enchanting, every veinlet being <hi rend="italic">translucent</hi>,<note xml:id="ftn3-51" place="foot" n="51"> WC: On that account I had very nearly named it—<hi rend="italic">translucens.</hi>
            </note> and then the green was so delicate; the finely marked traceries ever changing, &amp; just glints and gleams of sun-light through the many myriads of veins,—in that living bower and on that occasion, were far beyond language!—</p>
         <p>My garden plant is still living, recovering but slowly from that long &amp; fearful drought on this very dry limestone hill: its fronds, however, are but 6–7 feet, and while healthy are as nothing, comparatively, to what they were 3 years ago.—</p>
         <p>I have been very busy of late; and now the Eng, Mail; so that I have not found time to dip <hi rend="italic">quietly </hi>into vol. xii,—that treat is still to come.—</p>
         <p>Hoping you are well,—</p>
         <p>I am, Yours truly</p>
         <p>Wm. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>