<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0989">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1897 February 14: to William Colenso</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL Ms-papers-10535-1.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1897-02-14">1897 February 14</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1897 February 14: to William Colenso<note xml:id="ftn3-819" place="foot" n="819"> ATL Ms-papers-10535-1.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, N. Zealand,<lb/>Feby. 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 1897.</p>
         <p>My dear Nephew William</p>
         <p>I can scarcely tell you how pleased I was on receiving your long and interesting letter of 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Decr.,―may I say, doubly so, as I (again) had begun to think you had <hi rend="italic">forgotten </hi>me: of course, in my so saying, I always bear in mind how greatly your time is taken up, in your 3-fold duties. Now I will just take up your letter in the order you have written it.</p>
         <p>1.) <hi rend="italic">The slab of Greenstone</hi>: I like your proper inscription on it (as sent)―and I hope that you may have recd. a <hi rend="italic">proper</hi> letter of thanks from the Secy. or President R.C.G.S. ―otherwise I shall think they are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> aware of the <hi rend="italic">value</hi> of the slab, (what it <hi rend="italic">cost</hi>―in money &amp; expenses to take it to Penzance―besides Latimer’s trouble! As it had to be paid (by him) extra―it was not allowed as passenger’s baggage: and here I may ask a foolish question (for a Penz. Man,) ―Have you <hi rend="italic">two </hi>Museums in Penz.? One attached to the Penz. Library &amp; one to the R.C.G.S. In former correspondence with Preby. Hedgeland, &amp;, also, with Dr. Millett (lately deceased) I thought <hi rend="italic">so</hi>. ―</p>
         <p>2.) <hi rend="italic">Your remarks on Glen T., &amp; its inmates. </hi>You say (<hi rend="underline italic">rightly,</hi>) “I feel sure if I can do anything to remove the feeling, which after all, may only be some mistake, some blunder, some mischief by some person or persons, and we both know that there is no worse injury than a fancied injury.” ―Good: Wm., good special pleading! ―Now, briefly, for the <hi rend="italic">facts</hi>: premising, that Willie’s wife, your sister, is, also, <hi rend="underline italic">my niece</hi>, as well as a d-in-l., &amp; so I have a <hi rend="italic">double </hi>claim on the score of relationship <hi rend="italic">alone. </hi>Were <hi rend="italic">you</hi> dead, also Rd., I should stand in the place of <hi rend="italic">her nearest male blood relation</hi>, but to all that, I add, Glen T., &amp; <hi rend="italic">all besides</hi>: hence it was, that I (in former letter) mentioned “<hi rend="italic">In gratitude &amp;c. Glen T.</hi>” ―<hi rend="italic">all</hi> the sad difference arises <hi rend="italic">from Sarah</hi>. (And I much fear she has blinded both your, &amp; Rd’s., &amp; her Mother’s eyes, ―just as she has done w. Willie:) in my <hi rend="italic">last letter </hi>to her, about 12 months ago, I asked her to tell me, <hi rend="italic">why</hi> she employed that Marketjew Quack―Helm? Why not have employed <hi rend="italic">superior </hi>med. aid in the larger town of Penz.? To this, W. replied (being <hi rend="italic">set on</hi>) ―S. <hi rend="italic">would not</hi> ansr., &amp; never write to me again: W., too, (for <hi rend="italic">first time </hi>in his life!) addressing me as “Dear Father”, his old uniform unfaltering style being “My dear darling F.,” besides the coldness and shortness of his letter―followed by another, in which the poor dear fellow charged me with “<hi rend="italic">insult</hi> to his wife”, and my being “<hi rend="italic">ungenerous</hi>,” (possibly not knowing the meaning of <hi rend="italic">this word</hi>)―but his last letter (3) <hi rend="italic">short </hi>&amp; <hi rend="underline italic">unansd.</hi> contains other similar remarks (as I read them― “<hi rend="underline italic">Sarah’s</hi>”), and so I considered it best for peace sake (though painful to me) to cease writing.―Let Sarah answer <hi rend="italic">fully &amp; truly</hi> that letter of mine, and then the broken bone <hi rend="underline italic">may</hi> be re-set &amp; become stronger than ever. But I have <hi rend="italic">lately </hi>recd. <hi rend="underline italic">two</hi> letters from <hi rend="italic">Sarah</hi>! In one (dated, “Augt. 18<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>”) she says, “No letter as usual: I sincerely hope <hi rend="italic">you </hi>will bury the hatchet &amp; smoke the <hi rend="italic">Calumet of Peace</hi>, which will be far better for us all.” And in the second (dated “Decr. 8<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.”) she has the hardihood, or cunning, to say, ― “I feel I must write to you again, knowing all your goodness to us. I am quite sure, if I have offended you in any way, also W., I will ask you to forgive us. It is now drawing to Xmas. A time of peace on Earth &amp; goodwill towards men.– – – the past 2 years―95 W. losing his sight, and 96 your not writing to him. If you did but know how rejoiced we both were to receive your beautiful letters, in London, &amp; here―and, <hi rend="italic">all at once </hi>your good letters ceased. Poor aunt is gone, I freely forgive her for making so much mischief between us.”——</p>
         <p>Now I have quoted this <hi rend="italic">last sentence </hi>partly on <hi rend="italic">your own </hi>account, Wm.―You <hi rend="italic">seem </hi>to hint in that direction in what I have quoted from your letter. And there never was a greater mistake made, than in your (both, or all,) supposing, that Mrs. T. ever made mischief between us,―or, <hi rend="italic">me &amp; W.</hi> &amp; S. Exactly the <hi rend="italic">very contrary</hi>, &amp; that from the <hi rend="underline italic">first</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> beginning</hi>, before you or your Father ever saw Willie’s face, Indeed I may say, <hi rend="italic">truly</hi>, that had not Mrs. T. <hi rend="italic">continually urged me</hi>, aye &amp; got her London friend Mr Brock, <hi rend="italic">Senr.</hi>, to back her, &amp; to freely offer to help,―It is likely, I should <hi rend="italic">never</hi> have got W. an annuity―<hi rend="italic">never </hi>have remitted that £2000 to your Father―and Glen T. would <hi rend="italic">never</hi> have been purchased! The <hi rend="italic">best, truest, friend, </hi>that W. ever had in England, was Mrs Tucker, in <hi rend="italic">that respect</hi>, Wm., far before my brother your father. As, in <hi rend="italic">her case</hi>, all she did was from pure <hi rend="italic">disinterested </hi>love―even, too, in some respects, <hi rend="italic">against </hi>herself. To return to Sarah’s letter:―she says, therein, <hi rend="italic">as if the fault, the sudden change, was my own</hi>!!―when she <hi rend="italic">knows </hi>(from my last to W.) that my enforced silence arose <hi rend="italic">solely from her conduct</hi>: enough on this painful subject. You strangely (<hi rend="italic">ignorantly</hi>, perhaps, is the <hi rend="italic">better</hi> word) say,― “Both W. &amp; his wife seem to be utterly ignorant of any offence or ingratitude towards you.” (!!!)</p>
         <p>3.) <hi rend="italic">Dr. Millett</hi>: at one time we were <hi rend="italic">good </hi>correspondents: (for I knew his father <hi rend="italic">well</hi>, &amp; we had been trouting together in Gulval streams, &amp; elsewhere―I see <hi rend="italic">him </hi>now!) and Dr. M. sent me some of his published pamphlets (as I did mine to him) and he was going to get out a new book on “Old Penzance,” &amp; asked me to join―which I gladly agreed to: then he sent me an interleaved copy of one of his former pubs. (on Penzance) for me to write in, &amp;c, &amp;c. I did so, &amp; sent it to him (also a frozen sheep) but what I had written (or, struck out, or <hi rend="italic">altered</hi> in his) did not please him, and so a coldness―&amp; then an ending of correspondence between us―which I regretted. Did you ever read my paper (M.S.) on “Old Penz.”?―which I wrote for the N. H. &amp; A. Sy., (&amp; was read―I think, <hi rend="italic">there</hi>) If not, <hi rend="italic">read </hi>it: Willie has it now.―I have still a most retentive memory of “Old P.”, its people, their <hi rend="italic">dress</hi>, words, appearance, manner, occupation: its signs, colour of doors! &amp;c &amp;c. Even of the Country folks, coming into town on market days, Thursdays &amp; Saturdays; and of the Vegetable &amp; fruit stalls in the “Green-Market,” and of the women―their dresses &amp;c &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Alone</hi>, here (as to human society) I often conjure them all up, &amp; they pass along before me! Without speaking! I am pleased in knowing you have acqd. that house in Chapel St., formerly Mr. G. John’s, (I remember him too, &amp; his son, G.D. John, and his brother S. John another lawyer, his off. was on N. Parade, who escaped to America w. his <hi rend="italic">clients </hi>money! His Country house was the “Orchard,” Alverton). I suppose you have still there, in front, the very <hi rend="italic">narrow </hi>kerb! w. water flowing before it. Yes: that red blg. Hawthorn opposite—too, w. Lawyer Edmonds’ house above, at the corner of the lane, w. its <hi rend="italic">slate</hi> front &amp; peculiar twisted iron rails—over which, we boys, used to turn “cat-in-the-pan,” &amp;c, &amp;c. There, you have a specimen of the garrulosity of this <hi rend="italic">old </hi>man!——</p>
         <p>4.) <hi rend="italic">Re the J.P.ship</hi>.—Very much pleased to hear it from you: accept it, by all means, if offered, &amp; strive hard to do your duty, &amp; that <hi rend="italic">with mercy</hi>,—too much forgotten now a-days. (Gal. VI. 1,2) I am glad my dear nephew, that <hi rend="italic">you</hi> too are desirous of keeping-up (or <hi rend="underline italic">restoring</hi>) the n. &amp; Dignity of <hi rend="underline italic">our</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> old </hi>family—so <hi rend="underline italic">sadly</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> lowered </hi>in my bringing-up! Did I ever call <hi rend="italic">your </hi>attention to what I saw some years ago in the Penz. paper, and that at different <hi rend="italic">times</hi>, advertisements for letting estates in Parish of St. Hilary called, “<hi rend="italic">Colenso Cross</hi>,” and, also, “<hi rend="italic">Colenso manor</hi>”?—I think I did to <hi rend="italic">Latimer.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I have not overlooked <hi rend="italic">re </hi>your wanting so many feet (or yards) of <hi rend="italic">books</hi> for your empty bookshelves: “bide-a-wee”. I have a very large Libraryfor this place, or even all N.Z. and the <hi rend="italic">leaving it </hi>is just my only grief. Of course <hi rend="italic">much </hi>of it (Sc. works, Latin, Greek, &amp;c, &amp;c) would be of no great service <hi rend="italic">to you</hi>—even if nearer: many of my books were very expensive ones—being <hi rend="italic">scarce</hi>, some cost me £2.2.0—to £12. a vol. You may have heard of my “<hi rend="italic">offer</hi>” here last May, to our H.B. Philosophl. Institute &amp; Museum, this <hi rend="italic">not </hi>having been accepted (according to my plan) has <hi rend="italic">fallen through</hi>—but <hi rend="italic">our</hi> annual meeting is <hi rend="italic">tomorrow</hi> night, when I expect <hi rend="italic">more </hi>of abuse from these Goths! There is an astonishing amount of <hi rend="italic">low jealousy </hi>about (so I am told): I go but <hi rend="italic">little </hi>out into the town (only <hi rend="italic">twice</hi> there since 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. Jany.) and have <hi rend="italic">very few </hi>visitors—don’t wish for many: loving solitude &amp; work.</p>
         <p>I note your remark on <hi rend="italic">my mistake </hi>in a Maori photo. I regret it, hope to do better next time. I had purchased a dozen, and, somehow, in distributing them made the mistake. I write an enormous no. of letters yearly for a private person: I jot them down, and I find I wrote 899 (a <hi rend="italic">curious </hi>number) last year: this is <hi rend="italic">less </hi>than formerly when it ran <hi rend="italic">over </hi>1000—but some of my more recent ones were <hi rend="italic">longer</hi>.</p>
         <p>I went off to the <hi rend="italic">Bush</hi> (wooded interior) on 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Decr., to seek to get rid of my obstinate old cold (or rather its 3 relapses!) knowing the change would be beneficial: I returned on 31<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. Decr., earlier than I had intended, to help Rev. W. Welsh here in town he being unwell, I preached there &amp; assisted him 4 Sundays in Jany. And also last Sy. Evg. (7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.) and shall again (D.V.) This day was pouring rain! (and so 4 days last week,) and so I am a prisoner in doors. I am keeping well, on the whole, and hope next month to revisit the <hi rend="italic">Bush</hi>―and there take some Ch. Services. Our Bishop leaves next week for the Lambeth Conference. I hope some <hi rend="italic">real good </hi>may result from it―but I have my doubts!――</p>
         <p>Last month―during a long drought. Everything of herb kind, grass, &amp;c, all burnt up,―a fire took place on my hill, the paddock in front a few yards away, which alarmed me, but scores of ready hands, mostly boys (it being <hi rend="italic">holiday</hi> time) and the Fire Brigade, saved these premises!―And, only a few days after, came the heaviest gale, wind &amp; rain, I ever experienced <hi rend="italic">here</hi>! My dear old &amp; tall &amp; venerable &amp; handsome <hi rend="italic">Acacia </hi>trees, in front of my house, 40 years old, were <hi rend="italic">all uprooted</hi>, and my man says, about 40 others on this ground―house, too, leaking,―a perfect wreck: I could have cried over my <hi rend="italic">Acacias</hi>. ――</p>
         <p>I am greatly pleased in knowing your dear wife &amp; family with yourself being well <hi rend="italic">in health</hi>―that great that chief blessing: also, in your Sailor-son doing so very well in his profession (May God keep &amp; bless him!) and also your daughter preparing for Camb., may she succeed to the best of her wishes.―And I trust, my dear nephew, that this New Year of ’97 may be the best you have ever known―<hi rend="italic">in every respect</hi>.</p>
         <p>Your last letter was certainly the <hi rend="italic">longest</hi>, and I think the best you have ever written to me: I <hi rend="italic">must not</hi> expect to receive many such (as to length) from you―as your time is far too valuable, but write sometimes, &amp; sometimes <hi rend="underline italic">tell</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>the <hi rend="italic">Bachelor</hi> Dick, what to say―he, too, often writes a good letter, &amp; has <hi rend="italic">spare time. </hi>I send Willie some papers, as usual: I have the Penz. papers from him, but I don’t always look into them. And now, Good Bye, with love &amp; best wishes for you all―</p>
         <p>I am Your affect. Uncle―Wm. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. If you are sufficiently acquainted w. Preby. Hedgeland, &amp; Ald. Julyan, remember <hi rend="italic">very kindly</hi> to them.――</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="underline italic">No.2</hi>
         </p>
         <p>16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Feby. I find my letter is over ½ oz. so I will add a bit more.</p>
         <p>Last night we held our annual meeting—a kind of Report of it you will have in “<hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>” of this morning, of which I send you a copy. I said a great deal more than is there stated, upon <hi rend="italic">all </hi>matters connected with the Society, and its well-doing, as I was leaving it—never to go there again, unless those (late) Members of Council apologise amply—which they are not manly enough to do.—I <hi rend="italic">refused</hi> to shake hands w. Hill, Craig, &amp; Co., on meeting them last night. One or two errors in the long Report I have corrected in margin of paper. The Society has a <hi rend="italic">better</hi> Council now, &amp; I wish it, &amp; them, well.——</p>
         <p>Looking into your letter again I note what you say <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Helm. I don’t believe in him. Allow me to tell you that I <hi rend="italic">know</hi> something of medicine &amp; of disease by practice extensive for many years and study, at one time <hi rend="italic">I had the most complete surgery in N.Z.</hi>—&amp; helped the Colonial Surgeon to medicines which he had not.</p>
         <p>When your sister wrote to me what Helm had <hi rend="italic">said</hi>—on his <hi rend="italic">first </hi>visiting W., I laughed at it, &amp; <hi rend="italic">told her so in replying</hi>—it showed <hi rend="italic">his ignorance</hi>—H. said (pathetically!!) “a pity it did not occur earlier as it usually does”—(or words to that effect). This made our surgeons laugh outright for the disease is <hi rend="underline italic">one of age</hi> and when that ignoramus took poor W. up to L., it was to gain instruction on <hi rend="italic">himself</hi> how to act, (to gain his big sum!) being a novice. H. should then, in L., have placed W. in <hi rend="italic">proper </hi>hands.—The disease is not uncommon here, several of my own friends, lay &amp; clerical, have only one eye (with a glass or china one) and in the hands of a <hi rend="italic">skilled </hi>opthalmist the disease is <hi rend="italic">neither dangerous nor difficult</hi>.—–</p>
         <p>Several years ago I remember reading in the Penzance papers of that fellow Helm being a thorn in the side of Marketjew Road (or town) Board—always dogmatizing, always opposite. I <hi rend="italic">deferred </hi>asking Sarah, why she went to <hi rend="italic">him, there</hi>, until they had returned peaceably from London.—You (no doubt) truly say, “she is a good wife, &amp; therefore must be a good d-in law” and no doubt you are right apart from the thoughts which arise (<hi rend="underline italic">knowing</hi> her) Has she not <hi rend="italic">good reasons </hi>for being such?</p>
         <p>But this is a sad subject. I could <hi rend="underline italic">almost</hi> come to the conclusion,—Never again to write to one of the family; and perhaps for peace and quietness sake (<hi rend="underline italic">for me</hi>) such would be the best.—</p>
         <p>I have sent a copy of this day’s “Herald”—to Hedgeland, Julyan, Richard. &amp; Willie.—–</p>
         <p>Good Bye</p>
         <p>Yr. affect. Uncle W. Colenso</p>
         <p>VI, p.m. finished for Mail.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>