<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0833">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1892 June 27: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0497.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1892-06-27">1892 June 27</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1892 June 27: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-594" place="foot" n="594"> ATL qMS-0497.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke<lb/>June 27<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> 1892</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding,</p>
         <p>Your welcome letter of 26<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. inst. arrived here this day, (I suppose we came on together from Woodville?) and though I am very busy—yet I feel inclined to write to you at <hi rend="italic">once</hi>—to tell you a little <hi rend="italic">re </hi>myself that may interest you.—I suppose I duly informed you in my last of my writing to Cadman, 2 letters, 1, offl. &amp; 1 priv., well these posted on 16<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>—could only reach Wgn. that night &amp; <hi rend="italic">late</hi>, replies to <hi rend="italic">both </hi>were written &amp; <hi rend="italic">posted </hi>on 17<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> both <hi rend="italic">short</hi>, &amp; to say, no use to expect, as nothing would be done by Govt. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>ptg. Mao. Lex., owing to <hi rend="italic">financial </hi>wants!!! all I had asked for in the way of ptg. was that <hi rend="italic">first part</hi>, and surely <hi rend="italic">less </hi>than ₤50. would suffice for that.—However, we shall see: I hope Capt. R. will be able to get my letter to N. Mr. laid on table of House, &amp; <hi rend="italic">printed </hi>as a Parly. Paper, and so become a supplement to the last one.——</p>
         <p>From my last you will have gathered the Bp. was at Woodville on 19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. We returned together to Dvk. on 20<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>., he staid <hi rend="italic">here </hi>at this hotel till next mg. That night we (2) had our long &amp; serious talk, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Woodville—my stipulated time ending w. June: and as the Bp. had <hi rend="italic">no one yet </hi>to place there, &amp; I could not consey. agree to the Ch. to be <hi rend="italic">closed, </hi>I consented to continue to serve for some time longer—2–3 months, <hi rend="italic">perhaps. </hi>One of the factors (so to speak) was the <hi rend="italic">2 good winter rooms </hi>I now had at the “Club” hotel, late Murphy’s, which the Bp. also saw, and spent some time w. me in them.—On Tuesday, 21<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>, came a letter from Sandel (The Proprietor), informing me I could <hi rend="italic">no longer </hi>have those 2 rooms, as he wanted them for himself &amp; family!! this unexpected &amp; most unpleasant information upset me! Why did he not mention it to me while there—the day before &amp; seeing him often? I wrote to him that same night, &amp; next mg. to Burnett (the Warden &amp; Mayor), and also to the Bp. I asked S. to allow me to use them on 26<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. he wired back, “<hi rend="italic">Yes</hi>”: so I went thither again for last Sy. (24<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>)—on Monday had a long talk w. him!! trying <hi rend="italic">every way</hi>, even to <hi rend="italic">double </hi>payment, but could not succeed: he (or <hi rend="italic">his wife</hi>) wants them for their <hi rend="italic">priv. </hi>visitors &amp; friends on Sundays in particular!!!—However, as <hi rend="italic">I had given out in the Ch. </hi>that I would be there on 3<hi rend="sup ">rd</hi>. proxo. to hold D.S., I got him, <hi rend="italic">at last</hi>, to consent to my occupying them <hi rend="italic">once more </hi>for that Sunday. And so, when I go thither again, if I cannot get suitable <hi rend="italic">winter </hi>rooms, I fear I shall have to give up <hi rend="italic">the work</hi>, which <hi rend="underline italic">I shall be very sorry to do</hi>: but I cannot pass days in a room <hi rend="underline italic">there </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">without fire </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">in the very middle of winter</hi>. I can have a <hi rend="italic">good </hi>bedroom at Sandel’s without fire (not wanted by me in it), but no private sitting-room; and <hi rend="italic">I cannot </hi>exist in the “Commercial Room.”——</p>
         <p>Weather was wet &amp; cold when there last week, but a toly. fair Congn. on <hi rend="italic">Sunday </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">evg</hi>., about 55—less, in mg.—Mr. Luff’s eldest son was again there, &amp; spent an agreeable hour w. me in the aftern. he is a nice yg. man: I think you will like him:—would there were more! There, at the “Club”, in my sitting-room under a glass dome (20 in. high) is a beautiful colln. of our N.Z. Ferns—4–5 species from these woods, but all most exquisitely bleached dead white (almost resembling tissue paper) and <hi rend="italic">quite perfect</hi>, showing veins, and seed-cases, even the minutest: I have gazed on them w. astonished pleasure, wondering how such was done: have you seeen or heard of any such? Murphy is <hi rend="italic">now at Auckland</hi>, or I would have asked him. There are just 3 Corresponding Members left of Sir John Franklin’s original Sc. Socy. founded 1840,—Sir G. Grey, Sir J.D. Hooker, &amp; W.C.! [I am often led to think on the words of the Master—“A prophet” (teacher = preacher) “is not without honour save in his own country.” Jno. 4/44].</p>
         <p>I have had an extra heavy &amp; troublesome job! Two months ago, an Interpreter named Blake applied to me <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the <hi rend="italic">marriage </hi>of a <hi rend="italic">pakeha</hi> to a Maori girl—nearly 50 years bk.,—of children, &amp;c. I told him I cod. not help him, I did not marry him, &amp; referred to the 2 Archdns. Dil., &amp; L.W. Well, about a fortnight ago he came again bringing Certif. Marriage from L.W. performed by Hamlin at <hi rend="italic">Wairoa </hi>in 1845, &amp; Certif. of Baptism from S.W., girl, by me at Petani in 1851: but much more was still wanting to please Lawyers at Wgn. (&amp; at Home?)—the <hi rend="italic">death </hi>of that <hi rend="italic">pakeha</hi>, &amp;c &amp;c. and now after 2 days “overhaulings” of <hi rend="italic">all stores</hi>! I have found—copies of my letters—to Hamlin <hi rend="italic">for </hi>the Certificate of mge., written in 1853 which I also sent to firm of Lawyers in Lond., in ansr. to their letters, &amp;c—to the Lawyers (2), &amp; to the father of that <hi rend="italic">pakeha</hi>! a deal of <hi rend="italic">old </hi>writing, quant. suff. of new! and I have met w. much ’mong <hi rend="italic">old </hi>correspce., &amp; memoranda, and diaries—of a <hi rend="italic">pleasing </hi>character, all which I had <hi rend="italic">clean </hi>forgotten! You would have been delighted!!! A curious thing in the letters w. their <hi rend="italic">old </hi>postmarks (so <hi rend="italic">clearly done</hi>) e.g. “Farnham, Surrey, <hi rend="italic">Octr. </hi>16, 1852”: “Auckland, April 1853”: “Wellington May 6, 1853”: &amp; endorsed by me (<hi rend="italic">no </hi>P.O. then <hi rend="italic">here</hi>) “recd. June 29/53”: and the postages, <hi rend="italic">small </hi>letter, ¼d.—larger one 2/9 <hi rend="italic">no stamps</hi>. There was also a Power of Atty. sent out for this man to sign <hi rend="italic">re </hi>property at Home, but he was dead before it came. And I only opened the letters (to know the address of writers) <hi rend="italic">before </hi>McLean as T.P. on his first visit, <hi rend="italic">in Dec</hi>.! and I have had to make a summar of all!!</p>
         <p>I suppose you will have seen in Papers, of Capt. R. &amp; Stout going togr. to Premier (Seddon) <hi rend="italic">re </hi>ptg. <hi rend="italic">that </hi>1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. part (A.) Mao. Lex.?—Capt. R. was in N. last week and I saw him, &amp; shall have to <hi rend="italic">return</hi> to them that parcel!!! (Will it have better luck this time?) As I told Capt. R. it <hi rend="underline italic">is</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> as it came back—</hi>in its package, &amp; I should have sent it during past wk., only Jago, in reply to my enquiry, says, I have <hi rend="italic">not </hi>the priv. of franking—&amp; this I must enq. about on Tuesday when I go to town, as package weighs 6–7lbs.—and I have 2 Gazettes in which that priv. was granted me <hi rend="italic">for that purpose</hi>: more work, I suppose, for the old hoss! If it <hi rend="italic">is passed</hi> into Govt. Printer’s hands—I shall ask <hi rend="italic">you </hi>to see Didsbury’s successor about it. (I shall miss Dy.). But I suppose this new hand has <hi rend="italic">good overseers </hi>under him.—He must be informed by me—that in my receiving proofs the ms. (copy) <hi rend="italic">must </hi>come on with them. And when the part “A” is printed—<hi rend="underline italic">then</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> I will look into Tregear’s book, &amp; compare with </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">his</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> “A”.</hi> I suppose you recd. paper I sent you in which the redoubtable Taylor Wh. is come out—slashing <hi rend="italic">Howlett</hi>? I think I will also send you J. White’s vol.II, as you may not have it, but more party. that you <hi rend="italic">may see</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">his inscription &amp; what he said of me</hi>.</p>
         <p>Rees has got his <hi rend="italic">deserts</hi>:—but only <hi rend="italic">1</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">st</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. instalment</hi>. Did I ever mention to you of a <hi rend="italic">curious </hi>passage in his Memoirs of G.G.—that G. took Karaitiana to Te Aute to see Hapuku when dying, to make peace with him &amp; succeeded? (I doubt the truth of <hi rend="italic">this</hi>—but will enq.) Also, in a Paper in “Trans,” vol.__, by some surveyor, it is stated, that Grey ascended Tongariro, at an early date! I don’t believe it.——– A Mr. Bradbury (Curate under Mr. Coffey, there with you) is said, to be his successor. Our Bp. was at Dannevirke yesterday. Napthali has <hi rend="italic">resigned </hi>his J.P.ship. R. Price <hi rend="italic">left </hi>his old moorings last wk., &amp; is now at A. Clinton.</p>
         <p>I suppose you have seen something of <hi rend="italic">young</hi> Tanner’s <hi rend="italic">sayings </hi>at Sydney? Great fuss made by <hi rend="italic">him</hi> (poor boy!) to extricate himself—but Oh! his far-fetched notions of <hi rend="italic">himself</hi>!! (a <hi rend="italic">true </hi>chip off the <hi rend="italic">old </hi>block!!) he pitched into the Herald! unmercifully, &amp; also into all others! And now says—that <hi rend="underline italic">he</hi> has been asked to stand for 2 Constituencies;—and tho’ young—was not Wm. Pitt young also!—<hi rend="italic">usque ad nausm. </hi>Some one named Wiltshire has taken him up—<hi rend="italic">nicely</hi>; &amp; “Herald,” too, spares him not. Then there are some <hi rend="italic">choice </hi>letters between Ellis, the Mayor of Hastings, and Murdoch the “Herald’s” own correspdt. (Good night).</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 29</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>A truly fine day! I <hi rend="italic">well</hi>, again, and went down town on business: calling also on Canon Fox &amp; spent a nice ½ hour with him—my cab at door, <hi rend="italic">waiting</hi>: he spends 2 more Sundays here,—he was rather unwell today. Also, spent nearly 1 hour w. Knowles in his nice little <hi rend="italic">sanctum</hi>: told K. <hi rend="italic">again </hi>about badly ptd. “D.T.”, &amp; <hi rend="italic">he</hi>, too, had been finding <hi rend="italic">same fault </hi>that mg. so we went together into press room, <hi rend="italic">examd. </hi>machine, <hi rend="italic">heard </hi>pressman, &amp;c; the roller bed is worn, or uneven, the roller <hi rend="italic">patent </hi>composn. bad, &amp;c—but one thing I told <hi rend="italic">them</hi>—their paper rather harsh is not damped suffy., &amp; certy. copy <hi rend="italic">tonight </hi>better. Sorry to see in “D.T.”, the death of <hi rend="italic">another </hi>child (eldest son, 8½ yrs) of J.H. Davidson “Culverden, St. Leonards” (wherever that place is!) on Sunday: so there, too, is woe <hi rend="italic">bitter</hi>, over 2 <hi rend="italic">within a few days</hi>! The Waipawa natives have agreed to give a Mr. Carter of W.—£130. per ann. as their Band Master! Lamb’s case v. Dannevirke Bor. Council—£<hi rend="italic">100</hi>. for prelimy. exam. <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Water Supply,—is on here today. Dvk. offered £50. (in my opinion <hi rend="italic">quant suff.</hi>) L. would not hear of it. Last week I noticed, that L., who had been directed by E.B. to report on state of School Ho. at Mangaatua (Victoria nr. Wdv.), did so—£<hi rend="italic">15. </hi>would cover repairs! now what will his going thither, &amp; again, when done, to see &amp; certify come to!—I saw W. Miller in town today—as well as ever: John Begg seeming <hi rend="italic">much </hi>worn &amp; deaf: (<hi rend="italic">he </hi>went to Annabell’s funeral), &amp; Rev. Cornford—seeming <hi rend="underline italic">failing</hi> fast; I always like to meet with <hi rend="italic">him </hi>so kind, so cheerful.—A long letter to hand from Hamilton today, after long silence (<hi rend="italic">both sides</hi>!) I wrote to him on Friday last, &amp; so <hi rend="italic">our </hi>letters have again crossed: somewhat curious that <hi rend="italic">we </hi>(as sometimes you &amp; I) should <hi rend="italic">think of &amp; write to </hi>ea. other <hi rend="italic">about same time</hi>—after nearly 2 months silence.—H. &amp; w. &amp; fy. all <hi rend="italic">well</hi>, complaining of cold raw weather. Knowles wished me to see his <hi rend="italic">new</hi> “Ed.”, but, as it was nearly 1 o’clock, on calling him he was gone to his dinner: Edw’s. room is upstairs. [Again, to your letter]: never mind <hi rend="italic">dates </hi>re von H., <hi rend="italic">this </hi>of his death will suffice. You ask, “If I see Jl. Polynesian Society?” No: I refused to join it—mainly because of the detestable snobbery of the “<hi rend="italic">Queen</hi> of H,” <hi rend="italic">made </hi>the Boss!!—and, also, of Smith having so much to do &amp; say. <hi rend="italic">S. </hi>I look on (to use Sir W. Fox’s words) as “a brain-sucker”! I notice in one of his papers in “Trans,” XXV. no small amount of cribbings from mine—&amp; then (stupid <hi rend="italic">Auckland-</hi>like) he, knowing how I had <hi rend="italic">upset </hi>Dr. Purchase Prest. of <hi rend="italic">their </hi>Sy., <hi rend="italic">re Rangitoto</hi>, now comes out saying—he “had heard from an old Maori years ago, of a great battle fought in the Thames, &amp; very likely “<hi rend="italic">Rangitoto</hi>” was <hi rend="italic">then </hi>given given to the islet to comm. it”!!! Goodbye, kindest regards, Yours truly, W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
