<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0980">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1896 December 28: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1896-12-28">1896 December 28</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1896 December 28: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-808" place="foot" n="808"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Dannevirke, Decr. 28/96.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I duly recd. yours of 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. inst., which (as on former occasions) seems to have crossed mine of <hi rend="italic">same date</hi> in transit. I thank you for it—tho’ it 1. surprised, 2. vexed, &amp; 3. pleased me! (<hi rend="underline italic">surprised</hi> at your illness—of body &amp; <hi rend="italic">mind</hi>—<hi rend="italic">pro tem</hi>—yet <hi rend="italic">this</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">some way</hi>, I had long been <hi rend="italic">expecting</hi> to hear of, simply because you, though <hi rend="italic">not </hi>physically strong, will <hi rend="italic">not </hi>take <hi rend="italic">proper</hi> care of yourself, which, as I have before now ventured to tell you,—you are <hi rend="underline italic">primarily</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> bound to do</hi>, for the sake of growing family: and this, too, <hi rend="italic">in sight of </hi>
            <hi rend="smallcaps italic">God</hi>: <hi rend="underline italic">Vexed</hi> at not getting any replies (or even notices!) of several items in late letters (though this is nothing new!) <hi rend="underline italic">pleased</hi> in finding you were <hi rend="italic">agreeing</hi> w. <hi rend="underline italic">us</hi> re late Napier &amp; H.B. elections: this alone is compensation!! ditto ditto re “evangelists.”—so now we are <hi rend="italic">quits</hi>.—–</p>
         <p>I purpose leaving here tomorrow &amp; hope to reach N. on 31<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. by <hi rend="italic">Goods </hi>train, the “Express”, these holiday times, being so crowded: I would prefer staying here a month longer (though <hi rend="italic">idle </hi>as to Ch. work), as I believe by doing so I should get quite rid of my obstinate chest complaint, (remainder of severe influenza-cold caught <hi rend="italic">here</hi> in Augt. last!) <hi rend="italic">I feel very much better</hi> and would not now leave, but to help Mr Welsh at Augustine’s—he wished me to do so last wk., &amp; yesty., &amp; I have promised him for 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>. proxo.</p>
         <p>I enclose your photos. (since you wish to have them <hi rend="italic">returned</hi>) they are rather curious, &amp;, in a measure, <hi rend="italic">unknown </hi>to me: nos. 1–3, especially so: no.4, may have been intended for a <hi rend="italic">projecting</hi> side beam of a <hi rend="italic">kumara</hi> store (always <hi rend="italic">tapu</hi>, &amp; often elaborately ornamented): no.6, as an ear-ring or hook for a dress-mat—you do not give its <hi rend="italic">material</hi>—jade, bone, or wood.—</p>
         <p>I have been hard at wk. writing letters here (about 50, some very long!) have been nowhere, save once to hills beyond Matahiwi, in buggy, to seek some plants, having <hi rend="underline italic">long ago</hi> noticed, in <hi rend="italic">passing</hi>, difference in vegetation: and I had such a job!—climbing steep hills ’mong <hi rend="underline italic">old</hi> vegetation,—got <hi rend="italic">some</hi>, wh. pleased me much, &amp; got out of my thick dense low bush w. <hi rend="italic">difficulty</hi>! Could only be <hi rend="italic">allowed</hi> 1¼ hours in it.—</p>
         <p>I have not since heard from your brother-chip Mackay (but <hi rend="italic">you</hi> don’t care for <hi rend="italic">that</hi>!)—Have had <hi rend="italic">another</hi> terrifically long letter from Hamilton (always so <hi rend="italic">full</hi> of Mao. enquiries!) written <hi rend="underline italic">closely</hi> on fcp. folio! He may be <hi rend="italic">now </hi>at N. Plym., on his way to Auckld., having 1 mo. holiday, &amp; having also the photographing <hi rend="italic">all old Maori curios</hi> on his brain! is to call at N. on his way back, end of Jany., like a bee laden!!—</p>
         <p>Dinwiddie our Secy. has written to me—but I hesitate to send my Prestl. “Address”, &amp;c, &amp;c, through him to Wgn., as (1) I fear it would <hi rend="italic">not </hi>be pubd. in vol. xxix, &amp; (2) it would be <hi rend="italic">picked</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="italic">pilfered</hi> from by <hi rend="italic">some about</hi> you, who are old hands at such work! and perhaps returned w. <hi rend="italic">difficulty</hi>!—And (may I add?) I can get no gleam of light, nor assistance, from R.C.H. “Evil comms. corrupt”, &amp;c. but R.V. has, I believe a <hi rend="italic">better </hi>transln.—but vol. not w. me.) Weather here very warm, &amp; Xmas. has passed quietly: I <hi rend="underline italic">always</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">in</hi> my den.</p>
         <p>Too much <hi rend="italic">fuss</hi> in N. over Bright killed by sharks <hi rend="italic">at </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">same</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> time</hi>, &amp; in <hi rend="italic">papers</hi>, no less that 6–7 <hi rend="italic">sudden</hi> deaths: to me, <hi rend="italic">no difference</hi>; only, (it may be!,) that B. <hi rend="italic">knowing</hi> danger <hi rend="italic">courted it</hi>. And now, “D.T.”, “H.”, &amp; Hoadley &amp; Co., are wild after a 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. minor Bkwtr. scheme—enclosing front of esplanade for Bathers—<hi rend="underline italic">by Rates</hi>. No one has ever suffered more than myself, brought up to sea-bathing from childhood, and <hi rend="italic">that</hi>, too, <hi rend="italic">all the yr. round</hi>! (and I was a crack swimmer &amp; diver in <hi rend="italic">the Ocean</hi>!) yet, <hi rend="italic">knowing</hi> of sharks abounding, having early seen them, <hi rend="italic">gave up bathing<lb/>
            </hi>—&amp; they should do the same, &amp; learn, a <hi rend="italic">little</hi>, to control themselves. I was <hi rend="italic">not </hi>surprised to hear of Hornsby’s mad scheme, but hope he has abandoned it:—I never knew the fellow, &amp; <hi rend="italic">never liked </hi>him.</p>
         <p>Very glad to know—in all yr. troubles—your wife &amp; family were <hi rend="italic">well</hi>: may this find you <hi rend="italic">all</hi> so. And heartily (again) wishing you a Happy New Year, and (D.V.) <hi rend="italic">many </hi>of them: I am,</p>
         <p>My dear Friend</p>
         <p>Yours truly, &amp; affy.,</p>
         <p>W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
