<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1062">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1898 October 16: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1898-10-16">1898 October 16</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1898 October 16: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-917" place="foot" n="917"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, October 16<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>, 1898<lb/>(<hi rend="italic">early </hi>a.m.)</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>Yours of 14<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. came to hand <hi rend="italic">late </hi>last night,—I have just read it, &amp; reply at once: I have frequently thought on you, &amp; <hi rend="italic">going</hi> to write, but hands <hi rend="italic">full</hi>, &amp;c, for the last 2–3 weeks especially: Synod time, lasting 8–9 days, I attending every day (4–6 p.m., not nights) and on Sunday 2<hi rend="sup ">nd</hi> took Ch. duty at Clive for St. Hill. Owing to the <hi rend="italic">reporting </hi>of Synod doings being so <hi rend="italic">utterly meager</hi> (done by Bp’s. son, Herbert) I did not care to send you any of the Heralds—save those containing my letters: yesterday I sent you Bp’s. address, &amp;c.—I told Synod some patent old <hi rend="italic">Truths</hi>—concerning our Eng. Ch. (as the <hi rend="italic">old </hi>man of the S., and, it being probably <hi rend="italic">my last</hi>) which they <hi rend="italic">received well</hi>, and even loudly cheered—but <hi rend="italic">few </hi>(2–3 only) have called, &amp; Robertshawe &amp; Tuke, likely <hi rend="italic">made </hi>enemies!—I believe, my issue of “Sodor and Man’s charge” did good—several thanked me for it, &amp; from a few <hi rend="italic">pulpits it was read at Evg. S. on Sunday</hi>.</p>
         <p>But now to your last—particularly its Botanical enclosures:—<lb/>1, the minute moss-like silvery plant—is a sp. of<hi rend="italic">Raoulia</hi> probably <hi rend="italic">R. australis</hi>: your spns. have <hi rend="italic">no </hi>trace of flowers, their white silvery <hi rend="italic">leaves</hi> deceiving you: there are several sp. of this genus in Fl. N.Z., &amp; to them I have added 2–3 sp. more. <lb/>2, what you call a “<hi rend="italic">Moss</hi>”—is a sp. of <hi rend="italic">Tillæa </hi>very likely <hi rend="italic">T. verticillatus</hi>—past flowering.<lb/>3, in papers,<hi rend="italic">Discaria toumatou</hi>: nice little spn. one of my <hi rend="underline italic">earliest</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> discoveries</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">publishing </hi>(in “Tasmanian Jl. Sc.”), originally found at Poverty Bay: Sir <hi rend="underline">W.</hi> Hooker, thanked me for it early, said, I was right—but that, with <hi rend="italic">many </hi>others, all looked over by him, were kept for <hi rend="italic">Dr. </hi>J.H. to describe, &amp;c, on his return from India: so, by that detention, Raoul published his “<hi rend="italic">Choix</hi>” in ’46, &amp; named it (horridly—see “<hi rend="italic">3 Lity. papers</hi>) <hi rend="italic">toumatou</hi>! R. also found it at Akaroa. In <hi rend="italic">this plant</hi> a curious instance of <hi rend="italic">no petals</hi>.</p>
         <p>While on plants I may tell <hi rend="italic">you</hi> of a paper I have written for <hi rend="italic">our </hi>Instit., descriptions of some of Hill’s <hi rend="italic">last lot </hi>of Ruahine plants. The descriptions I had jotted roughly last winter &amp; early spring—but, on Hill’s leaving a month ago for E. Cape District, I promised him my p. (though only ½ of his “finds”) should be ready for <hi rend="italic">last </hi>(6<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) nt. of Inst., so, I had to work hard—Synod, too, in session, &amp; “Herald” letters! (all coming together!) As Hill would not be there &amp; I could not, I wrote a note to Hislop, Hony. Secy. &amp; he kindly called, twice,—the gale of wind &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">rain</hi> last Monday put it off, but I suppose it will be held <hi rend="italic">tomorrow</hi>, the mounting of some spns. to illustrate <hi rend="italic">gave me hard work</hi>—pressed, too, for time. From an <hi rend="underline italic">error</hi> in <hi rend="italic">advt</hi>., folks suppose <hi rend="italic">I shall be present</hi>. (Letters, congratulations, to hand!) a disappointment, I know, to some.—I did think of sending paper to Wgn.—Hill was against it.</p>
         <p>You <hi rend="italic">may </hi>have seen in papers, a local <hi rend="italic">re </hi>£<hi rend="italic">1000</hi> to the poor of Penzance, this put me out! Another mistake! It was not already sent but promised (conditionally) 3 years ago—it <hi rend="italic">goes</hi>, however, at last! by <hi rend="italic">next </hi>Mail: and my main reason for getting it together &amp; sending now—while <hi rend="italic">I live</hi>, instead of by <hi rend="italic">Will</hi>—arises from the <hi rend="underline italic">treatment</hi> Tiffen’s legacy to the Orphan Home, <hi rend="italic">re heavy probate </hi>duty, recd. from the Govt.—though I <hi rend="italic">lose </hi>the Bank Int. (£30. yearly) which to me, with <hi rend="italic">steadily falling Income—very much reduced—is serious</hi>: but, still another reason— “<hi rend="italic">What of the Banks</hi>?” <hi rend="italic">their </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">stability</hi>? Evils <hi rend="italic">thicken</hi>: yesterday &amp; this past week, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>a few ac. of land at Waipawa: rates, &amp;c pd. by <hi rend="italic">takers</hi>, on two paddocks, one, a <hi rend="italic">few</hi> shillings yearly, &amp; one 13/4: <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, under <hi rend="italic">Non</hi> Improvement,—one £4. &amp; t’other £12.15, yrly. to <hi rend="italic">them</hi>, besides Py. Tax. to Govt. Both occupiers have thrown up: and I suppose I shall have to do, as I did <hi rend="italic">here</hi> in N., sell by Auction, <hi rend="italic">no reserve</hi>!—in those Waipawa lands, the rents would <hi rend="italic">not </hi>meet the Rates &amp; T. It is not the money, so much as the <hi rend="italic">worry</hi>. But I have promised to be at W. on 25<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. to arrange (if possible): and if Tuke’s ruffled feathers have resumed their old smoothness, and I get a <hi rend="italic">suitable</hi> note from him, I hope to go to Wpku. <hi rend="italic">this wk. </hi>for next Sunday’s Ch. S. there,—but I scarcely expect it.—–</p>
         <p>I sent copies of my circular (Sodor &amp; M. chge) to the Bishops of Wgn., and of Auckland.—Thornton (Te Aute) read nearly the <hi rend="italic">whole</hi> of it, when speaking to his Motion in Synod! I called partr. attention of Bp. &amp; Archdn. S. to <hi rend="italic">their </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">bringing up</hi>—their <hi rend="italic">parents</hi> teachings—&amp;c &amp;c,—told “all hands” of what <hi rend="italic">I had known</hi> of Pusey &amp; Co’s. <hi rend="italic">heresies</hi>—of which <hi rend="italic">they knew nothing</hi>: and <hi rend="italic">adduced</hi> from our Ch. of E. <hi rend="italic">standards</hi>, (Homilies; “Eccl. Polity”, Hooker, &amp;c) that, “Ch. of R. <hi rend="italic">no </hi>Ch. of Xt,”— “Man of Sin”, &amp;c. So, that, what I had the <hi rend="italic">temerity</hi> to state in my booklet was <hi rend="italic">the true doct. of the Ch. E. </hi>I think I made some stare! but was cheered, espy. by “<hi rend="italic">laity</hi>”: Eccles, Jordan, Wills, Cato, O. Dean, Clarke (<hi rend="italic">clerics</hi>) with me. It was an exciting time: I told Hobbs, to his face (sitting close to me, in reply to his insidious arguments, that bec. <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi> had such &amp; such, <hi rend="italic">good, holy, ancient, </hi>we too should not disclaim them—quoting Rowland Hill, &amp; <hi rend="italic">pleasing</hi> tunes not to be left w. Devil, &amp;c.,) that he, Hobbs, had better leave us &amp; <hi rend="italic">go to Rome</hi>:—he had not, however, one supporter, and his motion would have died at birth had not Gardiner (sitting next to Hobbs) seconded, <hi rend="underline italic">pro forma</hi>. At Cathedral on Sunday Robertshawe (like a second Saul in alt.) donned a flaring vermilion stole, 4–5 in wide, w. golden fringes, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">2 big</hi>
            <hi rend="underline"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline"></hi> in front and 1 behind on back of neck: the only Philistine (<hi rend="italic">in dress</hi>) present: it <hi rend="italic">galled me</hi>, &amp; R. got it <hi rend="italic">hot</hi> in Synod! In all <hi rend="italic">such </hi>matters I spare none. Often of late, as opportunity offered, I have repeatedly warned in Sermons Paul’s <hi rend="underline italic">warnings</hi> to Timothy, &amp;c., <hi rend="italic">re </hi>last times— “<hi rend="italic">lovers of pleasure more than G., </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">from such turn away</hi>” (<hi rend="italic">awful</hi>!) <hi rend="italic">True </hi>Religion is at ebb here, &amp; every where! among the majority of those who are Church <hi rend="italic">goers</hi>—the form is (or may be,) there. A long affectionate yet <hi rend="underline italic">sad</hi> letter from Rev. R. Fraser (my <hi rend="italic">dear </hi>old &amp; valued Presbytn. Friend) confirms my belief: sad, sad, indeed is it <hi rend="italic">now </hi>in “auld Scotland—and yet, after all—<hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi>, <hi rend="underline italic">our Father</hi>—<hi rend="italic">liveth</hi>, &amp; knows all.—Ps.46.</p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">Afternoon</hi>: now I go on, &amp; finish my letter:—this mg. in reading the <hi rend="italic">2 Lessons for the day</hi> (as I always do, &amp; so keep up a kind of “<hi rend="underline italic">Commn.</hi> of Saints” throughout the world) Ezek. XIV was the 1<hi rend="sup ">st</hi>. Less., what an awful yet highly <hi rend="italic">suitable</hi> chap.! I have had to read it in course, before now, &amp; have preached from some of its verses.] It is sad to read—in yours—of those <hi rend="italic">new </hi>heresies, their development, &amp; rapidly growing increase: but such has ever been—even in the days of the Apostles, &amp; directly after them. I was amused (?) the other day in reading in English Papers, of the <hi rend="italic">early end </hi>of the sect— “The New &amp; Latter House of Israel”; they built a huge tower (“Jesreel’s tower”) in the hills above Chatham at a cost of many thousands! one of their tenets was that those who came to reside there would never die, the founder, however, died, &amp; sect scattered; gigantic castle, offered by auction—but withdrawn!—You, my friend, will live to see more yet of such little <hi rend="italic">frauds</hi>: but <hi rend="smallcaps">God’s</hi> seal is sure: “The Lord knoweth them that are his”: “My sheep hear <hi rend="underline italic">My</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> Voice</hi>”, &amp;c. Two slashing (shameful) letters in “Herald” last wk <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the Churches &amp; their Ministers: I think, Walker should <hi rend="italic">not </hi>publish <hi rend="italic">such anonymously</hi>.—–</p>
         <p>And so! yr. Birthday draws nigh, &amp; you are 49! Reading <hi rend="italic">that</hi>, with the “Herald’s” <hi rend="italic">long article</hi> of last month of <hi rend="italic">its </hi>Birthday, also of my letter <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Govr. Eyre<note xml:id="ftn3-918" place="foot" n="918"> Governor Eyre. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi> 6 October 1898.</note>—all taking me back ½ century: set me <hi rend="italic">athinking</hi>! and <hi rend="italic">first</hi>, <hi rend="underline italic">to you</hi>: I heartily wish you every blessing—for soul &amp; body: for wife, family, estate—basket &amp; store, &amp; may you &amp; yours see <hi rend="italic">many </hi>happy returns of the season, each one excelling its predecessor: I should like to present you w. a vol. from my shelves as a reminder, but I hesitate to do so, as you may <hi rend="italic">have it already</hi>—so I will enclose a £1. note, that you may purchase one—in your city of books. It pleased me much to read your going w. family to Lyell’s Bay! I could wish I were with you. I have very little of Society <hi rend="italic">here</hi>—sometimes (though <hi rend="italic">rarely</hi>) <hi rend="italic">feel </hi>too solitary. I could <hi rend="italic">add</hi>—to J. Wood’s opening at spit with H.B.H. Think <hi rend="underline italic">little</hi> of <hi rend="underline italic">Tregear</hi> (&amp; Hector) on Kumi all <hi rend="italic">borrowed</hi>! old Mrs Tuke died last week,—one of our earliest <hi rend="italic">fem</hi>. Settlers. Fannin is, at <hi rend="italic">last</hi>, in his Office again, &amp; well. Rain last Monday did us <hi rend="italic">all</hi> good. Good Bye: kind regards.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> be with you: yours sincy.             W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. Have not heard from Welsh for some time, &amp; fear it is a <hi rend="italic">bad </hi>omen.</p>
         <p>Monday mg. 17<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I send you (unread) this mg’s. paper—another letter in it <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Layman &amp;c.!</p>
         <p>I omitted in my letter of yesterday, to say,<lb/>I have a copy of “Typogl. Jl.” of Melbourne, contg. much from your old “Typo,” &amp; “50 yrs. in N.Z.”<hi rend="italic">re </hi>self—I will send it to you if you have <hi rend="italic">not </hi>a copy.</p>
         <p>I do not comprehend Abp’s <hi rend="italic">meaning</hi>—re “<hi rend="italic">Trans.</hi>”<hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi>“<hi rend="italic">Cons.</hi>”<hi rend="italic"> </hi>as given in cablegram. <hi rend="italic">Lucus a non lucendo</hi>!<note xml:id="ftn3-919" place="foot" n="919"> It is a grove by not being light.</note>
         </p>
         <p>Biggest, oldest, Acacia blown down by night a fortnight ago—close to <hi rend="italic">little back gate </hi>trunk 2 ft. one way 20 inches together diameter—no injury to any one.</p>
         <p>I wrote late last nt. to Hamilton reply to his of 19<hi rend="sup ">th</hi> Sept.</p>
         <p>To my <hi rend="italic">surprise </hi>he said in his, “No. III Maori Art <hi rend="underline italic">issued</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Where are my copies? </hi>I have written to Gore.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Evening</hi>. “Woe’s me!” I must still go on! <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Re </hi>Larnach: <hi rend="italic">sad</hi>: I fear <hi rend="italic">financial difficulties </hi>will be found to be the cause: be not in haste to get rich.<lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Re</hi>. Kirk’s Flora: Enys writes to me from England, that the copy (a late sheet) he had recd. from Kirk, was of <hi rend="italic">the same size</hi> as <hi rend="italic">Hooker’s Flora </hi>Handbook. You had told me it was <hi rend="italic">larger</hi>.<lb/>Mr. Dodds, Schmr., of Kaikoura, H.B. still takes Ch. duty at St. Paul’s, &amp; is much liked.<lb/>I see, a German “Doctor” (!) is going to reside on Stephen’s Island—to<hi rend="italic">see habits</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Tuatara</hi>! <hi rend="italic">Scit </hi>to steal specimens!<lb/>Rev.—Eldridge has been inducted Presbytn. Ch. Dannevirke: cannot hear any<hi rend="italic">news</hi> of Mr. Paterson: Last week had 2 <hi rend="italic">pleasant</hi> visits, (<hi rend="italic">once &amp; no more</hi>!) from 2 Presbytn. Ministers—Rev. R. Stewart from Greymouth (on sick leave—but <hi rend="italic">now </hi>well), and Rev. A. Grant, <hi rend="italic">Wpku</hi>. Crerar well. Dr. Sidey ailing. The Dean well. Bp. gone to Gisborne: some portion of his “charge”, <hi rend="italic">good</hi>: and so I told Hobbs—who had. also, <hi rend="italic">heard it</hi>. The Pope has issued his Bull to <hi rend="italic">his Scotch</hi> Episcopacy—<hi rend="underline italic">get me a R.C. translation</hi>.—</p>
         <p>Owing to that <hi rend="italic">foolish</hi> announcement<hi rend="italic"> </hi>in Papers re £<hi rend="italic">1000</hi>, I got <hi rend="italic">calls</hi> from all sides! even from a Cleric at “St. Thomas”, Wellington and from a ditto, Auckland—for a painted window, to cost £300, to memory of 3 Bishops:—with others, nearer:—one stereotyped reply, NO: help <hi rend="underline italic">poor</hi>, <hi rend="italic">not buildings</hi>.</p>
         <p>Nothing yet from Seddon <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Lexicon, and <hi rend="italic">now </hi>I wish I had <hi rend="italic">not offered </hi>to get<hi rend="italic"> </hi>out another such part: memory (Maori) &amp; physical powers failing fast: I <hi rend="italic">need</hi> a good, suitable pair of specs., particularly for <hi rend="italic">night </hi>work—these I have in use at night (for reading only) <hi rend="italic">hurt my eyes</hi> after, say, an hour’s using. I must try <hi rend="italic">again</hi>—at Collins’, also at Williams’.</p>
         <p>Will post your tractate,— “Light” to your Father, as directed—don’t think much of it, tho’ highly spiced with orthodox remarks. <hi rend="italic">Agree fully </hi>w. you, as to “<hi rend="italic">Missioners</hi>”, so I have constantly &amp; boldly said:—I fear Paterson’s <hi rend="italic">removal</hi> has been <hi rend="italic">somehow</hi> caused by Soltan, &amp;c, &amp;c.</p>
         <p>Once more good bye               yours ever</p>
         <p>W.C.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
