<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-1070">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1898 December 21: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0499.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1898-12-21">1898 December 21</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1898 December 21: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-929" place="foot" n="929"> ATL qMS-0499.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Decr. 21/98</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I must no longer delay writing to you, (having, at last! finished my heavy lot for the outgoing Mail.)—I fear (if my <hi rend="italic">notched </hi>stick is true) that I have not written to you for <hi rend="italic">this month</hi> of Decr., though I recollect sending you some papers. Your long &amp; full letter of the 7<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>. (posted 10<hi rend="sup ">th</hi>.) I duly received, &amp; thank you for it—also, for a paper containing a few items of interest, especially those <hi rend="italic">re </hi>“Philosophical”. I think <hi rend="italic">you</hi> will generally find that Buller, or Travers, will be pretty sure to be <hi rend="italic">ready to say</hi>,— “that well known” (or seen) “<hi rend="underline italic">before</hi>”; such (<hi rend="italic">to me</hi>) has ever been Travers’ hobby. I was interested in Hector’s <hi rend="italic">statement, re </hi>“Cuckoos being gorged w. <hi rend="italic">young</hi> birds”:—and, <hi rend="italic">when</hi> Buller up, &amp; said, he had known that <hi rend="italic">before</hi>—H. should have asked, If he had ever pubd. it? &amp; when, &amp; where? for B. has always been <hi rend="italic">very ready</hi> to bring forward everything new relating to <hi rend="italic">birds</hi>—whether of his <hi rend="italic">own</hi>, or of <hi rend="underline italic">others</hi>. I also notice what Hector said, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>grafting Europ. olives on our indig. N.Z. ones: supported, of course, by Travers, &amp; Co., and spoken of as if <hi rend="italic">original</hi>!! You will find that in my<hi rend="italic"> </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">early</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> </hi>“<hi rend="italic">Essay</hi>” on <hi rend="italic">Botany</hi> of N. Island, (which Hector I <hi rend="underline italic">know</hi> read, &amp;c.)— “Trans. N.Z. I.”, vol.I, §32, or last one of “Essay”:<note xml:id="ftn3-930" place="foot" n="930"> Wherein Colenso wrote in 1865, “the European Olive might be advantageously grafted upon the several indigenous Olives of the island.”</note> that was more than 30 years ago—&amp; has since been casually mentioned by me in Papers.<note xml:id="ftn3-931" place="foot" n="931"> The New Zealand olive. <hi rend="italic">Daily Telegraph</hi>, 11 &amp; 12 May 1882.</note> (I had lent my vol. I. to our friend Rev. A. Grant in the spring, and he returned it recently, so, having it <hi rend="italic">handy</hi>, I looked it up.) That, brings another item (from “Philosophical”)—some time ago, I saw, in a Wgn. p. you sent me, that Tregear had come out <hi rend="underline italic">in his way</hi>, about the “<hi rend="italic">kumi</hi>”, and had <hi rend="italic">said</hi>, all he had <hi rend="italic">heard</hi> about it from the Maoris, was, that it was “a huge fabulous reptile”. <hi rend="underline italic">Something</hi> at the time, told me—that was <hi rend="italic">false</hi> as to <hi rend="underline italic">his</hi> hearing of it from them, because the <hi rend="italic">word</hi> is strictly an <hi rend="italic">E. Coast</hi> word, &amp; Tregear had not been there: lately I have been enquiring <hi rend="italic">North</hi>, and am informed the Maoris never knew of “<hi rend="italic">kumi</hi>” so applied, (which I pretty well knew). And on looking into Wms’. Mao. Dicty., Ed. 1871,—there, <hi rend="italic">sure enough</hi>, is the <hi rend="italic">very sentence</hi> used (borrowed or filched) by Tregear!— “<hi rend="italic">kumi</hi>, a huge fabulous reptile”. Further, looking lately into Kirk’s compilation “Forest Flora”, (for a Mao. plant now growing in Robjohn’s garden) I lit on a nice bit, supplementary to your late information concerning that——Editor of a Taranaki paper and <hi rend="italic">his yarns</hi> re Maoris:—Kirk, at p.173, writing on a plant,—says, the Maoris say, they brought it with them from Hawaiki, but it is <hi rend="italic">strictly indig. to N.Z.</hi>, &amp; not in the Islands;—but Heaphy (<hi rend="underline italic">that</hi> Vict. Cross man!) states, re their Hawaiki, that the island has been subsequently submerged through volcanic action!! <hi rend="italic">Worse </hi>than a Prohibitionist—to support his (or their) fad <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Hawaiki. Every now &amp; then something of this kind I meet with, but I don’t bear it in mind, so as to, when I write, transmit it to you. <hi rend="italic">We </hi>have been having some talk lately on these, &amp; similar, matters—3–4 visitors here <hi rend="italic">together</hi>! (&amp; yet by chance!)—Walker (of “Herald”) Allom, his f-in-law—a <hi rend="italic">nice</hi> chatty well-informed old gentleman—first saw me at Wairarapa in ’45—he wrote from Tasmania to me, &amp; others, about “the Introdn. of Bees”,<note xml:id="ftn3-932" place="foot" n="932"> Introduction of bees. <hi rend="italic">Hawke’s Bay Herald</hi>, 10 December 1895.</note> a few year ago: <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, however, he <hi rend="italic">gives in</hi>:—and Mr. Hill:—other visitors, also, W.W. Yates, his son W.C.Y. several times, he has a <hi rend="italic">fine</hi> greenhouse with many Orchids &amp; Ferns: Mont. Lascelles, Carr, Henry Lascelles, &amp;c. The <hi rend="italic">Fourcraya </hi>in flower brought <hi rend="italic">some</hi>. You tell me a <hi rend="underline italic">strange</hi> story re a <hi rend="italic">F. </hi>at your Uncle John’s—of a <hi rend="italic">F. </hi>there, <hi rend="italic">changing </hi>its <hi rend="italic">flowers</hi> into <hi rend="italic">complete plants</hi>!! wh. dropping off <hi rend="italic">rooted in soil</hi>—but died:—<hi rend="underline italic">Did</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">you</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">see </hi>it? <hi rend="underline italic">examine</hi> it? I <hi rend="italic">cannot believe it</hi>: at same time <hi rend="italic">may </hi>be able to throw light on it: the <hi rend="italic">Fourcraya </hi>is allied to the <hi rend="italic">Agave</hi> flowering grandly at Waipawa:—to my surprise there shot up more than 20 <hi rend="italic">little tiny Agaves</hi> in a circle, like a big coach-wheel, around the main stem, each one bearing a little stalk of flowers—resembling a lily! I wrote about it to Kew—and it is in one of my Botl. papers in “Trans.”:<note xml:id="ftn3-933" place="foot" n="933"> Colenso W 1893. Notes, Remarks, and Reminiscences of Two Peculiar Introduced and Naturalised South American Plants. <hi rend="italic">Trans NZ Inst.</hi> 26: 323–332.</note> the flowers of the Fourcraya are in <hi rend="italic">thousands</hi>, covering the ground deeply: Bob placed his big barrow under the <hi rend="italic">F. </hi>here, to stand on &amp; get down a branch, and in a short time it was full of blossoms.—You tell me of Lindauer’s big picture—a yg. w. feeding an aged chief: yes, I saw it, more than once, &amp; found fault w. the instrument the yg. w. was using:—as to, “5 fingers”, such are <hi rend="italic">sometimes</hi>, curved (as Hamilton knows) but not commonly so: there <hi rend="underline italic">may</hi> have been a <hi rend="italic">natural</hi> cause for it, as 6-fingered hands &amp; toes to Maoris were sometimes to be met with. (See my “Essay Mao. Races”; §I, subsect. 8.)</p>
         <p>I wrote last week to Mr. Seddon re “A.” Mao. Eng. Lex.,—as I had found from Mackay that their charge of ₤82. was for <hi rend="italic">500</hi> copies, as ordered by me, and as S. retained <hi rend="italic">200 </hi>copies I wrote to ask him to determine what he would allow for them—that I might pay Govt. Ptr. the balance:—but, hitherto, <hi rend="italic">no reply</hi>!—–</p>
         <p>Yesterday Mr. Ormond kindly called &amp; spent an hour, or more, he would have called before—but was absent down S. I find that Hill made a sad mistake in telling me, that O. had told him, he (O.) had got a copy of <hi rend="italic">letter “A.”—</hi>O. says, he has <hi rend="italic">never seen it</hi>! in his talk in the train with H., he said, he had, years ago, seen <hi rend="italic">my bulky lot of Mss. &amp; reported on them to the House: heoi ano. </hi>O. had <hi rend="italic">never</hi> heard of any copies being distribd. at Wgn.—but, <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="italic">lately</hi>, R.D.D. McL. had told O., <hi rend="italic">he had a copy</hi>. O. seems very well, quite stoutish: I had not seen him for <hi rend="italic">many </hi>months.</p>
         <p>To your letter: right glad I am to hear such a <hi rend="italic">good account</hi> from you of your family: all well, in health of body &amp; mind, &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">growing</hi>. And you, too,—as a good <hi rend="italic">paterfam.</hi>, enjoying their loving clustering around you on your return to your <hi rend="underline italic">Home</hi>. Good: that reminds me of what I said <hi rend="underline italic">early in ’35</hi>, to the late Bp. Williams, in his garden at Paihia, on seeing his children run to meet &amp; embrace him on his arrival at Home:—<lb/>— “And climb his knees the envied kiss to share” <lb/>which pleased my<hi rend="italic">new </hi>acq. very much.</p>
         <p>Xmas. is near: and I enclose my Box for your children—you must carve the fowl—giving namesake the merry thought,—with an <hi rend="italic">old </hi>friend’s <hi rend="underline italic">love to all</hi>.</p>
         <p>I am keeping well: have not yet ventured to walk <hi rend="italic">to </hi>town: don’t think I shall go inland this summer, not having any Ch. wk. to call me. Heartily wishing you &amp; yours—<hi rend="italic">all—</hi>the good honest old wishes of our forefathers at these 2 grand seasons of the year,—</p>
         <p>         I am, Dear Mr. Harding</p>
         <p>                         Yours truly,            W. Colenso.</p>
         <p>P.S. I send you a D.T., note letter on p.4.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
