<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0800">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1891 September 14: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0496.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1891-09-14">1891 September 14</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1891 September 14: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-550" place="foot" n="550"> ATL qMS-0496.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier<lb/>Monday Septr. 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,<lb/>3 p.m.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I have been thinking on you this day, &amp; so have put up for you a copy of my Papers in vol. XIII “Trans.” that you might <hi rend="italic">have</hi> (if not read!) that paper on “Veg. food of Maoris” I wrote you about: and so I begin this letter to you, but I shall not finish it today, as I wish to be at our Sy’s. meeting tonight—weather permitting. It has been <hi rend="italic">very fine</hi> until now, when a change seems to be at hand.</p>
         <p>It is some time since my last. Yours of the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I duly recd.—but I was too much engd. last wk. to write. Early days of wk—Eng. Mail—then on Wedy. to Waipawa (on my way to Ormondville)—to O. on Thursday to attend opening of new Ch., &amp; staid till Friday aftn. returning that night—but much shook in the <hi rend="italic">new</hi> carriage, wh. I do not like at all.</p>
         <p>Saty’s. “Herald” informed me, I was in for the mg. S. yesty. at Augustine’s &amp; for this I had to prepare—tho’ not well, but better towards evg. I was there twice yesterday, in the evg. assisting the Dean.—and this mg. opened my batch of foreign letters, leaving books &amp; papers.—</p>
         <p>With your last came (<hi rend="italic">returned</hi>) those 2 letters I had sent you: I was pleased at your being pleased w. Mr. Watts’—&amp; could tell you a deal about him &amp; <hi rend="italic">his</hi> there: but you make <hi rend="italic">no</hi> remark on Quaife’s wh. I had supposed wod. have interested you: but then you <hi rend="italic">not unfrequently</hi> omit half! Here, while on ptg., I must tell you something—Have you a copy of Bp. Wms.’ “Xy. ’mong the NZrs.”? <hi rend="italic">Seeing it advd.</hi> in L.P. I gave Craig an order for a copy—never having seen it—he reported—“out of print” (!!) but of his own accord wrote to Auckland, &amp; was chgd. 10/- for the book! I cut it, &amp; <hi rend="italic">ran</hi> thro’ it, &amp; (could you believe it?) <hi rend="italic">Wms. says not a word about the Introdn. of the press! Nor ptg. the N.T.</hi>
            <hi rend="bold italic">—</hi>he does <hi rend="italic">re</hi> obtg. early a few small things from Sydney (which we know), and remarks briefly &amp; casually, what great good ensued the distribn. of N.T., &amp; how soon the copies were disposed of.—I did not <hi rend="italic">quite</hi> expect that from <hi rend="italic">him</hi>. Did I tell you of <hi rend="italic">his</hi> lst. letter to Dr. Buckland re Moa bones?—(How truly Williams-like!) I wish I had my 10/- back—will sell for 5/- (shall tell Craig <hi rend="italic">this</hi>.)—</p>
         <p>I thank you for the scrap re the “Awhiorangi”: and, as you have (you say) those 2 vols. containing it, <hi rend="italic">&amp;</hi> “Ngatangata Maori,” just let me know in <hi rend="italic">what year</hi> that fight took place mentd. at p.92,—“Barrett &amp; his cannonades.”—The writers—are too much in the John White-<hi rend="italic">vein</hi> for me.—</p>
         <p>When last in town (10 days or so back) I took your copy of Vol. XXIII to yr brother for you: On not finding him there went up stairs &amp; knocked, &amp; knocked! At last I (seeing a coat hanging up) ventured to open a door—then I saw your F. <hi rend="italic">closely</hi> engd. nr. window, at something, I knocked, &amp; bawled! &amp; at last <hi rend="italic">went up</hi>—bang! &amp; lo! my old friend started up, glad to see me. By this time yr bror. had retd. from P.O.</p>
         <p>I wish for <hi rend="italic">more</hi> copies of “Bush Jottings”: <hi rend="italic">you</hi> can <hi rend="italic">well</hi> tell me, what 100 wod. come to, done here by brother. It seemed strange to me, that so much should be sd. about it—from <hi rend="italic">strangers</hi> too, as well as the Bp., the Dean, &amp; Clerics &amp; others here—&amp; <hi rend="italic">not by R.C.H.</hi>! to whom I had sent 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> copy.</p>
         <p>I think I told you, a month ago, I had written to Hill (<hi rend="italic">President</hi>) <hi rend="italic">re</hi> my papers &amp; my right (?) to this meeting.—but <hi rend="italic">no reply</hi>: in advts. it is stated, 4 papers—“Tuberculine,” Dr.Sp.; “Ferns” Pinkney; “Climatology,” Westall; “Philology”——–: I noticed last wk. that Hon. Secy. White has borrowed Tregear’s Dicty.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">8.pm.</hi> Rain prevents my moving out, so I proceed w. my letter. I should much like to know something of Pinkney’s “Ferns,”—for, at least, 2 reasons:—at the last month’s meeting after it was over, P. (whom I did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> then know) came up to me &amp; showed me a <hi rend="italic">small</hi> fern living (lately gathered), he said, he had got it from a Maori, &amp; was going to have <hi rend="italic">more</hi>—it is rare <hi rend="italic">now</hi> here, though I had it growing in my garden at Waitangi, H.B., Two days after, I wrote to P., saying I would thank him to get me a spn. or two, when he should see the said Maori, or, failing that, to lend me his: but <hi rend="italic">no reply</hi>! (Craig had given me his name.)—I cannot conceive what P. can have <hi rend="italic">original</hi> in the matter of <hi rend="italic">Ferns</hi>.—I wished to be present tonight, to see what (if any) arrangement would be made, or offered, for my Papers. The important one re Dr. Mantell &amp; self I am thinking of sending <hi rend="italic">to Wgn. </hi>which, if I do, I <hi rend="italic">must</hi> send to Gore: I should prefer sending it to <hi rend="italic">you</hi> to read there for me, but I have not forgotten <hi rend="italic">how I was taken-up by G.</hi> some 8 yrs. ago, when I sent my p. to Buller to read, he being <hi rend="italic">Prest</hi>. that year, as it had been arranged between us: if I do this, I shall write to Hector, and to Mantell, about the said paper. Wgn would be the <hi rend="italic">proper</hi> place to read it, as there is no one <hi rend="italic">here</hi> who would, or could, speak a word concg. it.—</p>
         <p>Since my last to you I have had a <hi rend="italic">very long letter</hi> from Hamilton, w. papers, too! Containing (1) Report &amp;c of University (long &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">dry</hi>): and (2) a Paper on destruction of our N.Z. birds, another long affair. H’s letter is written on fol. fcp. <hi rend="italic">many</hi> ½-sheets! &amp; in very <hi rend="italic">small</hi> hand, trying to one’s eyes to read. I almost dread the task of ansg. it: but this <hi rend="italic">must</hi> be done: he was <hi rend="italic">well</hi>, &amp; evidently had <hi rend="italic">pleased</hi> his Sc. masters,—spoken highly of in Report.</p>
         <p>In “Herald” this mg. was the death of Rev. J. Eccles youngest son—20 months old: this child, a pretty little fellow, made me to think of <hi rend="italic">yours</hi>, he had been long ailing, intermittently: E. went with me to O. on Thursday, &amp; remd. there on Friday to preach that night, retg. on Saty. to W.—poor man! his son died on Sunday yesty., &amp; I fear he has had a sad time, I know it was <hi rend="italic">unexpected</hi>. In “D.T.” this evg., arrival of Parkinson &amp; wife at Bluff is stated—so, I suppose, he will be in his own Ch. again next Sunday.</p>
         <p>In the “Barbados” book, the author mentions a plant called <hi rend="italic">Mum</hi>. (as being ident. w. Brit. one of <hi rend="italic">that name</hi>,) and so does Parkinson, who was here in N.Z. w. Cook, as being found <hi rend="italic">here</hi>:—if you should light on this word, in any old Eng. Dy., &amp;c., let me know of it: I cannot find it out: as P. was a Sc., it <hi rend="italic">may</hi> be a <hi rend="italic">Sc.</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">word</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I attended meeting Subsn. to Sir D. McLean Memol. Fund, on 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> inst.—I had been previously invited by Goudy Hon. Secy., but I would not go. I found Jy. Anderson in Chr., &amp; room <hi rend="italic">full</hi> of Scots. As they had <hi rend="italic">abandoned</hi> the 25 ac. of land, for Recreation Ground (<hi rend="italic">obliged</hi>), I proposed, for Museum &amp; Libr. of brick &amp; made “an <hi rend="italic">oration</hi>”! offering to raise their <hi rend="italic">present</hi> sum of £600. to £1000. No one seconded, nor sd. a word:—&amp; then they went in for a <hi rend="italic">statue</hi>!—They wished to have me on their Comee.—“No I thank you.”—</p>
         <p>I believe I shall be strolling Dannek. way, by end of next wk. I want to get flrs. of 2 shrubs there (sps. nov.) that flr. <hi rend="italic">early</hi>; I may not make any stay. I saw yr Uncle John, last wk, &amp; told him he was getting <hi rend="italic">stout</hi>.—</p>
         <p>Thanks for yr. information <hi rend="italic">re</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Gorse</hi>—all that is new to me: but alas! those “fads” (of <hi rend="italic">all kinds</hi>) are sadly on the increase! Were you <hi rend="italic">here</hi> &amp; w. me—<hi rend="italic">We would talk</hi> about them! May you &amp; I, my dear friend, be ever kept from harbouring them!</p>
         <p>Staying 1 night at Canon Webb’s, I saw his big Liby.! &amp; thought on <hi rend="italic">you</hi>. Another parcel by last E.M. from Linn. Sy.—making 7–8 still <hi rend="italic">un</hi>opened! Are you going on with Archd. Wm’s. Dy? and, are there any Ch. of Engld. <hi rend="italic">Maori</hi> prayer Books to be had at Wgn.? I see a terrible amount of – – – well, “blarney”, in “D.T.” of this evg. re Governor &amp; his “<hi rend="italic">Huia” </hi>(Buller’s doings!) at <hi rend="italic">Otaki</hi>! Do you know anything more of Opotiki doings? I suppose, that “Solicitor” <hi rend="italic">Shortland</hi>,—“2 yrs. impt” this day,—is a son of <hi rend="italic">Dr Shortland</hi>?—he seems to have richly deserved his doom.</p>
         <p>I trust your son is <hi rend="italic">better</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Mrs</hi> H. must have a trying time of it, I hope her health will continue good: You, too, seem to be made of iron! To stand so <hi rend="italic">much</hi> worry.—</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">15</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. 3 p.m.</hi> I proceed w. my letter. Wet to day, yet I went to town—as I had business there, already too long delayed. Showers heavy &amp; frequent, yet I managed to get along &amp; back dry. Friend Craig told me they had a fair meeting last night, about 20 present, (Bp. being one, also this new arrival, Mr Humphries (who has become a member (with his wife)—3 Papers were read, (those first 3, supra,) Pinkney’s pleased, &amp; yet it was, &amp; is, only a <hi rend="italic">resumé</hi> of what is already known! The one on <hi rend="italic">Philology </hi>is by that irrepressible man—Taylor White!—this the Cl. have concluded to “take as read”.—Craig said, I was <hi rend="italic">expected</hi>, (&amp; so Large this day): and that Hon. Sy. is to write to me re my papers for next month’s meeting:—when I may not be here! Paterson is at Whanganui, Ch. work: Grant at Woodville &amp; Stewart at ’Pukurau, on Sunday last. I suppose you have seen the <hi rend="italic">big blow</hi>! <hi rend="italic">re</hi> “Wealth of N.Z.”, &amp; the <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Lister, &amp;c. &amp;c. another 4 Maori (?) meds.—attested by Abp. Redwood. I never heard of any such Maori plants, &amp; I suspect those 4 names are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> Maori: they sound to me as if Brazilian—<hi rend="italic">i.e. Natives</hi> of Amazon, &amp;c.</p>
         <p>             I am keeping pretty well:—weather still mild, w. little wind.</p>
         <p>                     Good bye—</p>
         <p>                             Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>                                     W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
