<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PrL-0949">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private Letter: 1895 November 22: to Harding</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/9614/">William Colenso</name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ATL qMS-0498.</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
               
               <correspAction type="received">
                  <name type="person" key="http://wtap.vuw.ac.nz/eats/entity/115/">Harding</name>
               </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
         <creation xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <date when="1895-11-22">1895 November 22</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>1895 November 22: to Harding<note xml:id="ftn3-763" place="foot" n="763"> ATL qMS-0498.</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p rend="end">Napier, Novr. 22/95, (night).</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Harding</p>
         <p>I feel very much inclined to <hi rend="italic">begin </hi>a letter to you this night: to acknowledge with thanks your 2 last letters to me, also 2 papers (of which, I have, also, recd. 2 others from Wgn. <hi rend="italic">not </hi>from Luff, but (I <hi rend="italic">think</hi>) from W. B__r.)—Since my last to you I have been busily employed writing—day &amp; night! have sent off my <hi rend="italic">long L.</hi> to Dr. Hocken, on his Tasman Papers, and have just finished copying my Botanical papers (2) for Dinwiddie—a heavy job, &amp; perhaps my <hi rend="underline italic">last</hi> of <hi rend="italic">that kind</hi>. (I think I told you, that I had shown at our last mtg. the <hi rend="italic">rough drafts</hi> of the same, when I exhibd. specimens.) I also wrote a <hi rend="italic">long </hi>letter to Hill, in reply to his from Woodville: and a letter to Sir J. Hector, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>this curious sandstone <hi rend="italic">globe </hi>I have lately recd.—of which I suppose I informed you. And now—tomorrow &amp; Monday—my usual heavy lot—letters &amp; papers—to Engd. by S.F. Mail. Yesty. I sent you the <hi rend="italic">Herald </hi>of that day contg. Presbytn. Annual news, &amp;c.—Also, another P., a few days ago, &amp; this day, “the British Printer”—I feel pleased w. myself, that I had mentioned <hi rend="underline italic">this</hi> to you—to <hi rend="italic">enable you to complete your file</hi>.—</p>
         <p>I thank you for all your remarks &amp; hints <hi rend="italic">re </hi>Govt. Ptg. O. &amp; Printer: have not yet heard from that quarter—&amp; <hi rend="italic">may not</hi>! after all: and really I shall not care. (Don’t be surprised.) I have several reasons for this, every yr. of late has <hi rend="italic">lessened</hi> my desire, and <hi rend="italic">now </hi>I feel as if I were not adequate to the task of correcting proofs of such a work (small though it is): another reason is it containing <hi rend="italic">only </hi>the <hi rend="italic">letter A</hi>. Now if my spn. had been of K, or M, or T., then there would be something to show: and even if I were allowed to (&amp; <hi rend="italic">could </hi>go on and add the next <hi rend="italic">E</hi>., and <hi rend="italic">I</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">O</hi>,—it would still be dreadfully meagre! but enough of that:—the many would never understand—<hi rend="italic">few </hi>M. words <hi rend="italic">begin </hi>w. vowels.</p>
         <p>I notice what you say, <hi rend="italic">re </hi>the <hi rend="italic">spns. </hi>of <hi rend="italic">Dactylanthus</hi> shown at your meetings, and <hi rend="italic">not </hi>drawings—and I find <hi rend="italic">you are right</hi>: still a fine drawing w. dissections, by Hooker, is to be found in that <hi rend="italic">last </hi>wk. of Taylor’s (look it up in Library). Of course, <hi rend="italic">all that is copied </hi>from the “Trans. Linn. Sy.”, royal 4to. Tregear’s story of Taylor &amp; the reinga, I believe to have been from <hi rend="italic">mine</hi>—with <hi rend="italic">his </hi>additions, &amp;c. You will find all about it in “Three Lity. Papers,” pp.6 &amp; 12, also, in my paper on M. <hi rend="italic">proverbs</hi>, Trans. N.Z. Inst. vol. XII, p.122, this is a <hi rend="italic">good </hi>instance. I should also tell <hi rend="italic">you</hi>—that “<hi rend="italic">reinga</hi>” came to be used for “hell” in this way: in the <hi rend="italic">first </hi>early transln. of a part of Ch. of E., Mg. &amp; Evg. Services, printed at Sydney, in 4to., “reinga” was used for “hell”, in the Ap. Creed, &amp;c.—Referring to “Trans. N.Z. I.”, vols XII, &amp; XIII, contain my <hi rend="italic">best </hi>papers, (<hi rend="italic">i.e. in my opn.</hi>) I wish you had <hi rend="italic">those vols</hi>. They have been largely used (pilfered?) of late: by Tregear, by Seth Smith, and by Stack of Canterbury, especially!—this <hi rend="italic">last</hi> I only found out by chance! a few days ago—in his long paper on Maoris pubd. in vol. III, “Aust. Ass. Sc.”—and all of them seem to have taken up <hi rend="italic">one </hi>mode—<hi rend="italic">i.e. </hi>quoting a <hi rend="underline italic">bit</hi> w. “turned commas”, &amp; then adopting a lot.</p>
         <p>Last wk. was a great time w. the Baptists <hi rend="italic">here</hi>: the adventists, &amp; mormons were as <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> in comparison w. them—indeed in some respects, they made more noise than the Harmy! flaring gaudy calico printed signs, streamers &amp; banners, outside their own building—the Theatre Royal &amp; Athenæum. I was <hi rend="italic">sorry </hi>to see Mr. Paterson &amp; Mr. Beck supporting them. I said to Craig—that I wondered at the <hi rend="italic">old estab. Ch. of Scotland </hi>so acting. And then poor <hi rend="italic">Miller</hi>! of the “Congregationalists”, <hi rend="italic">seeking in every way </hi>to make <hi rend="italic">himself </hi>&amp; his clique, small though it is! of consequence. Both of those sects have drawn away a number from Paterson. Walker, of “Herald”, is <hi rend="italic">one </hi>of the Baptists, hence such a fuss about them in the “Hd.” The Dean went to Gisborne for a week, on the day he left G. for N., he saw Bp. W. going off on his long journey overland to Bay of Plenty, w. a packhorse, &amp; a Maori; the Bp., who has been <hi rend="italic">laid</hi> up w. <hi rend="italic">Lumbago </hi>&amp; not yet recovered, was “looking very ill indeed”: <hi rend="italic">I am sorry for him</hi>.</p>
         <p>One of the chief items I have wished to write to you about, is the matter of yr. <hi rend="italic">Will</hi>, (revolving in mind what you have sd.) I think you should <hi rend="italic">make it—</hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">mainly</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">at once</hi>: you can always add, &amp;c, &amp;c, by a Codicil: this is what I have done—but the <hi rend="italic">Codicil</hi>, which I also wish to execute, is, <hi rend="italic">to me</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">difficulty</hi>—this includes <hi rend="italic">all personally</hi>, <hi rend="italic">not </hi>funds. How best to dispose of my <hi rend="underline italic">Books</hi> (many of them <hi rend="italic">very valuable</hi>) I do not <hi rend="italic">yet </hi>know! then <hi rend="underline italic">specimens</hi>!—then <hi rend="underline italic">Papers, Mss</hi>. <hi rend="italic">At present</hi>, I can see nothing better, than <hi rend="italic">all Books </hi>(espy. the val. &amp; expensive ones) to <hi rend="italic">London </hi>for the hammer,—or to the Pub. Liby. in my nat. Town: all <hi rend="italic">spns. </hi>to Kew. I know of<hi rend="italic"> no one here</hi>, to whose<hi rend="italic"> care </hi>(say) for Museum &amp; Liby. I could safely leave them; besides (as I view it,) here in this miserable Athenm. building, &amp; still worse Comee., whose <hi rend="italic">only care is</hi>, to <hi rend="underline italic">gain the extra 6d</hi>!—such would, ere very long, undergo a <hi rend="italic">fiery </hi>ordeal!!—–</p>
         <p>If <hi rend="italic">you </hi>were here living, <hi rend="italic">settled</hi>, things would be different—in many respects. Hill has vastly too much to do, to <hi rend="italic">attend to home matters</hi>: besides, he has lately taken up w. the “<hi rend="italic">Junior Club”, </hi>and this swallows all! Last night, they held one of their Meetings: H. Chn., Hill, Junior (is Captn.) Mrs Hill, &amp; Miss H. engd. in brewing Coffee &amp;c &amp;c, Hill only retd. from Bush &amp; Cape Turnagain Dist., yesty. when I was in town and I believe he hurried back to be at <hi rend="italic">this </hi>Meeting: as <hi rend="italic">I view </hi>that Club, it will, in time, break down, through materials being far too <hi rend="italic">heterogenous</hi>—like Nebuchr. Image in his dream, clay &amp; brass, &amp;c, &amp;c, mingled,—I suppose you saw in our Papers, that Worboys &amp; Co. have offd. the <hi rend="italic">Edn. Board </hi>their chapel &amp; property for £1600!!. The “Harmy” have also come this way, taken “Waterworth’s Hall” in Cl. Sq.—Swan is again—Mayor! (of course): and Luke <hi rend="italic">may </hi>be also with you. [Past ix. Good night.]</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">26</hi>
            <hi rend="sup italic">th</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">. </hi>night) Having got rid of my S.F. mail budget &amp; worry—I take up my old letter to finish, &amp; despatch tomorrow. On looking over it I feel dissatisfied w. myself &amp; it, but it must go! The weather with us, <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, changed to rain last evg. &amp; this has continued ever since—at times very heavy. My man, who has been to P.O. w. letters, &amp;c, tells me the pathway down the face of the hill is all but impassable &amp; the new one just as bad! I have not yet seen, nor heard from, Mr. Hill. I have a reply from Sir J. Hector <hi rend="italic">re </hi>my <hi rend="italic">round stone</hi>, he says, such are very common, especially in the Amuri District—a <hi rend="italic">short </hi>letter &amp; <hi rend="underline italic">not</hi> a nice one! written by some assistant, &amp; signed by him: <hi rend="italic">very different, </hi>in style, &amp;c, to his former, &amp; last one—perhaps owing to our Council’s resolution on <hi rend="italic">my letter</hi>—or <hi rend="underline italic">to both</hi>: I am sorry for this. Yesterday I recd. 2 papers from Hamilton, continuing his Lecture “Antarctica”, lately given there. I have not yet read it—it seems to be a very erudite and—how different! the <hi rend="italic">papers </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">there</hi>
            <hi rend="italic"> print </hi>
            <hi rend="underline italic">such</hi>! here, <hi rend="italic">NO</hi>!—Have you seen the N.Z. School Reader lately, pubd. by Govt. Got up, I am told, by <hi rend="italic">Habens</hi>. I have had a glance at a copy—and am surprised (I might say, ashamed!) for there is little in it of <hi rend="italic">A1</hi>, or of real authority in N.Z. History &amp; matters. From my hasty glance into this vol. I should think that Habens had carefully avoided the true &amp; real. I hear, that the season inland on the plains has been the wettest known for many years, in matter of <hi rend="italic">shearing</hi>. A ’Bus is now laid on for the <hi rend="italic">other</hi> end of “Scinde Island”, from N. &amp; Close’s Corner to Bungalow—fare 6d. Did you know that young Mackintosh who shot himself? This letter does not require any <hi rend="italic">immediate </hi>ansr., if <hi rend="italic">any</hi>. I hope it may find you &amp; yours all well—in health. How is Victor <hi rend="italic">now</hi>? Kindest regards </p>
         <p rend="justify">Sometimes think on me.—</p>
         <p rend="justify">Yours very sincerely,—W. Colenso.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
